Like if someone's caring for a parent or kids, we'll do everything we can to work with them.
But if someone's a 25-year-old tech bro, like you come into the office, mate.
There's no need, there's no reason why you shouldn't.
It's really easy to hire people who work from home.
It's just easier as a manager to say work from home.
The harder thing to do is let's get in.
Let's make sure your mental health's right.
Let's make sure your collaboration's right.
You've got much more chance of being promoted if you're working from the office.
The data came out of Bloomberg a couple of weeks ago, 50% more chance of being fired
if you're working remotely.
This week's conversation on the Empowering Leaders podcast is with one of the most clear
thinking, intelligent, and capable people I think I have ever met, Adam Swobb, the CEO
and co-founder of Luxury Escapes.
Catching up with Adam for this conversation, it's easy to see in my mind why Luxury Escapes
has become such a trusted and respected brand.
You're going to hear Adam talk about the sophisticated way that he and his team look
after each other, and that has led to Luxury Escapes being one of the most
sought-after places to work in the country.
Adam Swobb is very passionate about getting people back into the office, and you'll hear
him explain why he believes that this is actually a more compassionate and caring thing to do
than allowing people to work from home.
If you're an aspiring entrepreneur or someone who's got a vision and you're wanting to make
it happen, then I'm sure you're going to love this conversation with Adam Swobb as much
as I did.
People like Adam Swobb, the founder of Luxury Escapes, who inspire the work that we do at
Alita.
Go to alitacollective.com, check out our signature Alita Connect program.
We facilitate and connect groups of five to six people around the globe to learn, to connect,
and to share.
You don't have to be the founder of Luxury Escapes to be part of it.
You can sign up and book a discovery call.
We would love to chat to you today.
Huge thank you to the team at Temper Bedding, to Jason Nicholas and his team for their ongoing
support of bringing conversations like this one with Adam Swobb to the table.
Temper is a mattress like no other.
Investing in your sleep is what you need.
One of the great investments you can make in your life.
I encourage you to check out Temper today.
Adam Swobb is the founder and CEO of Luxury Escapes, an online travel booking platform
that generates more than a billion dollars of luxury travel experiences a year.
Adam started his career as a mergers and acquisitions lawyer at Freehills before embarking on a number
of entrepreneurial pursuits, leading to an incredible success story called Luxury Escapes.
He's the co-host of the brilliant Contrarians podcast, chairman of online art marketplace
Bluthumb.com.
I'm a board member of private media and in his spare time runs marathons without shoes
on.
Adam, you strike me.
Great to see you, first of all.
Thanks for joining me.
Thanks for having me, Daz.
You strike me as someone that's got great discipline and focus in everything you do.
Is that accurate and where did that come from?
I don't know if I do, actually.
I think I was never a professional sports person like you, so I think that's a different
level of focus you need to compete at that level.
I think I just like to, I'm somebody who's always been satisfied with stuff that's pretty
menial.
I used to work at Colby.
I was happy to stack shelves.
I was happy to do whatever.
I worked for my uncle as a lawyer.
He was a lawyer when I was 13, 14, filing the most boring job in the world, but I was
kind of okay with it.
So I've always been someone who's sort of happy with what I'm doing as long as I can
get the job done.
So it's sort of less about super high performance, more about just trying to get as much right
as we can day in, day out.
But I see you're inspired to be vegetarian by the Netflix show Game Changers.
It had an impact on a lot of people.
You're inspired to run barefoot on the back of the great book, Born to Run.
A lot of people are inspired, but they might last six weeks or a couple of weeks.
You stay the course, don't you?
You've been vegetarian ever since and you've run without shoes ever since.
Yeah.
Credit to my wife.
She became vegetarian before me and both of us ate heaps of meat and I knew I was eating
too much meat at the time.
And you hear all that.
Things about why meat's not good or good or whatever.
But clearly anything not moderation is not great.
I was eating too much meat.
I was probably getting a bit heavier than I should have.
So I tried a bunch of stuff.
This is probably five years ago.
I tried a few different, how am I going to lose weight?
And I was sort of caught 80 kilos at the time.
Wanted to get to 71, 72.
How do I get there?
One thing was I started fasting, which sort of everyone does now.
It was sort of early days of IF.
Started doing that.
Still doing it.
Intermittent fasting.
Yeah.
So to explain that again to people, tell me what your version of that is.
So my version is I'll generally...
I eat dinner at seven o'clock, six o'clock, seven o'clock, or stop eating by about seven
ideally.
Different if you've got something on, you can't always do that, but try and finish by
seven and then probably eat again at 12 o'clock the next day.
So I do kind of like a 17 hour, sometimes longer, sometimes shorter.
And the basic idea of that is that you're giving your body all that recuperative time.
You're not putting other fuel in that makes it work harder.
And there's a huge amount of research into why that's a positive thing.
That's worked for you?
Yeah.
I think Chris Hemsworth did it in his show when he did those sort of six different episodes.
One of them was on fasting.
And yeah, that's the theory for me.
I just do it just, I'm eating less calories essentially.
It's why I started doing it.
I used to be in big breakfast.
I'd had meat at breakfast, always unhealthy stuff at breakfast.
And just cutting that out, I found really helpful.
And also I find I get less hungry now than I did when I ate breakfast or when I ate breakfast.
So I'll try and always do something in the morning.
It might not be a 5k run, whatever, it might be longer, but I'll try.
If I don't do anything in the morning, I should find I get hungrier.
If I can run 5k plus, I find I'm easily get to a midday.
Yeah.
If I can get to 1.32, you just sort of keep going forever.
So I'll generally eat at 12, 12.31, whatever.
When we finish this, we'll do it.
But so it was a combination of that.
I started using MyFitnessPal, which is just gamifying sort of weight loss.
It's a really simple app.
The more exercise you do, you get bonus for it.
And the more you eat, the more calories.
So it's just a simple calorie counting app.
They gamify.
Did those two things.
And then watched the game changer stuff and thought, why don't I do the veg as well?
Give it a try.
I didn't think I'd last a month or two months to your earlier point.
And it's been a long time.
It's been a lot easier these days to be vegan.
I think a lot of people sort of still look down on vegetarians as not being proper men
or whatever.
Funny enough, like some of the strongest people and fastest, best ultra marathon runners tend
to be vegetarian or vegan.
But I find it just being a lot lighter.
Like you have a biggish meal, finish the meal, and 10 minutes later, you're feeling light
again.
Yeah.
Do you have your day?
I'm fascinated by the ability to stick to something, Adam, because that is what the
whole weight loss industry is about.
People can't do that.
Or the fitness industry.
The fitness industry relies on people not turning up to the gym.
If everyone did, it would be overloaded.
But is it just part of you?
If something works for you, you've got been able to, is there a skill in that?
Or is it just because you're in the elite percentage on that?
I don't know.
I think it definitely is a habit.
So like my biggest weakness clearly is eating sugar.
Like I eat too much chocolate or sugar.
If I eat chocolate one night, I'll open the Pandora's box and eat it every night.
If I just say, don't eat it, and I go, I didn't eat it last night, I was fine.
And then I'll try and brush my teeth straight after dinner.
So you just can't eat after that because it just tastes weird.
So you sort of force yourself in a way.
But you also don't want to just take any kind of joy out of life as well.
So there's a bit of a balance.
But I don't want to open that Pandora's box if I can avoid it of just being unhealthy.
So I parlay that, Adam, into to create a global travel business in a highly competitive space
and have the success you've had.
I suspect the discipline that you've got is a huge part of that.
And then also, I listen to your stuff.
There's a nice.
There's a nice natural self-confidence that comes out of the way you express yourself.
It almost feels a bit like a superpower.
Have you always had that belief in yourself that whatever I put my mind to, I'm going to succeed at?
It's a really good question in terms of looking at founders or entrepreneurs or founders in general.
Do you need to be almost to the point of narcissistic, optimistic, or do you need to be paranoid?
And the answer kind of is both.
You need to have the confidence.
So every time you start, anybody who starts a business, everybody's looking at you.
You've started a business.
You've got plenty of business.
People go, oh, you've got no chance.
You're a fool.
If it was good, somebody would have done it, and you're not able to do it.
So nobody ever looks at somebody else starting a business and goes, that person's going to succeed.
There's always reasons why.
So you've got to be able to get over that.
Me and my co-founder, best mate from school, Jeremy, started our first business in 2004.
It was a backpacker apartment business.
I was a lawyer at the time.
He was a banker.
People thought we were insane for doing that.
So I took a leave of absence, and everybody thought, oh, this guy's a complete moron.
What's he doing?
Leaving a blue-chip law firm for this random backpacking thing.
And people probably thought a similar thing of Jez for leaving A&Z at the time.
But we sort of had – and I give Jez a lot of credit for this.
And this is why he's actually a really good investor.
He was early in Bitcoin, all that kind of stuff.
He's completely willing to ignore every bit of noise and just push forward on what he thinks is the right strategy.
It doesn't always work for him, but when it works, it really works.
And that is a huge – I'm not as good at him as that, but I've been able to take his lead a bit.
So he's really good at that.
So we are – we do have that.
We have that confidence that every founder probably needs to have to get over the doubters.
At the same time, we're also paranoid.
And we're thinking – and the nature of our business, nature of travel, being competitive, as you said.
And we started the business almost like a deal, tactical-based business.
So you're only as good as your next deal, your next whatever you're selling.
We're not a business selling a subscription business that you sort of lock in revenue.
So we've always had that paranoia that if we don't do something real – like a consultant or a lawyer or a banker,
unless you're only as good as your next client.
We were only as good as the next client or next deal.
So if we weren't getting that –
if we weren't getting that next deal, we could go from revenue of a million dollars to zero and be out of business.
So there was an unusual mix – well, maybe it's a usual mix of confidence and absolute paranoia.
That's a great way to describe it, isn't it?
The extreme end is that narcissistic overconfidence, but that healthy bit of paranoia drives a lot of people at the same time.
And so many points I want to pick up on the back of what you just said, Dan.
And one of them is whenever you start something, you get whacked over the head by people.
Are people close to you?
And they go, do you know the stats on how many people fail in small business?
And people have tried that before, and there's other competitors out there.
And that feels like the 98% of what comes your way.
And so what's your advice?
I love – for someone that's about to embark on that or maybe gone through the hardship times of it, how should they approach it?
Yeah, I often get asked this question.
It's a really good one to ask.
And people come to me, and maybe they ask – maybe the subtext is they want some money or not,
because it's one of the angel stuff that we've done in the past.
But they also – I usually say to people, I'm not investing now, or this isn't my sector.
But I'm happy to give you sort of thoughts on what I think of the business and what I really should do.
And there are plenty of businesses that might not be my kind of business, but I might be wrong.
So I might – you come to me and say, Adam, I've got this idea for a podcast business.
I'll say, I'm not sure this is a great business to ask, but go do it, because I don't know.
And if you think you can do it, and if the business model makes sense, give it a crack.
If it's a ridiculous business, then I'll be a little bit more sort of pointed.
But that rarely happens.
Sort through what they're going to do.
But ultimately, like – so there's a great question that Guy Raz asks every guest he has on How I Built This,
is how much of your success is due to luck or hard work or intelligence?
And it's such a great question, because there is no real answer for it.
But my view has been there's kind of three different gates.
You've got to be super lucky.
You've got to – if you're born a white male in a developed country, you've got huge advantages over everyone else.
So you've got to get that sort of luck.
And let's just say if you're not one of those things, you can't succeed, because heaps of people don't.
You've got an advantage.
And I had a clear advantage there alongside other people.
Born in a country like Australia, where there's opportunity and access to good schooling and education.
It's middle-class parents, which is perfect.
You don't want to be too rich, because then you sort of don't understand the value of money.
And if you're sort of right down the bottom, it's really hard.
People do it, but it's really hard.
So I had the absolute rails run through that.
So that was usually – that's like 99% luck.
And then, yeah, there's the degree of you've got to work hard and have some sort of understanding of customer and empathy and all that kind of stuff.
So, yeah, there's the skill, hard work element.
Work 10 years without a day off.
So there's clearly hard work, but there are lots of people who work two jobs, who are single mums, who work just as hard.
So, yeah, there's hard work and skill.
And then you've got to have another piece called the third gate, which is luck again, where not only do you have that initial luck and you've got your sort of hard work, but you've got to have the right timing.
And we entered sort of e-commerce 2010.
We had a perfect run timing-wise.
I think of the 10 richest people of all time, nine of them – this is in Malcolm Gladwell's Outliers book – nine of them were born in like 1830.
Because they all –
They all came of age at that industrial revolution in the U.S.
That was just luck that Rockefeller, Carnegie, all those guys, all white guys, were born at the same time.
So you need to have that second bit of luck where you've just got to get that wave.
And we had that wave alongside – same with the Gabby and Hesham Catch of the Day, same as Rosalind Kogan from Kogan.
Like we all –
Amazon, you know.
Yeah, and Jeff in 1995 when the internet grew at 14,000% the year after we started or something like that.
So, yeah, you've just got to be right place, right time on top of that other luck.
Yeah, and you make a really interesting point there.
Around the skill meeting, luck meeting, and it's nice to hear the honesty in that approach.
But you've also got to have credible resilience and solution focused to be able to – you know, obstacles have come your way.
And when you sit across the table with someone who sounds like, God, it's his dream run.
But were there moments where you thought, hey, we're in over our head here.
We might have bitten off a bit more than we could chew.
There's two absolute moments that come to mind there.
And I think where your point is really good there is probably the most important.
The most important characteristic in a founder – take out the luck stuff because you kind of need luck – is – and what a lot of venture capitalists look for is grit.
And you could call it resilience as well.
Same thing.
Two sides of the same coin.
And if you're really gritty – because you're never going to get a perfect run.
Every business has struggles.
Like Amazon almost went under multiple times and now it's one of two truly.
Like Apple almost – like all these great businesses almost did.
But you've got to have that sort of grit and resilience and willing to not take no for an answer.
So, I think we did have that.
And I think Jez and I, we had that sort of – we follow – I forget what the actual –
exact comment was from Phil Knight and Nike.
But he's got – one of his ten values was obey the law, don't follow the rule, break the rules or something like that.
So, we sort of have a similar concept.
Yeah, you absolutely don't want to break the law.
Laws are there for a reason.
But a rule that somebody randomly made, we don't – that isn't necessarily a law, well, that's there to be broken.
And every startup person has to break heaps of rules.
Otherwise, you never have any creative destruction.
You have the same people doing the same thing and never get shifted.
So, the same – if you look at the biggest businesses 50 years ago, almost none of them are the biggest.
Maybe just Exxon.
But you look at the top ten businesses in the States, they're all sort of 30 years old or less.
Microsoft's probably one of the older ones.
Yeah, and all been disrupted at some level.
You've mentioned your co-founder, Jeremy, a number of times already.
I suppose there's another bit of, you know, good fortune, good skill at getting a great partner.
Yeah.
How does a great partnership work from your perspective?
I can speak from our perspective in that we just have really complementary skills.
And Jez hasn't been super operational or really at all operational in the business for about seven or eight years.
But he will speak every day.
He will message every day.
He looks at every number I look at, equal shareholders.
But it just worked well because his skill isn't operational stuff.
He still is.
He's a great strategist and he understands stuff.
And he'll help out where we need his help.
And he'll always – he'll never sort of shirk that.
But we had different skills.
And that – especially in the early days when we had our early apartments businesses.
I mean, he was very operational there.
We came into office every day together and all that kind of stuff.
Wore suits, even though it was ridiculous.
I don't know why we did.
But we had these really complementary skill sets.
And also, we want the same thing.
We both have very similar court morals.
I think we both want to do the right thing by other people.
And we're court long-term greedy in a way.
We'll always sacrifice short-term wins for a long-term good result.
It's treating customers well.
It's treating team members well.
So, we're very aligned in – like a marriage.
Really aligned in terms of morals.
You kind of have to be.
Yeah.
Like you have a super successful marriage.
I think we've got a super successful partnership.
Me and my wife have similar morals in almost everything.
So, I think that's really important.
So, I think business partnership is very similar to a marriage.
Yeah.
Almost every way.
And I love your language.
It's a common one that I've heard asking that question around.
If you haven't got shared values in a business partnership, you're almost gone.
And then the complementary skill set is super important, isn't it?
Because you're not – you're adding to each other rather than crossing over with each other.
And you mentioned you've invested and, Jeremy, you guys have been angel investors before.
What are you looking for when you – is it the founder?
Is it just the sheer scale ability of the business?
What are the things you look at?
I'm not an amazing angel.
I'm not an angel investor by any chance.
I've probably, again, had a bit of luck, had a bit of bad – good luck and bad luck and probably evened out.
And it probably ends up being similar to what?
If I just chuck it in the next fund in the end.
I tend to look for a founder and grit and smart is probably what I'm looking for in a founder.
Obviously, the business is relevant, but someone's going to pivot probably multiple times anyway.
So, in our path, I've also found good founders and the business hasn't worked just because for whatever.
So, I'm not sure I can actually got a great pattern recognition there and I haven't invested for about four or five years.
For that reason?
Is that because you've got a heavy investment in what you're doing day to day?
Have you felt –
Yeah, a little bit.
A little bit.
I'm pretty heavily invested in the core business.
Also, because of the way sort of the startup market's been the last few years, this hasn't been as much exits.
So, I had a few but not – there's probably two or three big ones that just haven't exited because they've just been – because of the way the market is.
So, haven't been able to recycle that cash, which is probably the main reason why.
So, famous bet, wasn't it?
Warren Buffett, the greatest investor of all time, challenging the investment bankers to a 10-year bet.
I think the legendary.
The legendary story goes and I'll back my – an index fund.
So, for those listening, you're going to be much more articulate on this than me, but an index fund is basically one that's pegged to the top companies on the share market and they roll through.
So, it's computerized.
There's no skill in it at all in index fund versus these high-profile, highly paid investors and the index fund beats them easily.
I think his bet was against a bucket of hedge funds.
Yeah.
So, index versus bucket of hedge funds and it was from – I think it was from 2008 to 2015 or something like that.
And it smashed them.
Like, there was no contest.
But Buffett's been talking about index fund, even though Buffett's obviously an active fund manager, so he picks stocks.
He's been talking about index funds for like 30 years, well before they became fashionable.
And now, everybody talks about index.
So, you listen to the Equity Mates guys who run a great podcast, third or fourth best business podcast.
And they also chuck in index funds and a little bit of spraying and prying along the side.
But it's become so mainstream now because basically it's the fees, the active fund.
This is not an investment advice show, obviously, but it's kind of knowing what you're good at.
Yeah.
So, it sort of relates to that.
And ultimately, in terms of me, should I – we probably could have just chucked it in index fund 10 years ago and end up separatist paraphrase.
Yeah, interesting.
I mean, I love, you know, delving into some of the culture that you've built yourself.
If you turn up at Luxury Escape, free Ben and Jerry's ice cream daily.
I read daily breakfast team members get access to all expenses paid.
Luxury Escape's trips themselves are recognized for your great work environment.
Tell us about how you built that.
I think we just built a place – I never worked in that.
I worked at a law firm for five years, but only two years as a proper lawyer.
A few years while I was at uni.
And so, I don't have a – and I worked at like supermarkets and stuff.
Were you disheartened in a law firm?
Did you find that – because a lot of people are.
Yeah.
I probably wasn't there quite long enough to be fully disheartened.
It's a pretty terrible job.
Like, especially at a junior.
When you get senior, it's probably less bad.
But at a junior level, you're basically proofreading documents.
You're putting together files.
It's not really law.
It's more administrative assistant in a way.
And you're getting paid like 50 grand a year as I was back then.
Maybe it's like 70K.
So, it's not – partners get paid like millions of dollars a year,
but the junior people don't.
It's kind of a pyramid scheme, which is how it works and whatever.
I remember I wrote this big manifesto, Jerry Maguire style,
when I left for Hills.
And to their credit, like multiple partners spoke to me about it.
So, you left them a manifesto and gave it to the partners, did you?
That's a bold thing to do.
Well, it was gone.
So, like it was –
Yeah, free year.
Free year.
And look, picking up on your style, I suspect you wouldn't have held back.
I didn't hold back.
But then they had Greg.
So, to their credit, like some of the most senior partners
wanted to speak to me about it.
I don't know how much they actually put into –
I actually did it –
I used to, when I was at Whistler working at a cafe in like 1999 and skiing,
I worked for a guy who owned this sort of –
I worked at this cafe basically.
And I worked on it.
And as I was leaving, I sent him just like a three or four page,
like a really bad McKinsey version of that.
This is what I think you should do.
Like put a post-mix machine in, install a deep fryer,
a few things I thought we should do just to –
and he was super grateful for that.
And he put –
I think he did a good chunk of them, like probably most of them he did.
And he was really –
and I actually went back and worked later years for him again.
And he'd implemented some of your strategies.
Yeah, we did most of them.
But like he let me work without a visa after a few years.
That was actually –
worked out for the best.
So, what did you –
massive law firm for you.
So, they're now an international giant.
What did you –
what was your advice?
I think my –
the big piece I talked about that I don't think has ever been picked up was –
so, law firms have sort of different levels, like all these partnerships.
And the big worry was you get to sort of the middle level
where you're doing all this work,
but you're not getting paid like –
so, the partnership –
So, you haven't made partner this time.
Yeah.
So, you're just below that.
It's called senior associate.
Yeah.
I was saying you need to put –
I think you should put an equity or profit share for that level to lock them in.
I see Gold had handcuffed them in.
Yeah.
That was my main –
and there's a bunch of other stuff I talked about as well.
Yeah.
That was the main –
and it's actually –
I think I also talked about –
they used to have these partners lunches.
So, partners are going to have this fancy lunch.
I said,
why don't you give lunch to everybody,
not just the partners?
And we do that at Luxury Escapes now,
finally, and after it took me a little while to get there.
But there was stuff like that,
and I can probably dig it out.
I've got it.
I've still got it.
I still occasionally refer back to it.
But I was more impressed that, like,
several partners actually did engage with me on it,
especially because they're law firm partners.
And I still have a great relationship with people at Freelance.
I still go back there,
and most people have moved on in some respect now.
But I still have a great relationship with people who are still there
or who were there.
Well, a lot of the AFL coaches from the era that I played in
played in that era,
and they were born out of just riding this town going,
this is insane.
Like, do we need to personally abuse?
Like, people on a daily basis,
does yelling at people actually work?
And so it's created this sort of emotionally intelligent,
you know,
sit across from this judo from Craig McRae
and listen to his style of leadership compared to,
you know,
what we all sort of grew up in.
Is that probably, you know,
the daily breakfast,
free ice cream?
I mean,
obviously it just makes commercial sense for you.
It's a bit of the Google sort of,
you know,
the Google cult,
effectively.
You enter and you never leave.
Is that part of why you've gone that?
Because you could see an opportunity?
It's funny,
going back to the Craig McRae point you make,
one thing I did pick up from the law firm
that I've tried to change in my sort of day,
I remember you'd work,
you'd do these all night as a law firm.
So you'd literally work all night
and kick on the next one.
I did it a few times.
Or regularly you'd work till 10,
11 o'clock.
And you're not getting paid by the hour.
You're getting paid 50 grand a year here.
So it's like three bucks an hour
whatever you're getting here.
And I remember you'd work through the night,
give a partner something.
It may not be a great piece of work,
but you give them,
and then three days of it's in on the desk.
And that would drive me crazy
that someone wouldn't respect the person
who did that work.
It wasn't just me,
it was everyone.
So I always make it,
it doesn't matter who emails me
or messages me,
it could be someone who started a day ago
or someone who's worked for us 10 years.
I'll try and reply,
as soon as I get a zero inbox,
I'll try and reply to everybody ASAP.
And they'll know that no one,
and I don't want to make anybody,
someone's waiting for approvals for ads
or whatever they're waiting for me to do.
I never want to make someone,
sometimes you have no choice,
but 95% of the time,
I don't want to make anybody wait
because I just remember what it was like to wait.
And it was just so inefficient
and so unfair to the person
who's done the work
and who's getting paid a fraction
of the senior person to do that.
So I've always tried to act that way
and try and make sure all our managers that way,
not just me.
So I don't want managers to sit on stuff
and make someone more junior than wait.
And we know there's some horrific research
around the big accounting firms,
a huge troubles of mental health.
There's been horrible stories
of people literally killing themselves at work
in some of these practices in recent times.
You can't imagine the culture
you're describing.
You're out early enough
not to probably get stuck there
and you found your own path,
but could you see how that could
produce problems for people?
I think it absolutely depends on the person.
For me, I sort of,
not thrive,
but didn't mind that kind of stuff.
Like I go,
I only did it for a couple of years.
So yeah,
10 years later,
it probably would be pretty bad.
I only did it for a few years.
I ran the social club there.
I did heaps of non-legal stuff as well.
So for me,
I was completely fine.
But yeah,
I never was in that zone
that you talk about.
But investment banking,
it's even worse
because their hours were like
till 2, 3 a.m.
like every day.
So that's like incredibly bad.
Law firms and accounting firms
are just one rung below that.
But I've got friends
who are investment bankers
and they work 10 years,
no day off,
like midnight every night.
And this is the constant,
it can't be healthy,
not just mentally,
but physically as well.
You built this brilliant brand.
Luxury Escapes to me
is one of the most recognizable brands
in Australia now.
And you see it
and even if you haven't transacted
with you guys,
it is a good feeling about
what you guys do.
What's been the secret
to get that level of traction
so quickly, effectively?
It's kind of an overnight success
14 years in the making.
We sort of worked,
we started our first e-commerce business
in 2010.
Luxury Escapes,
we spun off 2013.
So it's sort of like 11 years Lux
and three years before that.
Apprenticeship in other brands,
we had deals.com and Kudo
and the like.
We still get a thrill.
I still get a thrill
when somebody,
you say,
that still is thrilling for us.
I don't ever really get recognized.
I was in the street
like you probably do every day.
But if the odd person
ever recognized me,
that's like massively thrilling.
And yeah,
I'm sure Jay's the same.
So we still consider ourselves
not successful.
Maybe one day
we will think differently,
but we still get a kick out of,
like,
I speak to somebody in the street
and I usually say
I work for a travel business.
They might ask which one.
I say Luxury Escapes.
And some people are quite impressed
and some people aren't.
But the people who are impressed
is like a big thrill for us
because we still think
we're just two average dudes
who don't really know
what they're doing.
So,
yeah,
for us it's been trial and error
for 13 years
of trying things.
If it works,
we go hard.
If it doesn't work,
we pull back.
Getting an incredible team
to sort of further
a lot of this stuff
and try to have that same ethos
of asymmetric bets.
So if we bet on something,
if it works,
it's 20x return.
If it doesn't work,
you've lost the 1x.
So how do we get that
sort of entrepreneurial vibe
through the business?
Which I think we still have.
Obviously it gets harder.
Like Jeff Bezos
talked about Amazon
being a day one business.
How do we stay day one?
We want to stay day one forever.
It's really hard.
Like Amazon,
I think,
now it's actually almost day two
and I talked about it
on our pod last week.
Jeff's gone two years ago.
Andy Jassy's running it now
who was Jeff's protege
for many years.
But I feel like Amazon's
getting very day two-y.
We don't want to become day two.
So eventually every business does.
But how do we keep
on the cutting edge
of what customers want?
So we've got a really good
marketing team now
who are doing heaps of stuff
around social,
heaps of stuff around
influencer work,
obviously SEM, SEO,
all that kind of stuff
that everybody does
but we've just got to
stay ahead of it.
But you're good at it.
I've even done some homework
for this conversation.
Search engine,
optimization you just mentioned
but you put even the letter T
in for travel
and you guys pop up
at the top of the screen.
I mean that sort of stuff
obviously you put time.
How do you get good
at that for instance?
Hire people who know
a lot more than that
about you.
So we've got our CMO
who's got great background
in that.
He's building a team
who's doing SEO.
We had people before that
so our tech team's really good.
Our content team do it.
How heavy do you invest in that?
Is that a big expense
for you guys?
It's not huge.
Yeah.
When,
we're not a business
that naturally,
so SEO,
search engine optimization
leads itself really well
when you've got lots of content.
So marketplaces,
so your classic market,
so booking.com
who's a competitor of ours,
unbelievable SEO
because they've got
this huge marketplace
of 500,000 hotels
that have been live
for 20 years.
Our original business model
was really incredible value
tactical deals
on amazing hotels
but we only have that deal
available for two weeks maybe.
That doesn't lend itself
very well to SEO.
We built a marketplace
four years ago
which means we've got
a lot more product
on the site now.
It's like a mini booking.com
but with lots of stuff included
and a much better
contact center
because booking,
you can never speak to somebody.
It's a great business by the way,
booking 135 billion US business
so there are many,
many multiples
of what we'll ever be but-
135 billion a year
booking.com.
Market value.
They probably turn over
200 billion plus.
Yeah.
So like juggernaut.
So they've got incredible
SEO advantage
over everybody else.
Yeah.
So we're always going to struggle
in a way to compete against them
unless it's like a luxury term
which would be better
because of the name
and that kind of stuff.
So we're coming from
a bit way back there
but we've improved
in that area
but what we're probably better at
is that
because of what we do
because we effectively
are really good at storytelling,
we've got a TV show,
series seven,
maybe even series eight
is about to start now
on Foxtel on 10
later in the year
working with some great people
who go around the world
and we produce the show,
we create the show
in partnership with Foxtel now.
We've had a podcast,
Electric House podcast,
we're on multiple
different radio stations
with sort of shows essentially
so we do a bit of what
I can call a mini Red Bull
in a way.
Red Bull, the masters
will never be as good as them
but the way they mix
commerce and content
has been an inspiration for us
so we try and do a bit of that stuff
which we can,
Booking.com can never do that.
Booking.com can never have a TV show.
We're in a unique position
because of what we do
to be able to tell incredible stories.
And you're playing a space
where there are great stories.
We all,
if a travel show's on,
I can't help it
so I'm not a great watcher
of mainstream TV
but jeez,
I'd love to have gone there
and you know,
if you're telling those stories
the way that you guys do,
you can see how powerful it is.
Going back to the brand,
I think there was a time
where Qantas had a look
at maybe going to buy you guys out.
Yeah, look at the Qantas brand now
and I just,
there's a disdain for Qantas
that it's almost hard to understand
in such a short space of time.
Everyone's had a terrible experience
with Qantas.
You mentioned the name
and you can see,
you know,
you've probably not ever been
on a call centre conversation
with someone from Qantas
given what you do
but you have, yeah.
I mean,
you want to have a rough day
to go and do that.
I mean,
it's not a given, is it?
I mean, you can drop,
you know,
they were one of the most
prestigious brands in Australia
and now they're,
in my mind,
one of the most loathed brands.
So,
what do you make of that?
Yeah,
that could be a whole episode
on Qantas, I think
but we are constantly petrified
of damaging the brand.
We overinvest in customer service
because we want to make sure
our customers treat it really well.
So,
we've got a 24-7,
365-day-a-year call centre
which almost,
forget travel,
almost no one in the world
has that,
let alone travel,
like booking,
you can't speak to some expert,
you can't speak to someone,
you can't actually
don't have any call centre.
So,
having a call centre is unusual.
Having a 365-24-7
is like super unusual.
If something goes wrong
on a luxury escapes holiday,
I can ring
and someone's going to answer.
The opposite of what you get.
Yeah,
or call you back in half an hour
or something like that
if it's a really busy time.
And we actually want people,
if you go away,
you buy a luxury escape
and you go to Bali
and something's not quite right
and we don't own the hotel
so we don't control
the end-to-end experience.
So,
5-10% of the time
something goes not perfect
and that could be just,
most customers are really good,
they'll just roll with it.
Some customers maybe not as good
which is fine,
everybody's different.
And sometimes,
the hotel's complete,
sometimes it's misunderstood,
whatever it is,
we want to be able to,
we can contact the hotel
pretty quickly and fix it.
It's much easier for us to fix it
while day one
when you get to Kavinsky, Bali.
They probably wouldn't do
anything wrong
but we call the GM and say,
Darth has got a problem,
can you help him?
And they'll give you,
they'll fix up and whatever
and help you.
If we don't know until
someone gets back,
much harder.
So,
we want someone to contact us
while they're away,
not after they get back
because once they get back,
the hotel's got the money,
they don't want to hear about it,
we've paid the hotel
so we're sort of
hamstrung.
We don't want to lose a customer
but we can't give you
a five grand refund
when we've paid the hotel
the five grand.
So,
we're in a really
invidious position.
If you can tell us straight away,
we'll almost always fix it.
Yeah,
yeah,
jump on the phone
and which is what you want.
Someone to listen to you,
hear your problems,
see if they can solve it.
99% of people
are reasonable
in that space.
Adam,
we're fascinated by,
yours is an incredible story for me,
create something in this space
as successful as it is
and just the patterns
of what great leadership
looks like
and I'll come to that.
I want to ask you
one final question.
I meant to ask you
about the Contrarians podcast
which I love listening to
and it's,
a lot of your language,
to be honest with you,
it goes over my head.
You know,
it's rapid fire
but it's brilliant
and it's entertaining.
There's a natural chemistry
between you
and your co-host Adir
but you throw some haymakers
at two of you.
You're not prepared
which I enjoy.
In a business community
where you guys are operating in,
do you ever have that sense,
you know,
I know the footy industry,
if you go hard,
you're going to bump into someone
pretty,
you know,
readily.
Has that ever been
a cause for concern?
It's pretty topical.
I'm super flattered
that you listen
as someone who's got
huge respect for you
with everything you've done
from not just footy
but in the business world
and obviously in the media world
so it's hugely flattering
that you would even listen
but yeah,
I think part of the show
is you want to be natural
with each other
and disagree with each other.
I've been pretty outspoken on,
I won't name the business.
I've been threatened
to be sued multiple times.
That gets...
For those that haven't listened,
sorry to just jump in.
You know,
you guys will short a business
or, you know,
take a position
and say this business
is absolutely overvalued
or,
and doing a,
you know,
putting your reputation
and then explaining
very detailed why
and it's not a personal attack
on founders
or it's just saying
this is how we see the market
but I know how the world works.
People think personally.
Yeah.
And it's happened?
We,
I've written business articles
for sort of 15 years
so while we're running
the apartments business
I've written for
everything from Crikey
to The Age
to AFR,
whatever.
So I've written heaps of stuff.
I've wrote a book in 2010.
I've written a book in 2010
talking about corporate collapses
so that was a pretty
like harsh book.
No one's fully threatened.
Like I'm,
usually someone says
take the article down
I won't see it
and you just take it down
or sometimes you make mistakes
and I'm,
I don't,
last thing I want to do
is make a mistake
about someone that's,
especially that's critical.
I'll always fix it up
straight away.
If you say,
Adam,
I didn't have 25 kicks that day.
I had 30.
Fix it up.
Of course I'll fix it up.
Like it's,
you don't want something
that's wrong on it
but you also be able
to delineate between
when someone's trying
to take the piss
and get you to say
something that's not true
and I actually stopped
speaking to companies.
I used to write about
ABC Learning Centres years ago.
This is before it collapsed
and I was pretty critical
of it before it collapsed
and I was short
and you speak to the PR people
and they're always nice guys.
They're usually guys.
They're always nice
and they convince you
of stuff that you know
is not true
but you get convinced
so I actually try not to speak
to the companies I talk about
because you get very easily
influenced.
Someone comes and says,
Adam,
here's why you're wrong.
ABC,
here's the evidence.
Then we'll fix it
but I try not to practically
go out to speak to people
because I'm not a journalist.
It's not my job
to check with the company.
They're welcome
to contact me after
but yeah,
you definitely,
I've had some angry emails
but it's rare.
You said it's topical
at the moment.
Has there been one close call?
Yeah,
in recent time
I've been pretty harsh
on a couple of different businesses
and Adir is a public company guy.
He's chairman
of a well-known public company.
He's probably more nice
about people than I am
so I run a private company
so he's always
a bit my peacemaker.
I'm a bit more probably
the aggressor.
Not always,
sometimes we switch roles
but that's usually the role
so he's trying to,
and generally he's usually right.
So he'd say,
Adam,
you don't really need
to go that far.
Let's tone it down a bit
and I'll try and tone it down
where he says it
because he's a very smart guy
and we just try
and get that nice balance.
Fascinated by,
well,
we see these patterns
around what great leadership
looks like in different settings
from someone who's
got an incredible sense
of the commercial world
like you do
or someone from the arts
or sport.
And we think self-leadership
and I think this applies to you
is hard to lead anyone else
without an idea
of your own sense
of self-leadership.
What do you make of that?
Yeah,
I think,
I find it really hard
to describe my leadership
but what I've always tried to do
is lead by example
and I can't do everything
in the business
but I've done most
of the jobs or something.
So I've written deals,
I've done customer service
for five years,
I've sort of done finance,
obviously I was a lawyer.
So I've done,
I do a lot of sales
where I can.
Yeah,
the technical roles
probably haven't done less
because I've never done
anything.
I've never been an engineer
or coder.
So you'll jump in
and sell a holiday
like you've done that
in the past?
Yeah,
I'll do the radio,
like we do radio stuff
where I'll do that stuff
along with some other guys.
So I've done some sales
and if I have to,
I'll get on the customer service issue
which is a really big customer.
I'll certainly email customers
if I need to
and if I really need to,
I'll speak to them.
So I don't want to expect
anybody to do
what I won't do
and that's in terms of work hours,
in terms of,
nothing I hate more
than the fat cat part
of being paid two million bucks
a year leaving at four o'clock
to pay for a meal
to pay golf
and the poor person
earning 60 grand a year
having to stay and do all the work.
I'll find that
just really hard to stomach.
So as we get more,
as the business gets bigger
and there's more people
who work there,
I don't think my job should,
like yeah,
your job changes
in terms of I'm not handling,
I'm not doing content anymore,
I'm not doing customer service
like I used to every single day
but I don't think
you should not do it
so it becomes a balance
and ultimately,
the beauty of a founder
versus,
there's lots of amazing
hired CEOs
and hired CEOs
are great at resource allocation
it's a really important job
of a CEO
they're also great
at managing and building teams
if you can't do that
you can't really ever
lead a big team
and you have hundreds
of people who can do that.
The beauty of what a founder
can bring
and almost every founder
brings is
understanding the product
and by product
I mean product management
which is what
is sort of a development
technical term
but the very first product
we built
means there's product management
essentially
we product managed
for the first five or six years
till we hired product managers
to do it
and we got an amazing team
of product managers
and product managers
are the people
who sit between
commercial
and tech
so they've got a bit
of a tech background
but also really commercial people.
So in your world
they're doing the deal
with the Hilton in Bali
or is that?
That's a different
kind of product manager
that's very true as well
I'm talking about
so we're building
a flights portal
on the website
they're the liaison
between our flights
commercial person
who's doing with the airlines
and our coders
so the product manager
almost manages
the technical product
on the site
so that's sort of what
like Steve Jobs
is classic that
and the guys
who run
so Mel and Cliff
from Canva
they're product people
they're both super hands
on the products
still
I'm not sure
if Mike and Scott
still are at Atlassian
they probably
absolutely would have
been in the early days
so their business
was born out of
their passion
interest in you know
Canva
incredible story
but they wanted
to change
you know
the way
the graphic
design was
yeah
photo book
business
and they design
and they still
like Mel still
is the main product
person there
and Cliff is
kind of the main
product person
with it
so
and most products
that we build
I'm working with
my CPO
really closely
and I'm checking it
and most founders
tend to do that
because
as a founder
you probably
have that
customer empathy
bit more than
a hired gun CEO
like hired gun CEO
can have it as well
such as Nadella
at Microsoft
is an unbelievable
one of the best CEOs
ever
and he wasn't
he was a product
person ironically
but he wasn't
a founder
Gates was obviously
the founder
so the beauty
of a founder CEO
is you get that
product understanding
as well
and you probably
get that salesiness
as well
because every founder
has got to be
the head salesperson
as well
yeah
closer to home story
at a very
small level
but a great friend
of mine
I've been involved
in this business
for many years
learned to swim
business
it's been around
for 50 years
called Paul Sadler
Swim Land
I went to Paul Sadler
did you grow up
swimming in Paul
Bay Street
so many kids
unbelievable
and speaking to
his son Ben
who's second
generation
they get into
are we getting
enough kicking
in the water
in a prep class
so founders
get the detail
don't they
and you're right
that others can't
because they know
the history
and they've been
there
funny you mentioned
I didn't know
you were involved
which is
my kids
learn at MSAC
and it's not
a patch on
like
MSAC's
horrific
it's a public
government
funded thing
or whatever
it's terrible
but Paul
had the
colour certificates
which is a great
goal setting
thing
that business
was incredible
he had one
at the time
and I went to
that one
and now it's
apartments
it'll be tough
to hear that
so many kids
grew up
learning those
lessons
all our kids
went through
the same thing
smart about
incentivising
to get to
the next level
it's the one
renewable business
isn't it
we're all
in a water
locked
country
we need
to teach
our kids
to swim
with founders
and leaders
like you
Adam
really conscious
about impacting
people positively
every day
and they're
really thoughtful
about that
how have you
gone about
impacting people
in a positive
way
I think
that's what
ultimate leadership
is about
is you're
working with
people
every day
people don't
like you
and like
what you're
doing
and you're
not creating
a better
workplace
or a better
life for them
then you're
not really
a great leader
in any respect
you're kind of
just forcing
people to work
because you're
paying them
ultimately
we want
and retention
is a really
important metric
for us
and probably
every business
we want people
to love to
come to work
or really
like to come
to work
and having a
friend at
work is one
really big
input in that
but ultimately
if we're not
if you think
about sort of
stakeholders
in our business
we want to make sure
our customers are happy
obviously we've got to
think of shareholders
as well
I don't own
all the business
me and Jess
aren't the only
shareholders in this
business
we've got to
think of our
shareholders as well
but our
teams
are our most
important
stakeholders
our IP comes
in and out
of that classic
investment banker
line
our IP goes
up and down
the elevator
every day
so we want to
make sure our
team's really
loving coming
to work with us
or at the very
least really
liking coming
to work with us
and if we don't
improve our life
then what are we
doing?
And the next
dimension I want to
talk to you about
is the vision
for Luxury Escapes
as you said
started as a
flash sale
business
and doing
great deals
looking after
people in
those windows
of time
and now you've
built this
marketplace
that listening
to you
guys
it's got the
potential to be
a webjet element
to it
insurance element
so it's a
massive
vision really
and again
a highly
competitive
market
how do you
go about
sharing
that vision
with your
team
so that they
get it
the way you
do?
It's actually
a really
hard thing
to do
it's
especially
the whole
team
because you
want to
get as
much
buy-in
as possible
from everyone
but there's
a lot of
say we're
building a
wholesale
business
recently
which means
we sell
to travel
agents
around
Australia
so we
started
the
business
travel
agents
actually
often
hated
us
because
we
kind
of
competed
with
them
but they
kind
of
wanted
to sell
what we
had
but we
just
didn't
sell
to them
so now
we
sell
to travel
agents
and we
will
have
almost
like
30%
of
travel
agents
selling
luxury
escapes
hopefully
in the
next
six
months
so we've
gone from
travel
agents
hating
us
to being
in
partnership
with
travel
agents
and being
able to
pay
them
for
selling
our
stuff
so that's
a really
fun
product
to sell
but it's
not really
relevant to
call it
our
contact
center
because it's
kind of
tangential
so it is
a bit of
a balancing
act
how do
we
tell
everybody
what we're
doing
and what
we plan
on doing
without
disengaging
them
because it
doesn't
actually
directly
involve
that is
a challenge
and you
can only
have so
many
pillars
of growth
in a
business
at one
time
and not
everybody's
working on
those growth
pillars
because it
can be
a lot
of business
as usual
stuff
do our
best
to try
and engage
everyone
in the
business
as equals
in many
ways
you are
a contrarian
isn't it
everyone
wants the
online
business
and to
take away
from the
travel agent
onto online
and now
you go and
open a store
at Chadston
why?
we had a few
pop-up stores
over the
journey
and I
actually
love
and this
is
screw
Turner
who runs
flighties
who
obviously
has 300
stores
and they
still do
incredibly
well
from their
stores
people think
flighties
is dead
and travel
agents
are dead
flight
center
the
long-term
CEO
is still
the CEO
of that
it's a
huge
business
travel agents
are doing
really
which is
amazing
to see
they got
smashed
during
COVID
for
reasons
that we
know
and poor
travel
agents
if you're
a home-based
travel agent
you were
stuffed
during
COVID
we could
at least
sell
online
to
Australians
we had
revenue
coming
in
but
these
poor
agents
had
zero
revenue
and
were
spending
all day
refunding
people
and
again
the
mental
health
issues
and
the
depression
it was
just
unbelievable
how bad
they had
they weren't
getting
handouts
like
Qantas
and
Virgin
were
they
got
virtually
nothing
so
thankfully
the
people
who
survived
the
agents
who
survived
were
actually
doing
really
well
which
is
amazing
to see
so
technically
we
compete
with
them
but
we
want
to
see
the
sector
going
really
well
in
terms
of
chatty
we
think
that
so
there
are
people
who
love
buying
online
people
who
love
calling
it's
a bit
correlation
because
you
probably
want
to
speak
someone
because
you're
buying
a
more
complex
trip
so
if
you're
buying
a
Bali
holiday
we
sell
more
Bali
than
anyone
in
Australia
because
it's
a
really
easy
thing
Sofitel
or
Kapinski
Hyatt
whatever
and
you
bang
and
you
book
your
flight
through
us
or
Jetstar
whatever
and
it's
easy
if
you're
you
can
speak
for an
hour
to a
consultant
you
can
look
on the
big
screen
while
we
do
it
it's
a
beautiful
environment
it's
probably
the
world's
nicest
it's
like
an
Apple
store
for
travel
and
you
can
start
from
then
and
you
can
really
get
into
it
from
then
and
have
some
expert
advisors
build
an
unbelievable
trip
for
you
you're
not
paying
for
anything
this
is
all
sort
of
free
essentially
so
it's
that
so
we
can
sell
lots
of
product
and
we've
got
these
unbelievable
screens
out
the
front
which
is
incredible
landscapes
we
have
100,000
people
walk
past
our
store
every
day
there
are
still
people
who
don't
trust
us
because
we're
an
online
business
once
you've
walked
into
the
store
you
go
actually
these
luxury
sales
guys
are
probably
pretty
legit
like
this
is
a
business
but
nobody
knows
that
so
it
definitely
helps
for
trust
and
credibility
as
well
fascinating
curiosities
are where
we
hear all
the time
and people
we see
like you
are just
curious
and they
use that
curiosity
to just
constantly
want to
learn
and grow
does
that
resonate
with
you
yeah
absolutely
I think
both
you
and I
are
always
very
contrarian
so
I left
a bank
when
everybody
was doing
corporate
wasn't
cool
to be
a founder
now
it's
kind
of
cool
you've
got
Cliff
and
the
new
world
it's
not
that
long
ago
Amazon
wasn't
thought
of
highly
Apple
was a
disaster
so
it's
very
different
now
everybody
wants
to be
a founder
which is
amazing
I love
it
back
then
we were
considered
like
complete
outliers
doing
that
so
we've
always
we own
families
so
Sain
what are
you doing
was it
my dad
was always
was a
builder
so
naturally
entrepreneurial
really
supportive
mum
was
semi
supportive
but
she
had
a
lawyer
son
like
kind
of
started
doing
backpacker
apartments
like
and
she's
super
supportive
for a
long
time
since
but
probably
a little
bit
more
skeptical
which is
fine
but
we were
still
living at
home
then
it was
the
perfect
time
it was
a
classic
two
eight
or
perfect
time
I
could
have
always
gone
back
three
months
later
I
said
guys
not
come
back
we
took
a
risk
kids
we
had
no
girlfriends
or
whatever
we
didn't
have
wives
and
kids
at
the
time
no
mortgage
and
nothing
like
that
so
if
you
ever
got
funny
enough
like
most
yeah
I
think
the
average
unicorn
founder
is
mid
thirties
to
unfortunately
two
males
you
can
say
unfortunately
there
relatively
young
to
start
a
business
at
twenty
four
when
we
did
but
it's
much
easier
then
because
you
just
don't
have
I
was
speaking
to a
friend
yesterday
and
she
was
saying
I
would
love
to
start
a
business
but
she's
on a
huge
salary
like
hundred
thousand
dollar
salary
kids
at
private
schools
mortgage
like
really
hard
to
that's
huge
opportunity
cost
yeah
communicating
with
clarity
you've
as a
journalist
to
overlay
that
and
you
host
and
you
get
your
message
across
really
well
have
you
been
thoughtful
about
your
communication
probably
not
enough
I've
never
really
had
media
training
it's
a bit
of a
10,000
hour
thing
like
he's
doing
enough
of
it
he
could
probably
get
a
bit
better
at
it
but
I'm
like
you've
done
a lot
more
than
me
so
you
can
tell
the
difference
between
a
professional
and
an
amateur
like
I
am
but
I
used
to
do
sky
business
stuff
this
is
when
I
was
like
so
it
was
a
business
year
back
then
my
spare
time
so
go
on
sky
business
doesn't
exist
anymore
go
on
sky
business
remember
the
first
time
really
nervous
and
they
kept
looking
down
like
just
I
don't
know
I
didn't
have
any
notes
down
just
kept
looking
back
at
their
first
time
on
air
cringes
with
sort
of
you
can't
hear
the
sound
of
your
own
voice
still
today
but
you're
right
I
haven't
seen
good
media
training
I
haven't
seen
someone
that can
do it
replicate
actually
you know
go
on
stand
sky
business
live
audience
you
guess
the
feedback
loop
is
going
to
come
really
quickly
from
everyone
but
if you
get
through
that
you're
going
to
get
better
and
as
you
said
how
important
is
collaboration
been
in
your
world
really
important
like
we've
been
really
hot
on
coming
back
to
the
office
and
this
is
a
hot
topic
I've
written
heaps
on
this
I'm
usually
the
go
to
corporate
dude
people
come
around
now
I
probably
instinctively
hated
it
because
of
the
COVID
era
policy
and
I
hated
everything
about
that
but
we
always
absolutely
believe
in
person
collaboration
like
we
have
a
team
that
is
spread
around
the
world
so
it's
not
as
if
every
single
person
works
from
Melbourne
and
South
two
major
offices
and
we
do
have
people
who
work
remotely
and
there
are
pre
COVID
we
were
super
flexible
so
we
were
probably
more
flexible
than
99%
of
businesses
pre
COVID
people
not
necessarily
work
from
home
but
if
you
need
to
not
come
to
the
office
you
want
to
work
get
in
at
leave
get
in
at
leave
it
to
whatever
we
were
always
hugely
flexible
and
as
COVID
wound
up
it
never
made
sense
we
absolutely
want
to
be
flexible
the
most
key
reason
if
you
need
to
care
for
parents
special
needs
there's
absolutely
reason
Costco
which
isn't
one of
the
world's
best
businesses
they've
got
work
from
office
policy
doesn't
matter
we
actually
hired
someone
from
Costco
who's
unbelievable
and
she was
caring
for
a
parent
who's
very
unwell
and
years
of
service
and
Costco
said
sorry
it
was
very
friendly
they
said
sorry
you
can't
work
for
us
whereas
we
would
never
be
that
harsh
like
if
someone's
caring
for
a
parent
or
kids
we'll
do
everything
we
can
to
work
with
them
but
if
someone's
a
year
old
tech
bro
you
come
into
the
office
there's
no
reason
why
you
shouldn't
we
think
mental
health
reasons
absolutely
imperative
to come
in
collaboration
reasons
we
can
actually
get
more
productivity
out of
somebody
working
from
home
in
many
cases
you
probably
make
more
money
you
pay
less
rent
all
that
kind
of
stuff
but
it's
not
about
dollars
and
cents
it's
about
how
do
we
make
sure
our
team
is
engaged
working
closely
together
and
creating
better
customer
value
I
don't
think
you
can
do
you
mind
please
coming
in
to
the
office
I
mean
still
city
barren
for
days
at
a
time
I
think
you're
not
talking
about
lack
of
empathy
here
if
you've
got
a
boss
who's
totally
getting
the
real
no
but
if
someone's
just
decided
it's
healthier
to
actually
be
around
people
and
socialise
I'm
in
your
corner
on
that
my
view
is
actually
the
reverse
you're
really
easy
to
hire
people
who
work
from
home
it's
just
easier
as a
manager
to
say
work
from
home
the
harder
thing
to
do
is
let's
get
in
let's
make
sure
your
mental
health
is
right
let's
make
sure
your
collaboration
is
right
you've
got
much
more
chance
being
promoted
if
you're
working
from
the
office
that's
a
good
thing
but
that's
a
reality
you've
got
much
less
chance
being
fired
if
you're
working
from
the
office
50%
more
chance
of
being
fired
if
you're
working
remotely
I'm
not
saying
that's
good
or
bad
that
is
what
want
to
keep
your
job
you
want
to
get
promoted
you're
much
better
of
coming
in
if
you
want
to
have
better
mental
health
better
physical
health
Nick
Coatsworth
who's
a
great
guy
wrote
an
article
last
week
Nick
Coatsworth
was
the
assistant
chief
medical
officer
one
of
the
few
people
who
said
we
got
a
lot
wrong
perhaps
we
should
do
a
deeper
dive
on
that
not
many
people
are
doing
that
out
of
what
we've
just
been
through
who's
been
the
greatest
leader
in
your
life
that
is
a
really
good
question
I've
had a
couple
great
chair
person
who
I
don't
necessarily
have
that
many
mentors
myself
but
I've
worked
with
a
guy
called
Pato
Sullivan
who
ran
nine
in
the
days
who's
been
chairman
of
car
sales
for
more
than
years
I
think
he
was
a
fantastic
chairman
of
mine
still
an
incredible
guy
unbelievable
my
current
chairman
used to
run
tourism
Australia
been a
huge
support
for me
in the
business
during
COVID
and
before
then
so
I've
been
lucky
enough
to
have
two
unbelievable
chair
persons
who
have
been
great
guidance
for
me
from
a
personal
perspective
and
both
super
experienced
business
people
and
really
empathetic
and
understand
really
helpful
as
well
did
you
seek
them
out
or
I
actually
sought
both
of
them
out
yeah
and
it's
worked
out
incredibly
well
by the
sounds
of
it
we're
a bit
fascinated
in the
world
of
collaboration
in
the
space
we're
in
grouping
leaders
together
around
the
globe
and
just
people
getting
out
of
their
silos
and
getting
back
into
this
collaborative
spirit
as
you
said
you're
competing
with
travel
agents
but
at
the
same
time
you
want
them
to
do
well
and
now
you're
doing
deals
with
them
and
they're
selling
your
products
and
so
we're
a bit
obsessed
with
collaboration
is
there
one
person
in
the
world
so
I've
had a
great
partnership
with
Qantas
now
currently
great
partnership
with
Virgin
in
the
businesses
we
really
respect
Costco
is
an
incredible
business
LVMH
incredible
business
Amazon
incredible
business
Apple
incredible
business
not just
because
they're
highly
valued
business
but
just
because
of
the
franchises
they've
built
so
we
look
to
maybe
less
from
collaboration
perspective
maybe
yes
or
no
but
more
so
like
we
want
to
emulate
the
multi-generational
success
of these
it's very
rare that
business
lasts
you hear
the one
year
stat
then
it's
the
multi-generational
businesses
we want
to
create
a
multi-generational
legacy
business
and
that's
why
we
invest
so
much
in
customer
service
we're
not
thinking
of
the
customer
relationship
for
one
year
we're
thinking
of
a
plus
year
customer
relationship
and
if
you
look
at
the
Apples
Amazons
they have
multi-generational
businesses
now
I'd
love
to
be
able
to
build
something
like
what
some
of
these
businesses
have
built
it's
the
Jim
Collins
good
to
great
isn't
it
studying
those
businesses
and
the
reasons
why
as
you
said
look
back
years
and
very
few
of
the
biggest
businesses
in
the
world
are
currently
there
and
so
that's
the
mission
is it
for
you
is
to
build
something
that's
got
multi-generational
success
we're
super
lucky
we sell
happiness
essentially
and
it's
a
one
that
gives
me
more
joy
than
anything
there's
a
couple
of
different
things
I'll
quickly
touch
on
it
one's
from
the
customer
perspective
like
so
we
have
some
very
wealthy
customers
and
some
customers
like
everyday
Aussies
and
that's
amazing
and
it's
when
you
have
someone
who
said
I've
never
been
overseas
before
I was
able
to
go
Bali
because
you
made
it
so
much
better
value
and
it
was
the
best
experience
of
my
life
that's
incredibly
touching
and
funny
enough
coming
out
of
COVID
Bali
was
decimated
as
well
so
you
have
people
literally
living
in
poverty
over
there
such
a
tourism
based
economy
and
the
border
was
shut
so
imagine
the
devastation
Bali
Fiji
were
probably
the
two
most
hit
places
globally
almost
so
as
bad
we
were
at
least
we
could
job
keep
and
all
that
stuff
poor
people
in
Bali
had
virtually
nothing
the
hotels
may
have
funded
them
a bit
if
they
could
but
coming
out
of
COVID
so
borders
were
opening
or
just
opened
and
we've
got
an
amazing
guy
who
does
our
number
one
Bali
partnerships
guy
was
having
a
lunch
with
a
new
partner
and
they
went
to
lunch
and
we
just
put
our
deal
live
and
we
didn't
know
how
it
would
go
because
we
were
just
opening
up
Bali
and
these
guys
never
worked
with
us
before
and
no
revenue
for
a
couple
of
years
anyway
five
minutes
in
sale
comes
through
and
they're
popping
the
champagne
corks
pretty
heavy
another
sale
end
of
the
lunch
there's
like
grand
in
revenue
it's
like
grand
for
in
scheme
of
things
not
ridiculous
this
is a
obviously
big
hotel
but
grand
for
the
first
grand
they've
seen
in
two
years
and
you've
got
staff
who
aren't
getting
paid
and
the
managers
of
this
hotel
actually
moved
to
tears
by
the
fact
that
we're
going
again
we can
now
bring
our
staff
back
and
pay
our
staff
and
to
be
able
to
be
a
part
of
that
was
incredible
and
we were
very
moved
it's
a
great
story
we've
owned
a
health
retreat
in
Bali
for
years
and
to
see
I
always
think
going
to
Bali
Bali's
got
this
fascinating
place
Australians
love it
a
portion
and
there's
a
group
that
refuse
to
ever
go
and
I
think
the
thing
that
people
don't
go
miss
is
they're
the
most
beautiful
people
on
earth
and
I
remember
all
through
that
time
what
more
can
we
do
to
help
lucky
enough
to
be
able
to
fund
and
pay
make
sure
everything
but
the
sense
of
community
the
life
lesson
around
how
generous
and
how
giving
that
group
of
people
are
so
I'm
not
surprised
and
just
the
way
that
they
got
together
to
support
each
other
in
that
time
was
just
quite
remarkable
so
great
story
to
finish
on
and
so
much
to
talk
you
about
hopefully
do
it
again
another
time
congratulations
it's an
incredible
success
story
and
enjoyed
catching
up
today
thanks
for
listening
to
another
episode
of
the
empowering
leaders
podcast
huge
thanks
as
always
to
our
great
friends
at
temper
and
we
encourage
you
to
check
out
our
leader
connect
program
new
episodes
are
out
every
Wednesday
morning
at
6am