This week's guest on the Empowering Leaders podcast, Anita Jacoby, is a genuine pioneer
for female success in Australian media. Anita talks about consistently being overlooked for
promotion simply because she was female. Interesting to hear her thoughts on the world
of clickbait, fake news that we have today compared with long form investigative style
journalism that she made her name with. The story of her own father is fascinating,
had a huge positive influence in her life, a World War II refugee, the founder of Sony in
Australia, to then discover after his death a very dark and tragic side to his life that he
had never revealed previously. Worth listening to this story because it's a fascinating one
on so many levels. It's people like Anita Jacoby who inspire the work that we do at Alita. We'd
love you to check out alitacollective.com and in particular our bespoke Alita Connect program
where we bring together diverse leaders from a range of backgrounds,
in bespoke groups of five or six to connect, to learn, to share and we would love to connect
with you. You don't have to be an award-winning journalist or in any particular sphere to want
to join in and connect and we are loving the stories that are coming out of our program Alita
Connect. Simply head to Alita Collective, book a discovery call, we'll give you a call and love
you to join our program. Thanks as always to our great friends at Temper Australia New Zealand,
Jason Nicholas and his team for their support of the Empowering Leaders podcast that helps us bring
what we think are compelling stories.
each and every week. Investing in a Temper mattress is a great investment. A third of our
life is spent in bed so quality sleep we know is a great key to success as many of the leaders that
we speak to value great sleep and great success. Thank you as always to the team at Temper.
Anita Jacoby is one of the most respected and decorated producers in Australian television
history. A multi-award winning career spanning more than 40 years including renowned program
60 Minutes, Enough Rope, The Guru and Transfer as well as securing interviews with the likes
of Bill Clinton, Sir David Attenborough, Jerry Seinfeld, John Travolta, Elton John and many many more
before eventually being headhunted for the managing director role of the Australian arm of Britain's
ITV studios. Anita is a passionate advocate for women in media and leadership, is currently the
chair of the ABC's Advisory Council, a board member of Chief Executive Women, Documentary Australia
and Women in Media. In 2019 Anita was made a member of the Order of Australia for her incredible
contribution.
Anita it's great to catch up with you today. Can I start by saying it feels like you've come a long
way from the girl who was expelled as a 15 year old at PLC in year 10. Can I ask you first up if
you could go back and talk to your 15 year old self what would you say? Push the boundaries like
I did when I was 15 because that's how you achieve success and I think look I think a lot of young
people when they're starting out they are pushing boundaries because often they don't know who and
what they are and it's only through life.
You discover you know who and what your capabilities are. I was fortunate I think a bit
like you Luke that I had a very influential father and he allowed influential in my life. I don't mean
that generally I mean that in my life and he actually created sort of some boundaries for me
but he gave me a lot of freedom to find out exactly who I was. So I think lots of young
people rebel when they're young and then they grow up and work out that in life you've actually got
to conform to a degree and probably not say exactly what you think.
Nita you've been an incredible pioneer in the male dominated media industry in Australia. How
difficult has it been for when you look back into the 1980s and it just seemed to be an incredibly
challenging environment for women. Can you reflect on what that was like?
Yes look I think growing up in commercial television as you say in the 1980s was pretty
tough for young women. We didn't have any female role models. There were no female mentors. All of
our bosses and senior bosses were male and it was a culture that was very much
quite a bullying and harassing culture and you just had to find the inner strength to actually
survive it and I remember for example I was working at the Today Show which was the old
nine network. I'm talking about the nine network of old not the nine network of today and I was
working as a supervising producer. You know that's the two I see on a particular television show
and today being exactly what Carl Stepanovich and Sarah Albo host today and I was
put my hand up to become the executive producer, the head of the program. Not once, not twice but
three times and I was passed over because I was young and I was a female and there were no young
females that were running any shows at the time. Not in news, not in current affairs, not sports,
not any entertainment or any other drama. They just didn't exist. So it was quite a tough culture
to grow up in but in some ways I'm glad that I did because it actually pushed me as an individual
to find skills and to be able to do what I wanted to do. So I think it was a really tough culture.
I guess the resilience that I probably didn't realize that I had and I think those things are
I think resilience particularly is really important. And you look back Anita and you know you think of
how heartbreaking that must have been for you having the skills and clearly the
ability and the dedication to do those roles better than male counterparts but you would
looked up into management it would have been all male and there just genuinely was I know the word
for it apart from that misogyny at the time that was commonplace and it just wasn't even
considered probably and it's not that long ago and I think it's what I admire a lot about you Anita
not only have you got the resilience out of it but you've genuinely been a champion
for wanting to tell those stories and to mentor other women going forward. Is that where that's
born out of for you the hardship that you faced? I think so. I think because I recognize from an
early stage that mentoring is really important. It actually empowers other individuals to recognize
their own skills and what they're capable of doing. So I think probably the most important thing is that
because I was so young and I was desperately looking for you know role models myself and my
role model was at home in my father but I didn't have any female role models whatsoever. So I've
gone into the industry and wherever possible I've mentored women. I also mentor you know men who are
in media industry as well because I find sometimes we just need others to tell us what we're really
good at and to point out what they can do and also to open door. Mentoring should also be about
opening doors as well to create a role model for women. I think that's a really important thing.
Opportunities for other people not just for yourself. So I'm really really passionate. I
co-chair an organization called Women in Media and that is all about empowering and mentoring
young women to find their capabilities, to find the resilience, the courage and to find where
their strengths lie and to go out into the workplace and really embrace whatever they
choose to do in life. And Anita the Jacoby Whatley scholarship is a great legacy as part of what you
do and and as you said the
change for me is that now you can see Anita Jacoby has been managing director. There actually
are those roles that you really pioneered and created and we've seen you know so many
brilliant females now that do the job as they could have done in the 80s had they been given
the opportunity. Has it changed where in 2023 are you comfortable with where the media shift because
it has been slow at times even from my experience working in the industry Anita. We've been slow
moving. We're happy to run programs on other people but not so much on the media. So I think
that's so good reflecting on our own space and we do it well enough now.
I certainly think it's it's a hell of a lot better than it was in the nineteen eighties. But I look at say for example commercial
network television. There has only been one female CEO of a commercial network and that has been Maureen Plasvick, who was in I think it was in 2001. So we're talking about now 22 years ago and there has not subsequently been a female CEO or maybe even a female CEO.
managing director of a commercial network in Australia. And so I feel that whilst we have
made a lot of progress, we haven't made enough progress in order to change that. And I still
think that the big companies, the major media players, their CEOs are predominantly men.
And until we change that, all of that culture and the way that we perceive things
flows from the top down. Yeah, it is a really great point you make. And obviously,
I spent a fair bit of time in the sporting world, Anita, in the AFL industry, and it feels like the
change there is happening a lot quicker. We've had several really successful presidents and
currently do of AFL clubs and CEOs currently in those roles and much more expanded across
board level and senior positions, albeit very slow in the 80s and 90s. So perhaps the media
industry still needs to put the mirror up and reflect back on its own performance. Can I go
back to Change Gear and talk to you about in the 1990s, you're working as a producer on 60 Minutes.
And you have horrific motorcycle accident results in having your leg amputated. Can you talk us
through what that experience was like? I mean, clearly horrible physically and emotional,
but how did you cope with that? Well, look, I've always from a very
young age been very fit and active, would throw myself into any sports. And I particularly love
surfing and diving and swimming. The ocean was my absolute retreat, and it still is.
I would always ride motorbikes up at a farm that we had, which was in far north,
western New South Wales. And unfortunately, I did, I was a pillion passenger and I had an accident,
which resulted in the loss of my leg. It was one of the most traumatic things that's happened to
me in my life. Not because I don't necessarily want to, it's just that I don't like to be branded
in that way. And I think people who have had accidents or have disabilities are often branded
in that way. I think it's becoming less obvious. Yes, it's incredibly traumatic when you're
incredibly active to lose a limb. And especially when you're a young female, and you pride yourself
on what you wear, how you look, and especially working in an industry where image was everything.
You know, when you look at the media, and you look at television, image is everything that we
reflect. And so I found that very difficult to deal with it. But what I did was I just jumped
back into work at 60 minutes. And I think that's what I did. And I think that's what I did. And I
went off and travelled the world. And I just relied on my capabilities and my get up and go
in order to achieve what I could achieve. And I don't view that my career has suffered
in any way whatsoever as a result. Yeah, which is amazing. I guess you said the
resilience that you've had across your life to be able to deal with that and compartmentalise it,
not want to share it for those reasons, which I can understand completely. But to then,
as you said, go and travel the world and continue doing the work you're doing with
60 Minutes is quite remarkable. You're an incredible storyteller. And I look back and
look through your work and read a lot of what you've done. And some of your investigative
journalism has been brilliant, including a famous story you broke in 2001 that was titled
The Body Snatchers. Can you tell us a little bit about that and why proper storytelling has been
really important to you? Yes. I was working for the Sunday program. And I don't know how many
of your listeners and viewers remember Sunday. It was hosted by Jim Whaley. And it was like a
premier current affairs show on a Sunday morning. Kerry Packer was a huge supporter of it. And we
used to do long form stories, cover stories. And my executive producer had asked me to go and
research the area of organ donation. And I spent a few weeks going through all these files and
reading stuff. And I wasn't getting anywhere. And all of a sudden, I came across a story about what
they were called ratters. And what had happened was they had been stealing from corpses at the
Glebe Morgue in Sydney, which is our
largest morgue. And the ratters had been stealing from corpses, you know, small amounts of money,
sand shoes. And what had happened were they were investigated by ICAC, the Independent Commission
Against Corruption here in New South Wales. And they had been fined and, you know, ostracized as
a result of that. And I couldn't work out why would ICAC investigate some people that were
stealing $10 here or sand shoes here. It just didn't seem a big enough story. So I started
contacting the ratters just to have a conversation.
And what I discovered through three of these people that I contacted was there was a far
bigger story that ICAC had failed to investigate, which was the widespread theft of body parts
by doctors, registered doctors from Glebe Morgue, with no permission from any relatives whatsoever.
So Helen Daly, the reporter, and I set out to tell the story of a body parts supermarket
at Glebe here in New South Wales, our leading morgue, where wholesale theft of body parts,
and I think the power of storytelling to make a change was in this case, that story went to air.
And in fact, it went to air on Sunday, and it went to air on my old alma mater, 60 Minutes.
And it created so much interest and government interest that it managed to change number of
government acts. So good storytelling, really positive storytelling, and admittedly, this
wasn't a positive story per se, can actually lead to fundamental change. And I think that's the
really, that's the gift of storytelling. And I think that's the gift of storytelling.
And it does take investment, as you said, Anita, Kerry Packer, a great, a great supporter,
you know, at the very top of the chain saying we need to invest in long form current affairs. So
people like you have got the budget to be able to go and actually find those stories and bring
them to attention. And, you know, very distressing, disturbing, I imagine for families that
had their loved ones' body parts harvested. It's a pretty gruesome story when you when you think
about it. How do you compare that, Anita, to the sort of clickbait world of 20,
23, where we're sucked into a headline that has no relevance at all to the actual truth of a
story? And it feels like long form journalism that you cut your teeth on is a bit of a dying art.
Well, there's still Four Corners. And, you know, there's still other programs that do long form
journalism, thank God. But I think that the rise and rise of misinformation and worse,
disinformation is absolutely, it's a real battle between public interest journalism
and what's happening in the media. And I think that's a really, really good story.
Because social media platforms, there is, I go on there, I go on to Twitter, for example,
and read a lot of the, you know, what people are talking about and what all the, you know,
key issues of the day are. And there is so much misinformation out there. And it's actually quite
disturbing. And I know people or organizations like Google are actually spending more money and
putting more money into actually media literacy, and actually combating misinformation and
disinformation, as do I'm involved with an organization called the Australian Journalist
and Media Authority. We are looking at misinformation and disinformation,
because it impacts on all of us. And we actually lose sight of what the truth is.
And that's good journalism, good journalism we need in a democracy, because it allows us to
understand the truth. And that's the fundamental core of all good story, all good storytelling and
journalism. And it's a really interesting time, Anita, on that front. And, you know,
passionate about leadership. And I feel going forward that the actual,
the search for facts and being able to verify that in a meaningful way is almost going to be a
currency going forward, because it's complex, isn't it? When you've got special interest and
huge amounts of money that have got an interest in maybe disinformation, as you said, or trying
to skew the truth, or even wholly owned independent advisory boards now that are infiltrated probably
by special interest at time as well to produce studies that favor better commercial outcomes,
it's, you know, the whole fake news, it sounds a bit like a pantomime at times, but it's now become
so hard, isn't it? We used to be able to sit around and have a debate, Anita, and say,
here's the facts, and we can disagree on our thoughts on what we should do with them. But
now we can't even agree on the facts. That seems like a hard genie to put back in the bottle.
That's right. It does. And then you look at America and what's happening with Trump,
and the rise and rise and rise of fake news. And it doesn't matter how many times,
you know, he's before the courts,
and he's, you know, there are the misdemeanors, and there are the charges and everything,
you know, the impeachment, still a percentage of the American population doesn't realize that
that's fake news. That's not just misinformation, it's disinformation. And it's deliberately going
out there. So it is actually infiltrating, it's impacting on the American culture more broadly.
That's a terrifying scenario in a democracy. It really is.
It is when you've got 74 million people who vote that way.
That's right.
And, you know, it's such a hotbed conversation. You'll get people who hear, you know, have a dog
in a fight to, apart from the fight for, as you said, factual information and truth, and it just
becomes so skewed, doesn't it? Any conversation used to be in America, you know, Democrats and
Republicans would be great friends and sit around at dinner and debate. Now we're armed, and we want
to actually, you know, kill each other because of our difference of opinion. It's, you know,
from a world where you came from,
where you genuinely could agree on how a good story was brought to the table. It is an interesting
time, isn't it? I don't know where it ends up. Well, I think it's quite scary in America,
because if you look at it, the country is so divided that, you know, it's almost, you think
to yourself, anything could start some sort of conflict within America, where I've always viewed
America as the heart of democracy. But you can't really say that now. Yeah, amazing time. I want to
pivot now to, you know, I think it's a really important time for us to be able to talk about the
story of your incredible memoir that you've written, Secrets Beyond the Screen, and congratulations.
It's a brilliant piece of work and enjoyed reading through in preparation for the central to the
story. And you've already mentioned your father, Philip, who was a World War II refugee who escaped
Germany, self-made businessman, started Sony here in Australia, amongst other incredible things. But
firstly, you start there. Tell us about your relationship with your dad. Look, I was really
fortunate to have a father who was very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very,
very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very. And I think
have a father who was very worldly. He was a much older dad. He was, you know, about almost 50 when
the time I was born. And he, as you rightly said, he had escaped Nazi Germany and fled to Australia,
the farthest country he could get to, away from what was happening and about to happen in Europe.
And he arrived with nothing here in Australia. And I think we often don't recognise how he was
a political refugee fleeing Nazi Germany, but how we could view those that flee either persecution
or come as migrants, what it's like to arrive in a new country with nothing and set up on your own,
which is what my father did. He was a very clever businessman, and he managed to create a company
that was listed on the Australian Stock Exchange. No mean feat, I don't think. And mind you, I'm
biased, of course. And you get this with your kids and your father and your...
Real relationships. But he was a very clever man, and he just taught me to feel very comfortable
as a young woman in my own skin. And I think if a parent can do that, particularly to a young woman
or, you know, to a young male, that's a really important thing. It sort of sets you up for the
life that you're going to pursue. He was a very, very strong role model for me.
And clearly, Anita, you've got great affection for your dad and the role that he played in your life,
which is...
As you said, what a gift, isn't it? You've got someone who has that influence over you. But you
open your book with a Nietzsche quote that I want to read back to you. Underneath this reality in
which we live and have our being, another and altogether different reality lies concealed. And
so you've uncovered through your research that there was a dark side to your dad and a past that
was somewhat disturbing is the only way I could describe it. How do you relate that to the person
that you loved and know when you've gone back and found out lots of things that you weren't able to
imagine yourself?
Look, I found that very difficult. I think most kids, a lot of kids have a very idealized version
of their parents and they accept their parents' life from when you're born and you move forward.
We very rarely ask our parents about their lives before you came on the scene. And then when you
come on the scene, it's all about going to tennis lessons or ballet or whatever. So about many years
after he'd passed away, I was at a dinner party. And I was at a dinner party and I was at a dinner party
and lots of lawyers and journalists, a lot of alcohol had been drunk. And all of a sudden,
one of the lawyers looks me directly in the face and said, do you know about this infamous court
case involving your father in the 1950s? And he bounced off some legal cases that we'd been
talking about. And when he said that about this infamous legal case in the 1950s, way before I was
born, I had no idea what he was talking about. And I, like most of us, thought that I knew my
parents and I knew my father and I knew him. And I thought, well, I don't know. I don't know. I don't
know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't
know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. But I actually knew probably this of
that. And yes, I uncovered some really dark parts about his past that I had no knowledge of, which
is, as a storyteller and as a journalist and a producer, quite confronting to find after you've
told hundreds and hundreds of stories all over the world, only to find the most extraordinary story
in your own family, in your own backyard that you weren't aware of, was quite confronting.
And especially when I found out things about him that I'm not sure that he would have wanted me to
find out about, to be honest. Nietzsche was referring to the fact that we all have our
secrets, that we are like icebergs. You can see that top bit, but there's not a lot that you can
see below the surface. And we keep a lot of stuff to ourselves. And I think as a father,
you might appreciate some of that. I don't judge my father for the decisions that he made in his
life. But I really found that I was confronted by some of those decisions and found them quite
disturbing. Yeah, that's an incredible perspective you've got, Anita, that forgiving element to you.
I think most people would struggle when you uncover that two of his partners committed
suicide, not that long apart, and the same tragic way. And your half-sister at the age of four was
sent off to boarding school in what has to be a fairly brutal way. I mean, they're
not great reflections, are they, as an independent person looking at someone who was brilliant to
you. How do you sort of reconcile with that, that clearly he had an amazing impact on you in a
positive way, but perhaps didn't have that with others? It's a hard one to get your head around,
isn't it? It is. It is. And look, I recognise that we're all flawed individuals. Some have
greater flaws than others. I don't condone his behaviour, but I also
think maybe he was attracted to vulnerable women, as some men are. I don't try and rationalise it,
and I don't try and excuse what happened. It would have been a terrible circumstance to have been
in that position that he was. And I also, what I've learnt with my sister that you referred to
who was four when she was sent off to boarding school, I can rationalise that in the sense that
if you're a man who's arrived with nothing, and you have a young child, and you don't have
a mother for that child, and you have to try and somehow make an income during the war,
you know, and after the war, times were really tough for people. So I can step back and very
objectively try and look at that. What it's given me is an understanding of my sister better,
which I think is a gift in the sense that we get on much better now, because I understand some of
the factors that influenced her life when she was growing up, that I had no understanding of when I
was younger. Clearly, that resilience comes out in
you.
And all the storytelling, and I'm full of admiration for the way you handle it. Even
that story, I think, would sort of rock a lot of people. What are the traits you think that help
you to be able to get that perspective? I think because I'm quite pragmatic,
I like to get to the truth of whatever I'm doing. I think it's really important knowing truth,
not just as a journalist or television producer, but as an individual, understanding truth and
getting to that, and then being able to put it into a story. And I think that's really important.
process that truth. And recognizing that's part of your heritage, that's part of your background.
It doesn't define who you are. But it's you, you come to a recognition that that has actually
shaped who and what you are. I, as I said earlier, I now see that my father was a much more flawed
and complex man than I ever imagined when I was growing up. Does it make me love him less? No,
it doesn't. I still love him very dearly. But I now see him with a different lens.
And I think that's, for me, at my age, when I think probably one of my greatest regrets is I
could never sit down and have this conversation with him and ask him all the dozens and dozens
and dozens of questions I'd love to ask him. Well, I can't do that now.
And as you said, we, yeah, sorry to interrupt. As you said, we are all, you know, flawed at every
level, to the core, all of us, isn't it? And we choose to show the parts of us to those that are
closest to us. And everyone has.
An element to them. It's, yeah, profound story the way that, as you said, you've been telling
stories all around the world. To have one so close to home that you didn't know about is quite
remarkable. I love what you've done, Anita, in the leadership space around mentoring women. And
I lifted off a whole range of actionable things that you do. You know, you look after and make
sure that people have a better opportunity and maybe an easier path than you've had.
When we sit down and talk to people like you,
I feel like there's some successfully clues, patterns around how people do have a successful
life. And we often start with this idea of self-leadership, but it's hard to actually
impact someone else without an idea of your own self-leadership. Does that make sense to you?
Yeah, it does. It does. I think self-leadership is actually living life with a purpose.
And I've always done that, actually, since I was fairly young. You know, I grew up in a household
where we did support, you know, those less privileged,
I think I mentioned my father was very successful. And so I was taught always to
support and help others that are less privileged than yourself. And I think I've applied that
throughout my life. And having a meaning and a purpose in life gives you a perspective on who
and what you are. And I think that's really for, you know, self-leadership, that's a really
important aspect of it. Having purpose and having purpose in leadership is really,
really important. And having purpose and meaning, you know, all feeds into one another,
but it comes directly from you as a leader and your personal values. And I think personal values
are getting increasingly important. I think, you know, in days gone by, we didn't really talk about
empathy and emotional quotient, and we might have talked about resilience and courage,
but we never talked about how you deal with people on an empathetic level. And I think increasingly,
what I'd call a human,
human principles of leadership are becoming more and more critical in the way that you
manage and interact with people. And that's why we love sharing these
stories in lots of ways, Anita, because, you know, empathy is a skill in some ways. Some
people are born with a lot of natural empathy, but you can practice it. You can actually
pass that on and want to, you know, particularly in a position of power to be more empathetic.
There's no downside to that at all. And your description is really apt. How do you go about
positively impacting others in your
environment? You've been in a lot of diverse environments, and we see people really conscious
now about the impact they have on everyone on a daily basis.
Oh, I think it's an attitude of caring. I mean, if I would walk into an office every day,
and whoever's sitting on the reception desk or wherever, I will always say, hello,
how are you? Just those simple things that show that you care about them. And I'll engage in
conversations, not just on a work level, but on a social level, so I understand how people are
feeling. I think
listening is a really important element of this. And I probably, because I've, you know,
worked with Andrew Denton and John Laws, and I've listened to great interviews,
the art of listening gets lost in a lot of leadership. It's not just hearing or thinking
that you're hearing what somebody's saying, but actually stepping back and trying to analyze what
they are really saying. And also the art of active listening, that, you know, the body language that
somebody's exhibiting is actually really interesting in probably, actually, I don't know,
showing you what they're not saying, as opposed to what they are saying. So I think there are some
certain leadership skills that are really important, that aren't hard to actually adopt in
your leadership style. And when you talk about empathy, I guess I'm fortunate in, or fortunate,
I've told stories with a lot of, in a lot of cases where there's been great tragedy,
and I've had to muster those skills of empathy and really apply them. For example, looking after
the families of the Ivermellat backpacker,
a case, you know, I looked after four of the families throughout three months of a trial here
in Sydney. That was one of the toughest things I ever worked on. Sitting in a court, hearing the
most appalling evidence day in, day out for three months, with four families and looking after those
families, you can't but not be empathetic to what they've experienced. And I think empathy comes
from actually understanding other people, and understanding that they are facing sometimes the
most horrendous of situations. And I think that's one of the things that I've worked on,
or less. It could be a drug and alcohol problem. It could be, you know, anything. You need to find
that empathy, and you need to learn to have empathy. And when we've all been in that situation,
that's what you want, isn't it, from those around you, is that just authentic sense that someone
cares. But clearly, you haven't done what you've done in your life, Anuta, without a clear vision
and a sense of purpose. How have you gone about sharing and creating that vision for your life
that has been pioneering, is the word I've used a couple of times.
Oh, look, I think I've always liked to look at innovation as a part of, you know, how am I going
to share a vision and create a vision. I was at one stage managing director of ITV, which is,
as you mentioned earlier, it's the Australian operation of the British conglomerate and,
you know, PLC company. And I walked in to start as managing director and found there was only
one commission, you know, which was only, was worth less than $2 million. We had a lot of
staff, a large number of contractors. So I immediately started to think, well, I have to
have a vision for this company. I have to actually have a strategic approach as a leader. And my
approach was literally to start hanging out the shingle to attract digital natives and creative
people, start building programs around known celebrities that networks would want to buy
programs from, you know, and featuring. I looked at the formats that ITV, not just me, it was with
a team. I don't want to take all the credit for this.
I worked with a team. We looked at some of the formats that ITV had internationally,
and we recognised that we could adapt them to the Australian marketplace. So I was providing
a vision and a direction on what this company could do. And as a result, we successfully,
I successfully sold I'm a Celebrity to 10, which is still on air today, and which has done very
well for 10. We sold The Chase to Channel 7, which turned Channel 7's fortunes around.
So it was coming in and looking at an organisation,
and thinking, how can I take this organisation, which was Morabund, to the next level by looking
at those forces about the digital world, about digitising assets, looking at those things that
you could do as a leader, but setting an example and actually provoking discussion and ideas,
creative ideas, and creating a hotbed for ideas. Because that's what, at the end of the day,
in my industry, it's all about ideas and creativity.
And the courage to get them, you know, to the line, isn't it?
It's a lot of fail. And then, as you said, there are a couple of huge transformative
success stories, I'm a Celebrity and The Chase for both those networks. But in a competitive space,
you can't have too many misses. And I always admire, as you said, the creative space of being
able to do that regularly, to me, is a skill that's really fascinating to understand. And
clearly, you've done a great job with that. We see leaders that have the success, like we've
just talked about with you, are really curious. And through curiosity, that's how they
think about constantly learning and get better. What do you think about curiosity?
Oh, I think it's, well, I'm a journalist. I go to a dinner party, and I never, it's interesting,
I'm sitting talking to you today, but I'll go to a dinner party, and I'll ask whoever's sitting
around me a thousand questions, but I'll never say anything. I think curiosity is really, really
vital. Because, I mean, if you're not curious about the world, curious about the people you
associate with, curious about the business that you're running, curious about being,
you know, a good leader, then how can we possibly succeed? Curiosity should be at the heart of
everything that we do.
Beautifully, beautifully said. You're in the communications business as well, and we see
now communicating with clarity is a skill that a lot of leaders are really passionate about.
That's been your stock standard trade from day one. How have you gone about it?
Well, communication to me is about telling stories. So it's really about informing and,
you know, entertaining audiences, but also it's really about listening. Again, what I was saying
earlier, in order to communicate, you need to listen, because you need to understand what
somebody is saying in order to communicate back to them. And as I said earlier, it's actually about
often what people are not saying rather than what they are saying. And look, I've been fortunate to
be involved with, you know, hundreds and hundreds of interviews from Bill Clinton to some of the
people that you named earlier. I've listened to some of the great communicators of the world,
communicate. They're very clear, they're very sharp, they're on message. They've got, you know,
what they're setting out to say, whatever that is, very clearly. And you can tell in interviews,
and I've listened to enough of them to know what that message is. So that's what communicating is
about. It's being able to actually talk to somebody on a one-on-one and come away and,
you know, really feel like you've both gained something from that communication, whatever that
is. I'm sorry, it sounds a bit naff, but I think...
I think communication's at the heart of everything that we do.
I agree wholeheartedly. And, you know, we love sharing the different perspectives on it,
isn't it, from someone that is in the communications industry, but it's overlooked
often in other spheres around just how much you can achieve by consistently communicating well
with your team or being, you know, informed. And you look at people in different areas and
different spaces. The ones that succeed consistently are really, really understanding.
You don't have to be a naturally great orator,
or, you know, come up with brilliant inspirational quotes, but it's just the
consistency of it, I think, in lots of ways, Anita, is a real pattern that we're seeing.
Likewise with collaboration. How important has collaboration been for you?
Oh, incredibly important. I mean, I've been fortunate to collaborate with some very
talented and creative people. I spent 10 years collaborating with Andrew Dent, and
that was one of... That was a fantastic partnership. You know, we collaborated on enough rope,
which was a very successful interview show. We collaborated on the Gruen Transfer,
which was a very innovative program. Can you imagine going to the ABC and trying to sell
a program on advertising when you've got a charter that says you can't have ads on the ABC?
It's genius, isn't it, Anita? I'd love to, sorry, just jump in there. And Gruen,
with my great old mate, Will Anderson as host, is still just brilliant. And, you know,
that creative idea that came out of your space with Andrew Dent, it's brilliant, isn't it? To take
to the ABC was such success. Worth pressing pause for a moment to understand how good that was.
Well, but I've got to say, Luke, it originally started, the Gruen Transfer originally started
as three one-hour documentaries. And then what we realised was there was so much material there,
it then became apparent that you could build a panel show. But yes, as I said,
going into pitch that day, the Gruen Transfer to the head of editorial policy and the director
of television, and they're sitting there looking at us, they're like,
this is brilliant. This is brilliant. This is brilliant. This is brilliant. This is brilliant.
15 years ago now, it's been on air. I think this is heading into its 15th season.
They just looked at us blankly, like, how could you possibly, how could we possibly
put ads on the ABC? But then they came around to recognising that what we were doing was actually
looking at the psychology of people and what advertising tells us about ourselves. And so
once we were able to flip it and show them, they embraced the idea straight away. And Will
Anderson has been absolutely fabulous as a host. He's a brilliant host. And
Yeah.
Russell Howcroft, I love those, the most passionate person about advertising,
having Russ sitting there on the ABC, brilliantly cast and a great piece of creativity.
And then who's been the greatest leader in your life?
The greatest leader, I think, probably a man called Kevin Weldon. Kevin Weldon,
to your audience, if they don't know of him, he formed and founded a company called Paul
Hamlins here in Australia. It was one of the largest book publishing,
publishing companies in Australia, extremely successful. And I worked with Hamlins when I
first came out of school. And Kevin was an incredibly entrepreneurial man. So I was about
18. And I started there and we were given mini minors and we were dressed up in outfits and
sent out to sell books because he was such an entrepreneurial character. But what he taught
me really was to always not to be afraid of risks at all. At 18, he gave us all an
assignment. There were eight of us, eight marketing trainees that he brought on straight
out of school. And the assignment was that we had to go and ring somebody important and set up an
interview and go and interview them. Now you can imagine at 18, I was pretty intimidated by that,
even having had a very strong father. I was given Sir Robert Norman, who was then the CEO of the
Bank of New South Wales, which is now the Westpac Bank. And I went home and I did all my research
and I spent an hour with Sir Robert Norman talking about the economy. I knew nothing,
about the economy, I've got to say. I just sat there and actually spent an hour talking to him.
What it taught me was that anybody's accessible. And Kevin Weldon gave me these great skills to
recognise resilience, courage, entrepreneurial, being entrepreneurial. He was just a terrific
boss to have at a young age in my life. And he informed a lot of my thinking about the way to
approach business and be a leader.
Yeah, what a great,
what a great idea, isn't it? Have an 18-year-old go and interview someone at that level of CEO of a
bank in that time. It must have been transformative. It can clearly set you on a path too, didn't it,
to securing interviews with people. As you said, everyone's human, everyone has got a story to tell
and why not with you? And that's formed a big part of your life. If you could collaborate with
anyone on anything, as you said, you have worked with Andrew Denton and John Laws and, as you said,
back to the Kerry Packer era.
Through Current Affair, has it been someone you thought, God, this would be in any area of your
life that you'd love to collaborate with?
Do you know who I wished I'd been able to collaborate with when he was much younger
was Sir David Attenborough. Because I just feel here he is, he's 95 or 96. And he had a recognition
about endangered species. And he had a recognition about the way that the planet was changing with
climate. And I wish we'd been able to tell that story about 30 years ago.
So when my collaboration is actually a retrospective of going back and being able to actually inform
people far earlier than we really started to become aware of this issue. And I think he was
one of the shining lights, both an endangered species and the nature of climate change. And
I would love to have collaborated with him to tell stories then in order to educate audiences
about how audiences, the whole of society, about how important these issues are.
Remarkable human being in every sense of the word.
And still creating incredible stories and wisdom around, as you said, someone that picked that
many, many, many years ago. Anita, it's a great story of yours. I love
listening to it, understanding the industry a little bit and what you were able to do to break
new ground for so many females. And what I love even more as much is just how you are passing
that on and in a really profound way of mentoring the next generation to break through what was a
challenging situation. And congratulations on all your work and your book is fantastic. Have a
look at it. It's genuinely worth a read, a great memoir and a fascinating, intriguing story along
the way. I couldn't believe the twist and turn. So thanks for joining me today.
Isn't it incredible? I mean, every chapter, every time I sat down to write a chapter,
I realised there was another story. So it's just, in some ways, as I said earlier,
it's really easily the hardest story I've told.
Secrets beyond the screen with Anita.
Jacoby, thanks for joining me today.
Luke, thank you so much for your time. I appreciate it.
Thank you for listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast, powered by Temper,
a mattress like no other. And to make sure you don't miss an episode,
click subscribe wherever you get your podcasts.