I think the best leaders we've had in our country, a Bob Hawke or a Keating or a Howard,
they're not tortured in their language and they know what they believe in and they're
willing to fight for it.
And sometimes you can get yourself in trouble because it's not filtered or there's a full
stop instead of a comma, so the qualification in the sentence is not included in the grab
on the news.
And sometimes, you know, I listen to the PM at the moment and I think he's trying to
please everyone on the issue and you've got to stand up for what you believe in and you're
not going to please everyone.
And if you're trying to please everyone, then generally it means you haven't arrived at
the right outcome.
So I think decomplicate it and don't forget where you've come from and keep your feet
on the ground.
I think they're always good lessons.
Hello, welcome to another episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
At Alita, we are passionate about inspiring connections and creating a world of collaboration.
Our signature program, Alita Connect, curates groups of five to six leaders from diverse
backgrounds in sport, industry, social venture and the arts who come together to learn, to
connect and to collaborate.
Dr. Troy Flanagan, Vice President of Performance for the Milwaukee Bucks.
I've probably had some of the most radical changes out of that leadership group.
The significance of their work and how much it's really about helping others.
It made me think, what else could I be doing?
And I approached our owner and within a few weeks, we'd raised $5 million to try and solve
obesity in the underprivileged community in Milwaukee.
So that's one spark that that leadership course has caused to contribute and leave the world
as a better place.
Umrah Omer, founder of Safari Doctors.
It defines the word creativity for me.
The ability to like see connections.
Where none seem to exist.
And I think that's the magic of Alita.
Definitely not my usual, you know, workshop panels like humanitarian spaces, but more
of an intentional dissection of leadership.
The Empowering Leaders podcast is proudly brought to you by Victoria University, where
cutting edge sports and exercise science facilities like heat chambers, performance labs and altitude
environments mean VU is ranked seventh in the world.
And that's the magic of Alita.
Thank you.
As always, a big thank you to Jason Nicholas and his team at Tempur-Bedding, a mattress
like no other.
If you enjoy listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast, be sure to subscribe.
And please, if you have a moment, we would love you to leave a review so we can reach
more listeners and empower more leaders.
Peter Dutton is hoping to be the next Prime Minister of Australia.
And on the Empowering Leaders podcast, we aim to tell great leadership stories.
We have invited the current Prime Minister of Australia, Peter Dutton.
current Prime Minister Anthony Albanese, and hope to have him on the podcast as well soon.
Peter, I first met you around 12 years ago, and we share a great mutual friend,
Geoffrey Thomas, who we were just talking about before we hit record. And over the last 10 years,
I've had the great pleasure of meeting Kiralee and your family. And declaring this interview,
I consider you a friend. And I think when people ask me about Peter Dutton, the words I use is
the most misrepresented person in public life that I've ever met. In a short space of time,
you're a great chance to be the next Prime Minister of Australia. I thought I'd start with,
in your own words, what's Peter Dutton really like?
Well, Darce, great to be with you. Thank you, mate. And thanks for your leadership. But
look, I think people can get to know you through longer form interviews. And
instead of just the soundbites on a package, you know, TV of a night time in the news,
and as the campaign goes on, I hope people can see more of my story and who I am and my
background. And people can make their own judgments instead of being defined by your
opponents or those who have an axe to grind. So I'm a pretty open book. I'm not too complicated
in that sense. I'm just happy to be open and honest about my values, what I stand for. And
that's the basis on which I make decisions. And people, as I say, can draw a positive or
negative conclusion out of that.
I don't sort of, I've never gone into politics to crave that popularity or that recognition.
It's just, that's not been part of my, you know, my sort of being. And I'm pretty
comfortable in my own skin.
Your wife clearly described you as this, relaxed, very gentle, empathetic. He's a great mate. He's
a good son. He's an excellent dad. And that's the person that I've met. As you said just then,
the opposition did this, maybe too good a job of painting of some sort of
Batman villain at times. And do you think that now in these sort of formats,
people are starting to see the real version of you?
Yeah, I think so. I think people stop you and say, oh, I heard that interview the other day,
and I didn't know this about you. I hadn't heard that before. And it's funny because I've been in
public life for over 23 years or so. And people have seen me through the lens of being the sports
minister or immigration minister or health minister or home affairs minister, defence
minister, whatever it might be, that sort of snapshot and that point in time. And leader of
the house. I mean, some of these roles, you sort of take on the attack dog role, which is a necessary
one in the parliament. It's an adversarial environment. And I've always said that I went in
to politics, not wanting to sit on the fence, but stand up for what I believe in. And it's a game of
of tackle, not touch.
If you, you know, if you walk away with your head held high, didn't make every call as you would want
in hindsight, but not to live with those regrets. And yeah, I think that's, people can appreciate
that.
First thing, whenever I see you always ask about family, as you did first thing this morning,
I just thought you could go back and tell us about your extended family,
mum and dad and your siblings growing up and your current family.
Yeah, so pretty humble, sort of out of suburbs upbringing. And, you know,
dad was a big fan of my dad. He was a big fan of my dad. He was a big fan of my dad.
Worked hard. Mum worked hard. Raised five kids and really, you know, they sacrificed and went
without to give us a good education, sort of, I guess, second tier school, not sort of first tier
private schools that they couldn't afford back in the day. But, you know, mum took in kids as a
family daycare mum to pull some extra dollars together to save to send us to school. Dad
started out as a bricklayer and a builder and ultimately was, you know,
successful in, through hard work and his endeavours and, you know, with mum's support. So
that was the grounding. It was a, you know, a carefree life and jumping on the bike and
playing backyard cricket until dark, you know, jumping around in the pool, the above ground pool
in those days in the backyard. And, you know, I think it gives you an appreciation,
A, of what you've got now, but also,
that there are a lot of people in humble households right now who are really doing it tough.
Oldest of five?
Yes.
Are you close to the siblings?
Yeah, I am. Yeah, I am. And there's 10 years between myself and my youngest sister
and they're all different, different jobs. And, but we've always remained close. And my mum and
dad separated when I finished year 12 in 1987. Sort of, you know, I guess one of those
family days.
It's one of those dynamics where you wait until, you know, you finished year 12 before they separated.
And that was, you know, that was a messy situation. And for us as siblings, it probably drew us
closer together. But we grew up as kids with a really close relationship with our cousins. And
that was, you know, a real highlight for me as a child growing up. And
I've wanted that for our kids as well, to be close to, you know, my, my brother and sisters,
their kids. And they are, and it's nice to see them together and, you know,
seeing them playing together. And it's also the highlight for, you know, we sort of congregate
largely at dad's place and, and, you know, it's the joy of his life as well. And it's good to
see him enjoying the grandkids and the joy that comes with seeing all of them together.
I think, Peter, that immediately it humanises people when you know their backstory,
and, and, and even your own, you were married at 23 for a short time. And I think
Rebecca, your beautiful daughter was with a partner you're engaged with, and you meet Kiraly
pretty soon after, who's been your lifelong partner. You had the two boys with, that's a
bit of complexity for a young man at that stage, mate. How did you, how'd you work your way through
all that? I didn't do too well to start with. So I was married at 23 and, and we'd, we'd sort of
lived together for, I don't know, 12, 18 months or something before that.
And I, you know, I picked my then wife up from, she was a nurse and picked her up from work one day
and after a night shift and she just said, look, I don't love you anymore. And I tried to work on
that, but it just didn't work. And, and I was working two jobs. I was, you know, you know,
keen to make money and, and try and set ourselves up. She wanted to travel and, and it was just,
you know, we were too young for that relationship. And, and it was,
yeah, it was confronting because I'd always, particularly with my parents having separated,
which really, you know, upset and, and, and, you know, and I didn't cope with that well
at the time as a, as a 17 year old. And I always thought, you know, I wanted to get married and I
wanted to be for life and I wanted to raise a big family and, and, and that wasn't the case. And
yeah, so that was- Did it knock you around?
Yeah, it did. And it, yeah, it sort of, it takes,
takes a while to recover from that. And, you know, that I guess you, you deal with all those
knockbacks and setbacks. And, and when you look at it with the benefit of hindsight,
it was just a level of immaturity and, and, you know, there was no third parties or anything
like that. It was just, just the reality of, for me, working two jobs and working hard and,
and, and yeah, it just, we were together at the wrong time.
One of those two jobs was as a police officer.
Yeah.
You started out, I know you, you spent some time as a kid working in a butcher shop as well. What,
what drew you to, to want to be in uniform and tell us about that time?
But I'd wanted to be a policeman from a young age. I don't know why. I mean, I listened to my
mother's advice, which you should always do, I suppose, but, you know, no one in our family
had been to university before and she was keen for me to go and, and, you know, and I was keen
to go too. But I started out doing a bachelor of business. I really wanted to go to university.
I wanted to go to the police academy, but, but she wanted me to do that. And, and it was good
advice. I did it for two years and I, I was majoring in accountancy, which I didn't enjoy.
So I decided to, to defer and I finished my degree later on, but I went into policing because I
couldn't see myself, you know, sitting in a bank nine to five behind a desk or an accountancy firm
or something like that. I, and, and I liked the, you know, sort of the pace or the excitement or
the, you know, the, you know, the, you know, the, you know, the, you know, the, you know, the, you
know, the, the unknown factor within a policing career. And that's, I guess what I enjoyed. And
it's a little bit like this job. You don't know what the news cycle holds today. You don't know
the next question in a, in an, in an interview, which is not encouragement to ask a horrible
question, but, but as a policeman, you just don't know what that next radio call is going to be or
what's behind that door that, you know, that you're about to, to enter. And there is, for me,
I've, you know, I've always sort of been attracted to that, um, to that dynamic.
The, the theme that I understand runs through your life as a, as a policeman, you were
zero tolerance on violence against women and children and, and fast track to your political
life. I want to ask you about what I think might be one of your proudest achievements, the
formation of ACE, the Australian Centre to Counter Child Exploitation. It's a,
it's a hundred million dollar investment. It's regarded as a global leader in that space.
Is that,
is that the reason why you're drawn to politics, the chance to, to do things like that?
Yeah, uh, short answer is yes. And, uh, I'm incredibly proud of what, you know, the work
that the, the police and the analysts and, uh, all of the tech people do. And, and for those,
you know, who aren't aware of the work, it's really interesting to have a look at them online,
actually, because they are, it's, it's a function of the Australian Federal Police
and they counter child exploitation here, but in the region as well. So, uh, they,
you know,
I think they've, they've saved now over 1500 lives of, of young kids that were in the hands
of pedophiles or subject to those networks. And the, the technical aspect of it, where they can
look at a photo, an image, uh, of a child sitting at the end of a bed or, uh, in a car, and they can
analyse that to try and identify where, you know, and, and the circumstances, um, of, of, you know,
that child being at risk and how they can recover that child. It's the talent and the expertise is
amazing, but it was underfunded and it wasn't a priority. Uh, and when I came into that portfolio
and had responsibility for the federal police, I, I really, well, I gave it a direction to the
commissioner to prioritise that because in my household, you know, we, we were just very
fortunate that, you know, it, you know, there was no sexual abuse that, that I was aware of in my
world I'd never seen, or I probably had a pretty naive upbringing, but, but as a police officer,
a 19 year old, uh, you know,
walking into domestic violence situations and seeing blood splattered across the walls or
kids screaming and, you know, uh, you know, grabbing onto mum or dad's leg, uh, as, you know,
people are fighting, all of that is just horrible and scars you. And, uh, and I'd work then in the
sex offender squad, uh, where you're taking statements from rape victims or visiting crime
scenes and, uh, interviewing offenders and taking people through the courts and the frustration of
that process when, uh, there's not,
an adequate sentence given at the end of it. And so, yes, I mean, that, that's been a driver for me
and the protection of women and children, I think is paramount because I think the, the, the protection
of that innocence of their upbringing and allowing them to be children, uh, and allowing women to,
uh, you know, to live their lives freely as, uh, as, as most men would expect. I just think it's
a human right and it's, it's, it's not a given, unfortunately.
Bizarrely, uh, I used to sit in a breakfast radio studio, Peter, for 11 years and, and you read the
paper front and center, and it's, it's, it's not a given, unfortunately.
Every day because you're looking at the news. Hidden on page 18 would be some horrific,
you know, child sex offense that had two, two paragraphs. On the front page would be
some footballer, you know, with a new girlfriend and you, and you think,
have we got our priorities so wrong? It doesn't seem as though the, the thing that I know drives
you gets the attention from mainstream. Have you got a theory on that?
Uh, yeah, look, I do. And I, I think it's a, it's a real societal issue because
at one level it's understandable.
At dinner parties, you know, people will be talking about, you know, houses being broken into or cars being stolen or the, you know, the gangland wars or the tobacco shop, you know, arsons, whatever it might be, because it's in the news.
People can see the footage and, you know, it affects them.
But the next conversation about the pedophile ring that's just been discovered and the child that's been sexually abused, understandably, people don't want to talk about that either in front of their children or at a dinner party where people are trying to enjoy each other at a barbecue, whatever it might be.
And it's wrong because we have to lift the veil.
The images of these offenders are blurred out because the law requires that to be.
The names are normally protected.
And so the footage is, you know, there's no CCTV from the robbery at the service station that people can see and conceptualize and see the violence that, you know, that was the subject of that crime.
And so I just think as a society, we have to accept that this is a very significant, you know, crime type.
And it really, yeah.
It upsets me that we don't talk more about it because I think the awareness, encouraging children to speak up, encouraging adults to look for signs, all of that hopefully would lead to a reduction in the incidents.
But sadly, it doesn't.
I want to chat to you about, you know, a few of the issues that you seem to find clarity on whether people agree with you or not.
We caught up, I don't know if you remember, had a beer in the city in Melbourne and the voice to parliament had just been,
and you asked me about it and I really hadn't understood it at all.
And the idea that our Indigenous brothers and sisters would have a voice in the government of Australia and on the surface, everyone who cares about Indigenous Australians,
immediately you think about what you can do and what that means.
You just come back from visiting a number of the remote Indigenous communities and mid-sentence you stopped and you actually had a tear.
And you were talking about just how horrific.
Some of the circumstances that you'd seen, where and how much it affected you.
And yet in public life, you were opposed to the voice.
And I think someone in parliament would have even called you a racist at the time.
And I'm just, this theme of this person I know that cares deeply versus this image is polar opposites.
Can you tell us about how you arrived to that decision?
So just go back a second though.
We caught up for a beer and I think you introduced me to some low-carb trendy beer that I hadn't had before.
Yeah.
Which you got.
Which you graciously said was okay.
I gave you a gluten-free beer, mate, and you went, mate.
I sucked it down.
It was okay.
Yeah.
So look, mate, every Australian wants a better outcome for Indigenous Australians.
And it's not a lack of money.
The money is there.
And it's this huge funnel that just becomes a drip at the end when you get to these communities.
And you go up to a place like Gove to Unupingu land and you look at the great work that he did during his life.
His lifetime and what his brothers and others are doing there now.
But there's a 90% attendance rate at school.
I walked into a classroom where these young kids were preparing for a robotics competition
in the United States.
They were travelling from this little Indigenous community to the US and they were just beaming
with excitement.
And they were in uniform.
And, you know.
Barker College had a relationship with this local school and it was just an amazing demonstration
of leadership within a community where they had a sustainable logging business, a building
business, the streets were clean, health services were provided, and it was a functioning society.
And I was in that classroom with those kids and I don't mind saying, I went to the side
and I can be a bit emotional sometimes, but I had to compose myself because what I'd seen
there compared to what I'd seen only a couple of hours by plane away in other communities
was just chalk and cheese.
And in some communities where you've got kids who are living in complete squalor, kids who
are out breaking into homes or businesses and stealing cars over nighttime because they're
afraid to go.
They're afraid to go home to an unsafe environment and they sleep during the day, therefore they
miss school.
And the contrast, it just really hit me that why can these kids live a life that we would
expect for all of our kids, but exactly the same kids, Australians, each one of them in
another community like Alice Springs can't enjoy that normality.
And so I just thought the voice was...
Ultimately more about the elites than it was about those kids and about their parents.
And you speak to the elderly women and the elders otherwise in the communities and the
town camps, they want what every parent does across the country.
They want a stable home environment.
They want an education for their kids.
They want health.
They want running water and they want to have jobs there for their kids as they graduate
from school.
And the whole conversation is diverted by a group of people that care more about themselves
than the people they're supposed to represent.
And I want to see those kids going into a trade.
I want to see them going to university.
I want to see them enjoying the normality of life.
And I don't think that's too much to ask for.
And I just thought the voice was going to be an entrenchment or an enshrinement in the
constitution of something that was going to set back.
I don't think that's going to set back the prospects of Indigenous people for a long
time.
But you've been handed the tough portfolios traditionally of defence and immigration and
these complex issues, just like the one you described then.
And you have a way of seeing through difficult issues, even when they're really emotional.
When we've got people detained on places like Manus Highland and immigration detention centres,
anyone understands how horrific that is.
How do you...
Even when you sit in those leadership roles, how do you come to a clear decision?
Do you wrestle with that or how would you explain something like that?
Look, they're tough decisions.
But in the end, if you're the Home Affairs Minister, when the file lands on your desk,
it's gone through 10 other hands and the decision ultimately hasn't been made by those people.
And so it's the toughest of decisions you're presiding over.
And normally, you look at the...
There's facts before you and there's a terrible decision and just two degrees less than that.
It's the devil's curse in terms of the decision you've got before you.
But ultimately, your job is to take a decision that's in our country's best interest, that's
going to provide a safe outcome for Australians.
It's going to preserve our sovereignty or our rule of law.
And that's the...
I guess the lens that you have to look at.
You have to look at it through and you have to look obviously at the human side.
And there are countless visas that I issued for kids and for their parents and parents
whose mother or father had come here from a part of the world and had a stroke or been
diagnosed with dementia and couldn't return home.
And you do all of that without the public seeing any of it.
And when I went into the portfolio, there were kids in detention and boats obviously
had arrived.
And...
Our desire was A, to stop the boats and then to get the kids out of detention.
I was proud that on my watch, we got everyone out.
And if you don't have border security and you don't have integrity, then people take
advantage of that.
And the people smugglers will take the money off innocent men, women and children because
they're just another commodity.
And when the people aren't there paying the money, they're running prostitutes, they're
running the human trafficking, they're running drugs.
They're running drugs.
They're running tobacco.
These people just don't have the same set of standards that we do.
And you have to deal with that and you have to try and take that business model away from
them because ultimately people drown at sea and kids end up in detention.
The much better way to run the migration program is to bring people in in a regularised way,
give them an opportunity.
I mean, we brought in thousands of women who were Yazidis and the Yazidis had been subject
to sexual servitude and had been raped and brutalised by ISIS and ISIL.
And those women came in, have made amazing Australians, have started a life that their
parents, that they could never have imagined themselves as children.
And two, three, four, 10 generations time, those kids and those generations will be talking
about how brave they are.
They're great, great, great grandmothers.
They're great, great grandmothers who came to Australia and, so you've got to get that
balance right.
I guess that's the point.
Speaker 1 We all are born different.
As we grow, the experiences we have develop into outlooks, uniquely our own, charting
our life's course.
No one sees an idea, opinion, or opportunity like you.
And no one sees you like me.
Speaker 1 It's not like you.
Like VU.
Victoria University.
Uniquely you.
Hi, my name's Mim.
I do a Bachelor of Social Work.
I got this tattoo done for my 20th birthday present
because I was born as a twin,
but she passed away because my mum had ovarian cancer
during pregnancy.
So my name's Miriindi, which means rainbow,
and it means the bridge between,
for our ancestors to reach their afterlife,
which is what my sister was called,
which is the Wadahputi, which is the Milky Way,
and that's where they go as, like, the stars,
and they live there.
VU's very supportive.
It doesn't matter if you're an Indigenous student.
Wunday Bola to make sure that you're very well taken care of.
At Alita, our signature program, Alita Connect,
is something we're really passionate and proud of.
We bring together groups of five to six people
around the globe from diverse backgrounds,
sport, industry, social venture and the arts.
We come together to learn, to connect and to collaborate.
Vanessa Ford, Chief Operating Officer at Kukua.
The Alita Connect experience for me has been transformational.
I met people that I would never have met
from totally different spheres.
It's very basic.
It's all about relationships.
It's all about how we communicate
and what the Alita Connect group does that is so powerful
is when you bring two people
from two totally different worlds together,
there's no ego.
It just leaves room for,
for the real you.
And I think that's what Alita gave me
was bringing back the real me
and really connecting to my own leadership style.
We're doing this interview this morning in Melbourne, Australia
and the common place to have had a home invasion
or have had a neighbors have one.
We have had a couple in recent times at our own home
and you speak to the neighbors
and almost everyone in this street.
In your role at Home Affairs,
you, you,
you've deported and canceled the visas of more,
thousands and thousands and thousands of people,
pedophiles and bikies and violent criminals.
Their connections then went after your family
in the most horrific way,
which is an untold story.
And your kids were subjected to having federal police
at the front of their classrooms
and some horrific things to kill your wife.
Was there a moment where you thought,
is this all worth it?
Did, did that get, get to you?
Uh, it's a, it's a tough question
because I've always said that I would leave this job overnight
if one of my kids went off the rails or,
uh, you know, they, they needed me more than, than the job did.
The most remarkable thing about, uh, you know,
my wife, Kiralee, and, and my kids
is that they've never complained about it.
And, uh, it, it, it's, it's intrusive
because you have 24-7 security.
Uh, it means you, you know, you don't lead a normal life.
And, uh, and, and, but that, that's the price you pay.
I mean, I think we're a safer community,
safer society because of those people that we, we deported.
These were serious criminals.
And, uh, and no, I, I don't think that I thought about leaving the job.
And, and that was never something that, that, you know,
a conversation that Kiralee and I had where she said,
you know, this is too much, you, you know, you need to get out.
She's been stoic and supportive, uh, every day.
And, and I've been incredibly grateful for that
because you couldn't do this job without, uh, that support,
and without a strong family.
Because I think that's the, that's the most important thing
that you have to do.
I mean, it's, it's, it's, it's a, it's a very,
a very strong relationship and it's, it gives you the ballast.
And it also allows you when you get back home to, um,
to be able to reset.
And I, and I think mentally that's important as well,
that you don't just carry the burden of this job,
which, which is a vocation.
It's not a normal job where you go home and, you know,
ten past five, you, um, you know, you're off the train
and you're back home and, and you can switch off.
It's, it, it goes constantly.
So, so to be able to have that, uh, that support network with your wife and kids,
kids, and your close friends as well, that for me has been really important.
And it hurts me that I put them at risk because of my job, but I'm incredibly grateful that
they take it in their stride.
And I mean, I probably told this story before, but I think the only complaint, maybe two
complaints.
I mean, one is that the kids have done their hundred hours of driving with the AFP and
the rear vision mirror.
It comes with a layer.
Well, it becomes a bit hard because they're on their L's and you're sitting in the passenger
seat trying to give them guidance.
But when you take off from the stop sign, you've got to allow room for two cars, so
your car and the car behind you to make the turn.
And so it all becomes a bit stressful for them.
And so there's a bit of a gripe about that.
And then the bum bags at school that the AFP carry and trying to convince your kids that
nobody knows who they are.
But kids are much smarter than what you realize.
So, but no, they've been great and they've grown up to be now young adults and I'm incredibly
proud of them.
I've heard you talking in recent times a lot about the Australian dream of owning your
own house and how that's become harder for the current generation than perhaps ever before
in Australian history.
In a few months time, you could be the next prime minister of Australia.
What are some of the things that people should know that you want to achieve?
Well, I will break my back to make sure that people can achieve their dream of home
education.
Because I think it's such an important part of our culture.
For me personally, it's been a way to, you know, I've renovated homes over the years,
bought and sold, and it's been a way to create wealth.
And I think it is the foundation of being able to form a stable relationship and raise
kids.
I think the value increase in an asset, as we've seen in housing over recent years, means
that you can live a comfortable life in retirement.
And it's an asset that grows in value such that you can bequeath it to your children
and help set them up.
And renting for life is not part of our culture.
And ultimately, it's not a way to generate wealth.
The other aspect to it, which is important to us as a Liberal Party, is that generally
it's the asset that is the security to start a small business.
And, you know, small business is very important to our party.
And just giving people that choice, if that's what they want to do.
That's great.
If they don't want to do it, well, that's fine.
So we've got a huge problem, though, because the migration program has brought in about
a million people over the last two years.
And we're a great country because of migration, but it needs to be in a managed way because
at the same time, we've had a record low of building approvals, construction costs have
gone through the roof, land supply has been limited, and we've had this perfect storm.
We've seen rents go up by about...
About 20%.
You've seen people lose the hope of and the aspiration of home ownership.
And I want to restore that hope and that dream again.
And we've announced a $5 billion package to provide support to councils, to help them
with sewerage and water infrastructure and road infrastructure so that they can develop
the land more quickly and bring that on.
And we'll have more to say in relation to housing because I think it's a really significant
problem in the community.
And, you know...
I want those young people who are working hard to have an expectation that they can
own a home.
And I don't think that's unreasonable.
Peter, I had the great privilege of sitting across from a range of different people and
what I would say are great leadership stories as yours is absolutely, and these sort of
patterns around what great leaders do.
And I'm keen to ask you a handful of questions on that.
We think this idea of sort of self-leadership, that it's very hard to lead someone else unless
you know what fills you.
What do you do on that front?
What do you do to make sure you're feeling well to be able to do the job you do?
Well, as you know, and I suspect as some people have heard me say before, but you've been
a big influence on me in this regard in terms of meditation.
And I spoke about our dear friend, mutual friend Jeffrey before, and he's a big believer
as well.
And so I've looked at successful people and I see, you know, the success and the balance
that you've had in your life, which...
You know, I think is and should be a role model for many people because you've got the
balance right, I think, and it's, you know, there are always pressures and, you know,
always issues you've got to deal with, but in your work life, most importantly in your
home life and obviously your business life and your sporting career as well.
And so meditation has been important for me.
Exercise is important.
And I think the...
Yeah.
The ability to have those relationships where you can talk freely and it's not a download
because you don't want to burden somebody else with all of your problems, but it is having
those trusted people around you that you can bounce ideas off and they don't have to be
connected with your workplace and they can be different people in your life for different
elements that you can compartmentalize.
So, yeah, meditation has been important for me and it allows a reset and it allows that
refreshing of the mind.
I think that's been important and each to their own.
People can find their solace or their good place, you know, according to what's important
to them.
It doesn't fit the public profile, but you're a meditator.
It's not something that people are going to understand, but it's, again, it's something
I...
You're a great listener when you're around, you genuinely feel like when you're talking
to you, you're not focused on anyone else and I've watched your take on things that
other people would be surprised in a range of different areas.
Is there one thing that you've noticed in your work life?
Yeah.
Is there one piece of leadership advice that you pass on to others?
I've always found it important to surround yourself with good people and I have a very
low turnover of staff and I think it's important to identify those people that you can help
create a culture with and that you can bounce off and that you can trust each other and
that the workplace doesn't become, you know, sort of a hard labour.
You can't be turning up in an environment each day that's just not conducive to positive
outcomes.
So I think bringing those people together and, you know, if there's any leadership skill
that I've got, it's identifying good people and generally people who are smarter than
you as well, which is always a good lesson in life and making sure that those people
can blend together.
And I think that works.
I think that way you get the most out of them and I think you self-develop yourself as well
and I think that's an important part and it's sort of a statement of the obvious for many
but for me that's been very effective.
You've got a really clear vision for what Australia should be.
I can hear it in your words, the ability to own your own house, to live a healthy life,
whether you're in Gove or in Mossman in Sydney or Toorak in Melbourne, this idea of living
a safe environment.
Treating people with dignity and respect, but you come together in this environment
of MPs and a pretty brutal world of politics.
How do you try and get a team like that to share that vision and be on the same page?
Well, politics is better than it used to be.
There used to be, you know, sort of the gladiator age where you could lob limbs off and attack
each other.
So it's always been an adversarial environment.
That's the nature of it.
It's like a courtroom.
And people, you know
Yeah.
are right to be passionate about arguing their beliefs and, you know, I've spoken
publicly, the Prime Minister's spoken publicly about the relationship that he and I have
and we got on well.
We are able to talk about issues that are important for our country and come together
at moments where it's necessary to resolve matters, particularly of national security,
quickly and to deal with those threats or those issues.
I think that's important.
But there is a
There is an adversarial element to it.
Sometimes it gets personal, which it shouldn't.
And sometimes the people around you, you know, can feel the impact of that as well and you
need to be conscious of that.
Yeah.
I've heard you say that before, that you like Anthony Albanese, you think he's a decent
person.
You don't think he's a particularly good Prime Minister.
But I think that is another trait of yours.
I don't hear you talk down about anyone, that you treat people with dignity and respect.
And even in that adversarial environment
You strike me as someone who's inherently curious.
You know, the fact that, you know, meditation's a random thing a decade ago when we spoke
about it.
But is there a path of curiosity that you've gone down recently that people might be surprised
about?
Well, I'm discovering this world of podcasts, which has been a bit foreign.
And it's hard to sort of find that block of time.
So
But, you know, I do try and go for a walk or go for a run or go to the gym.
And it's
Yeah.
And then I do some of my eight-day routines each morning.
And it can be part of that.
I like listening to music as well.
And that helps clear the mind or just distract from what's ahead for the day.
But it also allows some clear thinking.
And one of the things that I haven't been successful at doing is just trying to block
out that period of time during the day that does give you the ability to think and to
read more broadly.
I
When I was Defence Minister
I remember
first came into this job, I thought as Defence Minister, you just absorb with the briefs every
day and stuff is coming up and getting calls and being dragged into important meetings and the rest
of it. And it's hard to find that sort of thinking time and that bigger picture time.
And I thought when I came into this job, I would have that because you didn't have the burden of
a portfolio or a department, et cetera, but it's not really turned out to be the case. And so I
want to work better on that. And it obviously becomes harder as Prime Minister to be able to
do that. But I do think you need to stop just dealing with the minute-to-minute engagement of
your job and allow some time in your diary designated and specific and deliberate to
think a little bit further afield. We love the saying, Peter, that the cost of
leadership is the cost of leadership. And I think that's a really good point.
Is time and you can't fake that time, but then you still seem to be able to balance family life
and be able to collaborate and you've got great friends and put that together. How do you get all
that done? Well, I think you have to prioritise and you have to be a good time manager or in my
case, if you're not a good time manager, have a great PA and people around you that can manage
time well. So, you know, my diary sort of goes,
15-minute blocks and it's a fail for us if I have to go to the airport lounge.
People talk about the chairman's lounge or all this sort of stuff. I like to go straight from
security to, you know, the gate. It's boarding because, you know, I mean, we do 200 flights a
year and another half hour in the lounge on every one of those just detracts from the time that I
could be spending at home or on another task. So it's a matter of managing that effectively.
And it's also a matter of putting that date night or that appointment, you know, that you want to go
to with your wife or with your kids or their sporting event. For me, it's been, you know,
my kid's, Rebecca's 22 and Harry's 20, Tommy's 19. So they're, you know, they've finished school
now. But even, you know, Tom's playing footy after school, even trying to get to as many of
those games as possible is important. And even if you're,
even if you're not there during the week, this is, you know, again, every family's different, but
the kids are so busy with their lives that, you know, they want you to be there. But if you're
not during the week, I think that was balanced by the fact that I always tried to get there for,
you know, swim club on a Friday night and, you know, do the timekeeping and be there for that,
or go to the footy match on a Saturday or, you know, training on Friday afternoon, whatever,
it is. And if you can get to those, and I found it incredibly rewarding, you know, selfishly
for myself, because to watch them develop and to go from puppy pack into, you know,
you know, into a skilled sort of player, I sort of, I was so proud of that. And it was also the
most normal part of my week. But they were watching me on the sideline. And I think they had
a pride that I was there.
Taking an interest in them. And it helped, you know, build a really strong relationship
as well. And sometimes you can make excuses for not being there. And even as a minister,
you know, travelling to Europe or to the US, I loathed being away on weekends and would fly
through the night to get back for weekend games. And so you have to get that balance right. And,
you know, I've said it would kill me as a member of the ADF, the Defence Force,
to be away.
For a six-month posting and how they do it, I don't know. But to their great credit, they do.
And yeah, that's what's worked for us.
Well, I said, you can't fake your time. You're either there or you weren't. And clearly you
made sure you were. We always see great leaders really understanding of how they communicate.
And you're an excellent communicator in your own unique way. Do you give it some thought?
Have you got a strategy around how you get your message across?
Just don't complicate it. And sometimes, I'll give this example where I have a great deal of
respect for Julia Gillard. I don't think she was a great prime minister by any stretch. But
I remember in the debate around gay marriage at the time, and I think some leaders torture
themselves in the language because they want to say what they really believe, but they
filter it or they don't say it in its sort of raw form. And I remember hearing her say that,
well, I think the better way that she could have put her position was to say, look, I believe in
gay marriage, but I don't think the country's ready for it. And I respect that. Hopefully one
day it will be. And as opposed to saying that you don't believe in gay marriage, because
that's what was probably...
The public mood at the time, it was a complicated debate, but it was just a sort of a snapshot and
maybe it's sort of an awkward demonstration of it. But I think the best leaders we've had in our
country, a Bob Hawke or a Keating or a Howard, they're not tortured in their language and they
know what they believe in and they're willing to fight for it. And sometimes you can get yourself
in trouble because it's not filtered, but all the, there's a full stop instead of a comma. So
the qualification in the sentence is not included in the grab on the news. But sometimes, I listen
to the PM at the moment and I think he's trying to please everyone on the issue. And I think,
mate, you've got to stand up for what you believe in and you're not going to please everyone. And
if you're trying to please everyone, then generally it means you haven't arrived at the right outcome.
So,
I think de-complicate it and don't forget where you've come from and keep your feet on the ground.
I think they're always good lessons.
Peter, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
For me, John Howard. And I watched John from afar growing up and I worked very closely with him. I
was very grateful that he put me into the ministry at a pretty young age after only one term in
parliament. And he's still a mentor and a friend and a confidant for me now. And he's not somebody
bearing or on the phone every day at all. But I'll ring him time to time and say, you know,
how do you think we're going or what do you think about this issue? And he's always obliging,
very giving of his time and very generous.
Didn't hesitate on that. That was a question without notice for you. It's clearly had an
impact on you and you value having that mentor still in your life.
Yes. Yeah. I think, again, I think John came from the suburbs. He understood the value of hard work.
Of respect. And he wasn't afraid to argue his beliefs and his structures. And that's been a
quality that I've admired for a long time. And he hasn't got every call right by his own admission.
No human being can. So he comes with that caveat. But I think he did a lot of good for our country.
And he set us up for a period of,
along with Peter Costello, they did a great job in managing the economy. And
if you manage the economy well, then people can succeed in their own
business lives and in their own personal lives.
We're a bit obsessed with this idea of collaboration in the leadership groups that
we're curating around the globe and putting someone from your background with someone from
a creative field or a sports leader with a leader of the business world. As you enter this chapter
for you, is there someone that you think about?
In any of your passions in life, I mean, clearly being prime minister of Australia is forefront of
mine, that is there someone you thought, God, that'd be a great person to collaborate with
in the future? Well, I look to a lot of people with
sporting success because I think there's a synergy between politics and sport. And I mean,
you've got a lot more natural talent that you can rely on. Our game, not so much.
But I do look at successful sports people and I see the discipline, the sacrifice that they've made,
and in some cases too, the sort of dragging into the public spotlight where really they just want
to play sport and play it well and chase their lifetime passion and don't necessarily enjoy
the spotlight. And I'm sort of similar in that way. I don't crave the public spotlight. I never
have, but it's a necessary part of the job that I really enjoy. And that is making decisions or
putting in place decisions that
I believe in our country's best interests and help people and provide that support to them. So
that would for me be a bit of a yin and yang. And I think what you've done in your collaboration and
the leadership group and the personalities, having listened to a lot of the podcasts that you've done
and the people that you've brought together, I think it's quite a remarkable model.
It may not be without precedent, but it's been a novel approach. And I really think it's
a lot of good comes of that. Very kind of you to say. That was the final question.
I've got to follow up one on the back of it. We're seeing in the US, President Trump,
which is a whole nother topic, but happy to bring in Elon Musk into government efficiency program
and curate people from outside industries. Is that a model that, not that in particular,
but do outside people have a role?
I think some business people being involved in the upper levels of the public service would be
a great thing. I think as a defence minister, I was incredibly well served from the public service
and the senior public servants are professional. They sometimes don't make decisions as quickly
as you would want to. But if you're a leader in that portfolio or those portfolios, you can give
direction and people do react and they respond. And I think that's a really good point.
Respond according to your direction and the decisions that you're making. But in some public
service families in Canberra, they're a second, third, fourth, fifth generation. And I think we
need a greater breadth of understanding of the real world and different experiences. And bringing
that in is important. Many years ago, I was the assistant treasurer and had responsibility for
the tax office. And I was very aware of the insular.
Sort of almost Stockholm syndrome nature of the place because they're constantly under attack.
Nobody likes a tax office. But I tried to develop a program there where people could go out and work
in some of the companies and bring some of those people back in to get a better understanding of
what was happening on both sides of the fence. And I think that's an important aspect as well.
But it's always a great pleasure to spend.
Some time with you. Every time I've been around you, you only treat people with great dignity
and respect. And my hope is that people listen to these conversations. They actually get to see
the real Peter Dutton and then they can make up their own mind. But thanks again. It's been great
to catch up. I really appreciate it. Nice to see you. Thank you.