What does it take to become a great leader?
Is it taking your team to win a premiership?
Is it teaching future generations about compassion and respect?
What interests you the most? What are you passionate about?
And absolutely, I knew if I was to get out of bed every day
and put my heart and soul into something,
that was the number one thing I wanted to do.
Is it empowering colleagues so they can be their best at work?
You get that input into projects early
so there's a sense of ownership.
Over not just the outcome,
but also the process on how we're going to get there.
Leadership isn't something we're born with.
It's something we learn by collaborating with others
to create positive change.
I feel informed. I feel inspired.
I've got lots of things to take away from our chat.
G'day, it's Luke Darcy here.
I've been involved in leadership both on and off the field
for most of my life, and I'm passionate about
the positive change I've seen in leadership
to giving people a voice in their environment.
So,
I've created this podcast,
Empowering Leaders.
In this series,
we'll unpack learnings and life lessons
from people who are game changers in their chosen field,
whether it's sport,
art,
business,
or education.
We'll break down the fundamentals
of the new style of leadership,
such as collaboration,
integrity,
and innovation
through the stories of these iconic leaders.
Listen to Empowering Leaders with me,
Luke Darcy.
Search Empowering Leaders podcast
or download the listener app now
and listen for free.
I'm Luke Darcy.
I'll see you next week.