There was a hashtag on Twitter.
Get John Wayne on Joe Rogan.
Then one day he replied, I'd love to get John Wayne on.
I'm a big fan.
So I shot him a DM.
Hey, my name's John Wayne.
He goes, yeah, for sure.
I'd love to have you on.
Let's pick a date.
So we picked a date.
Got my bag, jumped in a taxi, went straight to the studio.
Eddie Bravo, Brian Kellan, Brendan Shaw, Joe Rogan all sitting there talking about the fires.
It's like, whoa.
And Joe's like, oh, since we don't really know each other,
well, do you want to come to my house tomorrow morning?
And we'll do a session.
Then we'll have something to talk about on the podcast.
I'm like, whoa, yes.
So he goes to me in a dress.
We go back up to his house.
Yeah, it's just amazing.
And then what you see on TV is the same Joe you see in real life, too.
He's so nice and so humble, so funny.
He's the man.
He's so cool.
Hello and welcome to another episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
At Alita, we are passionate about inspiring connections and creating a world of collaboration.
Our signature program, Alita Connect, curates groups of five to six leaders
from diverse backgrounds in sport, industry, and business.
Social venture and the arts who come together to learn, to connect, and to collaborate.
Dr. Troy Flanagan, Vice President of Performance for the Milwaukee Bucks.
I've probably had some of the most radical changes out of that leadership group.
The significance of their work and how much it's really about helping others,
it made me think, what else could I be doing?
And I approached our owner, and within a few weeks,
we've raised $5 million to try and solve obesity in the underprivileged,
community in Milwaukee.
So that's one spark that that leadership course has caused to contribute
and leave the world as a better place.
Umrah Omer, founder of Safari Doctors.
It defines the word creativity for me.
The ability to see connections where none seem to exist.
And I think that's the magic of Alita.
Definitely not my usual workshop panels like humanitarian spaces,
but.
But more of an intentional, um, um,
dissection of leadership.
The Empowering Leaders podcast is proudly brought to you by Victoria University,
where cutting edge sports and exercise science facilities like heat chambers,
performance labs, and altitude environments mean VU is ranked seventh in the world for sports science.
VU, uniquely you.
As always, a big thank you to Jason Nicholas and his team at Temper Bedding,
a mattress like no other.
Thank you.
And please, if you have a moment, we would love you to leave a review so we can reach
more listeners and empower more leaders.
John Wayne Parr is one of the world's most revered combat sport athletes, a 10-time world
champion and a legend of the world of Muay Thai and kickboxing.
Wayne's story is told brilliantly in his new book, The Fighter, The Legendary Life of an
Australian Champion, written by Jared Boyle.
Influential UFC commentator and podcast pioneer, Joe Rogan.
He's a huge fan of John Wayne Parr's
and describes him as one of the baddest dudes ever.
His skill level, his toughness,
his dedication to the sport are unparalleled.
He is an icon.
John Wayne Parr moved constantly around Australia as a kid.
His parents were racehorse trainers
and they were forced to regularly move towns
in search of work.
And the story of a young Australian boy
living in the brutal martial arts training camps in Thailand,
going on to arguably be the most revered Westerner ever
in the ancient sport of Mai Tai
is nothing short of remarkable.
Wayne, it's great to meet you.
It's an extraordinary life that you have lived
and it's captured brilliantly in the book
that's just been released about your life
called The Fighter.
The story of a legendary Australian champion
written by Jarrod Boyle.
Can you tell me, how does the boy that grew up
in the Gold Coast and moved house regularly
turn out to be a 10-time world champion?
How did it happen?
So my parents were horse trainers
and we moved a lot as kids.
So I was very isolated.
We lived on big property.
So I wasn't just an only child,
but the fact that our house would be here
and then our neighbor would be like 4Ks
on top of a hill,
like it was so, so bad.
And then my parents worked crazy hours
where they'd have to wake up at 3.30,
be at the track by 4.
So I'd wake up by myself.
There'd be $2 on the table,
I'd get my $2 and then I'd go to my tuck shop
and I'd come home and they'd be at work again
because the afternoon session starts from say 3 to say 6.30.
So by the time they get home,
so I spend a lot of time by myself.
And I was infatuated by martial arts movies.
All I wanted to do was be a martial artist.
I seen the kind of kid.
He's the kid that moves around.
He's the new kid.
I can understand exactly what he's going through.
So maybe if I find martial arts,
that'll help fill in a hole.
And then the moment I started martial arts
at the age of 11,
I haven't stopped since.
I'm 48.
And the only regret is that
we didn't start at five instead of 11.
Wayne, you ended up in the brutal training camps
of Thailand in the ancient sport of Mai Tai.
You're a legend in that part of the world
and accomplished things
that almost no other Westerner has been able to achieve.
Tell us about the path to living
in the most basic accommodation
and the brutal training regime you went through.
I'm very lucky to have a Thai sponsor named Richard.
He took me under his wing
at the age of approximately 17.
I fought my first Thai.
He seen my potential.
I got knocked out in 30 seconds.
But the fact that I fought a Thai,
he said, oh, you showed a big heart.
It's very important in Thailand,
the heart's everything.
So even the fact that I fought a Thai,
the fact that I lost,
but the fact that I fought him
was an accomplishment.
And then I lived approximately
a 10-minute walk away.
So during the day,
I'd sit in the kitchen.
And then as he's preparing the chicken skewers
and getting them ready,
I just listened to this mystical place
of this place of that,
that their national sport is Thai boxing.
And it's their heritage.
And it's there.
They're so proud.
And people spend their lives
from the eight years old
living in this camp.
It just sounded so amazing.
It sounded just exactly what I wanted.
And then I got the opportunity
at the age of 19
to move over there.
Originally just for six months.
Ended up having five fights,
five wins.
And then I came back to Australia.
A few months later,
the camp rang and said,
can you please send me back?
We believe there's a big future in the sport.
So Richard had a courtesy
to send me back.
But he said, instead of six months,
I'll just send you back for 12 months
so you make sure you get the techniques down perfect.
So I went for another 12 months,
had nine fights that year.
I won, I think, seven.
I'm pretty sure seven.
I fought in the stadiums
and the big things,
but that's 100,000 people.
for the first time.
And I just kept snowballing
and snowballing and snowballing.
And then once I started
making a name in Thailand,
and then the rest of the world
wanted getting offers
from every country,
Holland, France.
I've even fought in Jamaica.
I fought in Jamaica once.
That's pretty cool.
Jamaica, China, you name it,
I've fought there.
So I think I worked out,
I've had 149 fights
and approximately 85 of those fights
have been international
because I lived overseas for so long.
So yeah, I've had more fights overseas
than back home.
You fought some of
the most important
and the most dangerous people
you could possibly imagine.
And reading the book,
which I loved,
and I encourage people
to read your story.
It's an amazing story
of courage and resilience.
But the names are incredible.
Arono, the black Superman,
Break Hell with Punch,
the Deadly Kisser was a mentor,
the Thai called you
the dangerous kangaroo.
I'm fascinated.
So the Deadly Kisser,
Sengten Noi's fight name,
broken down,
his name means
the small candlelight flame.
So he used to put a candle
on his shorts
and then the name was
and the Deadly Kisser
was another name
that was preceded by him
after he showed the people
that are gambling in the crowd
that he gave his kisser
and then around two,
he believed that it was his fight
so they'd all bet on him.
So that was his way
of signaling,
I've got this.
And then,
yeah, and that sort of stuck.
But the Sengten Noi
actually means
the small candlelight flame.
And you're talking about
stepping into the ring
where you're fighting warriors
of the highest order.
How do you deal with fear?
For those of us
that have never done that,
what's your secret
to being able to fight?
Clearly,
you have some level of fear.
How did you deal with it?
So my thing is
I want to be best.
I want to be regarded
as a champion.
And the only way
to prove to be I'm a champion
is to cross the ropes.
So no matter
how scary they are,
I can say,
yeah, I can do this,
I can do that.
Here'd be nothing.
Unless I cross those ropes,
nothing matters.
So it's very important.
That's the hardest part.
Once you're in,
all the fear goes away
because you're already there.
It's just that block.
And then,
also the passion.
I told myself early,
I'm there for a reason.
I'm there to be successful.
I'm there to be great.
The only way to take
that next step
is to get in there
and the facial fears.
And then,
and then money.
So let's say,
I've had times
where I made $35,000
and then I was
rematching a gentleman.
He cut me four different times
in two different fights.
And then as I'm walking
to the ring,
I'm like,
oh man,
this is going to hurt so bad.
But listen,
I got $35,000.
So it's okay.
Wayne,
an incredible life
on so many levels.
I look at a great warrior
going on the ring
and when you win,
you celebrate as you should,
but the defeats are brutal.
And when you see a fighter
exit the ring having lost,
that looks as painful a loss
as you could imagine.
How did you deal with those?
Because every fighter,
almost every fighter
has to deal with defeat.
How did you handle that?
Oh, it's terrible.
I won my first live fight,
St. Thylian Street.
So I was very fortunate.
The ranking's really fast.
I got to number four
at Lumpini Stadium
in the rankings
and I was one fight away from,
actually the promoter
came into my changing room
and he said,
if you win today,
your next fight will be
for the Lumpini title.
And then I was so excited
and then I ended up
getting cut 21 stitches
and the fight ended up
stopping round three
from too much blood
and excess
and the whole business.
And then,
yeah,
for the next week,
I just hid in the room
because I was so embarrassed.
Even though the guy was a legend
and the inclusion to him
is no big,
it's just the fact that I fought him,
but in my head,
I've lost.
And I was on TV,
through Thai TV
and every media outlets
and then,
oh,
Thylian's finally got their
their honor back
after the Australian
had won in the first nine fights
and everything.
And then I front page
of the magazine the next day
showing the suit.
But during the fights,
I knew I made my mistakes
and just having the pain of a loss,
you don't want to have that feeling again.
And then as soon as you come back
and you have another win,
all of a sudden,
you feel that rush
and that's the reason you're there
to get that endorphin drop.
Have you ever seen the movie Highlander
when the lightning comes down from the sky?
That's what I feel like
is when you're wounded by KO.
And then you can't sleep
for three, four, five days.
Yeah,
your skin's always,
you're just so happy.
Wayne,
the UFC's become
the fastest growing sport in the world
by almost every measure.
And,
you know,
it's a brutal world.
It's a world that you know really well.
I mean,
is it something that you admire?
Do you think
if you were born in the UFC,
born a generation earlier,
that would have been your path
into the UFC?
Oh, definitely.
The fact that these guys
are making hundreds of thousands of dollars
per fight,
getting pay-per-view points
and we're getting generational money,
not just retirement money,
generational wealth.
Yeah,
it's so exciting to see the sport
prosper
because it helps me as well
because people need more high schools
to get into the next level of UFC
and also,
I've started Jiu-Jitsu at my gym
the last five years also.
And so,
I was never sort of a Jiu-Jitsu guy
but since,
the last five years,
we have a Brazilian instructor
that comes to our gym
every day.
So,
I'm starting to steer into that world myself
with competing.
I want to start getting into Jiu-Jitsu competitions
to fill in a hole
for where my Muay Thai competition used to go.
Joe Rogan is an incredibly influential figure
in America now.
Maybe the most influential voice
in some ways
heading into the US election.
He's a UFC commentator
and he loves John Wayne Parr.
He's a huge fan of yours.
I know you went to his house,
trained him in his private gym
and then you've been a guest
on the Joe Rogan show.
Tell me about your relationship
with Joe Rogan.
Yeah, Joe is amazing.
Our first time on the podcast,
there was a hashtag on Twitter.
Get John Wayne on Joe Rogan.
Get John Wayne.
And then one day he replied,
I'd love to get John Wayne on.
I'm a big fan.
I'm like,
whoa,
Joe Rogan replied to the tweet.
So,
I showed him a DM.
Hey,
my name's John Wayne.
I'm just wondering,
is it okay?
He goes,
yeah, for sure.
I'd love to have you on.
Let's pick a date.
So, we picked a date.
I got to the Brisbane airport
on a Saturday,
turned my phone off,
arrived in LA,
turned my phone back on
and I get a beep beep
and it's Joe.
He goes,
oh,
I know we're doing the podcast tomorrow
but is there any chance
you want to come and do
the fight campaign with us now?
So, I went straight from the,
got my bag,
jumped in a taxi,
went straight to the studio.
Eddie Bravo,
Brian Callen,
Brendan Shaw,
Joe Rogan are all sitting there
talking about the fight.
It's like,
whoa.
And then we finished the podcast
and Joe's like,
oh,
since we don't really know each other,
well,
do you want to come to my house
tomorrow morning
and we'll do a session
and then we'll have something
to talk about on the podcast.
I'm like,
whoa,
yes.
So, he gave me a dress
and said we could rock up
to his house.
Yeah,
it's just amazing.
And then what you see on TV
is the same Joe you see
in real life too.
He's so nice
and so humble
and so funny
and he's just,
he's the man.
He's so cool.
Wayne,
you spent a huge amount
of time living
and training
with the Thai people
and understanding
their love of the sport.
Tell us about
your relationship
with the Thai people.
So,
my Thai trainer,
after the first three
or four days of being there,
he said,
I'm not going to teach you
Thai boxing.
I'm going to teach you
how to be a Thai.
So,
pretty much
from there,
learning how to sit on the floor
to eat every meal.
You have to sit cross-legged
and then you put
a plate of rice in front
so you've got to lean
over your hips,
which sounds easy
until you have to try and do it
and then let's bring your rice
and then sit on the floor
is the thing.
You spoke about their care
and their love
and their incredible people
but also,
if you do the wrong thing,
they can be pretty brutal
as well.
Oh, yeah.
The life's so cheap.
So,
there's a thing over there
in Thailand
where fighters will get
persuaded by the mafia
to throw fights.
Let's say you're making
$20,000 a fight
and then the mafia
might come in
and say,
we'll give you $100,000
but if you happen to
fall over round two,
per se,
and then
all of a sudden
these fighters have money
and then they do it
so obviously
and it's obvious,
yes,
I've known Thai trainers
that have paid the police
to make their files go missing
for them to disappear
and no questions asked.
And then
there was one camp
where two guys
disappeared
and then the trainer's like,
alright, guy,
gym meeting.
Has anyone seen
Stephen Darren?
Stephen,
yeah,
either of you.
Maybe they shouldn't have
done it.
Anyone else want to
throw a fight?
And then, yeah,
no one wants to throw
one after that.
Oh, Stephen Dazza.
Steve-o.
We all are born different.
As we grow,
the experiences we have
develop into outlooks
uniquely our own.
Charting our life's course.
No one sees an idea,
opinion,
or opportunity
like you.
And no one sees you
like VU.
Victoria University.
Uniquely you.
My name's Gabrielle.
I'm studying law.
What made me want to get into law
is, I guess,
the reward you get after
the feelings that you get
for helping other people.
I'm really passionate
about making sure
that people have that voice,
especially for people
that don't feel like
they can be heard.
And that's something
that's really important to me.
I have quite deep
personal values,
so it was really important
to me to find a university
that aligns with those values
and VU's that for me.
At Alita,
our signature program,
Alita Connect,
is something we're really
passionate and proud of.
We bring together groups
of five to six people
around the globe
from diverse backgrounds,
sport, industry,
social venture,
and the arts.
We come together
to learn,
to connect,
and to collaborate.
Vanessa Ford,
Chief Operating Officer
at Kukua.
The Alita Connect experience
for me has been
transformational.
I met people
that I would never have met
from totally different spheres.
It's very basic.
It's all about relationships.
It's all about
how we communicate
and what the Alita Connect group does
that is so powerful
is when you bring two people
from two totally different worlds
together,
there's no ego.
It just leaves room
for the real you.
And I think
that's what Alita gave me
was bringing back
the real me
and really connecting
to my own leadership style.
You're married
a very accomplished fighter
and your daughter
has joined the family business
as well
and was a fighter
from a young age
and you're saluting
and cheering.
What's it like
watching at a young age
your daughter in the ring?
How do you feel?
Do you get nervous watching it?
I know.
I'm so excited.
I hear it.
Archie trains
and I know how passionate
she is also.
If she was missing days
and she wasn't hitting hard
and she wasn't moving her head
and she was losing in sparring,
I'd be very nervous.
But because I see
how accomplished she is
and how passionate she was,
she has the same
stubbornness that I do.
So they're helping us
through in the weight
and she's so determined
to be successful.
She started at the age of eight,
which was very controversial
at the time
because people weren't
adjusted to martial arts then.
But now,
with the popularity,
of UFC
and martial arts culture
and everyone's a lot more educated,
it's now just the age.
Jiu-Jitsu competitions
are held every weekend.
No one cares anymore.
It's just,
I find it quite humbling
to have the kids training
in the gym with me every day.
So a lot of people,
they'll go to work,
have some beers,
sit on the couch
and that's their day
where I'm lucky
to spend all my time
with the kids in the gym,
holding pads,
sparring,
having fun.
And then I'm so happy
that we have
a lot of people
I bond through fighting
and then we're there
in each other's corner
when we fight
and then we have a thing
in our family
where if someone's fighting,
it's their day.
So you're not allowed
to swear at that person.
They're not allowed
to do dishes
or pick up rubbish
and then they can say,
hey, pick up my plate,
it's my day.
And then they've got
the right thing
because it's their day.
So yeah,
they're the special player
and after their day's done,
it's like,
you pick it up,
you've got to pick it up.
The only thing is
you've got to get in the ring
and fight an opponent
which for most families,
most people would be happy
to do the dishes, Wayne,
but it's a unique family
that you've got.
I love asking these questions,
John Wayne Parr,
of different people,
whether you're talking
to someone who's been
a conductor of an orchestra
or a legend of their sport
or an entrepreneur with success
and what great leadership
looks like
and yours is a brave story
to leave as a 16 or 17-year-old
to live in Thailand
and take on the world
and the courage
to be one of the world's
great combat sports athletes.
I want to ask you
about this idea of
how do you make sure
you're at your best
so that you've been able
to lead others in your family
and have an impact on others?
What do you do
to fill your cup up, John,
before you can help
someone else?
Since 1999,
I haven't had a trainer.
I've been self-driven.
I'll pay my friends
to come and I'll pass for me.
The promoter will call me
and say,
hey, we want you to fight
this guy in this country
at this weight
for this much money.
I'll study my own opponents.
I'll matchmake myself.
I'll make sure
that I get my weight down.
I've never,
I've never replied.
The only person I need
is someone to help pass for me
and their sparring partners.
Besides that,
I've never once
have I woke up in the morning
and not wanted to
put my shoes on
and go for a run.
And then,
all the fear
I face is all me.
And then,
you want to fight my dean?
Sure.
You want to fight this guy?
Yeah.
The only way to prove
that I'm the best
is I have to fight him.
I have to beat him.
So,
the passion
of wanting to be
remembered.
I know
once you pass
it doesn't matter
but I want to leave
a legacy where
even when you look
at Muhammad Ali now
your skin crawls
because you know
how amazing he is.
Or there's a gentleman
who used to
Raymond Deckers
who was a famous
Muay Thai guy
back in the day.
And I think of those guys' names
and hopefully
I can be put in that
a tier
after I pass
and people can
hopefully still be inspired
by what I did
when I was younger.
Yeah,
if you read the book
The Fighter
you'll see
the incredible story
that is John Wayne Parr
and I love this idea
of what,
what leadership looks like
and yours is a unique story.
What advice
do you pass on
to others
who maybe want to
follow your path
from a leadership
point of view?
You have to want it
so bad.
more than you want
to breathe.
My thing since I've
been approximately
I don't know,
11,
is no one's going
to get in my way.
So yeah,
whether it be
work,
job,
location,
money,
nothing's going to
stop me from
achieving what I want
to achieve.
There might be hurdles
but they're not
going to stop me.
So if the girlfriend
doesn't like me
training,
see ya.
New job,
alright,
I won't work.
I haven't worked
since I was 19.
My last retirement
job was 1996.
So yeah,
work's going to get
in the way of my
training.
I love it.
You've got to want it.
A bit of an
endurance bit.
Yeah,
you've got to want it
as much as you want
to breathe
is a pretty
amazing answer.
You had this vision
from a young age.
You wanted to be a champion.
It's the final words
of your book
and every waking
breath it seems
was about being
a world champion
and,
and the very best.
It's a,
it's an incredible
vision from a young age.
How do you go about
working with a team
to allow that vision
to take place?
What did you put in place
to make that happen?
Just being successful
by my,
by my fighting.
I have to win.
Every win is a new
impression on a new
person.
And not just fight,
but fight exciting.
Everyone can fight,
but I want to fight.
So I mentioned
in the book
where it doesn't
matter where you're
on the card to be
the first card,
the first fight of the
card or the middle,
last,
doesn't matter.
I want you talking
about my fight
when you're walking
to your car.
The main event
might be here,
but if you're going,
oh,
how good was that
young kid?
Oh,
I can't wait to watch him.
And then all of a sudden
you've got more money
generating and then
all of a sudden
the promoters know
that you're an asset
and then your prize
might go from $1,000
and all of a sudden
you're on $5,000
and next minute
you're on $10,000
you're on $15,000.
So important to fight
exciting so people
cancel their events
to make sure they're
coming to see you fight.
When we see people
who are successful
like you in whatever
area,
I just heard you talk
about adding jiu-jitsu
to your gym
or wanting to
keep learning.
Is that you?
Do you relate to that?
Do you go down
different rabbit holes
of where curiosity
takes you?
Can you tell us a story
about how that works
for you?
Martial arts is amazing.
Martial arts never ends.
It just keeps going
and going and going.
Sure,
there's the 10,000
bad ones,
but the good ones
are so impactful
and so addicting.
You're going to have
the worst day
and come into a session
and then leave it here
with the worst day
with the biggest smile
on your face.
The endorphin
when you rush,
it makes you forget
about whatever problems
you have.
You walk in the door
and then you just want
to be successful
in there for an hour.
Once you walk out
and you go back
to thinking about
whatever happened
before you walked in,
but while you're in there,
it's just thinking
about sweating,
having fun,
chatting with your partner,
just having fun.
That's the best part
about my job
is it's not a job,
it's just fun.
And you can see that
in the smile on your face.
Everything you say,
you said you've
lived this joyful life
and it comes out.
We love this quote
that the cost
of great leadership
is time.
You said before
nothing gets in your way
of your dream
as it was
to be a world champion,
but how have you been able
to manage that
and be married
and have two kids
and be able
to make all that work?
What's your secret there?
I'm not really a money guy.
When it comes to money,
if I can survive
when I was competing anyway,
from this fight
to that fight,
I'm okay.
So I have no
long-term plans
or anything like that.
Because of being a millionaire,
as long as I can get
to my next fight,
that's all I need.
And that's all I did
for 35 years
is just trying to get by,
get by, get by,
get by, get by.
But nothing,
like I said,
even when times were tough
and I was below
and I was in debt,
it's like,
I know,
but my next fight
will get me above water again.
And then it just so happens
every time I needed money,
just as the bad,
in Thai,
the Thai used to call me
John Wayne Never Dies
because I'd be down
to my last 10 baht
and then boom,
20,000 baht would come.
I'd be down to my last 50 baht,
another 20,000 baht.
It would come or something.
It was just,
yeah,
the Thais were astonished
how I kept surviving.
I live in there,
I made all this money
from competing professionally.
So,
yeah,
that's how I got to live so long.
I just survived
off my prize money
that whole time I was there.
Which is amazing,
isn't it?
Most people can't cope
with that level of stress
of not being down
to your last dollar
and you read the book
and that was you.
You just seemed to find a way
every time,
even when you had,
your daughter was born,
you'd jump on a plane
and you'd find a fight
that would,
you know,
keep you going.
It's an incredible story.
This idea of people
being able to communicate well
to have success.
You moved to a country
where you didn't speak
a word of the language
and you didn't have
any formal training.
How were you able
to communicate
to build that respect
with the people
that you work with?
And there was no iPhones
back then either.
There was no Google.
There was no,
then you had to read a book
and then you'd read
the words in the book.
So,
but the only thing
was the pronunciation
and the reading
were two different things.
It wasn't,
that,
what you said
and what that writes
is nothing.
It's not even close.
So yeah,
it just had to be a fact of,
oh,
so where I lived,
imagine you're the only
white person
in all of Sydney.
So where I lived,
I was it.
And then I'd go to the shops
and people would stare at me
and point at me
because I'd never seen
a white person before
in real life.
So then I got to the stage
where I can't do hand signals
so I couldn't eat,
sleepy,
tired.
I've got to learn.
So every,
every day I'd try
and give myself five words.
All right,
hats this,
all right,
t-shirts this.
And then the next day
I'd start another
and then I remember
my first sentence.
I want one bag of ice.
Pom dong ga nam keng nung tung.
That's it all.
And then I got my first
bag of ice.
I got my first sentence.
And then I could just
change the last word
I want now.
I know I can ask for stuff.
And then it slowly progressed.
And then I got to the stage
where I'd hear the Thai songs
on the radio
and I knew they were popular.
So I'd go down to the radio,
add the record store
and buy that CD.
And then I'd press play
and pause.
And then I'd write in English
what I'd heard.
Pom, P-O-M,
dong ga nam,
D-O-N-G.
And then I remember the words
that I'd go to the Thai karaoke
and all the Thais would be there.
I'd put in my suggestion.
They'd look at me going,
and then I'd start singing.
And everyone would start
standing up
and start jiggling around.
And then even the guy
doing the karaoke goes,
do you know any more songs?
And I'd make,
I know the whole album.
He goes,
oh, can you do us more?
I can do heaps.
And then I'd hear
and it was so much fun
being the only white guy.
I didn't know if I was
saying the right stuff or not,
but at least the Thais
were getting into it.
That made me laugh
at the party then.
Learning Thai by karaoke.
That's a unique way
to go about it.
John Wayne Parr,
who's been the greatest leader
in your life?
Greatest leader.
Probably Raymond Deckard
is the gentleman
that I mentioned from Holland.
Just aspiring to be like him.
He was the first Western
to go to Thailand
and beat the Thais
and not only win,
but knock them out.
And before then,
everyone just feared them
because they were untouchable.
So he inspired me.
When I was living in Thailand
for the long term,
every time I went to the stage
where I was homesick
and I wanted to
come home and say,
what would Raymond do?
All right, I'll stay.
And that would just inspire me
to say another six months,
12 months,
how long I ever was there.
Wayne, you're revered
in the fight game
and around the world
for your courage
and your history
and taking any fight
anytime, anywhere
and you've been able
to connect with unique people
around the globe.
We're a bit obsessed
around this idea
that collaborating
with other people
is how great things happen.
Is there someone
that you've thought,
whether it be in the fight game
or another area of your life,
God, I'd love to have
been with whoever,
you know, Ali
or another fighter
or is there a story
or a person
that springs to mind?
I actually had Raymond Deckers
come to Australia
and then he had
one of these fighters
competing against
another gentleman
called Nathan Corbett
here in the Gold Coast
and then the promoter
rang me and said,
oh, because it's my show,
I can't have Raymond here.
Is there any chance
Raymond Deckers
can train in your gym
for the next seven days
as they prepare for the fight?
So Raymond brought
his fighter here.
Every day we'd hang out
and after the session
we'd go for lunch
and I'd sit there
like a little boy
asking stories.
What happened
when you brought this guy?
Well, I went for a vet class
and then I was like
his little puppy
for seven days
and then he got my shirt
and we corresponded
regularly after that
and then unfortunately
he passed away.
So I lost one of my heroes
but he's still there
every day.
He's still always there.
I'll still never forget
how much he inspires me.
There's an old saying
that be careful
meeting your heroes.
You can be disappointed
but it sounds like
the opposite for you
in that experience.
I encourage everyone,
the fighter,
the legendary
like-minded fighter
and the life
of an Australian champion.
The story of John Wayne Parr
is a remarkable story
on any level.
If you haven't had
any exposure at all
to his world,
it will blow you away
the life this man's lived
and to see the smile
on your face,
still training,
still loving life
and with all the things
that you've been through
is a great story.
It's written by Jared Boyle.
It's a great book
and Wayne,
it's a great privilege
to spend some time with you.
Thanks for taking the time.
Thank you so much
for such a positive interview.
I really appreciate it.
Thank you.