It is fantastic to be back with you in 2024 on the Empowering Leaders podcast and our
second guest for the year is Kirsten King, the founder of Fluid Form Pilates, a brilliant
success story and you'll find this conversation is one that is incredibly transparent, honest
and open and really love catching up with Kirsten and hearing about her story.
Kirsten was incredibly generous in this conversation to share with us the family tragedy of losing
her brother at 16 years of age and how that shaped her and her life going forward in so
many ways.
Kirsten speaks a lot about her Leader Connect group and how she's been able to let her guard
down and share so openly to help others in that group and herself face some of the problems
that occur for all of us on a daily basis.
She also talks a lot about the example of putting family first and by leading through
example herself, she allows others in her team to feel comfortable in the same way.
You're also going to hear about the quite incredible series of events.
That led to Fluid Form Packs being sent by the hundreds to places all over the world
from Afghanistan to Iceland, the US and beyond 99 countries in total and how the COVID challenges
really turbocharged her business and what it meant to her.
We're really passionate about creating a world of collaboration, inspiring connections at
a leader with people like Kirsten King and that shared knowledge, the idea of curating
groups of five or six people to learn and share for a better life, something we'd love
to see happen.
Talk to you about.
Huge thanks to the team at Temper Bedding Australia and New Zealand.
Jason Nicholas and his team have been great supporters ongoing of the Empowering Leaders
podcast.
Some great conversations coming your way this year.
If you are wanting to invest in a better life, Temper is a mattress like no other.
I encourage you to check it out today.
Kirsten King is the face of Pilates in Australia with an expanding reputation for her work
around the globe.
Having been a Pilates instructor for more than two decades, opening her first studio
in Waterloo, Sydney, now expanding.
To seven sites across Sydney and Melbourne.
Her forward-thinking decision to create a fluid form Pilates online platform two years
prior to the COVID period has seen her grow a community of more than 65,000 users in 90
countries around the world.
15 million minutes of fluid form content are consumed annually each year.
Kirsten is a mother to three daughters and married to NRL legend Matt King.
Great to see you, Kirsten.
Thanks for taking the time.
Thanks, Luke.
Nice to see you too.
Fluid form Pilates is an incredible.
Success story.
Congratulations.
You must feel very proud.
Yeah, thank you.
I do.
I mean, I never set out for it to be what it is today.
My sole purpose initially was just to help people and, you know, make their lives better,
free them of pain, rebalance their bodies to see where it is today and to see the number
of people that we have helped around the world is super fulfilling.
When you look back at your decision to create that.
Online platform, which was really ahead of the game in lots of ways prior to COVID.
Do you look back and think that was a real game changer for you?
Yeah, it definitely was.
It definitely was.
I wouldn't say that I had foresight into what was going to happen.
I know you'll talk to a lot of people about their business success and there's always a component of luck to it.
Um, but fluid from at home was created from a really authentic place.
I had clients that traveled a lot, uh, when they, they couldn't get into the studio,
potentially their issues would flare up.
There were people regionally that didn't have access to great Pilates.
And so there just was this need in my, you know, very.
Um, close community of clients to help them, but also in the larger community that, that couldn't get access to things.
So yeah, fluid form was create fluid form at home was created.
So where did the passion for Pilates come from?
So I think I've always.
I've always loved movement and the body.
I studied commerce and marketing at university.
Um, I always toyed around with the thought of being a physio, but I've always been active.
I danced growing up.
Um, you know, I used to run a lot.
I had a knee injury actually, that took me to Pilates and I fell in love with it.
And I've never, you know, I've never looked back.
I did my training.
And then when I moved to the UK with Kingy, I started teaching.
Talk to you about, uh, Kingy.
You're a brilliant, uh, partner in, in a moment, but it takes a lot of school from starting as an instructor to then go on and a lot of vision, create a 65,000 strong community around the world.
Looking back now, what, what do you think's been the keys to enable you to have that success?
Uh, I'm super passionate about helping people.
I get, you know, I don't think there's any bigger buzz in life than, you know, fixing someone, helping people, helping people get rid of their pain.
And just seeing them enjoy life to their fullest.
And so that driver for me and my ability to work, I'm a great worker.
I, um, yeah, I, I'm not afraid to get up early to stay up late.
I can operate on very little sleep that coupled with my passion to help people has definitely helped me get to where I am today.
You hear that a lot, isn't it?
That someone you didn't start out to have this global community that comes from that authentic passion.
That you genuinely love supporting people.
And then maybe a perfect storm.
You've got a commerce degree and a work ethic that is legendary from what I hear.
And you put all those pieces together.
It's probably, as you described, helped you in a way.
And then you've had some really high profile people coming into your world, haven't you?
I was doing my homework and Rita Auras, uh, you know, got a big following.
Elle McPherson, you're in the sporting community.
You've done a huge amount of work with a whole range of people.
How helpful has that been to have those people?
As sort of ambassadors effectively.
Yeah, I mean, they, they are amazing ambassadors and, you know, I'm very grateful that they sort of knock on my door and allow me the privilege to teach them.
You know, I always say it's a privilege to teach people Pilates, you know, people walk in with their greatest asset and hand it over to you.
So you should take care of them and take up, take care of their body.
So those guys, to be honest, I treat them like everyone else because the client that comes in.
Yeah.
Every day that lives around the corner to a business starting out is just as important as those high profile names.
And I think ensuring that there was always that balance for me in my business, not just going out there to teach, you know, the high profile person, because at the end of the day, they won't necessarily enable you to continue to run your business because they come and they go.
So having that balance between the core community, you know, your local community of clients.
And then through that, through that authenticity and that vibration that your business gives out to the world, you attract all of these legendary people.
And they definitely help raise your profile.
Now that I have a global business, I can teach anyone and, you know, teaching Rita enabled me to have more impact into the UK.
Also teaching her husband allowed me to penetrate New Zealand a little bit more.
You know, it definitely all helps, but it's not something that I.
I'm obsessed in and out there trying to do.
Yeah.
It only helps if what you're doing works too, doesn't it?
It's only helps if it's authentic and you can see that come out in everything that you say.
I rang your husband, Matty King, who NRL legend is a great way to describe Matty, but he's one of the nicest people on the planet, your partner, and he's got such a big heart.
And every time you get the privilege to speak to him, it just makes you smile.
And the way he spoke about you yesterday made me smile all day.
Yeah.
He's loved for you clearly, but he said, and I think this is a good point.
You read the headline, you think, God, Kirsten King's had this remarkable success and life must come easy.
And he said, well, you probably need to understand more about some of the hardships along the way.
And he was encouraging me to ask you about it.
And I know some of this you probably haven't shared so widely, but, you know, he was sharing with me a really personal, tragic story from you as a 16-year-old growing up.
He said that you lost your brother who was 19 at that stage in a car accident.
And it's every family's worst nightmare.
I just can't even imagine what you went through at that age.
Did that shape you a lot as a 16-year-old?
Yeah.
Yeah, definitely.
I think it's probably was a turning point in my life.
At the time, I don't think I fully understood what my mum and dad were going through.
And I've only really understood that now once I've had my own children.
So the loss was obviously significant and heartbreaking.
For me, as I was the middle child, even more so probably at that time, had more impact on my little sister.
And then mum and dad just, you know, they tried to continue on.
But for a long time, I was there, you know, holding everyone's hand, keeping everything going and had to compartmentalise, I guess, the loss of my brother to ensure that everyone else was OK.
And whether I was born that way or learnt how to do that, you know, during that time, it is definitely a skill, I think, to be able to, you know, compartmentalise something so tragic and hard and then selflessly move forward and look after those around you.
And that's something that I started doing then and I probably still do or I definitely still do today.
Does that come at a cost sometimes?
For you personally, when in a devastating situation, you've got everyone else's back sorted, but looking after yourself sometimes, is that hard?
Yeah, definitely.
You know, you have to look after yourself to look after others, you know, a great leadership quality.
And I've probably learnt that along the way.
As a 16-year-old girl, you're pretty resilient.
You know, your mum and dad are everything to you.
So is your younger sister.
You still have to turn up to school and no one wants to talk to you because no one wants to, you know, broach that subject.
So you just learn to move on.
And I think it does affect you later down the track.
I probably have become a lot more emotional in my older age.
I suppressed my emotions definitely when I was younger.
And it just changes your perspective on things.
And how you don't sweat the small stuff.
You know, it's not life or death.
Okay, let's move on.
So, yeah, I definitely look at things in a different way.
Kingy was sharing with me yesterday.
He said he just has got such admiration for your resilience.
And when tragic things happen, he said you have this ability that's unique.
You know, he was again sharing.
And I hope you don't mind.
You've got three beautiful daughters.
But he said there were three miscarriages, you know, before that.
And he said...
Your ability to just, okay, we're going to go to work the next day
and we're going to get through this.
I mean, how is that?
Do you think, as you said, being the middle child part of who you are
or what you developed from that early tragedy?
I think it has to be a little bit of it, a little bit of both.
I think the pressure as well of having your own business and being a leader.
You know, you're the one that always has to be positive.
You're the one out the front.
You know, you're climbing that hill.
You might be struggling, but if you start to struggle
and you're not going to be able to do it, you're going to be struggling.
When you look over your shoulder, you know,
your greater team are going to start struggling too.
I'm surrounded by a lot of females in my business
and everyone goes through tragedy.
Everyone has lost.
And I think that's probably what, you know,
I learnt from my brother's passing too.
You know, we lost him and it was a tragedy.
But there's a lot of people that go through some pretty tough stuff.
And I think because I was one that, you know,
compartmentalised it and moved on,
and you just never know what anyone else is going through in the world.
So, you know, you have to be kind and you have to just be aware
of others and how they're feeling.
I think, you know, with my miscarriages,
it wasn't that I didn't want to share, but for me, it's not about me.
It's about everyone else.
You know, I take care of everyone else.
And maybe sometimes I suffer in silence.
I don't think I do.
I think maybe I'm just born that way.
I have this ability.
But, you know, it's in my nature to take care of you
before I'll take care of myself.
Beautiful quality to have, isn't it?
It's fascinating to hear.
And, again, I think I know when I sit down and have these conversations,
the headlines are always amazing and you think,
well, how do you start and create what you've created?
But I think allowing people in to see that there's been incredible hurdles
along the way and including in your partnership.
And I know you've had some challenges.
I know you've had some challenges there where partners have come
and it's not worked out and you've had to have some legal challenges
along the way.
Have you got some insight in to share about what, you know,
good partnerships look like and what lessons you've learned
along the way in that front?
Yeah, definitely.
I think, you know, my partnerships in business came about from, you know,
being lonely in business.
People don't often talk about when you're a leader and, you know,
you're pioneering a way.
You're, you know, in your chosen profession and you're at the top of your game.
All of a sudden, you can look around and there's no one really next to you.
You've got your team, definitely, who are supporting you and embracing that vision.
But people start, whether it's jealousy or they don't believe you should have
that success, people start to change.
And it's all of a sudden you're standing at the top on your own
and it becomes lonely.
And that was the driver for me to move into a partnership in my business.
I thought it was the way to go to begin and it just didn't end up working out in the end.
And I think my biggest learning from that was it's not about that initial relationship.
It's not about that initial marriage.
And at the time, everything seems rosy and everything seems like we're going
to do this together.
But it's not.
It's not.
It's actually you need to have the foresight to look at what happens
if there is a divorce, for want of a better word.
And I have friends at the moment in business.
I call them and they might be doing deals and I say to them, you know,
they say, oh, but this, this, and this, it's great.
It's going to work.
And I'm like, okay.
And you don't want to be, you know, mis-negative.
But I just say to them, that's fine now, but you just don't know what's going
to change in people's lives or in their,
people aren't all resilient.
You know, they can't get on with stuff for a long time.
And when there starts to get a few hurdles and potentially the job isn't
panning out like you thought it was going to, sometimes then that relationship
can fracture and can break.
You know, more often than not in business, they can't be repaired.
And so the divorce clause has to be executed and you just need
to make sure it's a good one.
Yeah, it's stressful, isn't it?
And I have been through that a couple of times as well.
And you're right, you start up with great intentions and great vision
and you can see the harmony, but you're right.
It's not always with malice that it ends, but then when it does,
trying to unpick that if you're not clear at the start is just a nightmare
and stressful and relationships break down.
And you're right.
I mean, it's a common thing you hear, but it's still, you know,
I always think the greatest learnings I ever had were in those situations.
And I didn't have any idea of setting it up right at the start,
but you certainly learn along the way, Kirsten.
I can hear that that's something you have definitely done along the way.
Is it going to stand you in better stead now, you think,
having weathered those storms?
Yeah.
I mean, there's, if you have, if anyone has had a partnership breakdown
in the past in business, you definitely want to learn from it
and you don't want to be scarred from it.
You don't want it to stop who you are.
As a person, and I am super trusting and kind
and I am fully supportive of everyone around me.
And when you're taken advantage of, for want of a better word,
you start to look at yourself in the mirror and you think,
well, maybe I need to be tougher.
Maybe I shouldn't say yes all the time.
Maybe I, you know, need to be a bit meaner.
But then that takes away from who you are and why all these amazing things
have been attracted to you.
And why you're allowed to take care of people
and they let you into their life.
So that's probably one of the hardest things after a breakdown
is just taking the learnings and then parking that and moving forward
and not going back to it.
You almost need to erase it.
Learn from it, erase it, and let's go.
Reminds me of my dad, Kirsten.
We grew up in the hospitality industry and the old-fashioned pubs
and lived upstairs.
And I can think of as a kid four or five times where someone had worked
with my mum and dad really closely or been a partner and there was a range
of disastrous things that happened.
And I remember as I got older, I asked dad, I said, how did you move on?
And he said, well, you just have to trust the next person and you just move on
and you hope the next person is a great person because it's going to be
a really narrow life if you don't trust again.
And it's always stayed with me that, yeah, if you decide then that that's it,
I'm never going to collaborate.
But again, it's a pretty narrow world you live in.
You mentioned before, Kirsten, that loneliness is something that leaders face
and we feel really privileged to have crossed over with you.
And A Leader Connect, it's something we're really passionate about
and inspiring people like you with your stories and appreciate you sharing
it so openly today.
And then having a group of five or six who come from different worlds
around you and collaborating and sharing and learning together.
Can I ask you about A Leader Connect?
Has that had an influence on you?
Yeah, it's been amazing.
I had no idea what I was embarking on when I dove, you know, headfirst into it.
Obviously, Kingy had been part of it and through COVID, I'd hear him on Zoom calls
and he would always get off so inspired and just and almost look forward,
you know, you look forward to the next one.
And that intrigued me.
And so, obviously, you know, I joined a group.
And the same thing happened to me, you know, a group of like-minded but so different.
And here you are on this Zoom call feeling within the first session
like you intimately know these people and care for them
and want to help them and look after them.
And then all of a sudden realizing that even though you're
in totally different industries, different ages in terms of and,
you know, like years of experience, but we're all going through the,
you know, same thing, or we've been through it and we can help each other.
Or there's just this hurdle that you can't see past.
And then you share it with the group and there's five answers in 40 minutes.
And you think, I have not slept for two weeks thinking about that.
Like, how is this possible?
So, yeah, it's extraordinary.
It's pretty special.
I mean, I've said it to Matt as well, your business partner, it is, it's really special.
And the fact that the people that join a leader totally let down their guard.
I think that's what's so amazing because as leaders and, you know,
in my group, some extraordinary people with extraordinary experience
have just come on this phone call and dropped their guard.
And what happens there is magical.
That's a beautiful description of it, Kirsten.
I appreciate it.
And if you don't mind, I might share just some of the diversity in your group.
I think it paints a picture.
Yeah.
It's a picture.
Di Richardson's founded a business called Principal Media Group and they do amazing
things in their world.
Sean Wellman is one of the great people I've met in sport.
Well, he was a premiership player at Essendon, but runs a really successful finance space.
Justin Walter and ASX listed medical imaging business.
Andrew Sutherland's the happiest person on the planet, Kirsten.
You've never met anyone quite like Sutherland.
I'm lucky to call him a friend, but from his world of cybersecurity to property,
and incredible personality, Blackburn's doing amazing things as a leader in her world
as a captain of an AFLW team, the Western Bulldogs.
It's very different backgrounds, isn't it?
You put Kirsten King in with your experience.
It's fascinating to see the different thinking and how that benefits people.
And that sounds like what you found.
Yeah, definitely.
It's at the end of the day, you know, we all realized it comes down to people and making
sure, you know, what you learn on that journey is making sure that you can take care of yourself
first.
And then take care of others around you.
And in its simplest form, that is leadership.
But when you are at the top as a leader, you sometimes forget about yourself.
And you get so stuck in the day-to-day of your own business, and you're tired because
you're not taking care of yourself.
And then you start to lose that ability to make decisions and make good ones and make
them in a timely manner.
And I think that too, with being able to connect.
With all those amazing people, you know, fortnightly, you will force to take a self-check each time
too.
So for some of us that were out of the habit, maybe of taking care of ourselves, it really
allowed us to get back on that pathway.
Yeah, the experience across the board, you know, even from Ellie in the AFL world and
through to Andrew with, you know, from Visi to cybersecurity, it's, you know, leadership
doesn't really change what's happening.
What's happening in business doesn't really change.
It's just great to be surrounded by people who are willing to share their experience
intimately.
And at times your solution is just right there.
Yeah, beautifully said, Kirsten.
You articulate that in a really fascinating way for me.
And leading into what we have found is exactly as you said, is that success leaves clues
and there are patterns around, whether it's growing an online community in the health
and fitness space as you've done, or an elite athlete or someone in a, in a completely different,
you know, environment.
And we think that idea, as you mentioned before, that leaders have to show up for themselves
first to lead others.
And self-leadership is really the dimension we always think of at the start.
And you probably just answered that.
When you think about self-leadership, Kirsten, what does that mean to you?
I think first and foremost, it is about turning up for you.
You know, you are in my role as a leader, I'm very compassionate, caring, supportive.
So, yeah.
In order for me to fill everyone else's cup, my cup needs to be filled up.
And don't get me wrong, I'm not always great at it, but you become aware really quickly
when you're starting to be depleted, whether that's in your workplace or at home.
You know, I'm not, I'm not only a leader at Fluidform, I'm also a leader at home.
I've got three young girls and I want to be the best possible role model I can to them.
So I've got to have two leadership hats.
And that can be, you know, draining.
And fatiguing as well.
So for me, you know, making sure that movement is part of every day for me, whether it's
15 minutes at home, whether it's a class in one of the studios, making sure I'm having
time just to think, you know, to think about, to dream, you know, about that big picture
stuff, because that really motivates you when you're dealing with the day to day.
I think making sure that your dream is constant.
And you're thinking about it is so important and not being so hard on yourself.
I think we are just as human beings, just so hard on ourselves these days from, you
know, the access of social media and everything that is thrown at us and what we see and the
pressures we just need to be more compassionate to our own self.
And if we need that time out to have it, you know, you need our eldest daughter, Charlie,
she graduated from primary school.
It was like a fanfare.
There was so many activities on and, you know, I was trying to juggle work the entire week
and it was just at one point I was like, I can't go to work on Wednesday, I've got too
much on.
And you know, I'm always really honest with my team, guys, this is what's on with Charlie,
can't make it in, call me if you need me, but I'll see you on Thursday.
And just knowing that I had that time for her and didn't have to worry about anything
on that day.
It just allowed everything else to continue to flow.
Because it's all about flow, you know, find your state of flow and stay in it when you
can.
And how brilliant is that for your team that you've just shown them that family comes first
by taking that action.
And as the leader, no matter how busy work was, I'm having that day because that is the
most important thing in my life.
And that allows them to be able to ring you one day and say, hey, Kirsten, I really need
this day and know that they're going to be supported.
And that's, you know, how great culture starts and continues.
And you can see, listening to you about your passion was about helping people.
And we see that for leaders, they're really conscious about how they have a positive impact
on a daily basis.
How have you gone about that?
Yeah, for me, I mean, probably going back to what you said, what I said before, I'm
really transparent with my team.
I treat them like an extension of my family.
I need them to understand that.
As much as fluid form is a passion, that, you know, my family, you know, is equally,
if not, you know, my greatest passion.
So I find what works for me is allowing them in.
You know, there's no need for them not to know what I'm doing, where I am.
Some days I might have to leave early and I'm on the tennis court with the girls.
They're doing a tennis lesson.
I've got my computer on my lap.
I'm working away.
I'm watching them.
And, you know, you just have to do it.
You become really great at juggling.
But always just allowing them to know where I am and what I'm doing and likewise them
with me.
You know, it's not, like you said, uncommon for someone to say, hey, Ki, can I leave at
4.30?
I've got a physio appointment.
It's never, ever a question of yes or no.
It's just they're letting me know and I know where they are.
And so I think that is really important.
I never wanted to be that leader that was like up there in her glass box and no one
really knew what she did when she left her glass box.
Yeah.
We have an open environment in the office, but also in our studios.
So a fluid form studio is not segmented into rooms.
It's open plan.
And the thinking from that comes back to being able to collaborate, you know, to learn on
the job.
A lot of new instructors are young.
So I don't want them in a room with the door shut on their own, in their own thoughts,
potentially.
They're getting lost in their programming.
I want them in a space where there's other instructors around them that they can feel
confident from and potentially see someone teaching and it might interest them.
And they ask after a lesson, oh, Ki, why did you teach that?
I'd love to know what you were doing there and why that helped that client so much.
So even in our studios, it's very much about supporting each other and having that transparency
across what we do.
Yeah.
The next dimension I wanted to ask you about.
It's a, it's a big vision to, to create a global community.
How have you gone about creating and sharing that vision with your team?
Well, Fluid Form at Home started as a local sort of Australian thought process.
And then two years after it launched, COVID hit.
So we very quickly overnight were sending our equipment packs all around the world.
I guess that wasn't a planned vision.
Yeah.
But as it started to happen, we were all together sending packs to Afghanistan, to the frontline,
to, you know, Iceland, to Barbados, you name it, there was a Fluid Form pack flying there.
And so as a team that we were on that journey together, we very much were holding each other's
hands.
And that's probably something as well, as a leader, I like to be, to work alongside
the team.
I don't always want it to be me at first.
Yeah.
I think it's important to be able to be together and to, you know, everyone needs to be able
to roll their sleeves up.
I think that vision as those packs started to fly around the world, it just became really
apparent to us that we can actually help people all around the world.
We can make people's lives better.
And because of the intimacy and the access to me as a founder, and I wanted to be so
heavily involved in it.
We, I constantly receive, you know, probably 20 emails a day from Fluid Form at Home members
telling me about, you know, I was going in for back surgery, just went to see my surgeon.
I'm not anymore.
I haven't been able to get down on the rug and play with my son in over three years.
Now I can, you know, my football career, I was being injured again and again and again,
and I've just played the most number of games in my career without an injury, you know,
and that is all.
It's all from Fluid Form at Home.
So once we started to see and experience what was, you know, this brand was capable of,
we then, we knew what our vision was, you know, we're in 99 countries around the world
now.
We just continue to exceed expectations is, you know, what we say internally, no matter
whether that's online or in the studio.
And we come from a really great place together as a team of wanting to make people's lives
better.
And we've made a lot of progress.
And I think we've all been successful in that.
And I think that's what it's all about.
We've been successful in that.
And I'm sure we've all done well, but I think it's just the time and order coming in from
Iceland and Afghanistan.
And I can just imagine how full on that would have been, but you then have to execute too,
don't you?
People have to get their products.
They have to still be able to, as you said, value it and change their lives around the
globe.
It's a, it's a brilliant story.
Curiosity is a word that comes up in our space all the time at Elida and we see through curiosity,
people are constantly trying to learn and develop and how they approach their life through
curiosity.
Is that something that resonates with you?
Yeah, definitely.
Yeah, definitely. I'm always curious as to what we can do next as a team. Where can the brand go?
You know, what would it look like if we did this? And I think you have to be curious. Otherwise,
you become fatigued in your day-to-day capabilities and your day-to-day role. I think
for your clients, you don't want them to become fatigued with the product. You know,
you need to continue to challenge what's out there, challenge the norm, you know,
be curious about potentially where you could take the brand. And particularly from an IT
point of view and, you know, at the moment, you know, I say to the team, the answer should never
be, no, we can't. It should be, why can't, you know, why can't we do that and find out what the
is and let's fix that. And for me, that's probably one of the
key pillars as a leader. You know, you want to be, even with your staff, never assume that they
don't want to grow or never assume that they don't want that next step or they don't want to move
from operations into marketing. You know, be curious, talk to them, start the conversation
because you just never know what's in their head or what's out there.
Yeah, which leads really to that communication part of anyone who's had success in communicating
with clarity. It sounds like you've got some clear...
Yeah, I think for us, you know, traditionally as a studio, because Fluidform started as a studio
in person, when you are a Pilates instructor or you're an instructor of any type of movement
method, your communication is key. I would like to think I'm a good communicator. But then
likewise with your team, you know, I haven't always got it right. I stumbled initially because
I thought, oh, Kirsten doesn't know how to do it. I don't know how to do it. I don't know how to
do it. She doesn't want to work Thursday nights and Saturdays. She wouldn't want to do that.
And next thing, Kirsten has a job with someone else on a Thursday night and a Saturday. And you're
like, oh, my gosh, how? And why didn't you come to me first? And, you know, why, why, why? And so
I learned early on, never assume, ask the question, because the worst thing that can happen is that
they say no. And sometimes the no doesn't mean no as well. I mean, you have to really keep the
communication open. Also, if you're a Pilates instructor, you have to know how to communicate
that is why I'm super transparent with my life outside of the office, because I want my staff
to be like that. I want to know how they're feeling. I want to know if things aren't
going well in their life. And I have a pretty good radar with people and I have a pretty good gut.
And I can sort of tell when someone's not OK. And I'm very comfortable with having
those conversations. You know, when you teach Pilates movements, probably
60 percent of it and 40 percent of it is life coach slash counselor. You learn to communicate
with your clients. You know, you're essentially doing that as much as you are teaching them and
strengthening their bodies. But my biggest, I guess my biggest project with communication was
before I launched Fluidform at home. You know, it was a big deal. I sat on it for probably 12
months because it meant I was taking myself out there to the world.
Well, here I am. This is my movement method. You're going to be judged. You're going to be
criticized. You're going to have copycats, all of it. So I had to be really comfortable. I had to
be confident. I'm quite conservative in my approach. So I did my programs. I set it up in
the studio. I had clients in the space and I stood in the corner of the room and I faced the wall
and I had a video camera up and I just spoke.
Through the programs. So, you know, stand with your left leg forward, right leg back, hinge at
the hip, blah, blah, blah. Recorded it and then watched it back. And so I needed to know that
without seeing anyone, without having hands-on corrections, which is a big part of our in-studio
experience, that people could follow my cues, my, you know, my instruction and still get a great
workout, feel it the next day, but have the same experience that they did in studio.
So, you know, for a few weeks I stood in the corner looking at the wall and just went through
all my programs and it worked. So when I was confident with that, I was then confident to
say, okay, let's do this. Let's take that out to everyone else.
Yeah. What an amazing way to test it. And then to see it go around the globe must have been
incredibly satisfying and to translate into different language, different countries,
different fields and movement perhaps is a common language, but it's brilliant to see.
How important has collaboration been for you?
Huge. I mean, for me in my studios, I collaborate with my instructors on a, you know, day-to-day
basis, but probably the biggest collaboration for me was fluid form at home. I had to build a website.
I needed someone to do the video. I needed sound. I needed editing. So there is a team,
a team of people that, who are external, obviously to fluid form,
but they are so important. They are like, they work with us day-to-day and I needed to share
my vision with them, you know, so I make them part of the experience of fluid form. I send them,
I, you know, I make sure that they receive client feedback because, you know, as much as it's me on
the screen, they put as much time into it as I do. So, you know, we're all equal. Collaboration
for me is about, like we said early, sharing the vision, but making everyone feel,
supported and equal, you know, part of the team. I'm not, I'm not huge into sort of hierarchy. I
understand that you need, obviously people have different roles on paper and different
responsibilities, but at the end of the day, everyone is here for a reason. You know, you
have a skill that I don't have, you know, you have a responsibility that I don't have and together
we share a common vision and should be working together. And when you create those conditions,
Kirsten, we often,
see that someone might be working as an editor on your video, but has an idea about something that
you've never even thought of, but you've allowed them to share it because of the way that you set
up. And you're right. Someone has to make the decision. So we understand that, but the best
organizations we're seeing have that space where someone on their first day may have an idea,
but you'll never know if you don't have the space for them to feel comfortable to share it. And
that sounds like you're doing that. Yeah, definitely. It's important. You,
the little pearls of wisdom that
have come out of the most unexpected mouth sometimes is just, I mean, that's what,
that's what running a business is about. That's what being a great leader is. And then taking
that and allowing people to just feel valued. Yeah. I often say having worked in the television
and called sport on TV, the people who know TV better than anyone else are holding the cameras
or working behind the scenes, but I often wonder, I know they don't get asked, you know, they don't
get asked their thoughts and it's a,
it's a waste of all this great experience and, and knowledge. Kirsten, who's been the greatest
leader in your life? I think, you know, definitely my mom and dad, you know, from an early age,
they, they taught me about work ethic. They're both great workers, super, super resilient humans
and, you know, the ability to juggle, you know, multiple things at once. So they obviously,
you know, have led,
that pathway for me. And then I think, you know, from, from a business perspective,
you know, I've had some great mentors over the years, but probably starting fluid form,
it would be the people around me every day that I'm learning from, you know, not, not necessarily
that person that gave me, you know, the task when I was younger, but watching my team around me
lead their clients, look after their clients and learning from them. I have so many leaders in my
business. You know, we all approach things slightly differently. You know, I'm still
learning every day, which is what I love. Brilliant answer, isn't it? To, to, you know,
not put yourself in a position where you feel like you're the font of all the knowledge in
your organization, that the great leaders actually come into your space and you learn from them. It's
a, it's a really intriguing to hear you describe that. I'm, I'm not surprised by the,
by the person that you are.
I love asking this question as well, Kirsten, and the spirit of collaboration. And we love that
at a leader, this world of collaboration and inspiring connections. Is there been someone
you thought on any, you know, you've done some great collaborations with unique people and
to get into 99 countries now, you have to collaborate. Has there been somebody who
thought, God, that's the person or the organization I'd love to collaborate with?
Yeah, I must say I'm a bit of a Gwyneth Paltrow goop fan. So I feel like if a fluid form
could, you know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't know, I don't
know. I would do a goop collaboration. I mean, she's so inspiring in, you know, just from like
health, physical, mental, you know, sexual sort of unspoken topics, what she's done in that space
for females is extraordinary. So from a movement point of view, I really feel like, you know,
we could add value, it would be, you know, a collaboration, which could be, you know,
quite amazing. So that would be one that I would.
I would definitely have on my storyboard. And then not from a person point of view, but
I've always, you know, like Nike as a brand, you know, Phil Knight, you know, his book,
he has just fearless ambition. And Nike still haven't had a Pilates ambassador worldwide.
So that's, you know, they've got yoga, they've got every other sport.
But they haven't dived into Pilates as yet. And that would be something that I think
would be pretty cool too.
There's a couple of inspiring collaborations, Kirsten. I loved it. It's, you know, think of
from a Hollywood actress into creating that movement is an amazing story, isn't it? And
hadn't thought of that, isn't it? Nike have got every other base covered, but Pilates is such a
huge and so well known now, isn't it? Athletes and people understand that the power of what you do,
I wouldn't put it past fluid form ending up in either of those spaces. And I really appreciate
you taking the time to share your story so openly and really learned a lot from it today. We love
collaborating with you in our space as well. And I wish you all the best. It's a great story
unfolding. I feel like you're just getting started as well, Kirsten. So thanks again for
taking the time today. Thanks, Luke. It's been fun. Thanks for having me.
Thank you for listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast powered by temper, a mattress like no
other.
And to make sure you don't miss an episode, click subscribe wherever you get your podcasts.