Tony Blauer is an internationally renowned expert when it comes to fear management and
self-defense. Here, Tony explained why he thinks making friends with fear is such an
important skill to learn. I realized something very powerful, this is about 1985,
and it became this expression that the people who manage their fear manage to fight it. And
it didn't matter if that was in business, for your relationship, for your health,
for your finances, or for your personal safety. There's so much I could talk about this,
but it's really been the story of my life. Also, I found it interesting to hear Tony explain
that no one teaches us that really courageous people feel fear as well.
Famous stories of George St. Pierre, one of the greatest mixed martial artists.
Mike Tyson used to throw up and cry before fights. St. Pierre, who's considered the goat
in MMA, one of them, recently came out and said the worst day of his life was every day he had
to fight. He loved the training, but he hated, he dreaded,
dreaded, dreaded, dreaded, dreaded, dreaded, dreaded, dreaded, dreaded, dreaded, dreaded,
dreaded, dreaded, dreaded, dreaded, dreaded, dreaded, dreaded, dreaded, dreaded, dreaded, dreaded,
fight day. We all want our kids to be resilient and deal with the inevitable hurdles that life
throws our way. Have a listen to Tony's advice for parents. So I've got a program with the words
no fear on it, and it's spelled K-N-O-W, not N-O, because I don't believe there's such a thing as
no fear. That's rationalizing. Remember the Richard Feynman quote, right? But there's
getting to no fear. When you get to no fear, you can use fear as fuel. You become
adaptive. You become more resilient. You become mentally tough. International leaders,
and fear experts, people like Tony Blau, inspire the work that we do at Alita.
We're passionate about removing people from silos, bringing people together to learn to
share and connect. Check out our signature program called Alita Connect. Go to alitacollective.com,
book a discovery call today. We'd love to collaborate with you. Big thanks to Jason
Nicholas and his team from Temper Bedding Australia. Great leaders, people who understand
success, all value their sleep. Temper is a mattress like no other. NASA approved.
Buying a Temper mattress will change your life.
Tony Blau is a world-renowned self-defense and fear management expert and has been a visible
force in the martial arts, self-defense, defensive tactics, and combatives industry for over four
decades. As the CEO of Blau Tactical Systems, his organization has grown into one of the world's
leading consulting companies specializing in the research and development of performance psychology,
personal safety, and close quarter tactic and scenario-based training for defensive tactics,
combatives, and professional self-defense.
Blau's training systems and equipment are used by the military, law enforcement,
martial artists, and citizens around the world. He has researched and studied fear and believes
strongly that if you can change your relationship with fear, you can change your life. Tony,
great to catch up with you. Thanks for joining me today.
Thank you.
Well, you've achieved a lot over a long period of time in a unique way, and it's a fascinating
story. A leading psychologist wrote that he found your research on fear to have been more effective
for clients.
Any material learned in 20 years of practice, why has understanding fear been so important for you?
That's crazy. And the day that there's a gentleman named Jeff D'Ateso, the day he said that to me,
we were on a call. He works with vets, military vets dealing with PTSD, one of his specialties.
And he said to me, this really resonates. It's helping them more than anything in 20 years.
I go, holy shit, Jeff, that might be the best thing I've ever heard about my,
in 20 years of practice.
I said, too bad we can't use it because you can't say that. He said, you can say that. It's true.
So it's on our No Fear website. But I love sharing that anecdote because it's outrageous
at a certain level. My relationship and my experience with fear has been, I'm turning 65
this year, has been like every day I have fear about something. I make the joke that if you
want to learn how to manage fear, you need to talk to somebody who manages fear. I'm very,
Very often when we want to experience courage or have a more courageous lifestyle, whether
it's being an entrepreneur, being a better parent, being able to protect ourselves, we
very often seek out people that I refer to as unicorns in their world.
Like, I want to be like that.
And if you talk to somebody who doesn't manage fear, they won't understand how to teach you
because they're the unicorn.
They don't go, I don't know why I'm not afraid here.
And so the number one fear in the world still, it's not getting dragged into an alley and
beaten and raped and taken to a secondary crime scene.
It's public speaking is still the number one fear in the world.
It's wild what our minds do with that.
So I'm fascinated by the whole thing because I can't ever remember not being afraid, even
as a kid.
Every sport I played, whether wrestling, skiing, swimming, when I got into martial arts, if
I was in school, the teacher would go.
Okay, Tony, what is the answer?
I'd be like freaking out.
I couldn't understand it.
When I started teaching self-defense around 1977 and 1980, it became professional.
I realized that a lot of the people that were coming to learn from me had fear too.
And I was doing these scenario-based training.
I would make a joke.
It was kind of like Fight Club before Fight Club, the movie.
We were like doing these wild scenarios in the basement of my school.
And I noticed something that was so peculiar.
That people who I thought were going to do well in the scenario didn't and other people
did.
And I was always like intuitively, unconsciously studying behavior.
I didn't want to and couldn't talk about that vulnerability.
Like when you're 7 or 11 or 15 or 20, it doesn't occur to you to say, you know, to turn like
you and I are about to do something.
I'm not going to turn to you and go, hey, are you scared shitless, man?
Because I am, right?
And because especially guys were macho about that sort of stuff.
I realized something very powerful.
This is about 1985.
And it became this expression that the people who manage their fear managed to fight.
When I would talk to people after, like, how did you do that?
What was going on?
Like this kind of Socratic debrief.
The person I thought was going to like roll over, tap out, freak out.
And we were doing like full-on scenarios, like force on force scenarios.
And they would always talk about the same thing.
Well, I knew I couldn't stop or I didn't want to do this.
And even though I was scared and it just hit me one day, the people who managed their fear
managed to fight.
And it didn't.
It didn't matter if that was in business for your relationship, for your health, for your
finances or for your personal safety.
There's so much I could talk about about this, but it's really been the story of my life.
And I realized that if there's one superpower, you know, we talk about self-awareness as our
superpower, but you can't fully actualize self-awareness if you're rationalizing fear.
So if you're there's a Richard Feynman is a famous physicist, mathematician.
He said, the first principle is never fool yourself.
And remember, you're the easiest person to fool.
And what we do is we rationalize why we're going to do something or did something or not going to do
something.
And most of the time, it's the, it's the effect of psychological fear influencing our behavior.
And we can't manipulate that because we don't have the self-awareness to understand that.
That's a great point, Tony.
We're not told or taught that courageous people feel fear as well, whether it's a seal team,
six commando.
I played a sport called Australian rules football that I'm sure you know nothing about,
but the scariest player in our era was a guy called Tony Lockett.
And he was the most intimidating.
You didn't want to go near him on the field, but it wasn't until he retired.
We found out that he was so anxious before a game.
He was physically ill almost every game.
And like he made a lot of us feel physically ill because he was a chance to kill you if
you went near him.
But he obviously managed his fear in a way that made him so.
And I think that's the point you're making, isn't it?
That fear is normal.
It's just the ability to manage it is something that you're really passionate about.
Is that, is that how you'd sum it up?
Yeah.
I mean, you bring up a great point.
There's, there's famous stories of George St.
Pierre, one of the greatest mixed martial artists, Mike Tyson used to throw up and cry
before fights.
St.
Pierre, who was like one of the, you know, he's considered the goat, you know, in, in
MMA, one of them, you know, recently came out and said the worst day of his life was every
day he had to fight.
He loved the training.
But he hated, he dreaded, dreaded the fight day.
But what we see is 4% body fat, Superman punched through the air, knocking out all these people,
not realizing this guy didn't sleep the night before, couldn't eat the day before.
And then you go in there, see him and go, man, I got to be like that.
And I, it was funny because I was, I was on a call this morning with a group of people
that I coach.
And I said to them, I said, how many of you have been intimidated in your life?
All the hands come up.
And I went.
Do you realize that you, including myself, intimidate ourselves?
But what we tell people is I go, Hey, that guy intimidated me.
His intensity intimidated me.
His impact, the force of his nature intimidated me, or you threatened me.
And that was intimidating.
But what we're doing is we're talking about, I love the acronym, false expectations appearing
real, where we're visualizing an event in the future that's immobilizing us in the present.
It hasn't happened yet, but it's impacting our behavior.
And so probably two decades ago, I came up with this new way to think about the psychology
of intimidation and all of us experience intimidation.
The gift in this insight, if you grasp it, is that we intimidate ourselves by visualizing
what we think is going to happen.
And if you're feeling intimidation, it's because you're visualizing a negative outcome.
The power we have is suppressed.
It's because of the fear we hold.
And that fear isn't the enemy.
Fear is our energy, but only if you can change your relationship with it.
So when you get a fear spike in your body, anxiety, butterflies in your stomach, sweaty
palms, vertical breathing, whatever, however it shows up in you, is if you look at that
as if you were working in the military and you're monitoring radar, and you see a blip
and you go, is that a missile or is that a flock of birds?
You got to check it out.
But if you do this, you're going to see a blip.
You're going to see a blip.
And that's what a lot of us do when we get a psychological fear spike.
We say, we go into denial.
We go, man, I don't believe this is happening.
And that's the message.
Like in our self-defense protocol, we talk about like this timeline of violence or timeline
of escalation.
It's a 30,000 foot view.
And we talk about the three Ds, detect, defuse, defend, detect and avoid, defuse to de-escalate,
like defuse, like D-E-F-U-S-E, take the fuse out.
And then if you can't, you defend yourself.
So, you know, it's a lot of times when you're in a situation where you're in a situation
where you're in the D1, D2 phase is where you go, you get this bad feeling about anything.
What are you going to do now?
And to make decisions early, you need to manage fear.
Because when we're in the fear loop, we're procrastinating.
And whatever's happening is getting closer and closer and closer.
And it could be root canal.
It could be imminent danger.
It could be, you know, finances.
It could be health.
It could be a relationship.
Things rarely just happen.
Tony, I love your point around the mind and how...
You play out these scenarios of fear that become so real in our mind
that often don't eventuate either.
And your body reacts in the way that it may as well have happened to you anyway.
You produce the same chemical reactions in your body.
And that's where a lot of stress and anxiety comes for a lot of people.
And understanding that and understanding the mind the way you described
is a really powerful thing.
I want to go back to 2009, Tony.
I was reading in preparation for the conversation,
you experienced your own fear to deal with in a really extreme way.
Your family.
I had a violent confrontation that changed everything in your life at that time.
Within days of that home invasion, you had an employee betray you and forced you to shut
down the company.
You spent decades building and a group of trainers you've mentored effectively took
your IP and your contacts.
That's a whole lot of stuff to deal with.
And I'm assuming a lot of fear.
When you're in that scenario, how did you find a way through it?
I mean, it took years.
It literally took years.
And ironically, yesterday was the 15th anniversary of that event.
It was...
The most chaotic blend of fear and anger that I've ever experienced.
But listen, a home invasion, and I wasn't home for it, my family experienced it.
So I had, I carry around massive shame about that because I wasn't there to protect them.
So extreme anger and fear for me.
And I immediately focused on my family.
The week after it happened, I get a letter from one of our suppliers.
That they wanted to buy my equipment company for a ridiculously low number.
Like, if you know anything about valuations and EBITDA and stuff like that.
And I answered back.
I said, I literally said, are you high?
Like in the message, like you're drunk, you're smoking crack and you're on Jack Daniels.
What kind of number is that?
And then I get a call from the lawyer of the company that I'm partnered with saying, you
need to sell it to them or we're going to remove you of management.
You're the manager of the company.
And, and I'm like, how can you do that?
Like I'm the 50, 50 and the guy says, well, your COO has vested equity and he's voting with us.
So they had been planning this.
It turns out the cops caught the guys that did the home invasion.
And, uh, one of the guys worked for a carwash company that had a contract with my partner.
And they had been at my house the week before washing my wife's car.
So I'm dealing with, oh my God.
That's a setup because I was so unbalanced and I just wanted to protect my family that
when they started pushing to sell the company, I literally, I don't know if I can swear on
your show.
I said, fuck off.
I'm out of here.
And I signed without like, like really getting educated on the whole thing.
And then I immediately realized what was happening and I dissolved the company.
I signed off the manufacturing side and I dissolved the whole training side.
And three of the people I had mentored.
Who were like running different divisions.
We had a personal defense program.
We had a combatants program, military law enforcement.
I call them in and I say, listen, man, I'm dissolving the company.
Our equipment's being manufactured by these guys.
And we're going to rebuild the training division.
And they all like just went, we're out of here.
And next thing I know, like a month later, they're contacting my clients.
And this all literally happened like within a month and a half.
So I was being hit from my training.
I had a guy that was working for me, who's a family member, a brother-in-law
contacting clients saying, Hey, and it was a hard, hard lesson for me.
And when you say, how did you get through it?
I got through it in ways I can't imagine.
I mean, it took five years to rebuild the company.
I moved us to California and my wife's crying.
Like right after the crazy.
Craziness, man, like helicopters over our house, you know, reporters knocking
because what happened was unheard of in our area, which made it even more
suspicious that it did.
There was tears.
There was anger.
There was, Oh, what do I do to just at the end of the day?
You know what it is?
It's it's if I asked you, what was the hardest hit you ever took?
And were you relying on your back and you looked up and you see stars and
and there's three of your, there's one person looking over you and you see
three of them.
You know, did you get carried off the field or did you go and get up?
Like the warrior gets up and it was just that, it was just getting up, focused,
rebuild every day was managing fear, managing fear because the mind was just
going nuts, heavy experience, man.
For parents listening to this, what, what advice would you give to parents to
raise resilient kids in a generation where that feels it's getting harder and
harder?
That's such an amazing question because.
I don't have to point out that the world's gotten weird in the last four
years and there's something afoot and there's something going on.
A lot of it is it's, it's like half the world has lost critical thinking and
the other half that's going, what's going on, doesn't know what to do.
So we're sending each other memes as opposed to like taking action, but you
don't want to take action because you don't want to get canceled, which means
you're in the fear loop.
The future of our world is in the hands of.
These kids, what are we teaching them?
When you look at grown adults acting irrationally, that's the
flaw of education and parenting.
A good friend of mine who does a lot of my tattoos calls me a year and a half into
COVID and he says his 10 year old son is exhibiting anxiety.
His personality is completely changed at school with a mask, no smiles.
And he goes, it's killing me, Tony.
It's killing me.
I don't know what to do.
So I've got a program.
I've got a program with the words, no fear on it, and it's spelled K N O W not
N O because I don't believe there's a such a thing as no fear that's rationalizing.
Remember the Richard Feynman quote, right?
But there's getting to know fear.
When you get to know fear, you can use fear as fuel.
You become adaptive.
You become more resilient, you come mentally tough.
So my buddy Aaron's his name says his, his son Salem is exhibiting anxiety.
He says, is your no fear program too old for him?
He's only 10.
I said, Aaron, it's not too old for you.
And you're your son's coach, not just his dad.
You're his mentor and his coach and his teacher.
You can have him raised by the school system, but you can see what's happening.
Or you can coach him.
He gets the program a month later.
I'm in Vegas on business and he hands me a letter.
I open it up.
There's, but it's amazing.
It's this handwritten letter from this 10 year old.
Salem who says, dear Mr.
Blower, I want to thank you for, you know, uh, the no fear program.
And there's a line in it that I tell people, you can't be brave.
If you're not afraid, the primary ingredient of courage is fear, but
no one ever told us that as kids, like when I was growing up afraid, none of
my coaches, mentors, teachers, or parents said, it feels good, man.
It's okay.
If you're afraid.
To present or do something, it's because you care, you're nervous.
What people think of you, that's normal.
And here's how you can use it or just go through it.
And every time you do it, it's a rep that'll get better your first game.
You might've been shitting your pants, but you're 20 games later, 50 games later.
Now it's like, this is a big game.
We've got to win it to get to the championship level.
Now the anxiety is about the outcome, but not about your endurance, your stamina, or
whether you can take a hit or our fears become more specific.
Yeah.
And then we can, we can manage them.
And so, um, you want to improve sales in your company, address
the fears of your sales force.
You want to be better in a better relationship with your significant
other address the fears, because very often I'll come home.
I see that my wife's burdened by something and I go, Hey, are you okay?
What's up?
And she'll go, I don't know, or nothing.
Right.
And you know, it's always something.
So our inability.
To look at our fear and then articulate what it is means that it just lives on our head,
suppressing the communication or the movement that's required.
Yeah.
Beautifully, uh, beautifully said, uh, Tony, we have this belief that success leaves clues.
And, uh, someone on this podcast said that, uh, in this forum and the idea that someone
who grew up with your background, who becomes an expert in self-defense and techniques around
overcoming fear or someone from a diverse background in, in the arts.
Or theater have, uh, similar patterns as to why they're successful, even though their backgrounds are unique.
And we have this belief around self-leadership.
I want to ask you, what do you do to fill your own cup so that you can be the leader you want to be?
Um, it varies.
You know, I, I have this idea that what is important to us changes every 10 years.
That's not a law or a, but you know, what I was worried about or thinking about or interested in change.
And so what I'm doing now.
To fill my cup.
Uh, a lot of it is, is really esoteric and metaphysical, but it's really self-care taking time for myself.
Reminding myself and people like everything will happen when it's ready to happen.
We don't need to rush.
We don't need to panic.
I live near the ocean, try to go for walks, enjoy nature.
I got four dogs.
I got three kids.
I spent so much time building my business obsessed with that, that I realized I didn't
I neglected a lot of things that I wish I hadn't as, as a parent, as a, as a, as a dad.
So it's continually working on your own self-awareness and just trying to be a better person.
Self-care and self-awareness is, uh, absolutely.
Um, it makes a lot of sense.
So what's one thing that's always worked for you, Tony, as a leader that you would never change?
Wow.
Um, I think it's my relationship with, with intuition over the years.
Like in 1980, when I was conceptualizing my approach to self-defense, I was told by, uh, the, the term thought leaders didn't exist back then, but the thought leaders in the self-defense industry that I would never be successful.
I would never make it that my approach to training, no, no belts, no levels, no uniforms, just understanding kinesiology, physiology, psychology, that you couldn't, people didn't learn that way.
Um,
And I could have, because some of these people were like very high ranking people who I looked up to saying to the point where, you know, I'm struggling, struggling, struggling, where my first wife is, when are you going to get a real job?
And, and when she said that I knew we were going to get divorced, right?
My self-belief that I was onto something when I was 20 years old, I got asked by a venture capitalist that I got introduced to.
I didn't even know what venture capital was, but he said, Hey, Ricky said, you got this different idea about how to make money.
How to make the world safer, explain it to me.
And I explained it to him and he goes like this.
He goes, he puts his hands back, leans back in his executive chair.
He goes, uh, you don't think this idea of making the world safer is a little bit grandiose.
And I didn't understand why he would think that was grandiose.
And I left his office and never, but here we are 45 years later, I'm still trying to make the world safer.
So it was like, are you going to be a professional or going to the family business?
And my mom asked me when I was 15, have you started to?
Think about this because you're going to graduate high school and what you're going to go into law school.
You're gonna be a doctor.
And I looked up word for word.
I said, mom, school's not going to be that important to me.
I'm going to develop my own martial arts system, like Bruce Lee and teach self-defense.
And she said, what?
I said, yeah, I'm going to be a famous martial artist.
And she literally pat me on the head and said, okay, honey, we'll talk about this when you're a little bit older.
I just knew.
So that was like, that was intuition.
I describe intuition and as, as.
Something, you know, to be true, you just don't have the evidence yet.
And that's interesting.
You say that Tony, in that answer, that's a common thing I hear from a lot of people in this forum that when they've made great decisions, their intuition, they've trusted when they've gone away from that's often when they've made a decision that they regret in life.
We're interested in, in vision.
Have you got a story of a visionary leader that inspired you that you felt compelled to follow along your journey?
Well, ironically, I just mentioned him.
Bruce Lee, you know, was one of them.
I remember reading a story obsessed with him and he was Chinese American trying to make it as an actor and there was a lot of racism back then.
Oh, okay.
You can be, you could build a rail, like a railroad road, you know, with a bunch of other Chinese people in this Western movie.
Like that was the roles that were opposite.
You can run a, a laundry shop.
Like, it was like really like, like racist, uh, stereotyped.
And he was fighting that, fighting that, where he had to go back to Hong Kong to become successful.
And when the books and stories and interviews came out with him, he had written something to himself that said to hell with circumstances, I'll create my own circumstances.
And I read that when I was 15 and I memorized that it was emblazoned on my head to hell with circumstances.
I'll create my own circumstances.
So that combination of trusting my intuition.
Where in the eighties, when my business was going.
Struggling, my accountant said to me, Hey, seriously, kid, you should close your business and go get a job like this.
Isn't going to work.
So I have the subject matter experts saying, you're never going to make it.
My mom going, why don't you just go to work for your dad?
My accountant saying, you're never going to make it.
And I fired my accountant and, you know, here we are like all these years that line from that one of Bruce Lee's biographies.
Just.
Stuck in my head and I'm, I'm moved by great thinkers.
So there's been a lot of spiritual guides, if you will, over the years that, um, you know, just like even a sentence can blow my mind and, and put me off on a trajectory.
I don't know if you remember the author, Dan Millman, he wrote the book, the way the peaceful warrior, uh, this isn't from the book, but in, in being suddenly fascinated with like the way he would teach and educate and inspire, I came across one of his quotes.
That was, you know, when you.
Face just one opponent and you doubt yourself, you're outnumbered and that, like, if you don't give yourself permission to win, that's two against none, you know, you're, you're doubting yourself and the opponent is, or whatever the obstacle is, is, is all over you.
So there's been a number, but I, I would say, I guess the primary one that got me through my teens into my business life was that Bruce Lee line and trusting my intuition.
Creating your own circumstances.
I love it.
We see curiosity is a word that's very common.
And for people who've had great sustained success, like you have, how do you carve out time to be curious?
And do you integrate that into the work that you do?
Not deliberately, but my, my wife made a joke this morning on a private text with a friend of mine.
And she said, I think Tony's on the spectrum.
Like, so I make this joke that I have like entrepreneur, entrepreneurial ADD.
I'll go, oh my God, check this out.
And then I'll, I'll, I'll take the company off on this other direction.
And everyone's like, oh shit, come on.
Let's go.
And sometimes my enthusiasm is, is, is contagious.
But although I'm not using the word curious, I think that's a component of curiosity.
It drives a lot of people better.
Cause like, if you ask anyone on my team, we've got trainers all over the world.
And if you ask any of the ones that are on my actual mobile training team, and you ask them this question, what was the best course you ever taught for Blower Tactical or Blower Training Systems?
They will answer you without hesitation, my next course.
And you can't be thinking about reinventing yourself each time if you're not curious about how do I get better?
And so I always ask people, are you coachable?
And you've got to go, like, you can't be coachable if you're not curious.
Brilliantly said.
We're obsessed with collaboration in our world.
We bring leaders together from around the globe to learn and to connect and share from different backgrounds in a space we call a leader.
Have you had an example of a great collaboration in your life you could share with us?
Wow.
It's like in our spear system where someone sucker punches you and you flinch.
My brain is flinching right now.
The greatest collaboration I've had is something that happened in the last two years.
And there's been a number of, if I go back to the early 90s, 1993, I got asked to go teach at the world, at the time, the world's biggest law enforcement training symposium called ASLET, A-S-L-E-T, the American Society of Law Enforcement Trainers.
But they had, you know, they had a lot of people.
They had trainers from Australia, all over the world come in there, thousands of guys.
And I was talking and my system was very polarizing.
I'd be talking and I'd see these famous trainers.
They had books out in my class, like sitting there like this.
Who's this asshole?
Wow, they're telling us this, this, this.
Because our system was unlike anything they'd been exposed to.
And I had two guys that became mentors of mine that came up to me and said,
You're so on.
You're so on the money here.
But your bedside manner in approaching it, you're too enthusiastic and it's coming across as arrogance.
I'd say things like, there's no such thing as reactionary gap.
That's why you guys are getting dropped inside that six feet.
The language is messed up.
You got to change that.
And here's all these type A personalities going, who's this guy that's not a cop telling us what we should do?
Right?
And so these were significant collaborations where somebody took the minute to see that.
My passion, my obsession was being misconstrued by people because they didn't understand.
And, you know, like, how many people do you know love change?
Right?
Like, people don't like it.
So there were a bunch of people who put me, took me under their wing.
I'm trying to put my arm up here, the screen.
Like, and said, hey, don't say things like that.
But I was coachable.
I was resistant at first.
I go, that's bullshit.
They shouldn't be defensive.
They go, Tony, I'm just trying to help you.
You've got an antidote.
An antidote to this sort of metaphor.
We have a lot of poison in our industry, but nobody's going to take it because of how you're coming across.
And I was coachable.
And I would sit with it, and I would figure out different ways to explain stuff.
I had another guy named Bob Lindsay, one of the most famous police trainers in the world.
He saw me teach back then, and he said, you're going to face so much resistance, but please don't stop.
One day, people are going to go, oh, I was there when I heard that.
They won't understand for a long time.
And I was like, young and dumb.
And why is that?
Why are people defiant?
Why are people defensive?
But I listened to it, and I always hear his voice in my head when I want to quit or when I want to do something abrupt.
Right?
So I've had mentors that I am using collaboration differently.
It was their love of what they saw in my passion and obsession.
I use the word obsession, too.
I used to say I'm so passionate about this.
And I had somebody like you, who's like a thought leader, much more mature, say, you're not passionate.
You're obsessed.
You wake up in the middle of the night thinking about this stuff, don't you?
And I'm like, yeah, that's not passion.
Passion is I'm going to play guitar on Saturday.
You know, obsession is, you know, I'm playing guitar at the dinner table eating, you know, because I'm writing a song.
And that's how I am.
Collaboration is when somebody says, here's an idea that's going to improve the direction.
Or the product or the service.
And you integrate that.
Tony, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
The greatest leader?
I'm going to give you a weird fear answer.
A weird spiritual answer is my fear.
If you're asking, if you're looking for a name, my head went right to everything that has shaped me to who I am.
It's because of that, the dance of fear and intuition.
And I don't know if this is.
It's obnoxious to say the greatest leader would then be myself.
And I would argue if you said, oh, your mom or your dad or your coach, I would say, dude, you're the greatest leader.
And we need to teach our kids to be the greatest leader, their CEO of their business of their life.
When I'm training and mentoring coaches, I will always say to them, OK, here's a professional instructor.
All the hands come up.
I go, who is the most important student that you have?
And people start thinking outside and say, one person always goes yourself, right?
And that's it.
And so most important leader.
What a brilliant answer.
I love it.
Yeah.
And your own relationship with fear that has governed your whole life.
It's a brilliant answer.
And you can hear the obsession coming out in everything you say with full passion mixed in.
We are a bit obsessed with this idea of collaboration, Tony.
And you've been a self-driven guy by the sounds of it.
And you've tread.
You've tread your own path.
And even when the experts and so-called champions of your industry have doubted you.
But has there ever been one person you thought, wow, in your clear passion in life, I'd love to connect or collaborate with one person?
Is there a name that strings to mind on that front?
No, but probably so many.
I don't know if this is arrogance or love.
Like, I really believe.
Like, I've worked with world-class athletes.
I work with businessmen.
Businessmen that have companies that are literally 50 times the size of mine.
Like, running $100 million companies.
And I'm in awe of them.
And they'll bring me in for coaching and coaching their team and everything.
Because I think for whatever reason, they went and saw the power of just this no-fear change for people.
I love your really clear understanding of intuition, how we've all got it.
And for us to tap into that is an incredible power.
And becoming friends with fear.
It's a great message from listening to you today.
It's been your life's work, your life's obsession.
And you've clearly helped make the world a safer place.
If that was what you set out to do, it sounds like you're doing that in an incredible way.
I really appreciate you taking the time to join me today.
Knowing fear and understanding fear is a gift for all of us.
And I appreciate you taking the time.
And I get lost in rabbit holes.
And I hope your audience got something out of it because it just takes over.
But it's a...
It's a...
You know, if I just share one last thing for your audience is that we all have fear.
And if we can change our relationship with fear, we can change what we're thinking right there.
So if you change your mind, you can change the next action you take.
So managing fear helps you improve your self-awareness, which improves your critical thinking, which improves your situational awareness.
If you think about it, what's the only resource we can't regenerate?
Time.
When we're obsessing and consumed by fear, we are wasting time.
We are not spending time.
If we're thinking about the problem, we're spending time.
If we're in the fear loop worrying about the future, we're wasting time.
And so when you invest in trying to understand how to manage fear, you're actually investing in time management.
You know, I can't think of a more important skill.
Manage your time, manage your fear, manage your mind.
Beautifully said.
Tony Glassman, a great privilege.
Thanks for spending some time with me.
Thanks for joining me.
Thank you, sir.
Thanks for listening to another episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Huge thanks, as always, to our great friends at Temper.
And we encourage you to check out our Leader Connect program.
New episodes are out every Wednesday morning at 6 a.m.