I genuinely think this conversation with Kurt Fearnley will change the way you think about
pretty much everything. Kurt has the most beautiful, unique, powerful world view. And
in this conversation, you hear how he came to be as successful as he is in every facet of his life.
Kurt came from a large family in a small country town with a very clear idea of what life is meant
to be. How that community grew up and fought so hard for him to be part of their world,
not segregated in any way as many of the services his parents' access suggested. Time and time again,
the small town he grew up in insisted that he be included in absolutely everything. And what it
took for his mum to go against pretty much what everyone told her to do and how much of a legend
she is in Kurt's life. You hear the story of how at 13 years of age, the tiny town Kurt grew up in
raised $10,000 to buy his first race chair and send him to the city to compete.
He talks about how he would love to remove pity from the world and that if you're on the receiving
end of unrequited pity, how can you ever have an image of yourself that's strong and beautiful?
He talks about why the segregation of people with a disability is literally a scar on the
communities in which we live in. You can hear about the 18-month preparation involved in Kurt
crawling the 96 kilometres of the famous Kokoda track with his brothers and cousins who'd been
so instrumental in his upbringing.
From a very young age. He talks a lot about you can't save other people until you have the ability
to save yourself and why to start with the assumption that the person across from you
is the best in the world at what they do. Couldn't be more inspired by Kurt Fearnley,
a unique and brilliant Australian with a remarkable story. It's people like Kurt
Fearnley who inspire the work that we do at Alita. Love you in particular to have a look
at our signature Alita Connect program. We collaborate with great thinkers and interesting
people around the globe like Kurt Fearnley.
Come together to learn, to share and collaborate. Check it out. Head to alitacollective.com and book
a discovery call with us today. Thanks to the team at Temper, allowing conversations like this one
with Kurt Fearnley to come to the table. We know that Temper is a mattress like no other NASA
approved space age technology, the world's best in bedding. If you value your sleep,
check out Temper today. Kurt Fearnley AO is a three-time Paralympic gold medalist and two times
Commonwealth Games gold medal winner. He has won over 40 marathons, including New York,
Argo and London in a career spanning more than 20 years. In 2009, Kurt Fearnley crawled the Kokoda
track in Papua New Guinea to raise awareness of men's mental health. Kurt was also a member of
the winning Sydney to Hobart yacht crew Investec Loyal in 2012. He was the New South Wales
Australian of the Year in 2019. Kurt hosts several of his own podcasts, including the
brilliant Tiny Island where Kurt talks to great Australians about what it means to them to be
Australian. Born without the lower portion of his spine, he's never held Kurt Fearnley back from
his resilience and determination to succeed. He's nothing short of legendary, Kurt. I love sitting
back and reading your story again in the last few days. It's blown me away by what you've been able
to achieve. I really appreciate you spending some time with me today. No problems, Luke. Looking
forward to it. Now, you were born on a start, maybe from the beginning. You were born in a
small country town called Karkour in New South Wales, born without the lower portion of your
spine. I imagine, Kurt, it would be easy to accept that there's a lot of things you can't do. Where
did your determination and your resilience to go on and achieve what you have, where did that come
from? Well, it wasn't mine. You know, like all good kids, you kind of grow up in the community
that you're in. And your belief system and your approach to life is usually what is reflected back
at you. I grew up in that tiny little town of Karkour. It's in the middle of Wiradjuri land,
which is out in the centre of New South Wales. We didn't have a lot of resources.
My family were, I was the youngest of five kids. My dad was one of 11. You know, my mum was one of
five. But what we had was this solid idea of what life was meant to be. And although every time my
family touched the systems that were around to support people with disabilities, they usually
touched systems that, you know, tried to get me away from the people that I loved, that tried to
isolate me, that tried to segregate me, that tried to say that, you know, that the community that I'm
in is not going to be the same. And so, you know, I think it's a really good thing to have that
community. And so, you know, I think it's a really good thing to have that community. And so,
you know, I think it's a really good thing to have that community. And so, you know, I think it's
not made for me. The community that was there was the exact opposite. They demanded that I would
play a part in it. They valued and loved me as I was. They fought for me to be a part of every
corner of their community, whether it be my cousins who would carry me through paddocks to be a part
of life growing up in the bush or a principal of Karkour Public School who, when a four-year-old
kid wanted to go to his local school with his brothers and sisters, my parents were told that
I actually had to go to a local school. And so, you know, I think it's a really good thing to have
should be taken away from my home and sent through segregated education. I had a teacher
at Karkour Public that cemented the school as much as he possibly could, bought bags of concrete out
of his own money, and made sure and told my mother and father that there's no place else in the world
that I deserve to be than the place that values, the place that loves me, the place that is
my community and family.
I just have the hair standing on the back of my neck when you explain that. It's
the beauty of rural Australia, isn't it? I understand Karkour, total population at that
time, maybe 200 people. Is that correct? Yeah, 200 and shrinking.
And how brilliant, Kurt, that all the things that you've gone on and been an incredible advocate for,
that community got just intuitively, didn't they? There is no way Kurt deserves to be anywhere
apart from with the people that love him the most. It's pretty special, isn't it?
Well, they just did it time and time again, you know? So you'd think maybe it was just,
you know, the one moment...
One moment of kindness is easy. The repeated purposeful acts of inclusion, that was amazing.
They demanded that I went to school. They offered me pathways where I had to crawl around the bush
to be me, but it was just accepted. And where I needed help, they jumped in. And then when I was
shown the potential to race wheelchairs, you know, that town of 200 people and shrinking,
they got together against the wishes of my mother and father, who tried to stop them.
They raised 10,000 bucks in two weeks. And when my mother and father, who, like I said,
we weren't very financial, we were probably the wrong side of the poverty line, but we were
extraordinarily proud. And when they tried to stop them, the town simply said, stay out of it,
it's between us and the boy. You know, like that sense of community,
so naturally and so prevalent that every single time where, you know, there was the potential for
me to be ushered into isolation and segregation, the community were there and just making these
choices that were beyond, you know, beyond the year that we were in, beyond the time that we
were in. And Kurt, you mentioned you're the youngest of five. And my understanding from
reading in the last few days was that the doctors didn't think you'd survive. And I think that's
the first week of your life, if that's correct. And then that community, as you said, they raised
$10,000. That's not a small amount of sum from a tiny country town. And that was for a race chair
that set you on this elite athlete pass. Again, life-changing moments. Yeah. Well, being born out
in the bush with a disability that is quite rare, I think there was an immediate fear of whether or
not I'd live through the night, let alone the week. And then because of disability also has
a thousand other complications, usually.
That potentially running alongside the fear of how long I'd be around for was pretty real for a
while. Even from that first few days, I think my mum, because when you bring disability into a
world where you also exist, you know, in a pretty tough financial situation, there were lots of
people trying to offer her alternatives to taking me home. And again, there was no more natural
choice.
And my family's life then to take me back and whether I live a day or a week or a month,
I live a day or a week or a month as a family. And that means with the family.
And then when it come time to race wheelchairs and they just jumped up and started raising this
money, mate, these are cockies and chippies and laborers, you know, who were working for,
for, you know, if they're lucky, 10, 20 bucks an hour.
A fine of $10,000 amongst, you know, a few hundred people, because they knew that I deserved
the pathway that was out there. And that pathway would enrich everyone. They raised the 10 grand.
I was about 13 years old, 12, 13 years old. And they told my mother and father that that's for
a racing wheelchair and a trip to wherever, wherever I need to go to be around other kids
that are doing this same thing. And yeah, mate, it's hard to believe.
I actually do remember, I remember it all happening and just thinking it's not real,
you know, like you can see it in front of you. You can see it, you know, like you can
really almost feel that there's this big world out there, but you've always got this little
protective amount of doubt in you that, but will I get there? They own, I always like to say that,
that I live in Newcastle. I'm about as proud of Nova Castrian,
you know, I've been here 20 years and it's got my heart, but car core and
where I drew land that got my, that got my soul that owns, that owns a big chunk of me.
You talk about life and sliding doors moments, the, the, the people around the medical profession,
you're born and they're saying to mum and dad, Hey, you need to let Kurt, where exactly were
they thinking you should end up rather than with your family? Can I ask?
Oh, well, back in the, you know, seventies, eighties,
institutionalized life for people with disabilities was not uncommon. Like I said,
in 1984, when I went to go to school, the department of education, and it wasn't this
one off, it was like multiple times when you would interact with the system that we hope
would support people with disabilities often, often was set up to remove them away from the
people that love them and their immediate families, especially when you, when you put
disability and combine it with things like poverty.
It can be a really isolating experience. And for my family, I think that we did actually
isolate ourselves even more because each time we went in there, the, the, the interventions that
were encouraged were so unpalatable that we just, we interacted with them less and less and less
and less, you know, so that those, those, those fail points of the systems that were around people
with disabilities led to us becoming more isolated. But thankfully we backed in,
to a community that was so forward thinking and so forward leaning that it caught me, you know,
like it really caught me.
And I'm talking to a board member of the Australian Paralympic Committee. You're a founding member of
the National Disability Insurance Scheme Advisory Council and a whole range of other boards. I mean,
you have taken what Karkor, that tiny little country town in rural New South Wales gave you
and have you pass that on and you continue to fight. Can you just explain, it's so stark to
hear what your family was.
Yeah, it's so stark to hear what your family was confronted with compared to what they did. What,
what do we need to learn? People like me who haven't had to grow up with understanding your
world, what, what do we need to learn first and foremost to make life better for, for people in
our country who have a disability?
I think the first thing is remove any assumption of how horrible you would experience it. You know,
there is this inbuilt assumption that if I was in that situation, I wouldn't handle it.
If,
if I had a spinal injury, I would really, I would not do very well. If I had a kid with a disability
that would be so hard, I don't think I could deal with it. You deal with it because you've got to
deal with it. The, the, the environment that you live in is the environment that you live in. The
hardest thing that anyone's went through is the hardest thing that anyone's went through. The
first thing would be get rid of any assumption that you had of how hard or how, how horrible
any sort of variation in existence would be. And,
and just go in with an open mind that this person loves who they are, loves where they are, until I'm told otherwise.
When I get around in my day to day life, I genuinely assume that I'm doing great at it, right? Like I'm, I'm nailing this part of life until somebody comes up and goes, Ooh, that looks tough. And then it, it kind of brings you out of this moment where you think, is that how you seem? Is that, and, and I genuinely do believe that one of the things that a loved one can do is to be able to show a little bit more of that person's side.
One of the things that if I had a magic wand that I would remove
out of this world would be pity because pity is like a cancer
that it eats away at the foundation of the person.
Like how can you believe that you are great and that you are valued
and that you are valuable if you are the unrequited recipient of pity?
It's just how will I ever have an image of myself that is strong
and that is, you know, beautiful if I am forced to see myself
through another person's lens of pity?
That would be the first couple of things that I would kind of address.
And Kurt, it's a profound lesson to learn and to hear that, isn't it?
I know this almost sounds like a contrite thing to say,
but the thing an athlete hates the most is when you're injured
and someone asks you how you're feeling about your injury.
It's the worst thing.
And you know that.
You know that as well, don't you?
Like it just takes you to a place you don't want to be.
Because as you said, in your mind, I'm recovering, I'm going well.
It's, you know, and when you give a curt answer to someone, you know,
you've done your knee and it's like because it's probably the 100th person,
isn't it?
And it's probably at glance taking you back a way that you're not.
And as you said, I'm talking to a winner of the Don Award,
the most prestigious sporting award in Australia.
And for those who don't understand, it's named after the great Sir Donald Bradman.
It's about recognition.
It's about recognizing the Australian that inspires the nation the most,
not the person with a disability that inspires the nation the most.
You're the first person with a disability to win that award.
But that must, when you sit there and hear that, that's you, isn't it?
Not anything else.
And to speak at that level, that must fill you with great pride.
Can I say not really?
You're winding me up, mate.
Seriously.
Mate, I honestly don't know how to process those moments.
And I've never have, right?
Like the moments of recognition seem as foreign to me as anything else.
Like I just don't know how to handle them.
Like I do actually have that award out.
It's in the kitchen.
It's the only award that I have out because it's the great Don Bradman
and it was a pretty great night.
But.
I am 100% intrinsically motivated
and I have had either people coming into my life to offer me feedback
so often and for so long that you reduce the impact of that feedback.
So if somebody will jump into my life and portray it in a negative
or an extraordinarily positive way and I just want to live my life,
I can't let that in and I won't let that in.
So.
Somebody comes up and tells me how shit it must be to be in a wheelchair,
which they do, or how much of an idea,
you're a saint because you're in a wheelchair, you know, which they do.
You can't let either of it in because you just want to be you, right?
So you shut that down and you move on and do something else.
Now, there is feedback and there are people that you let in, of course,
that help build this idea of who you are and whose opinion on what you were doing
truly matters.
But I think that I spent so long removing anybody else
who isn't within my valued group.
I removed that so far from the reality of how I live that when I go
to an awards night and I receive an award, I don't know how to let it in
to feel about it.
I see that as one that's worth keeping out because the people
that I do love were there and they enjoyed it.
You know, they got this experience out of it.
So I'm like, okay, I get that.
But during sport, nobody else's opinion mattered about a race except for mine,
my coaches, my trainers, and maybe two or three other people in the world
that I really, really, really valued their opinion.
And that was it.
You could have somebody come out and say that that was the greatest race
in the world or the worst race in the world.
And it just didn't matter.
And Kurt, it's a fascinating mindset.
And to delve into that is intriguing to me.
And I get, as you said, to be able to not take on the stuff you don't need
to take on.
That's a superpower that you've created there.
But my question is, I wonder, has that enabled you to – I mean,
you've got so much that you have to celebrate.
They're remarkable things you've done, mate.
Are you able to enjoy them enough is my question.
I enjoy every day.
Like, honestly, like, I enjoy every day.
I am –
The most – I am more grateful for every moment of my life that, you know,
like I feel like I am living an absolute gift.
But an award, you know, in one of those really strange settings,
I wouldn't swap that for – there's this one memory I have crawling around
the bush with my kids when they were really little, you know,
and that was as perfect a moment as I've ever had in my life,
whether it's awards or racing or anything.
It was just perfect.
It was beautiful and amazing.
And so, yeah, you've got to try and enjoy every single moment.
But I don't know.
Sometimes I think you can't value too much the big and flashy ones
because then they stop, you know, like they stop.
And your value and worth in life, that can't stop.
I want to find value and joy and celebration in life when, you know,
when – well,
it's well and truly behind me, but when all of that is done and dusted,
you've still got to find those kind of – those perfect moments.
But, yeah, you celebrate them a bit, but not too much.
And I understand what you mean.
You're not attaching your identity to being the Don Award winner
or a three-time Olympic gold medalist or the numerous other marathons you've won.
I totally get the brilliance in your thinking on that.
I've got to ask, tell us about that day.
You're crawling around with the kids out in the country.
What was that?
It was so perfect about that day.
Well, we were looking for koalas.
And I was –
As you do.
As we do.
And we just disappeared into the scrub for hours and crawling through.
And they were having a ball because we were kind of half lost.
And we never saw a bloody koala, but we did lie down on the ground a heap
and just talk about the trees that were swaying and the – you know,
it's – I guess it's – if you think about it deeper,
it's probably just 100%.
Just being in the moment.
And you can see this little, you know, again,
somebody who is one of the cool people that you love,
you can see they're kind of growing and that they are in that moment too.
And I think that it was just – it was probably at my leaving –
at the time that I was leaving sport.
And I think there was just a moment of realisation that this moment
is as good as any sporting moment.
And it's okay to go.
You know, it was probably –
it was probably my brain kind of putting a bookend on something
and just saying, you're good.
And it just stayed with me.
And I love what you're referencing there too because sometimes we set up
these great trips for the kids and we've got this expectation
this is going to be – do you know how lucky you are to be here
in Port Douglas or whatever, but going for, you know,
a crawl around the bush and trying to find koalas is probably the thing
they're going to remember the most as well, isn't it?
Without having to worry about the expense of doing anything extravagant.
Well, it is going to be interesting to see what their stories are
because they have done some wild stuff, but they've also, you know,
seen their old men crawl alongside them for 5Ks.
Well, I don't know.
I just think that that might have an impact on them one day.
But you're right, mate.
Like the 12-month-olds, their birthday's in two weeks and people say,
what gift do you want them?
I don't know, a bag of tissues?
What do you – you know, like throw them up in the air for a bit?
You know?
Like kids just want – kids want presents and they – as in your presents,
your attendance, you to be in there with them.
And I got in the Hall of Fame last year and somebody asked me
what my kids thought about it.
And I'm like, I haven't told my kids.
Why would I tell my kids?
They would just be like, okay, well, whatever that means.
And they don't really have the context for it at the moment,
but they would – they care about whether or not you're there
for soccer training.
And, you know, they want the really normal father moments.
They want you to be mates with their friends' fathers.
You know, they want that.
They don't want the flashy stuff that you think that they would.
I always say you can't fake time with kids.
You're either there or you're not.
And that time is, as you said, the presence is what counts.
So how would you describe yourself?
Father of four, you've got the twin girls that, as you said,
are two weeks away from their first birth.
What are you like as a dad?
Oh, gee, I don't know.
I probably run them a bit hard.
I've got a couple of hundred acres just outside of Newcastle,
and me and the young fellow are there for six hours working yesterday.
And he's a 10-year-old.
He's almost 10, and he'd give me a solid six hours worth of work.
And I think that I remind them on a daily basis
that they're loved.
They're loved always.
There can't be a day go by that you can't tell them that you love them
and that they're strong and that they're valued.
I don't really know how to classify myself as a dad except for, like,
I make sure that they know that they're the most important thing in my life.
And, yeah, that's about it.
A little while ago, I got offered this acknowledgement as an award as a dad,
right?
And I couldn't take it.
Because I think the only person that should ever judge you as a dad is kids
on the other side of it.
And the thought of taking that without them having a word in it kind
of made me feel real sketchy.
So I don't know.
You can have all this intent at the end of the day that they're going
to be the judge.
But I do do everything I can to make sure that I've got a hand in their normal,
their average, their everyday.
I love your aversion to awards.
You're not even going to turn up.
I hate it, mate.
I'm picking up a common theme here and you're not even turning up for that one.
But I love what you just said, isn't it?
You know, they know they're loved.
They know they're the most important thing in my life.
You can't get a better start than that.
And we all make mistakes as parents.
But if you're coming from that lens, it's hard to do much more.
I have to ask you, you've done some extraordinary things.
But the one that I – and you probably know where I'm going.
But the Kokoda track, 96 kilometres.
Some of the toughest terrain.
And I know people have described that as just incredibly challenging.
You crawl that famous track that's got so much history in terms of Australia.
That must have been an amazing experience.
I think it is truly one of the most achievable adventures
that you could ever throw yourself into.
And it is really achievable.
We were so fortunate.
So I did it with my brothers and cousins or family or grew up.
We did it as a reminder to come back that we were all going to be there
for each other, to support each other.
And also that if a guy in a wheelchair can look for and ask for help
from those around him, then he'll feel confident and comfortable enough
to have a crack at the Kokoda track.
And then we were fortunate enough to find a tour company
that would talk to me because the first one was pretty –
they were pretty adamant.
But what I was doing was irresponsible
and shouldn't be even spoken about any further.
And then I called Wayne Wetherill at Kokoda Spirit
and he had just watched me race in Beijing.
And he said, it's crazy, but I want to meet you anyway.
And he flew down to Newcastle and I had grown up crawling
because Karkour had no concrete outside of the main street.
So I jumped out of my chair and we crawled for a few minutes.
We crawled for a few kilometres and he could see that it was possible
and he was ready to go.
And I said, give me 18 months because I knew that there would be
a lot of sideline preparations that were needed.
And they were to try and minimise blisters and impact on my joints,
to try and make sure that I had the confidence.
You know, you can say you're going to do something,
but then there's the lying in bed at midnight realising the thousands,
thousand risk areas that you've got to manage to do it.
So, you know, saying you're going to do it and then being comfortable
with going to bed at night are two different things.
And it took me 18 months to kind of slowly piece together equipment
that would keep me safe, that would keep everything in one piece,
and then build the physical strength to be able to go through the metre
by metre of just dragging yourself through mud again.
And dragging yourself up hills and, yeah, 18 months from the moment
that we first talked about it to the moment that we're all flying
over the top of the Owen Stanley Ranges and seeing this incredible jungle
behind or underneath us.
Yeah, that's remarkable.
And you did it with the Carcore cousins and brothers.
Is that the same crew that were there when they didn't accept anything
apart from Kurt Finley going everywhere they went?
That must have...
You've added another layer to it to go back for those guys.
They were all the guys that were instrumental in me growing up,
crawling around the bush, were all on the trip with me.
So I wasn't a...
It wasn't a surprise for them to see me crawling around.
And then we also had...
And the PNG people were one of the most beautiful, incredible,
strong, like fierce community that you could ever see.
But they...
They have this real strength that is layered with this generosity
and kindness and gentleness that is pretty amazing to kind of fall into.
And, you know, I think they saw me crawl off the plane
for the very first time as well.
And we had some porters there and they just didn't know how it was all
going to work as well.
And then I just started crawling and these porters kind of lined
up alongside me and then I kept on crawling and then they kept on trying
to get me.
They kept on trying to get me to sit on the stretcher.
They kept on trying to get me to...
They wanted to carry me.
I think a couple of them, the one guy in particular,
he had a brother with a disability who he lost.
We didn't find out until later in the crawl.
But every night he would come alongside me and he would sit down
and I don't talk about this as much, but he...
It was one of the most relieving moments in my day because he would say,
if you want to be home, tell me now.
And I'll have you in Moresby by morning.
Like he just had this, I'll throw you on my back and I'll run you out of here
the moment you tell me you're ready.
And knowing and just somebody giving me that just absolute comfort
and support and like knowledge that no, I'm okay was...
That was...
That allowed me to do the day-to-day...
Just drag and managing the pain of every moment was a lot easier
knowing that there was a relief valve there.
Okay, there's the legend of the Fuzzy Wuzzy Angels as they were called
in World War II, the New Guinea locals who just did that in World War II
for the Australians, didn't they?
That literally put Australian soldiers on their back
and showed incredible bravery and courage.
And how fascinating.
You got to experience...
A little bit of that of your own.
Did that sort of history dawn on you a bit at the time?
Yeah, there was a moment that I was being carried through a bit
of a swampy area and I am on a stretcher and I'm in a lot of pain
and the boys had me up on this stretcher and they're kind
of running me through it and you've got a treetop over you
so you're getting these speckles of light and I'm pretty emotional
because even though you had that moment every night,
there was still trying to wrestle yourself
into dealing...
And with the step after step after step and the doubt about,
you know, how am I going to feel tomorrow?
And I remember just being carried and being really vulnerable
because they have...
They literally have you in their hands, right?
And I can see the sun coming through these beautiful just trees
and thinking that this is the exact sight that our boys,
you know, that Australians who for the very first time
were fighting for their own defence were realising, you know,
that we are on the other side.
We're on the other side of the world and that there's no one
that's going to come and protect us.
These 17, 18-year-old kids off, you know, property or in the western suburbs
of, you know, Melbourne and Sydney and they went over there.
They fell victim to the realities of war and these beautiful people
who had no dog in the fight just wanted people to live.
They would throw them on this stretcher
and there was a lot of people who were like, you know,
there's a moment that I just remember feeling the vulnerability of that
and how vulnerable they would have felt, you know,
being carried away from conflict by a group of guys
who had no reason to do what they were doing
except for that they were these angels out of nowhere that would appear.
Amazing story and amazing bit of history.
If you haven't read it before, it's worth it and I still...
Just the mind is just incredible what you were able to achieve in doing that.
I didn't know that it was with...
The people you grew up with, what a special story.
Kurt, we use the term success leaves clues
and I love sitting down from people like you
and learning from your lived experience,
but we think there's these patterns around what great successful people do
in terms of the way they lead, starting with this idea of self-leadership
that very hard to do anything else for someone else
unless you've got an idea of your own sense of self-leadership
and your story is full of that.
But what does that mean to you?
Self-leadership.
I really believe you can't save other people
until you have the...
The ability to save yourself, right?
But I think when I think about leadership,
there are two different ways.
There is leadership that's thrust upon you
and then there is leadership that you show in day-to-day life,
like the leadership through osmosis.
It's like the stuff I was talking about with my kids.
I will go and I will crawl 5K with them
because I know at the end of the day
that I want them to value this adventure.
Of finding out what the view on the other side of the mountain is
and you're hoping that through living a certain way
that there will be this experience for them to get on the other side of.
And then there's the leadership,
when leadership is kind of thrust upon you,
where you were given these roles or these titles
because of something that you have shown
where you need to not forget about the reason
why you were given that title in the first place.
And that was usually because you live the day-to-day values
that people valued.
You live the life that people valued to give you that role
and you can't stop doing that.
Yeah, brilliant answer.
And it's so clear the way that you think about those things.
We see people really conscious, Kurt, on a daily basis
who have consistent success like you have
about how they positively impact others in their environment
every single day.
How have you thought?
How have you thought about that?
How have you thought about that impact on others?
I always think, I always start with the assumption
that the person next to me is the absolute best in the world
to do the tasks that they are buying into.
And then if I've invited them into this space,
then it's kind of, it's up to me as well to make sure
that that's a reality.
And I think that has come from my experience
of the alternative to that.
When you experience this and when you go into a setting
and you experience,
where people have this huge lack of expectation
of who you are and what you can do,
you realise pretty quickly how disempowering that is
and how that can be one of the things
that rip the hope out of you.
And I will never be a part of something
that rips the hope out of people.
So I will always assume that this person
who is lining up for this experience with me
or this, whatever it is that we're about to undertake,
they are the absolute best in the world.
They are what it is that they are undertaking.
And then when I adopt that approach,
I also own that with them.
I just couldn't imagine doing the alternative
because the alternative to that means
that you're having to fight scepticism
through every single thing that you approach.
And scepticism is another thing
that will just get in your road time and time again.
Like I accept there needs to be diligent work
to ensure that you are able to succeed at it.
But assuming,
assuming that that person that's with you on the event
is going to nail the things that they line up for
just allows you to kind of, I don't know,
give them the entire reign
that they could potentially need
to be the person that they believe they have to be.
What a brilliant thing to give people the benefit
that I trust you, isn't it?
Inherently, I trust you, not the opposite.
And so many of us do that.
We judge and we go,
this person might let us down.
This person's not up to the chart.
And we, for no reason,
no understanding most of the time, isn't it?
And, you know, I love that you always start there, isn't it?
And I'm going to trust this person
is going to be world-class and work my way from there.
What a brilliant way to think about life.
I love asking you about, you know,
creating and sharing a vision.
You've had some extraordinary visions
from your marathon success to your Olympic success
to Kokoda to your advocacy
and the board work that you do.
Your own media stuff is a big vision.
How have you gone about creating that
and sharing it to the level
that you've been able to achieve?
I've had a really good team around me,
a really, really, really good team around me
in everything that I've kind of been able to be a part of.
Look, my vision is genuinely,
I would say that I believe that segregation
is a scar on the community in which we live
and that whenever it exists,
we need to do everything possible
to make sure that it is,
that it is read.
I think that telling stories
that haven't been told in mediums
that allow the story to be told a little differently
is really, really important.
I love creating content
and creating conversations
where people are invited into a space
that they may not have heard it voiced in that way before.
You know, I love Tiny Island.
I love You Little Ripper,
which is a Paralympics podcast
where we just talk Paralympic sport.
I don't let any other sport,
in there, never will.
You know, like AFL and NRL Grand Final,
not for our audience, my friends.
This is all sport for people with disabilities
and it is, you know, it is a wild world
and one that is something that created,
you know, a big chunk of who I am.
I love to, I don't know,
if I find a pathway that I believe
that it aligns with purpose,
I love just chasing it
and just seeing where it'll end.
And I could never,
one of the, I guess I have FOMO
to the ninth or the hundredth degree.
I just hate the idea
of seeing an opportunity in front of me
and not kind of,
not shaking it as hard as I can
and not making sure that I've seen the view
on the other side of that mountain
or I've gave that, you know,
that pathway a hell of a shake.
I've got to pick up on what you said there,
segregation's a scar on our community.
Can I understand that a bit more?
Is that coming back to your experience around
just why do we need to put people in specialised schools
or why do we need to deviate off from,
all the resources are there,
if we just accept people, whatever shape, size,
is that being too simplistic?
Is that the message that we need to just,
as your community did,
200, just make a way for whoever
and whatever challenges they've got?
Yeah, I think it's about understanding
that the way that we live
and the life that we live
is not the only way that people experience life.
And I think that we all,
as a community,
would value, would benefit
from experiencing the way
that every other person experiences this life.
You know, like I said,
I've got four non-disabled children,
and we have a world that is changing pretty quickly.
And we get worried about, as a community,
the potential lack of resilience
that is in the next generation.
One of the parts of our community
that do not lack resilience
is this community of people with disabilities
who are learning to forge their way
in a world that's not made for them.
And one of the hardest things about creating resilience
is about making it a reality.
And I think that's a big part of our community.
I think that's a big part of our community.
We want to ensure that somebody
sees the very real world that is out there.
And it gives them a healthy sense
that this, I think I said earlier on,
the hardest thing you've done
is the hardest thing you've done.
Now, if you've never seen somebody
with a variation on life other than you
who's doing it pretty bloody tough,
but nailing it and loving it,
then that's doing yourself a disservice
because you're removing this experience
of a variation of life
that shows you the reality.
you that gives you context of of how you know to be grateful for the for the ease but give you the
context that if you found a tougher road you'd be able to nail it like they're able to nail it
so i see that it's this twofold thing that we need to make sure that that individual who has
a variation of life is a part of everything because they need to feel that they are not
somebody somebody's problem to be pushed to the side that they have they are valued and they can
be valued and loved as they are where they are but the rest of the everybody also gets this really
valuable gift of understanding that that life is varied and their experience is is only just that
it is their experience yet should it change you know pathway towards this kid with a disability
you'll be fine because they're fine so giving this real
solid
understanding of a tangible taste of variation of life i think that that is a gift for everyone
and i am a uh i'm a high school teacher and i believe that every single person in this country
would benefit from being a part of a really inclusive education system and i understand
the realities where parents come in and say you know this kid who has this disability is affecting
my child's experience
in a negative way yet not willing to take a moment to think about the long-term
amazing gift that that will give that your child or another person's child or my child
by experiencing every variation of life and there is nothing more natural in this world
than the variation that disability gives to every person that is around it
incredibly well said kurt it's a profound statement and you can tell that comes from
the heart of your of your lived experience and i think that's a very important thing to do and i
think you can Beyond what you've said a lot on your past garden faces and what Umm has
experienced as you said from your perspective as a as a high school teacher communicating
with clarity is another dimension arsed you and and you are brilliant communicator you just summed
up something that seems complex for a lot of us in in such a brilliant profound way
and you listen to all of your communication and all the podcasts and all the world that you're
in have you thought about the way you do that episode something that you've put time into i kind of landed in spaces where about being placed in these roles where you've
based in these roles where you've got to communicate, you know.
Like I was captain at Karkor Public School, all 16 kids.
So you had to talk in front of kids from, you know,
when you're in year six.
And then I was captain at Blaney School for high school.
So I've landed in these roles where you've kind of got to communicate.
I didn't really think about it until I was lucky to hear
Justice Michael Kirby speak maybe 15 years ago.
And then I spoke after him and we had a good yarn after him.
And he said that he told me that words,
being able to be eloquent with your words is like painting a picture
for everybody who hears them.
And we need more pictures and we need more people because
when they hear these pictures,
it allows them to feel.
Something that they otherwise wouldn't be able to be a part of.
And making people feel is the first pathway to allowing people
a chance to change.
I do think that if you are able to paint a picture with your words,
that you can potentially bring people who otherwise, you know,
have no interest in being a part of the pathway ahead,
you can bring them on board and you can bring them in with you.
So I think I did.
I think about it quite a lot after that about making sure that when I
talk, I try and describe, you know,
the pathway ahead in emotive ways so that people feel what it would be
like to not be invited into that pathway or to,
to feel what it would be like to be a part of that because feeling is
without it, then there's no hope of change.
And there's no hope of, you know, bringing people with you.
Yeah.
How important has collaboration been for you, Kurt?
Yeah, collaboration.
You might think a marathon is, is about an individual sport as you've
ever, ever seen, but I was a part of a team and that team was, you know,
I would back that team to be the best in the world at what we did.
You, you, you always need to recognise that no matter what you're going
through, although it is tempting to kind of feel like you're stuck
in a silo and this is only a you problem.
It's very rare that it is.
There's usually people that have gone through the exact same problem that
you're battling it out with that are able to potentially give you insights.
It's like, you know, experiencing life with a disability.
The first thing that I tell all people with disabilities who acquire it is hang
out with other people with disabilities, get the cheat codes.
You know, life isn't about having to, you fight it out in this silo to try
and find this pathway that just seems so bloody unattainable when, you know,
the majority of issues that are out there, people have fought them before
and, and found the cheat codes for it.
And it's cheat codes and it's, it's, it's not really cheating.
It's, it's just allowing you to do more and be more confident
and feel like you're less alone.
Kurt, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Oh, look, my mum probably.
Look, it's a little kid, five-year-old brought back into a pretty wild space.
And she allowed me to crawl away from the house as a toddler to,
to take these cuts and bruises that, you know, I would feel pretty motivated to,
you know, there would have been, there would have been a thousand voices
of doubt telling her to stop me doing this, you know,
stop allowing him to come back at the end of the night with all these cuts
and bruises and breaks.
But she backed herself.
She genuinely got the input, found out, listened to me,
learned about, you know, what was out there and then made a choice
and backed herself.
Pretty amazing, isn't it, Kurt?
With no, his true understanding, isn't it?
And the mother's instinct, she must have had, as you said,
had to override so much of that instinct to protect, you know,
your youngest sibling who's got challenges that they didn't understand.
I mean, pretty profound, isn't it?
Yeah, I think Alan Marshall's I Can Jump Puddles also helped her out of,
it got rid of any lingering voice of doubt that she was doing the,
potentially the wrong thing.
And Alan Marshall was a young Australian in the 50s, I think,
who grew up with polio and, you know, had fistfights,
crawled through mud, fell out of trees,
did all the mischief that all kids deserve to do.
But I think that's something about sharing a story will hopefully,
probably validate that next person who's going through that same feeling
of siloed, you know, hard, siloed, almost torment.
But I think that that was probably one of the biggest influences on her.
But it does take something, mate.
Like, it genuinely does take something to truly,
truly go against all of the advice that you've been given,
but just know and follow it.
One of the great Australian books, I Can Jump Puddles,
if you haven't read it, it is iconic and a classic.
You mentioned the silos and cheat codes in life.
We're a bit obsessed with collaboration and getting people out of their silos
to do what we're doing and share knowledge for a better life.
And as you described beautifully, you know,
the diversity of experience is brilliant for everyone
if you actually get your head into it.
In that spirit, if you could collaborate with anyone on anything,
you've done these remarkable things.
Have you ever thought,
God, that's someone that would really be fascinating to me
to be alongside of?
Oh, you know what?
I would do everything.
Look, I remember being in, I grew up in a pretty fully,
fully obsessed family when I was at rugby league.
When I was a young fellow,
my uncle was coaching New South Wales and Australia
and another cousin who was, he won a grand final in 91
for the P.
He was a great Benrith Banthers.
And I got to experience the great Craig Bellamy actually in our origin,
but just his ability to fire people up in a situation
and the way that he used parts of himself to give emotion
to others around him.
You name it, mate.
I think I've kind of exposed myself that if there is something out there
that is outside of my usual experience,
and I could be a part of something where somebody created either music
or, you know, just seeing how they do it is amazing.
And I don't think of, I can't think of one off the top of my head.
I'm an anything and everything type of guy, I guess.
What a brilliant answer to finish on.
And I could see, and that's your life, isn't it?
You have just, as you're given a red hot shake to anything in front of you,
and Kurt, it's inspiring to listen to your story
and understand, you know, your values and for really a deeper understanding
for me of what it means to live with a disability
and how you've attacked life.
And it's a fascinating and inspiring story
with plenty more chapters to play out
and some beautiful kids growing up right before your very eyes.
And I really appreciate you taking the time today.
Thanks so much.
No problem.
Thanks for listening to another episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Huge thanks as always to our great friends at Temper.
And we encourage you to check out our Leader Connect program.
New episodes are out every Wednesday morning at 6am.