Disney is one of the largest and most respected media companies in the world.
How do you make sure that you're creating a positive working environment
and a culture that encourages growth and diversity of thinking?
G'day, it's Luke Darson.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership,
both on and off the field, has been a lifelong passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective
and have had the privilege of working with thousands of leaders
in education, sport, industry and the arts
that have helped shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership
where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
I was joined by Kylie Watson-Wheeler, the General Manager of Disney Australia,
to talk about leadership in the workplace, Walt Disney's extraordinary legacy
and how you begin to understand the language of empowerment
and developing confidence.
So Kylie Watson-Wheeler, and this is quite an extraordinary CV
and I'm going to have to do it a little bit of justice here.
Kylie, as the Senior Vice President and Managing Director
for the Walt Disney Company Australia and New Zealand,
currently President of the Western Bulldogs Football Club,
Kylie's responsible for the Walt Disney Company Australia and New Zealand
across film, TV, digital, home entertainment and distribution
and streaming services.
She manages a portfolio of content and products across Disney, Pixar,
Marvel, Star Wars, ESPN, ABC Studios in the US,
20th Century Fox, National Geographic.
And Kylie's leadership history is extensive.
She was the Director of Advertising and Brand Management for Hallmark Cards,
based in Kansas City in the US.
She oversaw marketing for Hallmark's $4 billion business prior to moving to the US
and Kylie spent four years as the Marketing Manager for Hallmark.
Kylie had previous marketing positions with Coca-Cola, Amatil and Penguin Books.
She's a board member of Mentone Grammar here in Victoria,
Motion Pictures Distribution Association of Australia.
And I think the list could go on and on, Kylie, but we might start there.
Thank you.
Thank you for joining us.
It is an extraordinary CV.
Can I start by asking you, did you always have ambitions to be a leader?
No, I didn't actually.
You know, if I think about the progression of my career,
what was always really important to me was finding something that was meaningful to me
and something that I enjoyed and was passionate about.
And so my career journey has really taken me, you know,
through those pathways as I've always sought that.
But one of the key things for me was,
I've always really lent in to the creative side.
So the businesses that I have worked for and have progressed in
generally have really lent into that creative side that I have
and enabled me to really bring to life a vision that has creativity at its core.
And I think that for me, because I did seek out those opportunities
that were meaningful to me, I was able to build my strength
within those industries and within those companies, which led to progression.
Even at a school age, were you pretty clear on that?
At a school age, I knew that I wanted to do something creatively.
And I knew that perhaps being an artist wasn't really a great option for me
for multiple reasons, not only because I might have found myself on the breadline.
And while I say that I like creativity, I'm not sure I'm the best at that version of it.
But I knew that I needed to, that for me, I wanted to be involved in things
that were important to me, that were meaningful to me,
that I was passionate about.
And that was right from when you're at school, the subjects that you choose
and the journey that you head yourself on as a result of that.
So I think probably for me, it wasn't necessarily conscious,
but it was just a matter of always going towards and moving towards the things
that inspired and motivated me.
Yeah, a lot of people you talk to, Kylie, work day to day and they exist in their job
just to get through to some sort of joy on the weekend.
To me, it's one of the saddest things that you can hear people express
and they spend 40 years.
And they say, I didn't really enjoy my job.
And I find that hard to relate to.
I feel very lucky to have always done things that I've been passionate about as well.
So narrowing down on that, I want to get to the Walt Disney Company,
which for a lot of people is just this extraordinary organization.
But for you, were you prepared to pick roles that maybe were based purely on passion
rather than stuff like pay and finance at the start?
Yeah, definitely.
I never, ever chased money.
I always chased what interested me.
And I think in addition to that, sometimes I chose roles that I didn't like,
but for brands that I did.
So the perfect example is really when I had been living in the US for four years
and we made the decision to come home.
My son was one.
We wanted to raise him here in Australia.
And when I was looking at opportunities back here,
I really narrowed it down to brands that I wanted to work for
because I figured that whatever I did next, hopefully, would be a long career journey.
I'm quite loyal.
I worked for Hallmark for eight years.
I've worked for the Bulldogs my entire life, as she now does.
Loyalty is kind of at my core.
So I wasn't necessarily choosing a stepping stone.
I wanted to find something or somewhere that I thought I could have a long career.
And so Disney was high on my list.
I actually chose or applied for and got a role that wasn't actually that exciting to me.
And to be honest, I wasn't actually really qualified for either.
So I'm not really sure how I got that role, but it was in the product division.
So working on products.
Products and building the consumer products business there,
which is something I had never done before.
But I really wanted to work for Disney.
It was a brand that was really meaningful to me
and that I thought had values that would align with my own.
And so I went through a bit of a rocky early stage at Disney
as I tried to work out what on earth I was doing.
Ultimately, somehow worked it out and found myself on a pathway in there.
And Disney is, Kylie, known and legendary for its culture and values.
And you sit here today, as we said,
off the top as MD of this part of the world, Australia and New Zealand.
And then you work through Disney Plus.
It takes you across all the business worldwide.
Can you explain to people the culture and values at Disney
and why it appealed so much and what it's like now
being a leader of those culture and values?
Well, right at the core of our business is the company stands for entertainment with heart.
And regardless of what execution that is and what brand that's under,
it really is about fantastic,
great storytelling.
And that's really at the core of everything that we do.
So there's such a strong, authentic foundation in what we represent as a business.
But then as far as how we operate and I guess the culture that we build within the business,
it is centered around three key pillars of humility, teamwork, and optimism.
And if I break those down, humility basically means,
obviously, we're a really large, well-known company.
We have a lot of amazing assets and content.
But when we're working with our partners and when we're working,
you know, we really need to ensure that we're treating everyone with respect,
that we're not necessarily puffing out our chest.
We're valuing our brands and what we have,
but we're always partnering and creating relationships externally and internally with true integrity.
From a teamwork perspective, you know,
collaboration is at the heart of everything that we do.
And I think that's what's enabled our business to grow and evolve
and change as the industry itself has morphed.
And, you know,
a big legacy business, you know,
the Walt Disney Company is a hundred years old, nearly a hundred years old,
to have really kept pace with this ever-changing media and entertainment industry,
I think is really testament to that, that, you know,
really focusing on how we partner as a team internally and work together.
And then that optimism piece is really being prepared and open to what's coming
and what the future is and not being frightened and kind of entrenching yourself in,
well, this is how we've always operated.
This is what we've focused on.
Yeah.
And that openness to look into the future and a willingness as a team member in the business to be a part of that.
And Kylie, if you look back to the Walt Disney legacy,
those, you know,
clearly they're straight at the forefront of your mind as a leader in the business,
but you could read back and if you read about Disney innovation and quality and community and storytelling optimism and decency,
as you said, a hundred year old company,
it feels like that language has changed subtly,
but not a lot in a hundred years.
Was the Disney company just ahead of its time in understanding that?
Because it feels like a lot of companies didn't share those values for a long period of time.
Well, I think a lot definitely goes back to Walt Disney himself.
I mean, he truly was a visionary in many, many ways.
And I think that the leaders that have taken the mantle since him over many years have really understood that legacy
and understood that truly he was ahead of his time.
I mean, he was ahead of his time in filmmaking.
He invented a whole lot of different ways of making film that really set the future of the industry.
And he created the whole idea around,
creating franchises really,
and the opportunity that once you create a film,
it doesn't necessarily finish there.
You know, there's theme park rides,
there's products,
et cetera,
which was incredibly innovative when you think about how long ago that was and what a big industry that is now.
So I do think that that innovation and creativity is really at the foundation of our business and where it came from.
Also the creative risk taking,
you know,
Walt nearly went broke,
I think two or three times.
You know,
he really bit the farm.
And if you go back to the film,
you know,
if you go to the main building at the Disney head office in the U S the main building is held up by all of the dwarfs from Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs holding up the roof because it was that film Snow White that saved the business and won an Academy Award.
So there's a real understanding and an integration of that history and that leadership foundation that has really endured throughout the hundred years that the business has been around.
And it is such an experience,
Kyle.
I had the great pleasure.
And I've got to confess here.
Uh,
we were in the United States just before the lockdown happened and we're in Los Angeles.
We've got four kids.
So you've got to go and experience Disneyland and where,
you know,
there was lots to do and the U S sport.
And we were so lucky to have that trip looking back,
given the world has shut down.
And I must admit,
Disneyland was a bit of a go and take that one off for the kids.
And,
uh,
you know,
a bit like going to the show.
I had one of the best days I've ever had in my life.
I loved it.
I could have,
I could have gone back and spent the whole week there.
And there's something intangible.
About how friendly the people you smiled the whole time you were there.
And,
uh,
you know,
to me,
that,
that experience just was,
was hard to even explain.
Kyle,
is it,
is that the essence of what,
you know,
your,
your business does?
customer services is at the core of,
of that experience there.
And one of the things that the Walt Disney company really prides itself on is that ability to provide a level of service,
just incomparable.
And in fact,
even our language.
So we're all cast members.
So the people who work at Disney are called cast members.
And anyone who is either,
you know,
buying something from us or visiting our park is called a guest.
So it's really ingrained into the mindset of the culture of the business and everything that we do.
But another thing about your experience at Disneyland is that the whole idea of the park is that,
that is that it's the great leveler.
So before you step in those doors,
you're the dad and your kids are the kids.
But when you go through that door,
you actually are all of the same level.
You're all,
you're all equal and you're enjoying it together as a team rather than necessarily as parent and child.
And I think that's,
that's something that's really important in that experience too.
And you're,
and you hear people who like you,
Kylie,
who are part of the Disney family,
just talk about it being an incredible environment to work in and all of the language that,
you know,
businesses are striving to try and talk now about the inclusiveness and diversity and parental leave.
I understand Disney's famous for its parental leave,
you know,
system has had and its own internal leadership development.
Can,
can you give us a little bit of an insight into how that works?
Well,
I think one of the important things is,
is really,
is really valuing your people and,
and I think that's something as a company that we've always done and really ensured that there is that openness and understanding of how people and their needs change and evolve.
And certainly as you mentioned regarding recognising that that people have children and they have other lives.
And I think it is a matter of understanding that your staff member or cast members in our case are the whole people.
So rather than,
you're not necessarily just looking at them as a staff member,
but your understanding,
understanding the whole person and the importance of that.
And I think some of the strides that the business is making the US in relation to some of the,
the key cultural shifts,
particularly in the US around diversity and inclusion is really demonstrative of that focus of the business and the importance that that has.
Kyle,
we've been talking a lot to people on this podcast in what I think is a bit of a shift in leadership.
It's the 20th century of around hierarchy and the boss has the corner office and you know what,
you know,
good luck even getting a hello,
from the boss and you know,
let alone would they know anything about you or your family and people sit outside and it's very hard to get a voice in your own environment.
I feel like you guys have been well and truly down that path.
I heard your language before collaborations at the key,
humility's at the key.
Have you stayed away from environment?
Can you see that a lot of environments were run with hierarchy and is that the point of difference that you try and live?
Yeah,
absolutely.
I mean,
I certainly over my career,
I have worked in all different versions.
Of structures in the context of that.
But one of the things that,
you know,
as I mentioned before,
I do think that that collaboration component is really important.
And I've worked in in businesses before where as a leader,
I have been pitched against someone else and there's been a real competitive combative mindset that's been created.
And while that might deliver in the short term,
I don't think that delivers in the long long term.
I think what's much more important is you've got a whole lot of people working together and heading in the one direction.
And I,
I often say to the team,
you know,
the sum is greater than the parts.
And so anything that you can do that can help enhance and create that collaboration,
bring people together,
breaking down walls,
breaking down silos,
ensuring that there is that visibility and not necessarily the hierarchy that you mentioned that you've got people from all levels of the team working together on different projects.
And I think that's really important.
We have a structure around in our marketing group because there are so many different facets to our business that we need to try to connect the dots.
And create that consistency of messaging market across many different areas.
So we have created these groups called pods.
And so there's small groups of people that are come that come from each different part of the business.
And they,
they joined together in one group and work on projects together,
which happened to work incredibly well during a COVID lockdown period because,
you know,
you had these small groups of people who were meeting regularly and were really able to think outside the box.
And there was lots of different vision and different ideas and different thoughts coming together.
And it really ensured that that we really flourished during that time.
So grabbing people,
not necessarily from the same division,
but getting that collaborative and almost structurally forcing that to happen.
Is that was that the idea?
And you know,
the groups would get together.
How were they facilitated?
What was,
was it,
was it run by a leader or a specific part of the business?
Well,
generally there would be someone who would be a lead in that group.
They wouldn't necessarily be a leader or the most senior person either,
but just making sure that there was someone who,
who was connecting the dots and,
and I guess ensuring that,
that they were staying on task and focus.
But ultimately it was the group that was working closely together on the outcome.
But the important thing there is it can't be a massive group.
It has to be a nice tight team where everybody has a voice and it's easy to collaborate and bring things to fruition.
Well,
we've been doing something similar in a business that I'm involved in and passionate about,
and we've been grabbing,
you know,
these sort of leaders in sport who come from different areas and we've been able to pull them together
through.
COVID in the last period of time.
So people like Eddie Jones,
who's coaching the rugby team of England and Ange Postakoglu who's in Japan and Justin Lange has been involved and you know,
different areas,
but to see these guys come out of their environments with people who are experiencing,
you know,
very similar challenges,
albeit in different sports and the amazing amount of,
I suppose,
sharing of information and collaboration and the joy that those guys have got out of it has been really rewarding.
It sounds very similar to what you guys are doing at Disney.
Absolutely.
And I think,
the key to that too is that you're bringing people with different experiences.
So there's a commonality across what you're discussing,
but they're coming at it through different lenses.
And I think that's something really important in business too.
And something that I really strive to do is to make sure I'm surrounding myself with people with different views and different perspectives.
It's really easy to get into that groove of just surrounding yourself with people who all think the same way as you.
It makes it really easy,
but it doesn't bring the best outcome.
And so I think that's something really important as well.
Collie,
on this podcast,
I was talking to Sally Capp,
the Lord Mayor of Melbourne,
and she's had a lot of firsts like you in her life as a leader,
but going on to do extraordinary things and be elected as Lord Mayor of Melbourne and the first agent general to Victoria based in London and a whole series of things along the lines of your history.
But she spoke about as a 22 year old in a law firm,
she was invited in by a senior partner to a meeting and she'd done her research.
She's incredibly diligent,
Sally,
and,
she spoke up spoke to the client at that stage and because she knew the answer and she knew what to pass on.
She got in the lift and the senior partner turned to her a mail and said,
do not ever,
ever speak again in one of my meetings.
And you could see her still,
you know,
uh,
red with the frustrate.
Yeah.
The frustrate.
Have you had to deal with any of that along the way?
Has there been people tried to try and keep you,
you know,
in your box,
so to speak?
Wow.
I feel really confronted on behalf of Sally.
That would have been.
So did I.
Absolutely horrible experience.
Yeah.
But to be honest,
I actually haven't.
Um,
I have had some pretty strong mentors in my career who did the opposite,
actually,
who gave me a voice.
And I remember one in particular when I was working in the U S and,
um,
the guy who,
who headed up all of marketing and I was overseeing advertising and I was,
you know,
this,
this Australian girl who'd just come over and I was sitting around the table,
um,
with all of my new peers.
And I remember the ad agent,
she being in there,
they'd flown in from,
um,
from another state and from Chicago and we're all sitting,
it was a big intense meeting and they did their pitch.
And the very first thing he did was he turned to me and said,
Kylie,
what do you think?
And I think I'd been in the States for five minutes and I think I'd been in
the company for three and I answered and he obviously liked my answer.
Cause he asked me that first,
every single time,
but just that,
that encouragement that that guy,
I mean,
apart from the initial heart,
you know,
horror and shock.
I think he was asking me that in that room of people,
um,
just the encouragement that that gave to me and the confidence it gave.
So it's something that I've always thought about and tried to make sure that
I do for,
for people who are up and coming within the business as well.
Not,
not to put them on the spot,
but more to give them the opportunity to have a voice.
Yeah.
That language of empowering,
isn't it?
How,
how,
how important that was for you.
And you can understand that you then pass that on to others,
isn't it?
It's such a powerful model.
You mentioned mentors.
Is there,
is,
any,
how important a mentor has been in your life?
And can you maybe share with us some of those people who've had a big impact on you?
I think,
uh,
anyone that believes in you on your journey,
um,
you know,
really helps to contribute to your evolution as a leader.
And I think that when you feel that there is someone who really has your back and,
and really values you and what you bring to the table and can really encourage you to lean into that,
you know,
certainly that,
that,
um,
that leader in the States that I mentioned,
there are a couple of those,
Peter Gordon,
of course,
has been another one for me on the,
on the seven year journey at the Western Bulldogs,
uh,
working with him and,
you know,
really learning about how he converts his passion,
uh,
to value for the club has been,
has been really important.
So there's been lots of people on my journey who have,
have provided me,
you know,
where they get,
I guess,
a little insight into how I'd like to operate and how I would like to be a leader.
There's also been plenty who have taught me what not to do.
And I do think like Sally,
he's first manager.
I think that there are people that you can learn from.
You can learn as much from those that you think I would never,
ever treat people like that,
or I would never want to behave that way.
And I think that that's something that I think sometimes you can forget that even from an awful,
awful experience,
um,
within your career,
you can actually draw some really strong learnings from those and turn them into a positive by ensuring that you either do the counter of that,
or that you just never,
ever do that yourself.
It might be a good time to,
to jump into our shared passion for,
for the red,
white and blue and the Bulldogs.
And you mentioned Peter Gordon,
who's been the legendary president over a few decades,
really in two stints and had an extraordinary legacy at the Western Bulldogs.
And to the point where you've taken over from him and succeeded as his vice president into the president of the Bulldogs.
But your first encounter with Peter was back in 1989.
The Bulldogs were about to go out of existence.
Can you pick up the story there and explain what you were doing on that day?
Yeah,
it was the Save the Bulldogs rally.
At the Witten Oval.
And it was,
I was in year 12 and it was actually the,
my year 12 study week.
And I had said to my dad,
oh,
look,
I really want to go.
And he said,
well,
no way you've got to stay home and study.
And I said,
well,
what if I take my,
my homework with me?
So I did.
And I sat in the gravel behind the goals,
uh,
with my homework on my knee.
Although I don't think I did any,
any of that homework that day,
but you know,
Peter was up there on the podium,
you know,
flying the flag for our club and really ensuring our,
our continued exist.
And,
so that was a really important pivotal moment to me and to
my life.
And,
you know,
the club was very meaningful to me as it still is.
It it's really a huge part of my family history and
where my family has come from and my relationship with my
dad and my sister and my connection to my grandparents.
So it is,
there's,
it was incredibly important to me.
And,
and as you know,
DAS often football is way more than football.
It's way more than a game.
And so it was such an important pivotal moment for,
for me.
And for Peter and all of those who worked with him to be
successful and save the club was,
was really amazing.
So then,
you know,
30 plus years later for me to be succeeding him as the
president is,
is a very surreal experience.
That's for sure.
It's,
it's a magical story,
Kylie,
and,
and a bit of context for those that perhaps listen,
they don't understand AFL.
It's the inner west of Melbourne,
10,000 people turn up to that rally.
The AFL have given a deadline.
You're insolvent.
We're either going to merge you out of existence or,
or out of existence completely.
And,
and I think it was $1.6 million was raised in three
days from,
from the most working class of areas to,
to,
to find that and to,
you know,
effectively against all odds save the club.
And as you said,
you know,
I can hear the passion coming out in all your life,
but you know,
I did read that it was,
you used to stand on a wooden box that your grandfather
had built and you were there at the footy all the
time with,
with your sister.
So that,
that is pure passion,
isn't it?
That's,
that's taken place over a long period of time.
Yeah,
absolutely.
It truly is at my heart and you're that wooden box,
my grandfather was a French polisher.
So he,
he made me a little box so that I could stand
up and say,
cause as you know,
in those days,
you didn't necessarily get a seat and you're still on the
wing.
And,
and,
you know,
it was such an amazing time too,
because the people that stood around you,
we all stood in the same place and you grew up
together and you might not have even known each other's
names,
but you know,
you,
you spent a decade standing next to each other at
the footy.
So it was just a very special part of my life
and it remains so.
Yeah.
Amazing.
Isn't it?
I think my own family history as well.
My grandmother,
who lived to 95 and she saw every game my dad
played and every game that I played and it's,
it's,
it's in you,
isn't it?
You can't,
uh,
you can't hide the,
the history.
It's quite,
uh,
quite extraordinary.
I just,
Kyle,
you seem to me to be this incredibly capable person.
Uh,
I can't imagine you ever having,
you know,
a mistake or,
uh,
is there,
is there something that you look back and think I
learned,
I learned a little bit from,
from that mistake along the journey.
I make many mistakes like,
like everyone,
but I think one of the most important things is
that learning from them.
And,
you know,
I do frequently reflect on decisions that I've made.
And even if they haven't been disastrous,
disastrous,
I might kind of look back and say,
would I have done that differently?
Is there something that I could do better?
But the times where things have gone wrong have
generally been when I have not trusted my gut.
So when in my heart,
I know this isn't the right decision,
I can feel it in my bones,
but for a variety of reasons,
I'm going to hire this person,
or I'm going to agree,
to this deal.
And without fail,
whenever I have gone against that instinct,
it has always gone wrong.
So that's a big lesson for me.
Always trust my gut,
no matter what.
Yeah.
It's a,
it's an amazing thing there,
isn't it Kylie?
And I'd like to maybe ask you a little bit more
about that because it's,
it is so true,
isn't it?
That powerful instinct to think this doesn't feel right,
but our mind overrides that sometimes for,
for a variety of reasons.
Does that happen less for you now when you really
instinctively know that something is right?
Obviously,
you know,
you,
you use the word,
words of collaboration,
but do you find you just now really dial into that
more than you did in the past?
Yeah,
definitely.
And I think that comes with experience and trusting
yourself too.
I think,
I think the,
you know,
the times where your gut instincts have really delivered
for you.
And then the times where you haven't trusted them and,
you know,
the cleaning up of that is usually quite extensive.
You know,
you hire someone because on paper they look like the
right person and you really desperately need to fill
this role.
And it's been so hard to find someone,
but within the interview,
you just don't click.
There's something that just doesn't feel right.
And then you go ahead and hire that person and then
it's a disaster and it's an enormous amount of cleaning
up and time it takes to rectify that.
So I think the more times you do that,
the more scared away you are from that because you
recognize that you're going to set yourself up for a
tough journey.
So I do think that,
you know,
one of the key parts of leadership is,
is really learning to trust yourself,
to lean into your own values and recognize the importance
of those and also really being authentic in every way.
And I think that helps you to avoid some of those
issues and challenges and mistakes,
because if you're being truly authentic and you're really dialed in
to what's important,
I think you're less likely to go off task.
I want to ask you about the,
you know,
the balance of life.
I think to me,
something I think about every day,
you know,
as a father of four and to me,
I always think about it,
about not wanting to miss the point of life.
You want to,
you want to achieve and,
and you've got these things that motivate you from a passion
point of view.
But you know,
for me,
if I get the family balance part wrong,
then it's not worth anything at all.
And it's a constant battle to try and achieve all that.
You've got serious roles and,
and incredible leadership positions,
but you're also a mother of two.
How do you manage that?
I think the passion part is,
is really important too.
And I think one of the things that I'm really lucky in
my business is that it's interesting to my children.
And I mentioned,
you know,
my son was,
was one when I started at Disney and he's 18 now.
And I tease him that,
you know,
every time I thought that perhaps he might be growing out of our
content,
we acquire another studio.
So whether it be Marvel or Star Wars or Fox,
but I think one of the things that,
that has been really helpful to me is that I've been able
to take them on the journey with me.
And I do remember a time when my son was,
was quite little.
And at the time I was running publishing for the region,
I,
and I was going to,
I don't know,
Indonesia or somewhere the next day,
I remember I was tucking him into bed and I said,
oh,
you know,
I won't be here in the morning.
So I might have to fly out.
And,
and he said,
oh,
I wish you didn't have to go.
And I said,
oh,
look,
I wish I didn't have to go either,
but if I don't go,
then I don't work for Disney.
And he said,
see you,
mom,
there's more than happy for me to go.
Cause me,
me working for Disney was more important than me missing the next
few days.
So I think that that's been,
that's been an important part of it for me.
But I think also recognizing,
you know,
the balance piece that you mentioned is ensuring that I'm recognizing my
whole self,
as well.
I know I talked earlier about the importance of recognizing the whole
self of your staff,
but recognizing that all of these areas of my life are important to
me.
And I do think that career decisions that I've made have,
have been based on that as well.
You know,
I wouldn't,
I wouldn't take a role that had me overseas six months of the
year.
I moved back to Australia because I wanted my kids to grow up
around their family,
even though I had a really great career that was developing in the
state.
So I think there are,
I don't want to use,
use the word sacrifice because I don't think,
think they are,
but I think that there's definitely decisions that I've made to ensure
that I can live the life that I want to live and raise
my children the way I want to raise them.
Yeah.
The choices aren't they that make you successful in every part of
your life or,
or,
or attempt to,
is,
is there anything I always think of that the daily habits of
successful people are interesting?
Is there,
are there routines that set you up every day to,
to achieve that?
Well,
I'm,
I'm a pretty basic person.
I get up and I walk my dog,
the most important thing.
But,
um,
but it's also where I get my bit of headspace.
I think that's an important part for me to kick off the
day.
Um,
I'll often listen to a podcast or an audio book or,
you know,
just to get that bit of a,
a break from,
um,
you know,
the grind of the day and,
and of life and of school lunches and the like,
and,
and then,
and then also all of the things that you need to be
wrapping your head around,
uh,
at work.
So I think that's something that's really important for me,
just that bit of headspace,
that opportunity to think about or listen to something else.
Um,
can you,
I've got on my list to ask you about,
uh,
the world of social media.
It's something we're all,
uh,
whether we like it or not,
I suppose,
you know,
attached to our phones from,
from,
from a business point of view.
And then from a parenting point of view,
how do you manage it?
What's,
what's your strategies on that front?
Well,
business,
it's certainly an important way to connect with and engage
with our audiences.
And so we have multiple social media platform engagements
across all of our different brands.
So it's something that,
you know,
I think that,
is central to the way in which we operate today,
but you know,
you certainly have to be careful and cautious,
you know,
obviously in social media,
there's supposed to be an age level.
We know that then they're not necessarily is that the young kids
are on there as well.
So given what our brands represent,
we need to be really careful of that.
So moderating that space is something that we really lean into
and ensure that,
that we're really watching our feeds.
It's also a great way though,
to really temperature check how audiences are feeling about our content.
And,
and it's a great way,
to uncover if there are any issues or challenges.
So there can be some positive elements to it as well,
but,
but definitely protecting our audiences is really important.
From a kid's perspective,
it's,
it is really tricky because it's,
it's quite difficult.
I think to block kids once they're of a certain age,
and my daughter is 15,
my son is 18 and driving and at uni.
So I've lost all control there in every aspect.
That's for sure.
So you just have to hope that you've laid some pretty strong foundations
there and cross your fingers.
And I hope for the best.
But I do think that,
that as much as anything talking about it is really important,
helping your kids understand,
you know,
what the reality is of social media,
the,
the polished view that they're getting,
you know,
the,
the very specific stories that people are telling that is not necessarily
the full story,
you know,
talk to them,
of course,
about trolls and trolling and who these people are and,
and something that,
that you know,
if I,
if I think about people who comment in social media and,
and us,
you know,
I know that you would face this and,
and I have had some on a much smaller scale,
but I've certainly had some criticism in social media myself,
but someone actually told me once that if you think about everyone who's
reading,
reading the social media,
10% don't care at all and 10% care a lot and everyone else is
pretty neutral.
So I think if you can really understand that,
you know,
this is not the whole world that's saying this,
it's a really tiny percentage and you've got to put it in context.
I think with my kids,
helping them understand that,
helping them understand that the,
what is being written and said and presented is not necessarily the full
truth and certainly not the full opinion of everyone else.
Yeah.
It's a great way to look at it,
isn't it?
I mean,
it feels so personal,
doesn't it for,
you know,
and for,
for young kids in particular,
it's a lot to deal with,
isn't it?
That direct ability to,
um,
to get that,
you know,
not negative,
not positive,
uh,
feedback on a regular basis.
There was a,
uh,
a documentary I think came out in lockdown last year,
the social network,
and we,
uh,
forced the kids to sit down and have a look at it.
And it was a really great,
um,
experience.
They rolled their eyes.
This is going to be boring,
but they were really engaged.
You know,
I didn't understand,
I didn't understand when I gave over my personal details that that was being
collected for data.
And I didn't quite understand that,
you know,
food was being tailored then to,
to,
to my likes adding,
you know,
they,
it was,
uh,
an interesting conversation.
It's as you said,
it's,
I love the fact how quickly they can connect on.
I remember as a kid,
you know,
you sound so archaic,
don't you have to try and ring and catch up with someone.
The home phone was engaged or the amount of times you went to meet
someone and you miss them because they're on the other side of the
wall,
but they can connect so well,
but,
uh,
trying to manage it is,
is a,
is an ongoing challenge,
isn't it?
Absolutely.
No,
that's so true.
It certainly is,
is a very different environment for our kids than it was back in
our day,
Darce.
That's for sure.
Kylie,
there'd be a lot of people listening to this and hearing,
you know,
Kylie Watson,
Wheeler and thinking that's,
that's an unattainable level for me.
What,
what advice would you give someone who's got aspirations to,
to end up in leadership roles like you are?
I think,
as I've mentioned,
you know,
following your passions is the most important thing because you're
going to have the most credibility and the most likelihood of
success and advancement.
If it's something that you really care about and you're really
engaged in,
because I do think that all of the things that you need to
do to be able to progress in that way,
you need to care about,
about what you're working on and what's central to your
career,
because as a result of that,
then you're going to be inquisitive and curious,
and you're going to seek out what the opportunities and the
options are.
And so,
you know,
then I think also you're more likely to take educated risks
and risks that then will return something that's bigger and
out outside the box and something different.
And the other thing too,
I think,
you know,
you're really going to create the opportunity to take people
along a journey with you.
Cause I think that that's one of the important,
the things about leadership and you don't have to be a
lead in a leadership position to be a leader.
And I think that's really important.
And I think when I first realized that I probably had leadership
opportunity was when I was in the States and I had
received this random project due to a whole lot of strange
things that happened in the business hallmark was,
was sponsoring the salt lake winter Olympics.
And it was the first time that they had ever sponsored
anything like that.
And there was some movement.
And at the top,
some people left and it was this hot potato.
No one wanted to touch it.
They'd made this massive financial commitment.
It wasn't something that anybody really understood who was left in
the business understood.
And so I was handed this hot potato.
And so I thought,
okay, well,
I've got to make the most of this.
And I pulled together a team of my peers and,
you know,
between us,
we divvied up all of the different areas.
And it was quite an extensive sponsorship because it was the
flowers in the,
there was a retail component.
There was a store at the village where all of the,
the athletes lived.
There were multiple facets to it.
And so I split it up between my peers and we sat down
and we worked this out together and we absolutely worked our
guts out for the whole period of the Olympics.
And it was seen as a massive,
amazing success.
So for something that was a hot potato before it was
actually something that then was held up as a,
as a really strong demonstration of the power of the brand
within,
within the States.
And it was really through that collaboration of my team.
And for all of these people that I managed to,
uh,
convinced to come and work with me on this project that we
achieved that I wasn't their boss.
Um,
in some instances,
I was more junior than some of them,
but I think that that demonstrated to me that I can take
people on a journey.
And I think that that's ultimately what led me to the career
I've had.
Uh,
it's a great story,
Kyle.
And I love the,
you know,
all of what you said,
but one of it in particular,
you don't have to have a title to,
to be a leader.
And,
and,
um,
you know,
I'm really passionate about that.
You can impact people positively without a title.
Can't you just today by your actions and by your,
your interactions and engagements,
uh,
you know,
you sum that up beautifully.
There's a series of questions,
Kylie,
that I've been keen to ask different people from,
uh,
different leadership backgrounds around,
you know,
this thought that there are specific dimensions of what makes a
great leader.
So,
um,
I might start with self-leadership.
What,
what does that term mean to you?
I do think that self-leadership is about truly being authentic
to yourself and being the same version of yourself in all areas
of your business.
I do think that something that early on in my career that I
thought I needed to do was,
I needed to be the work version of myself and the home
version of myself.
And over time I've learned in some ways,
the hard ways,
hard ways that that's actually not the best way to do it.
The best way is to actually always be your authentic self.
And then,
you know,
you're more likely to get more engagement,
more out of people.
And,
you know,
I really think from that perspective,
it really helps to create that foundation of being able to
take people on the journey,
which is,
which is key to leadership.
The other thing that's,
that's close to my heart is,
is this idea that,
that your reputation is everything.
And I think that one of the things that has really helped my
growth and progression throughout the Walt Disney company,
and also my ability to bring to light some unusual or unique
or out of the box ideas is because I've built a reputation of,
of trust of collaboration of partnership and of being upfront.
And I think that that's,
that's really important and has been core to my success at Disney.
Most definitely.
Yeah,
that's a really fascinating Kylie and,
and make sense.
I just wanted to ask you a little bit about,
and I think for a lot of people,
we're all trying to be different versions of ourselves at times,
as you said,
and it's tiring,
isn't it?
You know,
in this environment,
I need to speak this way,
I act this way.
It wears people down.
Can you,
can you explore that a little bit more around,
is it being more open and saying,
this is me at home and,
and unashamedly,
and there's a bit of vulnerability.
And that was a conscious decision that you made to just,
to just,
let that go at work as well.
I think you articulated it perfectly.
Then trying to be different versions of yourself is exhausting because you're
trying to invent a persona that isn't necessarily true to you.
And then it's hard to maintain that.
And by that,
I mean,
you know,
people might be wondering what I'm talking about,
but if you think that at work,
all of a sudden you have to be this very formal,
very serious version of yourself.
Whereas at home,
you might be a bit lighthearted,
you know,
you bring a different type of energy.
And so,
you know,
I think what's important,
is that that home version of you actually is what differentiates you and what is special and unique about you.
So ensuring that you're always bringing that to the table,
I think really helps to create your place and,
and your opportunity in the work world.
But,
you know,
I think,
as I said before,
just,
just that whole idea of trying to,
to be someone different is tiring,
but then is also not all,
not authentic.
And it does reduce your ability to be vulnerable.
And I think that that's something that is spoken about a lot in leadership.
And it took me a really long time to understand what that meant,
but it means being prepared to be really open and to not always have to be,
you know,
in inverted commas,
the boss.
You can be someone who can say,
I've,
I learned from this,
this mistake because of X,
Y,
and Z,
or I did this this way and it didn't work for me,
or things didn't always work out for me.
And it just helps for people to understand that you are human and that we're all on a journey like this.
And you're not,
you're not untouchable or unattainable because that's another thing I think that's that helps people be successful in modern leadership is as a leader to be really approachable to be someone who people can relate to and engage with.
And something that,
that I did almost by accident over COVID was the first week that we were locked down.
I did a video from home.
You know,
I had my hair in a top knot and I was in my track suit and I'm like,
well,
here we are.
This is really interesting.
And I got a really positive response to that.
So then I did one,
one every single week for the entirety of COVID.
And now that we're,
well,
we're supposed to be back.
We're technically back.
I've been doing it every second week.
But one of the things that I noticed is that when we went back to the office,
all of these people that had never spoken to me before would come up and say,
Oh,
Hey,
Kylie,
how are you going?
And I felt like they knew me.
Whereas before I was like this unknown senior person,
you know,
in the office,
but it just created that opportunity for people to feel like they knew me.
And sometimes I was serious on them.
And sometimes I was a bit silly.
And sometimes my dog,
Mabel made a cameo appearance.
But I think just from that perspective,
ensuring that you as a leader is seen as a real person.
And I think that's really made a difference to the culture of our business almost by accident.
I think Mabel's become the star of your Zooms and the Bulldog board meeting.
You often see Mabel in the background.
That's been a big part of it.
And I love,
I've loved that too,
isn't it?
You actually go into people's homes and,
you know,
we're doing that today with you and it does open up the conversations.
So how do you go,
how do you go about Kylie trying to positively impact others in your environment?
No,
I think that a big part of my role is bringing the energy of the business and the excitement.
And as I mentioned,
the optimism when you work for a company that is in a phase of major change and evolution,
or it's in an industry that's in a phase of change and evolution,
which the media space is.
And within our portfolio,
you know,
we have long-term legacy businesses.
You know,
we have film,
we have physical home entertainment,
and we're moving into the digital space.
And so it's really important to keep the team energised and focused on the future and the opportunity for them to be a part of that,
regardless of what part of the business they're currently in.
So that's a really important part for me,
ensuring that there's focus,
that everybody really understands where we're heading as a business.
And then of course,
communication is certainly key.
And how do you go about creating and sharing that vision,
Kylie?
Well,
one of the things that,
that I think is really important.
So creating at first,
it's definitely about ensuring that I'm leaning into the expertise of the team.
Our business is really broad.
You know,
you read out at the beginning,
there are many facets to it.
You know,
we have our finger in lots of pies,
our fingers in lots of pies.
So ensuring that I'm leaning into the leaders of those businesses and the people who work within those teams to really understand the detail and what's important.
And as I mentioned before,
surrounding myself with people who are going to challenge and question and push on that thinking.
And then I think the other part of that is also really understanding and keeping an eye on what's happening outside of our company and how the industry itself is evolving.
So you really recognise what else is happening out there.
So not being too insular is really important.
And as far as communicating it,
I create a story in a triangle.
So I create a,
some buzzwords or some,
some language that really articulates our overarching strategy really,
really simply and clearly.
And that's at the top of the triangle.
So that's something that I want to make sure that everyone in the whole business,
regardless of their role,
really understands that.
And I use those words a lot.
So an example of that is we talk about our local and love strategy here in Australia,
which basically means that we take the amazing content that our parent provides us with,
but we overlay an Australian,
um,
thinking and mindset for a much deeper connection with our local audiences.
Now,
I think I say that so many times that I think pretty much everyone in our business could articulate that.
But then as you go down that pyramid where it gets kind of bigger at the base,
there's a lot of detail in that there's a lot of deep strategy,
high level strategy and articulation that,
that perhaps on the,
um,
you know,
the more senior experience people in the business would truly understand.
But I do think that ensuring that there's a connection point for everyone in the business so that they really understand the job,
understand the job,
the journey that the company is on so that then they can feel a part of it.
Learning and improvement.
Kylie,
what's your approach to that?
I definitely think learning from others is,
is really important.
And,
um,
I do think that you can learn from other people's journeys and other people's mistakes.
That's why I like the autobiographies because I think that's when people are truly raw and an open,
or you hope that they are some are not,
but,
um,
you know,
sometimes you do get under the skin of,
of some of the mistakes that people have made or,
um,
or the journeys that they have been on.
I definitely think that as our business evolves and changes,
learning about the new industries that we're going into,
certainly making sure that I'm on top of that digital space,
that I understand at least at some level how that is evolving and how that's changing.
But an important part of that too,
is I don't need to know all of that.
I can bring experts into the business who have a deeper understanding.
But one of the things that's important in my role is that I need to know,
a certain level about every part of the business.
And I need to be able to have somewhat intelligent conversations with senior people in,
in all of those industries,
uh,
whether it's the CEO of channel nine or the CEO of Optus,
or,
you know,
I need to know enough about their business and ours to be able to,
uh,
articulate what it is that we need as a business and also to understand what they need.
Cause I think that's,
that's the perfect part of partnership where you can find that intersect between the two.
So really learning and understanding,
understanding and keeping on top of the way industry is changing,
evolving and evolving is really important as well.
And,
uh,
and Kylie,
um,
you mentioned collaboration a lot.
How do you go about collaborating?
Well,
as I've said before,
collaboration is key.
And you know,
one of,
one of the things that I say a lot within the business is the sum is greater than the parts.
And also another one I use is all boats must rise and we need to link arms.
I say a lot of these things over and over again,
but it's,
but it's fairly clear then,
uh,
you know,
how important I see collaboration is.
And,
you know,
from that perspective,
it really is about everybody being on a shared journey and it can be difficult in a big,
broad business where each part of the business has a different set of objectives to try to help people understand that the business is evolving.
And so then they need to both focus on what their individual objectives are and then the overarching view and direction of the business.
And so the communication part is really key.
To that and really helping people understand the importance of that shared vision and being prepared to sometimes put the shared vision before your own objective.
And it's really important that you reward people against that.
So it'd be one thing if I was to say,
okay,
well,
here are your targets within your area,
but sometimes you need to relinquish those targets for the greater good,
but you're only being measured and valued on your targets.
So then all of a sudden the staff member or the cast member is in conflict.
So as a leader,
you really need to make sure that you're doing the right thing.
You really need to make sure that you're doing the right thing.
So as a leader,
you really need to make sure that you're doing the right thing.
you really need to make sure that you're facilitating that collaboration and making it easy for people to do.
It's not just a matter of telling them that's what they have to do.
It needs to actually make sense to them and their life and how they're working as well.
Could you name,
has there been someone who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Well,
it'd be really hard to go past Bob Iger.
And I know that's going right up to the top of the tree.
You know,
the vision that he set on the journey that I've been at Disney,
you know,
10,
well,
actually it was longer.
When I first started at Disney,
you know,
nearly 18 years ago,
Bob Iger had just taken over as the CEO.
And one of the things that he said is that,
you know,
at the time we had,
like all studios,
we might've had 25 different films on our slate that were,
you know,
non-branded.
Maybe there was Toy Story that was the only branded content that was on there.
And he said that we were going to become a franchise driven business and that all of the films that we would create and release would,
would have a knock on effect to other parts of the business,
you know,
really going back to Walt's original vision.
And I remember looking at the slate,
and thinking that makes total sense to me what he's saying,
but how on earth could you possibly turn this massive boat around this enormous Walt Disney company that has been operating this way now for several decades and really reinvent it.
And so while I loved his vision,
I had very little faith in it and he absolutely did it.
And I learned so much from him about that preparedness to trust your instincts,
to lean into creativity,
to make those big educated bets,
to really back yourself and your vision.
And he's probably one of the greatest leaders I think that I've ever seen.
And I've been incredibly lucky to work within an organization that he was running for the nearly two decades.
Kyle,
it's been incredible to spend some time with you this morning.
I've been writing notes.
I've got content to watch and lessons learned.
I'm sure lots of other people will feel the same way.
I really appreciate your time and feel very fortunate to be able to spend some time with you.
Thanks again.
Thanks,
Das.
Good to talk to you.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me,
Luke Darcy,
produced by Matt Dwyer with audio production by Darcy Thompson.
Start your leadership journey.
I encourage you to go to elitacollective.com.
Take our Empowering Leaders Indicator Tool and understand the impact you have on your environment.
Join us at Elida to learn,
lead and collaborate.