How do you build a mindset of incredible resilience,
gratefulness and positivity
despite life presenting you with extraordinary challenges?
G'day, it's Luke Darson.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership
both on and off the field has been a lifelong passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective
and have had the privilege of working with thousands of leaders
in education, sport, industry and the arts
that have helped shift to what we see
as the 21st century style of leadership
where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
Lakeisha Patterson, or Lucky as she is most commonly known,
is an Australian Paralympic swimming superstar.
She is a Queensland, Australian Commonwealth and Paralympic champion,
a six-time world record holder,
a seven-time Paralympic medalist,
including two gold in Rio and a gold in Tokyo.
She's also a two-time Paralympic Commonwealth Games gold medalist,
as well as being a recipient of the Order of Australia medal
for her outstanding achievements.
Lakeisha or Lucky, it is great to meet you.
Thanks for joining me.
Thanks for having me on.
Now, Lucky, I'm going to be familiar enough to go with Lucky.
And I asked you this before we started recording.
You said you feel like you're in trouble if we go with Lakeisha.
So, Lucky, a lot of people would think your start in life
was anything but Lucky.
Can you share with us what happened at birth?
Yeah, absolutely.
So, for those that don't know me,
I was born with cerebral palsy left hemiplegia
due to the trauma I sustained during birth.
So, essentially, I was born breech, blue and not breathing.
So, it was, yeah, a little bit of a tricky situation.
And essentially, down the line, because of that trauma sustained,
I was diagnosed with cerebral palsy.
So, essentially, that means that the left side of my body
doesn't quite work as well as my right.
I don't have as much function, balance,
coordination and, you know, a little challenging things along the way.
So, I can't, you know, fully open my left hand
as well as, like, balance and kind of dragging my left foot a little bit.
So, my right side is definitely more dominant
and I have to do a lot compared to my left.
But I suppose for myself, I've just been accustomed
to being able to adapt from a very young age.
And alongside that, I was also diagnosed
with epilepsy when I was five and micrographia at 12,
meaning that my writing is extremely minute.
So, I have to use technology to be able to communicate.
So, it's pretty awesome that we are able to live in the world
that we live in today, that I am able to be able to communicate with people.
But, yeah, I suppose for a lot of people,
it can be seen as quite a lot of challenges.
But for myself, I've just been raised to be able to overcome anything
that's come my way and I definitely don't see it as a disadvantage at all.
It's remarkable.
A story at the age of five is when you were diagnosed with epilepsy
and reading some of your life story, a theory that I think you were suggesting
that perhaps it was on the back of a bad batch of vaccinations.
And I'm going back to the lucky.
I'm here talking to lucky and a lot of people would think,
God, how much hardship does one person have to endure?
How much bad luck?
I mean, do you remember ever thinking, why me at some stage along the way?
I think it's definitely very easy for a lot of people when they, you know,
come into these difficult circumstances to say, why me?
And I definitely am human as well and have gone through that.
I suppose when I was younger, I didn't really know anything different.
So I don't think I really had that mindset then until, you know,
growing up a little bit more and actually being aware of these differences
compared to my classmates around primary school and high school age.
But I suppose for myself, I was just grown up with an incredibly strong mum
who raised myself and my two other sisters on her own.
And she really instilled in me that power of resilience.
And, you know, it's not what happens to you, it's how and what you make of it
and how you can overcome those circumstances.
And yeah, it is a bit ironic that my name and nickname is lucky,
but I suppose for myself, it's also a great way of showing that
despite what challenges have been thrown my way,
I have seen the other side of it.
So yeah, it's all, I suppose, how you approach the situation.
You're the middle of thresholds.
Three girls in the family.
And you mentioned your beautiful mother who raised the three of you as a single mum.
Tell us about the family support for you.
And clearly you had unique challenges along the way.
How did they, did they treat you differently?
Did they make allowances?
What was it like in your household?
Yeah, definitely to me, family is everything.
I would not be who I am or where I am without them.
And for as long as I can remember, it's just been us four girls.
And my mum really is the rock of our family.
And the glue that holds us all together.
And yeah, from a very young age, I suppose she really instilled in all of us girls
that we can do whatever we want and conceive whatever we want to achieve.
And she worked tirelessly three jobs in order to make sure
that we had access to every opportunity possible like everyone else, no matter what.
So I suppose for myself, I tried to just do everything that my sisters were doing.
And mum thought it was really important to throw us into all the different sports
and activities.
To make sure that, you know, we were doing something, keeping active and being able to
find something that we were interested in and find our passion.
And for me, that was really important.
So it felt like I belonged somewhere.
So I tried everything my sisters did.
I did karate, athletics, dancing.
I quickly realised that me and land sports don't really get along well with the balance
and everything.
So it wasn't until I found swimming that I really found, you know, felt like I found
my purpose and something that I could do.
Easily, easily enough compared to everyone else as well.
And yeah, I just felt free.
I could move easier than I could on land.
And it kind of all started from there.
And mum and my sisters were able to support me all along the way and, you know, never
told me different.
You know, if I was having a bad day saying, you know, oh, I'm really sore, really tired.
You know, they were the first ones to be my cheerleaders and pick me back up and say,
give it another go and try again.
And yeah.
Yeah.
I want to go back and touch.
You mentioned the word resilience and I often think, you know, people like me and others
will be listening that, you know, we have our bad moments and our down moments and we're
all striving.
I think if you wanted to instill something in your kids, I've got four of them, resilience
would be the word.
I mean, how do you build better resilience?
No one's better placed than you, I think, to understand that.
How does it work in your mind?
Yeah, absolutely.
As you mentioned, it's so important.
And I think it really...
It has to start from a young age.
It can be worked on at any age, really.
But I think, suppose that possibly anyone listening that does have kids, starting them
young is really important.
I think, you know, we're all going to face challenges in life, no matter what they may
be.
And I suppose what I've always learnt is trying to be creative in the situation.
And there is always another way, even when you can't see it at the time.
And I suppose for myself, if I can't see that other way around the roadblock, it's
asking someone else for help as well and not being afraid to reach out to find another
solution because there is always one there.
And I suppose, you know, instead of saying, why me?
Say, try me.
You know, it's all about changing that mindset and trying to, you know, remain as calm as
possible in the situation.
If you have to take some time out to just debrief and look at things a little bit differently,
ask those around you.
Take some time to yourself.
What's your favourite movie or your favourite show?
If that helps.
And yeah, it's all about just, it's really hard, I suppose, but it's, everything works
different for different people.
So it's just finding something that works for you, but just, yeah, not being able to
give up in those situations.
And if you do have kids and they're going through something like this or a friend or
a family member, it's just being able to support them in any way possible.
And I think that can really help you mentally feel a bit better to build that resilience.
And the more you do it, the stronger you're going to get.
Yeah, incredible words of wisdom from you, Lucky.
Instead of why me, try me.
I love that.
It just resonates.
And yeah, I'm sure for a lot of people, isn't it?
It's all perspective, isn't it?
The things that are enormous for one person aren't so big for another and, you know, we're
all facing adversity at some level, how we deal with it.
I think you have an incredible perspective on that.
I've got this theory, Lucky, that people who achieve great things in sport like you have
done and continue to do, have a bit of a sense that they're destined for it at some point
in time.
You said that you watched the London 2012 Paralympics and you might have turned to mum
and said, I'm going to be in Rio and I'm going to win gold.
Is that a true story?
Is that how it unfolded?
Yes, that definitely is.
I suppose for myself, growing up in a very small community and a very small place with
not a lot of people around, let alone people with disabilities, I never really saw other
people represented like myself and facing similar challenges.
So when the 2012 Paralympics came around.
So I was 13 and this was, I suppose, when I started watching TV and media was around
a little bit more.
And this was the first time I actually saw the Paralympics and people and athletes with
disabilities represented and doing phenomenal things.
And for myself there, that was such a pivotal moment because it showcased that people with
disabilities are more than just people with disabilities.
They can achieve anything they want.
You know?
They don't have to be an athlete or somebody else doing something extraordinary, but it
just shows the possibilities that are on offer and that really resonated with me to try and
do something.
And, you know, I saw the Australian athletes doing personal best times and winning medals
and yes, that story is absolutely true.
I saw the swimming and at that time that was my main focus on something that I was passionate
about.
So I turned to mum and I said, mum, I'm going to be competing at the next Paralympic Games.
I'm going to be competing at the next Paralympic Games.
I'm going to be competing at the next Paralympic Games in Rio in four years' time and I'm going
to win a gold medal.
And I think she was definitely thinking, wow, that's so ambitious.
Okay.
Don't know how you're going to do it.
But sure, you know, if you try hard enough, you'll get there.
Probably not really realising, but I was dead serious that this was going to be my goal.
So I worked at it and tried to, you know, figure out how I was going to make this possible.
So obviously I had to, you know, reach out to Paralympics Australia, became classified,
got in touch with swimming coaches.
And it all kind of started from there.
But I suppose for myself, I never really thought I was particularly talented and would actually
achieve this dream.
I think for myself, it was more the hard work and the determination, the resilience that
got me there.
We're seeing that trait, Lucky, with a lot of the people who have been fortunate enough
to interview on this podcast.
I caught up with John Aloisi recently, who scored the winning goal to get Australia into
the World Cup of Soccer and lucky enough that he's an old school friend.
And he told the story that he would turn to his wife.
Yeah.
And anyone around him that he was going to score the winning goal to get Australia into
the World Cup.
And the people were looking at him like, you're crazy, you know, and what people don't understand
were the setbacks and the hardships and not getting a game along the way.
But there was that inner belief that he was going to step up and do it.
And of course he did in legendary fashion.
And I look at you and I went back and watched your race.
You're on the starting blocks then.
So Rio 2016, it's a dream.
And then all of a sudden you're swimming against your idol.
You've followed Jess Long.
She's a Paralympic legend, a United States and a firm favourite.
And you just have the race of your life, a PB by five seconds.
You break the world record.
You win gold.
I mean, when you reflect on that, what are your thoughts now?
It's absolutely crazy thinking back to that moment, you know, it all kind of happened
so quickly.
But I suppose for myself heading into the games, not many other people probably had
expectations upon me as to what I could achieve.
And if I would get there.
And, you know, particularly win a gold medal per se, I'd been representing Australia now
for a couple of years in the lead up to this, but I hadn't really made my mark until 2016.
I changed coaches, worked the hardest I'd ever, you know, worked and trained in my life
while still trying to complete year 12.
And I did have this inner belief in me that I could achieve this goal.
I knew that I had put all the work in.
I knew that I had all the right support around me.
I had the faith.
I had the trust in my coach, my support team and my family.
And I just headed into that race, not suppose putting too much pressure on myself, but just
wanting to enjoy the moment.
And I knew that all the hard work was behind me.
So it was just about putting it all together and having fun.
And in a way still, though, I remember being on the blocks and telling myself, OK, lucky,
just breathe, go in, have fun.
After the first 50 meters, I remember thinking, lucky.
You didn't come all this way to come second.
So let's show them what you've got.
And every 100 meters was slightly, you know, edging a little bit further and further in front until, you know, I touched the wall, finished the race and seeing that number one next to my name and seeing that I had done a five second BB, I think for me was also the massive accomplishment.
And then realizing I had won and then broken the world record by 0.11 of a second was, I suppose, the cherry on top.
And, yeah, it was just such a such a relief and such a special moment to to show people that, you know, you can overcome anything and to prove all those people wrong that said I couldn't do it or I'll never get anywhere or never be anything.
And I think those that are really successful in life in whatever they choose to do, you know, have overcome adversity and have those people telling you you can't do this or you can't do that.
But it really does push us forward to strive to go more.
And.
To prove people wrong.
I think that's a big motivation for a lot of people and particularly me as well along my journey.
I encourage you, if you haven't seen that, go back and watch it.
You can check out Lucky's website.
Look up Lakeisha Patterson and you'll see it there.
And you look like someone who is born to swim.
I mean, you move so beautifully in the water and you describe the cerebral palsy effects, your left side and all the challenges.
It doesn't make sense when you watch you swim.
You think, God, you just.
Are so graceful in the water and you make it look.
Does it feel like when you're a water in the water that this really is what you're meant to do?
Yeah, definitely.
I think absolutely.
Since I started swimming as soon as I started, you know, initially for therapy, but I instantly knew that this was something that felt like home and could take me places.
So then when I watched, you know, the Paralympics, it kind of reinstilled that.
And for myself, it's just so freeing.
No matter.
No matter what it's, you know, you come home, you have a bad day or whatever.
You dive into the pool, you blow your bubbles and you just forget about everything else.
So for myself, it's not only, you know, physical therapy, it's mental therapy as well.
And I definitely notice, though, if there's days that I can't swim or I'm out for quite a period of time, I definitely notice it outside on the land.
My body is definitely a lot more stiff and and swimming by no means is easy for me.
It's taken a long time to get to this point.
And.
You know, a couple of days out of the water is like a year for me.
It takes a long time to get back into it and get into the rhythm.
But, yeah, I don't know.
It's just so freeing feeling when you when you can move through the water, you're at peace and it all just comes together.
Yeah.
Beautifully said.
You mentioned before about being inspired, seeing the London Olympics and watching people, you know, who had disabilities and thinking that could that could be me.
Dylan Alcott has just been named the Australian of the Year in recent times.
As someone who's a great ambassador yourself, how important is it to have someone like Dylan now as the as the Australian of the Year?
I think it's incredibly important and so exceptional and astonishing, you know, being able to have that representation out there and show others in the younger generation what is possible.
Because, you know, for a lot of us and particularly, you know, Dylan has mentioned it before growing up and the same for myself, if we're coming from small communities or even.
Larger communities, we're not always often represented in the media, on TV, social media, on, you know, in stories, movies in our communities.
So to be able to see ourselves represented on a large scale in a positive way is so important to show people not only people with disabilities, but showing everyone within our community what we can achieve.
And we are just like everyone else.
Yeah, we may be a little bit different, but that's what makes the world so incredible.
We're all unique if we're all the same.
I think it would be incredibly boring.
So it's absolutely fantastic.
And Dylan's really paving the way to show others, you know, what we're capable of and in the inclusion and diversity space is so important.
And, yeah, I encourage everyone, whether you have a disability or not, to, you know, reach out to those with a disability and see how you can talk to them, make their life a little bit easier.
And I think we can all learn a lot from each other.
It's such a great way.
It's such a great way to explain it, like, isn't it?
I mean, we've all got quirks and we are all different and we're all weird in some ways, isn't it?
When you break it all down, you think, you know, when you speak out loud about some of our traits and often we're scared to do that.
But really, as you said, that is the beauty, isn't it, of watching that diversity?
Do you feel like, you know, you're still young age, you know, you're in your early 20s, that it is a better place now that we're able to, A, have opportunities that weren't there perhaps 10, 15, 20 years ago?
Yeah.
Do you feel like we're moving forward or in your mind, hey, we've still got a long, long way to go here for people that have challenges like yours?
Yeah, absolutely.
I can tell myself, you know, being 23 now compared to on the Australian swim team, I feel like a veteran.
I feel like I've been there for quite a while.
But I do feel like particularly from when I first started swimming to, you know, where it is now, not only in the sport side of things, but worldwide and social media,
we are seeing a big improvement in diversity and inclusion and acceptance and representation.
However, we definitely do still have a long way to go.
But we are so thankful for those pioneers that started well before us to get us into this space.
And, you know, it's not just about the disability space as well, but, you know, race, gender, all of those, you know, minorities and groups.
We're really seeing the representation.
It matters now.
And we definitely still have a long way to go.
But I think it's great that we are able to have these role models and people that we can look up to now that are sharing and paving the way for us in the future.
And I hope that, you know, what I'm doing now is able to inspire other people to move in the right direction as well.
Yeah, it's great.
And as you said, going back to Dylan Alcott, he's an incredible person, a great person to meet and be around and, you know, a wonderful choice as Australian of the Year.
And hopefully that continues.
As you said, you mentioned social media.
I did want to touch on this with you.
Twenty-three years of age, it's in your sphere much more than it certainly was mine at the same age.
But you've also disgracefully and remarkably been on the receiving end, as probably everyone has, you know, of the nastiness of cyberbullying.
And tell us about that.
How have you dealt with that?
And I suppose to other young people, what's your advice?
Yeah, it's definitely tough, I suppose, in every situation.
You have pros and cons.
With the positives that come with social media, there are obviously definitely a lot of negatives as well.
And that does come with cyberbullying and a lot of more, a lot more people, sorry, you know, feel like they have the courage to say things to you online that they probably wouldn't say to your face in person because they can hide behind a keyboard and a different username and all of that.
And I have received quite a bit of cyberbullying, I suppose, when I started my swimming journey in the past.
A lot of negativity and nasty comments from, you know, different athletes, parents, people around the globe questioning my abilities and everything else.
It's quite difficult and challenging, I suppose, for myself going through that stage.
I was, you know, just an early teenager, you know, being thrust into the limelight, the international stage, and now all of these circumstances as well was really challenging it.
And it definitely hit me hard.
Initially, and I remember feeling worthless and getting really upset because I was like, you know, these people don't even know me.
They don't know what I go through and they, you know, what gives them the right to be able to say this about me.
But I'm really thankful that I have such an incredible support system around me, you know, with the swim team, my family, my coaches and that key network.
I was able to speak to sports psychologists.
And, um.
You know, family and friends that really helped me and reassured me and, you know, gave me the advice that really this is a small minority of people in the grand scheme of things that have this one opinion compared to everybody else that knows you and knows how hard you work.
So why are you letting it impact you and affect the way you feel?
And that was a real turning point for me to kind of push that aside and be like, you know what?
You're right.
I shouldn't let these people affect.
The way, you know, I'm living my life and the way I'm feeling when I have no idea who they are.
And, you know, we also have the beauty of being able to block people, delete comments and and things like that now, too.
So I suppose I would say to anyone else, you know, don't it's easier said than done, obviously, but try not to let it affect you.
If anything, it helps grow that motivation in me to to push harder and go faster and show them, I suppose, what they're missing out on by getting to know me.
Yeah, the the ability to compartmentalize that as you did and as you said, to lean on a support network, which is incredibly strong when you when you talk and read about your family and the team that you've got around you.
But as you said, it's it is difficult.
I see it in my own kids and the brilliance of how they can connect with it is incredible and how easily they communicate.
But, you know, at the same time, everyone knows each other's location, it seems.
And, you know, if you're if you're being invited somewhere.
It's like it's challenging, isn't it?
There's there's so many elements to it that are new and we're working our way through it.
It's it's been interesting.
So people like you and leaders that have found a way through it, it tells a great story.
And I wanted to talk to you about that.
We're really passionate about this new generation of leaders that we're talking to.
And I see you very much in that community of being humble and being self-aware and a self-improver and having a massive positive impact on others.
Do you see yourself as a leader?
I'd like to think.
So I think initially I probably didn't.
I was just sharing my story and being authentic to myself and showing others who I am and, you know, instilling that positive mindset and optimism, which is very much me.
But, yeah, now I think I definitely do.
And it's great to be told sometimes from younger swimmers or parents and families saying, hey, my daughter and my son or whoever looks up to you.
And, you know, your values and what you're instilling to them is really making a difference in their life.
And I think that is so humbling to me.
And it's really important because I just want to show who I am and show others that you don't have to be anyone else.
You just have to be your authentic self.
And I've definitely learned a lot.
I've done a lot of leadership courses and self-improvement.
And now I've been named as one of the para-athlete leaders on our swim team to, you know, carry our team towards the path.
To Paris and hopefully beyond that as well, which is really quite inciting.
But to myself, you know, you don't really need a title to be a leader.
Anyone can be a leader in their own way.
You know, we all have different strengths and tweaks and twerks that, you know, make us who we are.
And we all have something different and valuable to offer.
So it's being able to, you know, unite one another, speak to one another and learn a lot by listening.
And communicating to others.
So it is a really exciting space.
And I do hope that I can improve in the future.
I know I've got a lot to learn and a lot to share.
But it's exciting what can, you know, come.
Yeah.
And the characteristics we're talking about, someone who's achieved what you have at your age with the challenges but still have that thought about improving and getting better and sharing it with others.
They're the unique traits we think of great leadership.
And you've got all of that.
And I did want to flow from there now into these dimensions of leadership that we're really passionate about, the work that we're doing in this space.
And so please be expansive on this, Lucky.
There are questions without notice for you.
But we start with self-leadership.
We see leaders really are aware of their own sense of leadership for themselves.
What does that mean to you?
Yeah, absolutely.
I think it's so important.
And for myself, it's just improving me and being the best person I can, really.
First and foremost, I'm a person.
And I want to improve on that.
It's not always just the athlete side of things.
And I've always been drawn to bettering myself.
And I know not really in the sense of chasing perfection because I don't think perfection is really attainable.
Nobody is ever going to be perfect.
And that's 100% fine.
But, you know, learning more about yourself and how you operate and the way you do things and how you can also better interact with other people and by engaging them and listening.
And actively listening is also really important.
And, you know, taking time out for yourself and discovering hobbies and what you enjoy, I think, is really important.
Because if you don't look after yourself, you can't properly look after someone else or engage with them in a better way.
So I do a lot of reading, you know, autobiographies and self-improvement books, podcasts, all that kind of thing.
I love reading.
Learning and listening to other people's stories as well.
It's just so incredible because we've all come from different walks of life and doing things differently and achieving things differently as well.
So it's pretty incredible to see.
Yeah, you're speaking the language of a lot of leaders that I have spoken to on this podcast.
And a lot of the coaches are really now so much more about seeing their players as the whole person.
And if they support them as whole people, they naturally get better.
They get better results as athletes.
And, you know, it's very interesting that you see yourself in that way.
I'm not surprised, given who you are and what you've achieved.
The idea that leaders really consciously think about how they positively impact others in their environment.
Clearly, you have done that, continue to do it.
Is that something you think of, how you impact others?
Yeah, definitely.
And I think that's the world we live in today as well, particularly with social media.
You know, I personally think about, okay, what I'm putting out there, how it's going to affect me.
How it's going to affect other people.
I would never intentionally want to put something out there that's going to be, you know, offend people or, you know, those kind of things.
So for myself, I'm a very optimistic person most of the time.
I am human, though.
I have bad days.
Everyone does.
But, yeah, they're the messages I like to share as well as, you know, sometimes if also showing on social media, not just the highlights, because as I mentioned, not everything is going to be perfect.
And showing people that it is okay to be vulnerable.
It is okay to go through challenges and circumstances and not feel great all the time.
It's okay to not be okay and to, you know, but in those situations, you don't have to give up and give in.
There's support around you.
And so it's important for me to show both sides of that and to show people, you know, what they can do and leaning in on everyone else and just being, you know, authentic to yourself and being able to.
Represent that as much as I can.
We see leaders really conscious of how they create and share their vision.
And you shared a little bit of your vision as a 13-year-old on the couch with mum watching the Paralympics and really going after that.
How have you gone about doing that in terms of creating and sharing a vision?
Again, I think this is something that is different for everybody.
For myself, I'm a very big goal person.
I love setting goals.
And doing all of that.
And you can do that in multiple different ways.
If you're a visual person, you can write them down, create a vision board, little things like that.
Myself being technology savvy, because I have to be, that's the way I do it.
But also, you know, I'll write down or type up in my case, you know, my big goals, midterm goals and small goals.
And then break that down.
And then break that down even further into how I'm going to achieve them.
So the small steps along the way in order to get to that major goal.
But along the way, I suppose it can seem quite, you know, lofty.
I think a lot of people will have this big dream or big vision and no idea how to get there.
Or it could be a three-year goal and you have no idea how you're going to go in that time.
It's a long time to be working towards something.
So I think it's really important to set.
Celebrate those small goals and the small wins and victories along the way.
And you can tick them off your list.
And it's that sense of gratification along the journey that what you're doing is worth it.
And it's not all for nothing.
And you can see that you are actually working towards that goal.
And you are getting there.
You are making progress.
And I know for me, sometimes, say, I'm swimming.
I'm doing a session.
I'm incredibly sore.
I'm tired.
I'm not mentally feeling it.
And, you know, you're thinking, is this all worth it?
Like, what am I doing?
I'm pushing myself beyond breaking point.
For what?
So when it does get to those days, I go back to thinking about those small things.
I'm like, okay, instead of thinking about, you know, my time, I'll think about my execution.
Am I doing my turns properly?
I'll just focus on one thing at a time.
And it really does help you get to the big goals in the end.
So it's, yeah, just breaking things up and focusing on the small things and celebrating those victories whenever you can.
Yeah.
It's a common theme hearing, Lucky, the ability and the need to celebrate those little wins along the way.
It's a great trade.
And it was uncommon in the past.
It didn't seem as though that was encouraged unless you won a gold medal.
But that may never happen.
In your case, it's happened, you know, on a few occasions.
But for those that don't, if you're not really celebrating, perhaps it's harder to get there.
So it's great of you to share that.
The idea of curiosity, you just mentioned you love a reading, you love a learning.
I can hear that very much in the person that you are.
Yeah.
We see leaders really using curiosity as their way to learn and improve.
Does that resonate with you?
Yeah, absolutely.
And like you said, it's definitely something you do see in a lot of people, a lot of leaders.
They do have these common traits and characteristics and that ability and that need and that desire to become better and to learn more.
And as, you know, I've alluded to a little bit earlier, we obviously all do things differently.
But curiosity is really important.
And I think it's something that should be instilled in a lot of us from a very young age.
And I think that comes with being exposed to different things and different opportunities and trying your hand at everything.
Because unless you try all these different things, you never know what you're going to be interested in or what it could lead to.
Instead of just being, you know, shoved in one path, you have all these opportunities and possibilities that you're able to explore and being able to continuously work on that.
And try different things.
And try different things is going to help you get to where you want to go or places you never even dreamed you could go.
I'm really big on that at the moment, Lucky.
And I love the way you express that.
And I might have referenced in the podcast recently just a book that I read called Reigned.
The author, I think, is David Epstein off the top of my head.
And he talks exactly like you said, that people who really end up with this great creative life sample lots of different things.
And in the past, it might have looked like failure where, you know, as you said, I tried karate.
It wasn't for me.
I tried dancing.
But they really, you know, in the end, helped form what your passion was and not to be afraid of just continually trying to have range and collaborate with extensive people.
And it sounds like you do that regularly and you do that well.
Does that make sense?
Has that sort of helped you all those experiences along the way?
Yeah, absolutely.
And I suppose, as you just mentioned, a lot of people may think, you know, trying different things or it's not working out or failure means the end of it.
But I think really failure is just a step towards that success.
Everybody fails in life.
Even now in my swimming career, I don't always win.
Things don't always go my way.
You know, you're going to fail.
It's inevitable.
But really, it's how you pick yourself up after those failures that lead to those successes.
And failure is just a turning point and showing you, OK, this didn't work out.
Let's go back to the drawing board and see how I can make it better.
So being able to kind of.
Get over that fear of failure is going to essentially help you grow as well.
And so important when trying out different things.
Yeah.
And again, I'm thinking of the great coaches we've been lucky enough to speak to.
And they are just so big on making mistakes and taking risks and supporting, encouraging that more than ever.
And for the junior coaches listening and for the people that are mentoring young people, you just got to back people in and encourage them to make mistakes.
It's how you learn and coach through that lens.
I think you've got that so right.
But communicating with clarity is a dimension we're seeing as a really common trait of leaders like you.
You're an incredible speaker.
I've been listening to a lot of your talks in preparation for this.
If you want to book Lucky as a guest speaker, I encourage you to do that.
Check out her website.
She's incredibly articulate.
Is that something that you've worked on, your communication?
Yeah, absolutely.
And it's something that definitely hasn't come easy.
But I suppose from a very young age, my mum, as again, as I alluded to earlier,
really gave us the opportunity to do everything we could.
And for myself, having cerebral palsy, speaking hasn't always been something that has been very easy.
I struggle here and again, every now and again, you know, with my brain being impacted, obviously, neurologically.
It's not always easy.
So it's something that I wanted to work on to be able to give me the best opportunity at life and to be able to share my story is incredible.
And so, you know, from a very young age.
Mum got myself and my sisters involved in like gavel club and public speaking.
I'm just really putting us out there to try and do different things.
And I was vice captain in primary school.
And then obviously growing up through the swimming world, I was kind of thrust into that, that limelight very early on.
And I had to just learn how to adapt.
And I'm definitely not an extroverted person by any means.
So it's not always easy communicating to people.
But I do love it.
And I definitely learn a lot.
And that's something that I've really been passionate about growing and learning more so that I am able to communicate better and more effective with people.
And it's crazy.
Now I am studying a communication and digital media degree.
So it's really exciting.
And just being able to, again, work on, you know, weaknesses, develop them into your strengths and find where you go from there.
It's pretty incredible.
And I've been able to meet extraordinary people all over the world to be exceptional things.
And I'm definitely still learning and growing.
But, yeah, it is definitely something that's really important to me.
Yeah, she sounds like an incredible champion, your mum, in every sense, every time you mention her impact on you.
It's profound.
Collaboration is something that we're seeing regularly.
Leaders really valuing it.
And, you know, reading about you, you've had such a strong team.
And I haven't done this too much on the podcast, but I feel like I want to mention your sponsors as well because it looks like you've had some good support in that area as well.
I'm not sure.
Is it Funke?
It's a swimwear, true protein and pain pod.
So I do want to mention that because we need support of athletes.
It's a hard thing for a lot of athletes to find that support.
And you've also given back extensively in the community as well as a number of charities that you've supported.
How important has that collaboration been for you?
It's so important and so vital.
And I would not be where I am today without the support of, you know, my team around me.
I think it is incredibly important and vital to everyone.
That they have a network around them.
You know, it definitely does take a village to, well, it's taken a village to raise me and to get me along this journey that I'm on.
And it's not always easy, I suppose, being an athlete and to get sponsors and people that are willing to invest in you and help you out throughout your journey.
And I am very fortunate to have had incredible people around me.
And I want to make sure that the people that I work with align with my values.
And I want to make sure that the people that I work with align with theirs so that we can get the most out of, you know, the collaboration and the partnership.
And I can give back as much as they've been able to help me.
It's really special.
And I suppose, you know, from my family, my friends, my teammates, my squad to, you know, my sponsors supporting me with my recovery, my training,
where all the little things like that is able to help me grow and achieve the best that I can.
And, you know, also sharing what they do and the different organisations and how they can help different people in different areas is all really just networking as well.
And being able to get into that space and, you know, this could help someone else, this could help you.
And it's really made an impact in my life and I hope it can to others.
Final couple of questions.
Lucky we've been asking all the leaders that I've been lucky enough to speak to.
Lucky, keep saying that the luck's coming up everywhere talking to you.
Who has been the greatest leader in your life?
Oh, that's a tough question.
But I suppose probably as cliche as it is, it's definitely been my mum.
I know I've mentioned her a lot, but she really is such an incredible person.
And like I alluded to a little bit earlier, you know, you don't need a specific title to be a leader.
You don't have to be, you know, the prime minister, the CEO of a company.
You don't have to be a manager.
It can be those little people in your life that can make a huge difference.
And my mum has been a massive impact in my life.
And I can hands down say I would not be here without her in my life.
She's instilled all these remarkable traits in myself.
You know, the strength, determination, resilience, perseverance, going after what you want, not being afraid to fail, giving everything a go.
I've learned all of this from her and more.
And as well as, you know, a mix of what she's taught me and everyone else I've been able to encounter along my journey, be that coaches, other athletes and friends, people from different organizations and businesses I've been able to meet with and speak with have really shaped me into the person I am today.
And, yeah, it's really exciting to see the impact that they've had on my life.
And hopefully I can give that back to them and then to the community.
And hopefully.
And hopefully to other people.
Yeah, and hopefully mum listens to this.
And I'm sure, you know, you've said that to her, but that will be the reward, isn't it, as a parent to understand the impact that she's had, you know, I'm sure on you and your sisters and everyone around her is, you know, another incredible story.
And not told often enough, Lucky, the family legends like your mum.
It's great to hear you mention her the way that you do.
In the spirit of collaboration, we love it in our world.
We see great collaboration as a real strength.
Collaborate with anyone in the world, Lucky, on any plane, whether it's your sporting life or any other aspect of your life.
Is there someone that jumps out?
Oh, my gosh.
Throwing me in the deep end here.
That's a very tough question.
There's so many people I would love to meet and talk to in the world.
I couldn't narrow it down.
Like, there's so many different aspects of my life that have, you know, made me the person I am.
Being the athlete space, the personal development space, and person space.
Oh, I don't know.
I'll put you on the spot here, Lucky.
Can I give you some inspiration?
I've had people say, Lindsay Boyd is a great author and leadership coach in the UK.
She said, Elon Musk.
I want to collaborate with Elon Musk.
I had Luke Beveridge, who's the coach of the board, who said he wanted to collaborate with Peter Garrett,
who is starting to really reflect.
on the First Nations people and their influence.
So, we've had this rain.
It is a hard question.
I put everyone on the spot with that.
So, it could be anywhere in your life.
I'm buying you a bit of think time here.
Lucky, is there anyone now with a bit of time?
No, I can't think.
There's so many names coming to mind, but then I don't want to just, you know, choose one.
That's not who I am.
I'm sorry.
It's not quite the answer you're looking for.
That's good enough in itself.
I think there's so many aspects to you that you can't narrow it down.
It is a hard thing.
I'm not sure what my answer would be either.
So, it's easy when you ask the questions and you don't have to think about them yourself.
But, yeah, we might follow up with that.
I'll see if I can add it on when we hopefully catch up another time.
And I'd love to do it.
I've really been inspired meeting you.
Before we started, I said so many people got in touch with me and said,
if you will do it, you need to meet Lucky.
You need to hear Lakeisha Patterson's story.
It's an incredible one.
It feels like it's...
Clearly, just getting started and looking forward to seeing you in Paris
and leading the team there and everything else that's going on in your life.
It's a great inspiration, a great story of leadership.
And I'm really honoured that you were happy enough to speak with me.
Thanks so much.
It's been my pleasure and such an honour to be able to speak to you
and share my story a little bit more.
So, thank you so much for having me on.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me, Luke Darcy,
produced by Matt Dwyer, with audio production by Darcy Thompson.
To start your leadership journey,
I encourage you to go to elitacollective.com,
take our Empowering Leaders Indicator tool
and understand the impact you have on your environment.
Join us at Elita to learn, lead and collaborate.
Listener.