Hope you enjoy this conversation on the Empowering Leaders podcast with one of Australia's great
business success stories, Larry Kesselman. Larry was one of the co-founders of Dodo Internet back
in 2001. He is now the owner of the Australian National Basketball League, the NBL, among many
other successful business stories. In this conversation, we cover all the lessons Larry
learned along his journey from his humble beginnings growing up in the Ukraine to now
being known as one of Australia's greatest ever success stories. Fascinating to me,
but you're going to hear Larry put a whole lot of his success down to luck, which I find still
hard to believe, but he also admits to having been skilled at seizing opportunities and happy
to take on difficult challenges that others aren't. And you'll also hear what an unbelievably
deep understanding of people he has and their needs and how he focuses on that with his business
stories. As we chat, Larry emphasises to him just how important it is to always
be learning, to maintain a positive attitude when the going gets tough, and how self-leadership
for Larry Kesselman all comes back to knowing what your purpose is. It's people like Larry
Kesselman who inspire the work we do at Alita. Head to alitacollective.com. In particular,
we'd love you to look at our Alita Connect signature program. We bring together a diverse
range of leaders, people like Larry Kesselman in groups of five or six to connect, to learn,
and to share. We feel like the world has had this crisis of connection,
and the idea of sharing great stories and seeing the positive ripples that go on from these groups
is something that's really inspiring to us. You don't have to be a billionaire like Larry Kesselman
to be part of Alita Connect. You can just simply book a discovery call. Head to alitacollective.com
today. Huge thanks as always to Jason Nicholas and his team from Temper Bedding Australia.
Great success stories, understand the importance of sleep. We spend a third of our life in bed,
and so investing in a mattress like no other, like Temper,
is a serious investment.
That will change your life for the better. Quality sleep is life-enhancing,
and Temper is simply the best in bedding. Larry Kesselman was born in Odessa on the Black Sea
in what is now Ukraine and arrived in Australia at the age of 12 in 1978 with his parents.
He studied business at TAFE, majoring in accounting, and then began work as an auditor.
His first life-changing decision was to start the Dodo telecommunications business with his cousin,
becoming a huge success before eventually selling it to Alita Connect.
In 2013, for close to $250 million. It seems as though Larry has the unique ability to turn
his attention to a diverse range of industries and passions with remarkable consistent success.
Property development, range of tech companies, private equity, extremely successful call center
business in the Philippines, but he's probably best known for his ownership of the National
Basketball League here in Australia, becoming the only individual in Australia to own a sports league
and one of very few around the world.
Larry,
it's great to see you. Thanks for taking the time today.
Great to be here.
Larry, it's a full life that you've lived from humble beginnings to what is an incredible
Australian business success story. What are the traits that you've found in yourself that you
think have helped you to have that success? First of all, I think I feel extraordinarily
lucky. I think if anyone says that it's all knowledge, it's all skill-based,
I don't agree with them. I think a lot has to do with luck. I think you absolutely have to
make the most of it, but I feel very lucky and very privileged. I first,
give the credit to my parents for actually bringing me here. I'm a super proud Australian
and just think I live in the luckiest country in the world and feel very privileged to be here.
You generally believe that luck plays a big part in our life. As we get into your story,
there's consistencies and success everywhere that your life seems to take it. That suggests
that you've got a formula that works for you, but you generally feel the luck is an important
part in life? I think you have to take your opportunities. I think it's certainly not all
luck, but I think there's an aspect of being in the right place in the right time, seeing
opportunities and making the most of it. But I do think luck has to play some component. It wasn't
my choice to come to Australia. I could have right now been in the middle of a war raging in Ukraine
with Russia. So I think definitely a component of luck is there. Larry, the telecommunications
business is notoriously competitive. I'm fascinated by this story. I think of James
Packer and Lachlan Murdoch.
They're forming OneTel, two of the biggest families in Australian business life, and they
nearly came unstuck, or certainly did around that time. And a young immigrant from the Ukraine
moves into the outer suburbs of Melbourne, takes on the big boys in telecommunications.
How did you make that a success?
Well, I think it's something that I've realized now looking back is in my DNA,
I almost don't like something if it's too easy or it seems too easy and everyone can take it on. I
love a bit of that battler and get in there and do something.
Something that needs to be done. And it doesn't matter if it's hard, because the way I look at it,
if it's not hard, then a lot of other people will do it. So I'll back myself to get in there and do
it. But I first need to believe that it needs to be done. And when I got into the, well, we say
telecommunication now, it was very clearly internet and even more so it was such early
stages of internet with dial-up. When I got into it, there were nearly a thousand internet
providers. It was such a confusing space that even myself, I couldn't understand half of
the plans and what people were offering. And you had really the us and them approach.
You had the big boys and then everyone else was really struggling. So I thought what I want to do
is I want to bring to Australia a really simple version of the internet with one plan. I remember
we literally came out with one plan, one offer. This is what it's about. And be the leader of
the opposition of the rest of the internet providers against the big boys.
And you did a great job. I mean, everyone will remember, Zoto,
was everywhere, I remember, at the time. And you got a presence bigger than perhaps
your scale at the time, potentially. How did you manage that?
Oh, I think it's the unfair advantage of being able to do crazy things. So the Telstra's of
the world could not do anywhere near what it is that I could do. So I knew I didn't have the
budget to out-market them. So I had to really try to use everything that I could use to my
advantage, starting with the name of the actual company.
I thought, you know, I'm going to go a little bit left field. And how much more left field can
you go than call an internet company after an extinct bird that couldn't fly? And the slogan
I came up with was internet that flies. So yeah, I had to use every trick in the book to make sure
that I got cut through. Yeah, amazing story. I mean, we often get told in life, Larry,
you find something you're good at, and then people often tell us, hey, stick to that, because
you're good at it. And you're good at it. And you're good at it. And you're good at it. And you're
fantastic as a fireman, but you branched out and tried to run a pizza store and your life
unraveled or whatever it may be. But you would have heard that along the way. Your life is the
opposite of that, it seems, that you can turn your attention to very diverse things and make
them successful. How have you done that? It may seem that way, but in actual fact,
a lot of the businesses have one continual string through them. And that is the love of people.
And I think they understand that. And I think they understand that. And I think they understand
of people. So if you have a look at most of the businesses I'm involved in, they're consumer-based.
So it's about people and consumers and delivering something that I think is needed in the place. And
I don't care. I've gone from, as I said, the cheapest internet provider in Australia by a
long way at the time, because I felt that was what the consumer needed, through to the most
luxurious building in Australia, in Capital Grand in Satyara. So I don't care actually at what level,
but I feel like my love of people and understanding of people and wanting to
deliver something for people, whether it's internally people that work with me or people
that are my family, through to consumers, I really have a passion for that.
And that seems a great credit to you, Larry. And you're doing some homework for this
preparation. It seems as though some of the young 20-year-olds that started at Dodo with you
are now still part of the family and they stay with you for a long period of time,
which is a great indication that it's a good place to work. Does that fill you with,
what? Yeah, it does. And we joke about it,
but it's actually true. I think the family or the tribe that I have, it's one of two things.
You're either in and you're out in the first few months because you look around and go,
these people are just crazy. I just can't work with these people. They're nuts. Or the other
way around, they just stick around. They go, okay, this is my home and this is my tribe. And I think
I like the crazy. So it's one or the other. So yeah, we had a first, I remember, first five,
six people that I invited. And I think it's a great thing to do. And I think it's a great
that actually understood the internet, which I will own up to the fact that I was not enough of
an expert in. A couple of them are still in my world. One in particular is now 42 with a couple
of kids and running the offshore Philippines business and my partner in it. So more than
just proud, I'm just ecstatic because that's actually one of the most important things. And
so many examples of that in my world. Delving into that a little bit more,
you said there's a pattern there. It's around product,
and people, and consumables. But there's so much detail in running a call center offshore to
opening a hatted restaurant in your building in South Yarra. And people go, God, the restaurant
trade's got a whole heap of hand grenades that can appear pretty quickly. And then property
development. And well, so there are these trap doors that you can fall into. How have you avoided
that in the spaces are different though, aren't they? How have you been able to overcome the
challenges?
Yeah. So first of all, I don't want to give myself too much credit. I've tripped myself
up plenty of times and I've certainly got a lot of things wrong, but I'm a survivor. So
first of all, I think you have to have the resilience and the calmness to survive and
find a way forward. So I always say, if you haven't made mistakes, you haven't tried hard
enough. So I've made plenty of those. But I think what I do is I do always start from
belief. Is there a need? I think a lot of people get into businesses because they feel that's
something that we just love to do or it resonates with them. They love that space, but they
sometimes forget to check at the door. Does anyone except themselves actually need this or are they
truly onto something? So I usually start with a need and I need to believe that I'm fulfilling a
need. So what is the problem that I'm fixing? Is there a problem? And then I'm the right guy. I
don't care how hard it is. In actual fact, the harder it is, the more I enjoy it. So I'm not
sure what that's about. That's probably something I need to go away and explore. But I do love a
great challenge.
And I have a tribe of people around me who are just as crazy as I am and they believe in me and
we're together going, let's call it solve that problem. So when I got into the internet business,
I felt like I was really solving a very, very difficult, challenging problem. And it was. And
it was super hard. We could have failed over and over on a number of occasions, but we took it on
because it had to be done. And the same with basketball, the same with capital grant. I always
feel like we're in a little bit of a mission to solve a problem for others, not a problem that I
need solved necessarily. It's not so much about me, but if the consumer and the people we feel
need it, then we're heading in the right direction.
I want to come back and ask you about the taking on the impossible challenge in a moment, but pick
on what you said before. And I think this is important is that people listen to a podcast
like this, Larry, and they see the highlight reel that I read out at the start, success after
success. And it sounds impossible when people,
find that very hard to live up to. But you said, there's more than your fair share of
times you've fallen over yourself. Can you share a moment where it went horribly wrong or
a fail that you look back and think, God, that was one that went sideways?
Oh, there's a number. There's a number. But before I do that, I just want to say, I think
I embrace that. I embrace that now. At that time, it was super scary, but I embrace that now. I'm
okay with coming up against challenges and bits of the week. I'm okay with coming up against
what we get wrong. I have no problem with it. So I look back now and I go, one of probably the
hardest and the biggest things I had to overcome is when we go back to the dodo days, I'd say,
I'll tell you two. So one was we got into the internet business early and it was like the
wild west. So every day there was something new and building something totally different,
this small startup going up against the Telstras of the world. So it was a scary, scary time and
not understanding. And the industry was,
evolving so quickly. So I thought I was getting into the internet business when in actual fact,
I got into really a customer service business and providing services and billing. So we started a
call center. Success on the signup of the clients was great because I think we got the offer right,
but providing the service, we were not experts. So I nearly killed that business by not
understanding how to operate call centers, the technology of it, how to provide the right
customer service. So we grew to nearly 600 people in Moorabbin in a call center.
Operating on semi-domestic phones and, uh, and not, not having enough reports and management
and understanding it and nearly killed my business. So all servicing data at the time,
all servicing data at the time. And, uh, the growth was extraordinary. So we were doing the
right things on providing the service, but behind the scenes, we couldn't keep up with the, with the
demand and couldn't keep up with the customer service side of it. So I nearly killed my business
on the back of that and had to quickly hop on the plane and realized I'm not going to scale it
enough in Australia. So went to India, Australia, Australia, Australia, Australia, Australia, Australia,
went to the Philippines and had to start the call center, uh, in the Philippines, uh, from
literally person one. And it was a race to how quickly can I set that up versus, uh, do I kill
my business here whilst I'm setting it up? So it was a real race. What's going to happen first?
Uh, am I going to be able to provide the customer service quickly enough before the business
literally blows up? So, uh, it was, it was a race to who can do that first. And luckily we,
in the end succeeded and managed to set up a great operation that now looks after a lot of
other companies and provide services out of that experience to them, uh, out of the Philippines.
So huge learning, but that was a survival moment. I mean, how do you do it? I'm not an expert. So I
had to learn really quickly. So, um, that, that taught me, I think, along the journey of how to
become a quick learner as well. You ask enough questions, you find the right people. Uh, I don't
ever go in with an arrogant approach of, yeah, I've got this.
I'm actually always absolutely shit scared, I think is the, is the right word. So, uh, I always
just try to find the right people that I can quickly learn from. And that, um, um, I think
breeds that level of right fear where you don't have the arrogance. And, uh, that's one trait that
I cannot stand in people and hope, uh, no one around me ever feels that way where I ask a lot
of questions and try to be a learner. So that's one. And the other one, just delve into that area
that cutting you off. I'm fascinated. You're a race against time.
Your business is going to blow up if you keep the call center in Moorabbin by the sounds of it,
but you land in the Philippines and it's one language barrier. I mean, that's a big task,
isn't it? You know, the pressure on that must've been enormous. I mean, in a little bit of detail,
how did you get that right? So first of all, I love those scenarios. I really do. I really do.
You sort of drop me into a place and you sink or swim and you go figure it out. And it all for me
goes back to people. So I quickly try to connect with people and figure out who's who in the zoo
and, and how do I actually, you know, how do I, you know, how do I, you know, how do I, you know,
how do I actually get this done? So I remember I connected with a couple of Aussies that had
already been there. So I quickly connected with them. They had a few people I learned from them.
I talked to them. I thought maybe I partner with them. That didn't work out quickly. Then I ask a
lot of questions. Who are the best lawyers? Who are the best accountants buddy up with them?
It's about, I think, connecting with people for me. Yeah. Business is business, but I look for
the right humans and I'll look for my tribe there. Who are the people that are actually going to
care enough, not just on dollars and cents,
but to help me. So I quickly try to connect with people. And I found this amazing group of people
that taught me quickly, figure it out quickly and just work my butt off. I mean, you, you work,
I was working 18 hours a day just to set these things up and, uh, and find the right people.
And again, you make a lot of mistakes. You, that, that worked, that didn't, and just keep pivoting.
So I think that's the other really important thing. I don't lock myself into an exact path.
I know the direction I'm going, but I'm prepared to keep,
pivoting and, uh, until I get it right. Yeah. And I can see that, you know,
you sit down and you're, you're already firing questions at me and I can, that,
that curiosity comes out. I'll, I'll, uh, I'll ask you more about that in a moment's time.
Coming back to what you said as well before about taking on the impossible challenge and,
uh, what is now your home is a famous site here in Melbourne. Everyone who's come to the city
will know the corner of Chapel street and Turok road where your Capitol ground building sits.
And it was there for a long period of time, um, famously, and a lot of people failed on that site
from what I understand. And, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and,
and, you know, I remember the people saying, oh, that's Larry Kesselman. Good luck, you know,
making that work. I mean, have you got an idea of what's in you that says,
I will take that on when others can't. Yeah. So I think there were quite a lot
of people saying a bit more than, uh, Larry Kesselman staking that on. I think a lot of
people were cheering for me to fail because others had failed before me. So yeah, I think
four different developers had a crack at that site and, uh, and didn't manage to get her off
the ground. So I think, uh, I liken it to like wrestling.
Bear. Um, and I'm just one individual and that is the biggest development ever done
from a residential point of view in Australia. And it's now the most luxurious and,
and well-known one. So it was a, it was a real challenge. I'm not going to sit here and say
that was easy. It was not, it was, it was really hard. And, uh, when you take on such big projects,
there's also the aspect of time I had banking crisis. I ended up, uh, smacking right at the
end into COVID. So, and in the middle, when you're doing something so, so different, uh,
it was a challenge, but I'm super proud of what's, um, what's actually been created.
Amazing, uh, story and incredible location. I've got to ask you about the national basketball
league. Um, as I said in the intro is probably where people know you more than anywhere else.
Now, Larry, it was financially struggling. It was a sub tier sport in Australia without being,
uh, unfair. I think even, um, Andrew Gaze would see her and say that basketball wasn't in,
in a great space. Why turn your attention to,
to the NBO here in Australia when others again had failed?
Well, I think when you look at the consistent, so, you know, you go back and I'll take a step
back. So you think about it, the consistent part is, um, Dodo had to be done because the industry
was in a mess and all you could get were expensive plans. And I didn't think the consumers were being
served and, uh, it wasn't right. So I felt that it's something I can do. And once I believe I can
do it, um, I, I wrestle with myself to walk away. Uh, you've got the same, the same thing with
capital grand. I really felt that site needed something special for a particular group of
people to live in a particular way. Uh, I'd been lucky enough to travel the world and see it. Uh,
and the same with national basketball league. I had been part of it with my family prior with
a club, with the Melbourne tigers. Um, we were just supporters first, then we were sponsors.
Then we were sort of part owners and not because I ever grew up as a kid dreaming to be a club
owner. That was never my DNA. I'm an immigrant and a survivor. And,
and I don't even dare to dream of these things. If I can, if I can make ends meet and, uh, and be
a success and provide for my family, that was, that was the early aspirations. I didn't grow
up dreaming to own a club. Uh, owning the club came out of that club going broke and my family
and, uh, and in particular, my mother, uh, telling me, Larry, you're, you're this business guy and
you run businesses. Surely you can fix this club. Where are we going to go on the weekend? What are
we going to do? What are all the families going to go to? You cannot let this thing fail. Um,
and the same story again, I'm like, yeah, I think I can, I think I can fix it. And I came at,
at it from a point of, I need to build a sustainable business. 15 clubs had come and
gone in Melbourne prior to the Melbourne tigers being the last 15, 15 different brands, 15
different versions of teams had come and gone in Melbourne and Melbourne tigers was the last one
standing. So I thought, you know what? I think I can do it. And there's always, it was a hell of
a lot harder than I ever thought and learning and understanding the business of sustainable
sport and how to actually build, uh, what consumer needs. And it came again from the
same angle. Forget what I like. What do the consumers expect and want from a basketball
club? What are we in the business of? And understanding that and realizing that it's
like myself and my family, I was not a huge basketball nut. I didn't play basketball,
but I loved the family aspect. I loved the entertainment. I loved what it brought to my
family. And that's where I started rebuilding the club. And we first rebuilt the club until
last year. And that's where I started rebuilding the club. And we first rebuilt the club until
the league went, um, broke. I was about to go broke as well. And I came at it from the same
point of view. I couldn't walk away. And I truly believe that I can create something amazing
out of it. Why? Because the consumers wanted it. Yeah. 1.2 million registered people playing the
game. There's probably 2 million people actually playing the game. I can take zero credit for that.
That was there before me. So all I had to do was build a product that those people can be proud of
and follow and actually be in the game. And that's where I started rebuilding the club.
And what it does for them and their families. So, uh, I knew I had to do my part, but this sport
is a, is an amazing family product and that's why I'm involved in it. Yeah. And I've been along
recently. I was telling you before we started and as someone that hadn't been for 15 years because
of, uh, you know, I love all sport, but it was, uh, you know, underwhelmed, I suppose a bit like
a lot of people in Australia came back and it's, that's fun. That's entertaining. You've, um,
you've done the things that you see, you can tangibly see it and you, you sit there and,
um, well, you love basketball. You've done the things that you see, you can tangibly see it.
It's a good night out. It's a great night with the family, took the kids along.
Uh, and it's brilliant. And there's a lot of reasons why that shouldn't succeed, isn't it?
Because a lot of the kids now have access to the NBA and they see the American sport. And there's
always this theory, Larry, that if you're not, you know, having the top of your game, like soccer
struggled here in Australia for that reason, how have you overcome that? Can you give us some
examples around how you've made this product as inspiring as it seems to be now? So I think what
you said is spot on. I think, uh, consumers are tough judges.
And now the world is such an accessible place. So we had to actually look at ourselves and go,
well, we need to be good enough. And that was the aspiration. I'm going to say, honestly,
when I took over, that wasn't the case. And the NBL became just a little bit irrelevant because
you could see the NBA and the gap was so large. So for us, a big part of it was to create our
own version of the product, uh, and not actually just be something that is exactly like NBA or
exactly like EuroLeague.
To have our version of what the sport looks like. And I think that's what we've created. We've
created a product that is truly Australian. Uh, it is something that we can all be proud of. And I
think it is actually the best version of a day out for a family of entertainment. In my opinion,
it's better than the NBA. So when you go to an NBA game, I think what you see on the court is
extraordinary, uh, as a product of entertainment overall for the family, I think NBL is better.
So, uh, on the court, we're now the second best league in the world, without a doubt,
everyone accepts now as a domestic league. NBL is the second best product in the world. We have
25 players that have played in the NBL and have gone onto the NBA. We've got players that finished
playing here and go three days later onto the court in the NBA. So, uh, NBA is the North star
and it is by far the best league in the world without a doubt, without a shadow of a doubt.
But NBL is the second best on the court. But I think as a product, when people go along as a
family, mom, dad, couple of kids, uh, multicultural,
boys, girls, uh, it is just an extraordinary product that I think the Australians are now
completely embracing, loving. Uh, we're breaking all records. Like this season has started with
us breaking all records for attendance. Uh, viewership is 40% up. So Australians are
embracing it. Why? Because that's what they want, not what I want. That's what they wanted
as a product. And, um, they're showing that we're right.
It's a great story. Again, another one of the success stories you've been involved in people
listening to this.
Larry that have got an entrepreneurial spirit, like clearly you have, what's your advice to
someone who's maybe started and struggling or thinking about going down the entrepreneur path?
I think get over yourself. Uh, I think, uh, we're all very, very, um, smart people that get involved
in business and we think we're amazing. And I think get out of your own way and get out of your
own story in your own head and check in and make sure that you're actually doing it for others.
And when I say doing it for others, number one, make sure that you actually
are doing it for yourself. And then number two, make sure that you're actually doing it for the
people that you're talking to. And that's, that's the, that's the, that's the, that's the, that's the
thing that I think is really important.
Uh, and is it something that's going to resonate with them? Uh, not just because it's you. I don't
like the words niche. Niche is very dangerous. Um, if you're getting into a business that you
are going after consumers, make sure that it's actually something wide enough. Does your business
model work? Uh, do you have the right people around you that are actually going to help you
make it happen? Uh, if not, make sure you go and get them. Do you understand it? Are you a keen
learner so i think number one thing is just get over yourself um don't think about what you want
and what it is that you're trying to achieve for yourself and think much more about others
starting with your consumer what does your consumer want sound advice there isn't it because
you're right often people get it in reverse don't they it's good i've found this thing that i love
and i'm going to force through a product where maybe there isn't an audience for it and you know
we hear the stats on small business so often about failure in your view is that what really
brings people unstuck all the time is that they are maybe not solving a problem that needed to
be solved is it as simple as that at times i think it's actually a lot more complicated than that i
think you there are lots and lots of factors and i'm very happy to talk about those as well but i
think you need to start at the start it's almost like if you do the wrong deal at the start and
let's say if i'm in property if i've overpaid for the land and i haven't got my model right
uh it's
very hard to then undo it so i think that's the starting point i think just making sure that it's
not about you that it's about the others about the consumer about the product that's actually
just the starting point but that is if you don't get that right i think you are really in for a
tough tough road all the way along there are a lot of other factors but if you get that one wrong i
think it's very very hard to undo there i'm always fascinated about this idea of what does success
actually mean and and and to me there's a whole range of elements on the
world of business and i think it's a very very hard to undo
of what makes a happy life and a successful life and financial success is one portion of the pie and
happy family life and health and connection to your kids and contribution to others in a positive
way makes up this sort of pie of what i think a happy and successful life looks like i mean you've
clearly had remarkable business success how do you balance out the other areas of your life to
to fill that cup for you i think it's a very complicated formula but ultimately i think a
very simple one i think that i think it's a very simple formula i think it's a very simple formula
i think it's a very simple formula i think it's a very simple formula i think it's a very simple formula
i start with my family i find if i'm not happy at home i think it's very hard to be just generally
happy so i think having the right balance and the right uh feeling around yourself with the closest
people and you just look at through the circles as you go further and further out so i think for
me it starts there uh that's number one priority and it does not mean that i do everything just
around family i certainly don't i think it's a balance of of everything but if you're not happy
at home and if you're not putting in the effort to make sure that your relationship
they are great that's a challenge for me uh but relationships and how i feel and checking in
with myself and being honest is is really important i'm a i'm someone that will go after things really
really hard but as i've got older and i'm not going to say i was always that way i think as i
got older i'm much better at being honest with myself and going what feels good what doesn't
what is my purpose why do i do what i do uh and being honest with myself the japanese term
is fascinating isn't it i've been uh reading a lot in uh in recent times a guy called dan buten has
done an extensive study on what he calls the blue zones around these communities around the globe
and there are a handful of them where people routinely live past 100 years of age in perfect
health and have uh some patterns around what that is and in japan that term around purpose
shows up in parts of uh of greece where they have these blue zone communities or
in sardinia and italy around the globe and there are a handful of them where people routinely live
around you know purpose for people is such a big thing around you know nutrition comes into
and community and family and connection but uh without that sense of purpose that's one of his
things that's a really to long have uh healthy and happy successful life the studies are showing that
that is a big factor isn't it is yeah absolutely i think for me the idea of purpose and understanding
why you're here why do you do what you do community is really really important so those
couple of things you mentioned really really resonate i love love
life i really i'm so passionate about it and so thankful you know you get another day to have
another crack at this uh and the most valuable commodity and sure enough for your younger
listeners they're gonna think that's just something older people say but the only thing
that we have of value is time so how i spend my time what do i do what is my purpose uh i think
it's a privilege to have another day um on this planet to have another crack at doing something so
i don't take that lightly and um you know i'm a positive person so i struggle around people that
whinge and carry on and uh and i'm like you know get out of your own head and have a look how lucky
you are and especially when a lot of friends struggle with health and other things you're like
no just get out there and have a crack i hate a victim mentality i'm like okay you know you're
in charge of your own life so if you want to blame others go for it but see how how well that serves
you yeah we love this term larry
success leaves clues and i was sharing with you a bit of the community uh in our space a leader
that's growing and the idea of connecting people around what great life looks like and and sharing
those learning opportunities and out of that we've seen a handful of dimensions of what we
think great leadership looks like larry in this pattern i want to ask you a few of those now
starting this idea larry we think it's hard to lead someone else unless you've got an idea of
your own self and and self-leadership what does that term mean to you when i talk about
self-leadership i think it's being able to
control your emotions uh it's being able to have your own conversations and being honest with
yourself i think if you're living a lie and you're not actually honest where you're at
that that is a problem you've got to start there i think if you stop being a keen learner
i think that's a problem how do i lead others and the longer i lead others the smarter they
are around me like the people that are coming into my world now are bloody smart people so
if i don't keep improving myself and keep learning
so i think that concept of the way the western world has decided that you get some sort of a
certificate after school and college you're done at studying is a very dangerous one so
i think for me as a as a leader i want people that are keen learners that are open to learning that
are self-critical uh that are positive but at the same time realize that you never stop learning and
it's a journey so my leadership style is to care about others and their
evolution and how can i help them so the older i get and i'm an operator by nature but the older
i get the less i'm actually running and operating businesses so more and more my job is uh strategy
and how do i actually set people up for success and mentor them and and help them and not just
their own business but actually just help them be the best version of themselves they'll need to do
what they need to do but my job is to help them find that happiness i think you have another
japanese term while you're talking larry kazan they talk about you know you know you know you're
a constant never-ending self-improvement being one of the goals in japanese life and it sounds
like that sums up you and how you go about it we see people who have success like you've had larry
are really conscious now about how they positively impact people on a daily basis you know you talked
about the pride of having the dodo 20 year olds now in their 40s and still part of your world
how have you gone about that on a daily basis having that positive impact on those around you
i think it's a mindset i think it's understanding
your purpose so i understand my purpose now is a big part of it is around uh influencing and
affecting people so i start again with family with you know my wife with my son with my mother
how do i impact their life in a positive way what can i bring to them what what is it that i can do
to support them and for them to feel loved and supported and uh and that i'm doing my job as a
as a husband as a father as a you know as a son and because it goes in cycles you know my
parents looked after me and so that constant understanding of what my purpose is um on this
planet how do i in a privileged position that i am and we talked about what what does uh financial
success bring well the big one for me is freedom i mean i i have the freedom to make decisions to
do certain things i didn't have the freedom i you know i joke around i grew up looking through that
entertainment book as to where the special is at the at the restaurants and where can i get
a discount and one of the big privileges is that i can get a discount and i can get a discount and
i have now i love is i don't worry about how much you know the main course is and uh and i have the
freedom to work my schedule and how do i actually make the most impact number one on people around
me but also uh i have a group of people that are passionate about giving back so every organization
that i lead and there's probably about 15 different meaningful businesses that i'm in a charitable
and csr aspect is a huge part of what's important to me that they do and each ceo does their own
thing my wife
uh has worked in that sector for you know most of her life so she helps us guide as a group
how do we give back what do we do we've started our own academy for underprivileged kids who are
uh who are looking for a way into the into workplace to make the right decisions called
larita academy so it's a balance and the longer we go about giving back and making it more about
others uh is really really important to me now you've had some big visions and you've been able
to execute on on those
we've spoken about them before but from big development projects to telecommunications
how have you gone about when you're creating one of those visions and sharing it with your team so
that they get it and understand it early on it was uh sitting them down and uh and explaining it now
they just just expected they're like okay what's the next crazy thing that larry's gonna you know
dream up and uh and and they all know now it's not it's not a surprise to them what new things
we're actually going to dream up what problem are we solving and what are we creating or
why we're doing this uh they almost don't question it anymore they they just want to understand and
get on the journey and they know my for example my favorite tv ad of all time uh is the steve jobs ad
when he came back to apple after being fired and and coming back and there's no product and the
company is struggling and uh his ad was something along the lines of you know here's to the crazy
ones because they're the ones that will change the world so i'm not for one second suggesting
that i'm the one that will change the world but uh i love that i'm not the one that will change the
because i know being a little crazy like myself i'll take on things that actually have a bit of a
meaning and uh and maybe that others wouldn't take on so in that is i think a key to our success
now we see curiosity is a common trait of of people that i have the privilege of sitting down
with like you today and through curiosity they're constantly learning like you described before does
that term resonate with you absolutely i love it you know i love i love learning sometimes really
random things through to um industries that i don't understand but i start with people i'm really
curious what makes people tick and and who they are and how but yeah i'm i get i really i'm really
interested in all sorts of uh industries i may never get involved in i'm really interested in
learning about uh the most ridiculous uh things you know i was googling the other day as to
spaces and uh how many teaspoons fit into a square pound what does that look like and uh
yeah really random things and i'm really curious what makes people tick and who they are and how
things that expand your mind and uh and you you learn more about the world that we live in and uh
communicating with clarity is another dimension that we we see really consistent around people who
get their message across have you thought a lot about how you communicate with your team and your
projects that you work on i don't necessarily sit and think about communication what i do think about
is uh how do i affect the people around me and i think it's when you talk about communication
it's everything it's body language it's it's it's it's it's it's it's it's it's it's it's it's it's
you know eye contact it's what what does that mean how do i want the people to feel uh in certain
situations i think is really really important so uh you start almost thinking as a as a father to
your son all right if i'm uh acting in a particular way what what example am i setting what outcome do
i want and i think that sort of continues on to me and i have learned that in the tougher the
situation the calmer i get because everyone is looking and they're looking for leadership and
they're looking for guidance and and if i'm panicking and if i look erratic and i'm rattled
then uh i don't think the people are going to be that comfortable to uh look at me as a leader i
think someone told me i think it's fact or maybe they just told me a great story that uh leader or
leader in french was something that was given to uh the flag bearer at the front of the army so he
was the leader and carrying the flag and and leading the army into into war and i think we
all know what happens when you're in a situation like that and i think it's really important to
that dude he's probably usually the one that's shot first but if he's prepared to take up that
mantle and he's at the front and if he's walking around looking around shaking and uh and he's not
confident not too many people are going to lead him into battle so uh in my version of it is be
brave and if you want to be a leader know what actually goes with that title comes with some
responsibility larry doesn't and i was sitting across from craig mccurry the coach at collingwood
just a couple of days ago in this same forum and
and he spoke about that privilege of leadership and and that same sense around when the pressure
is on that's your time to be calm you can't fake that can you is is that something that is in your
dna larry or have you been able to work on that so that when those situations come and it's you
know dodo's on the line here i'll either get this right or we're going under it's a learned trait i
can tell you uh i would panic when i was young uh but i have to say when i look back in certain
situations even at the young age i've been able to work on that and i've been able to work on that
at a younger age i did manage to control and stay calm uh i would not say you know in some i was
maybe a little too fiery and a little too passionate and uh but i was leading less people
but uh i think it's something you have to have in you but it is a learned trait as well as you
faced with more and more situations i think it's like anything you know when you were playing
footy you got a lot better at what your trait was as as you did it more and more and i think
the same thing here the longer you are as a leader and and the more you do of it the repetition and
and being in more and more tough situations i think you figure that out so i wouldn't be too
harsh if you're an up and coming and you're a bit younger in life in your leadership role and
you're starting out give yourself a break and and yeah sometimes uh it might get the better of you
but uh it's a it's a learning and as you go on the journey you'll you'll learn more and more
how to control your emotions larry who's been the greatest leader in your life
uh unfortunately up until now i have not had a lot of mentors outside of my family
i have to say the one consistently that i have looked at is my mother and my father and the way
they stayed and dealt with such crazy adversity of moving countries not speaking the language
career challenges and how they've done it with a positive attitude and a strong resolve and
and the love for this country and for their community and for each other i think was a great
model to follow there was certainly not business people it was not about business
but i think they set an example for me and to this day my mom is 88 years old and every day she
gets up and uh and has a crack and loves life she does not miss a basketball game she's still at
every basketball game that she can get to it's getting harder and harder for her but she's there
at every game and how she embraces and loves life i think is a great model for people and
that that's been terrific from a business point of view my thing has been that from an early age
no one could really care so there has not been a lot of advice given because why would anyone bother
so i've learned to learn from everyone whether it's good bad indifferent i literally learn from
every conversation and that's been a trait that i've taught myself and now i'm lucky enough i look
at a number of people as amazing leaders i have to say one that i absolutely love as a human and
whatever time he can spare i love hanging out with him as a gentleman by the name of jack cohen
from hungry jacks
he's becoming a little bit of a mentor in whatever time he can spare i love
having a chat with him and he's got that sort of a calm demeanor that i love and he's lived
a life and a half and i enjoy spending time with him larry in the spirit of collaboration thanks
for that that answer it's a it's a great response we are a bit obsessed with what a collaborative
world looks like um have you looked and thought is there someone on the planet that you thought
i'd love to collaborate with and your whole range of passions is there anyone that springs to mind
you thought that's the person i'd love to uh to be alongside of one of the biggest privileges i
have now and i talk to my family about it all the time i sometimes pinch myself with the type of
people that i'm actually exposed to now so you think where i was starting and no one could care
less and i you know had to work my way from the bottom and up and and when i get a chance to talk
to someone who's achieved that was a real privilege now i'm so lucky to talk to so many amazing
leaders and amazing people so i'm really happy to be able to talk to them and i'm really happy to
so i don't like to label any one person because i don't believe in perfect humans so i would love
to talk to a whole range of people on a rate on different range of topics so for example
richard branson who i've you know met very briefly but i'd love to sit down and talk to him about
how his mind works around brands but on the other hand i know he's got challenges with you know
certain aspects of running businesses and so he he's an extraordinary success and i'd love to
talk to him about particular aspects i'd love to talk to
you know bill clinton about certain aspects of of global politics as to how he tackled certain
aspects so i think there are so many leaders but i would almost make a list and go but i only want
a couple of hours on a very specific topic i don't want to learn everything because i don't
necessarily either agree with all of it but uh yeah i'm very much about taking certain aspects
from certain people i love the curiosity larry appreciate your time as you said time uh is the
most precious thing we've got i really appreciate you taking the time to share your story it's
inspiring i love the humility in it as well and the constant life uh learning thanks for uh for
joining me today i really appreciate it such a pleasure thank you for listening to the empowering
leaders podcast powered by temper a mattress like no other and to make sure you don't miss
an episode click subscribe wherever you get your podcasts