How do you navigate the world of a start-up business and how do you find a way to deal
with the challenge and adversity that inevitably comes your way?
G'day, it's Luke Darson.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership both on and off the field has been a lifelong
passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective and have had the privilege
of working with thousands of leaders in education, sport, industry and the arts that have helped
shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
I was joined by the CEO of Keep It Cleaner, author and wellness entrepreneur, Laura Henshaw,
to talk about how she uses past experience to fuel her desire to help others, the benefits
and dangers of social media and how her naivety exploring the business world was actually
a good thing.
Well, very excited to speak to our next guest.
And it is a success story of the highest order.
She's a law and business graduate and initially launched an e-book for good for you recipes
that inspired tens of thousands, moved to a range of healthy products stocked in supermarkets
nationally that are now a leading influence in the competitive fast-moving consumer goods
world.
Her app, Keep It Cleaner, has over 250,000 subscribers.
And when you combine her and her business partner and the business together, they reach
over 2 million people on Instagram.
Laura Henshaw.
I'm sure an incredible story, a great success story as a 28-year-old young CEO.
What a great pleasure to meet you, Laura.
Thanks for joining us.
Thank you so much for having me, Luke.
And thank you for the intro.
I have to say, though, I wish we had 250,000 subscribers.
That's been our total uses to date, but not just so many more.
Well, I'm happy to be fact-checked.
That's good, Laura.
I mean, you've changed the business story.
It's 250,000 people that are accessing what you do for a start is a great success story,
isn't it?
To create something.
It clearly sounds like a passion for you, isn't it?
The well-being and wellness space.
Yes, absolutely.
I feel very, very lucky to be working in a business where we get to.
And I mean, especially through COVID, giving people a way to be able to exercise from home
and move their bodies and have fun with it has been really special because I think for
a lot of us, being able to move has been kind of one of the only things that we can control
and that makes us feel really good.
And I mean, as you know, coming from a sporting background, the way that physical activity
helps you mentally and physically with your health, it's contagious.
Once you live a healthy lifestyle, you just want to share it with everyone and you want
everyone to do it as well.
So I feel very lucky that we're able to do that with Keep It Cleaner.
So many things to talk to you about, so many different directions to go.
But just picking up on what you said there, I think an interest to me has always been
that people understand the physical part of exercise and what that means to your health.
And I think people have worked out that you need to put something in to that part of your
life to get an outcome.
If you want to be healthier and you want to feel the way that you potentially want
to feel, but maybe people are now getting the link between doing something for your
mental health as well.
And I know that's a passion for you as well.
Laura, has that been always part of your routine as well, looking after your mental health?
Yeah, absolutely.
I mean, as I've gotten older, I am now looking after it more.
I suppose it used to be subconscious and now I'm consciously looking after it.
But for me, actually running is one of the biggest ways for me to look after my mental
health.
And I've tried meditation.
I'm very, something that we have in the app on Kiva Cleaner, I'm not very good at it, but
I do like guided meditations because then at least someone is talking to me the entire
time and I don't have to sit with my own thoughts.
But yeah, it's so important looking after our mental health.
I'm with you.
It's not for everyone, is it?
I found it at a young age, at the age of 18 or 19, and it just worked for me and probably
the discipline of playing sport for a living.
I do it twice daily, but I know for some people, and that sort of turned me here, I'm not good
at meditation, whereas for me.
It's not something you need to be good at necessarily.
I suppose it's just working out if it works.
And there is a broad family in it.
Have you tried other aspects of that space or have you just worked out there are other
things that you do outside of meditation?
I think one thing that one of our meditation experts on Kik, she always speaks to, her
name's Megan, and I'm sure you would relate to this, that if your mind wanders elsewhere,
it doesn't mean that you're doing it wrong.
I used to think that if I could not just repeat the three words in my head the entire time
that I can't do it.
And so that I think that's really, really important.
And with most things, even the same thing with yoga, I used to hate yoga because I'm
inflexible.
I played a lot of sport growing up, but I was always in the B team and I just, I really
liked running.
So, you know, I did all the hockey, soccer, all those sports where you had to run.
I never got near the ball, but I was always there for defense and for offense.
But because I'm so unco and inflexible, yoga was something for me that I was like, just
can't do it.
And then it's been through Kik, we film yoga.
So I've had to be in the B team.
And I've slowly learned to, you know, to actually use it as something that is really
meditative.
And it really, the only time I was able to do that is when I stopped caring about, you
know, being perfect in every pose and focusing on exactly what I was doing instead, focusing
on, on, you know, doing my best and how it felt.
So that's how I try to approach my mental health and yeah, yoga and meditation.
Doesn't matter if you're not perfect at it.
It's just good to give it a go.
Married to a yoga instructor.
I am Laura and I found it very intimidating.
I was doing yoga next to her because there's no way in a hundred years I can ever even
potentially do the things that you're doing.
And, and, uh, used to, you know, the competitive nature of playing footy for me, she's like,
it's not competitive.
And I said, well, for me it is, I need to get better.
But the at-home yoga has been a bit of a gift to me because going into a studio hasn't had
a lot of appeal, but when you do it on the screen, you can do it at home.
And I think in lockdown, have you found that lots of people are accessing the yoga that
you guys are supportive of?
Yeah, absolutely.
And we found that for the whole app.
We've actually got quite a few types of training on the app and that's because everyone likes
different things.
Everyone's, you know, balance looks different.
Some people like to do six really intense workouts a week.
Some people might like to just do three and they might prefer yoga or Pilates.
So we've got yoga, Pilates, strength, training, HIIT and boxing as well.
And what we found is, is the most special.
I mean, definitely through COVID, I think it's been one of the positives is that people
have maybe realized that they can get active at home and especially for time poor people
that, you know, they're not as active as they used to be.
They don't have time, you know, to drive to the gym and do a class and then come home.
They can use 20 minutes and do an at-home workout.
And also, I find it really helps people with their confidence as well.
And we find that speaking to members of our community, they, especially a lot of gyms
in the weights area, it's quite a male dominated area of the gym.
And so a lot of women find when they walk in there, they have no idea what to do.
They feel really uncomfortable and they just leave.
But with Kik, what we're able to do is really empower our users, you know, to learn how
to do all the exercises.
That they want to do and, you know, master their technique and build that confidence
at home.
So then when they go into the gym, they don't have to worry, like they don't care about
who's looking at them or who's in the space.
They just go and do their workout.
Yeah.
What a great opportunity that is, isn't it, out of the challenges of being locked down.
I want to speak to you a lot about Keep It Cleaner and the great work you're doing, but
perhaps wanted to jump to, you know, I mentioned 250,000 subscribers.
You said not quite yet, but 2 million Instagram combined with you and your business partner
and your combined audience for the business is an incredible reach.
I know you've spoken a lot.
Clearly, Instagram has been a positive, but it's also had its challenges for you.
What's your relationship like with it now?
Yeah.
So, I mean, it's really important for me to say without social media, there probably
would not be a Keep It Cleaner or there definitely wouldn't be.
When Steph and I started, Steph, my business partner, was very, one of the first on Instagram
to really grow a following.
And so we were able to use that.
We were able to market our business.
I think before social media, it was almost impossible to, you know, have no connections
and start a business with not really any money and, you know, get people to see it because
marketing was so expensive.
Of course, you know, for Steph and I starting out, there is no way we would have been able
to afford a page in a magazine or a TV set.
Absolutely not.
So, Instagram in that way really enabled us to reach people and grow organically.
But I think then again, I suppose another...
One of the biggest instigators for Keep It Cleaner was the pressure that social media
was putting on young women, especially on their bodies and how you should look.
It opened up a whole new world.
I know for me, I grew up in a really healthy family.
I did a lot of sport.
I had no idea what a diet was.
I ate healthily, but I didn't even think about what I ate.
I just ate to feel my body.
And then I started doing Instagram when I think I was about 19.
And the what was on there, there was every type of diet in the whole world.
And I was all of a sudden exposed to all of these things.
And it was so interesting because I studied biology in high school.
I understand that everyone's genetics are different.
If I follow exactly the same diet as you, Luke, I'm not going to look like you.
We'll have different bodies.
We have completely different genetic makeups.
But it's funny looking when you're vulnerable and you might be low on confidence and you
go on these platforms, especially as a young woman, you all of a sudden compare yourself
to everyone and you start thinking that you're not good enough.
And then it can be a really, really dangerous place for myself and Steph as well.
We both developed disordered eating behavior and really developed a very unhealthy relationship
with exercise and food.
So we also have done modeling.
And so that also has a really bad, there's a lot of pressure in the modeling industry
as well.
But for me, Instagram and social media was the main instigator kind of for changing my
relationship for the worst with food and exercise.
And so when we started to think about, you know, keep it cleaner, the most important
thing for us was that we were creating a safe place for people to come where they could
exercise and eat well, you know, for how it made them feel and not focus on all the transformations
and weight loss and all of those things.
Because obviously being healthy is extremely important, but I've lived a time now where
I was, you know, the skinniest I've ever been.
I was exercising two hours a day and I was eating a hundred percent.
I was eating fish and vegetables and I was mentally the unhealthiest.
So that's extremely unbalanced.
And so now Kik has kind of become this place for us where we want to make sure that any
person that comes into there, any young woman feels safe and they don't feel like they have
to lose weight or they have to look a certain way.
Yeah.
What a great summation and congratulations, Laura.
It's looking at this conversation through the lens of leadership quite often.
And I did want to ask you specifically about that.
And we both live in Melbourne.
And, um, you know, some of the data that's coming out of this lockdown, particularly
in the teenage girl bracket, Laura, is just horrific and not being spoken about enough
in my view.
And to have role models like you and Steph, your business partner, so the data that came
out in the last few weeks was at the moment in Melbourne through the lockdown, we've got
830 teenage girls being diagnosed with an eating disorder every week in Melbourne, every
week.
So you think about, you know, the impact of that on the family.
And then to hear someone like you, who's clearly identified that, now being able to talk about
a creative business that I wants to talk about being positive in that space.
And I mean, there's four families I know directly through the schools we're in that are experiencing
that it's, it's heartbreaking.
I mean, do you still see it?
I mean, was it a hard thing for you to work your way through?
Can you explain a bit more about how you and Steph Rao navigate that challenging time?
That data is, it's so sad.
I think when it's hard with, and especially for me, I'm a really disciplined person.
And so when you're really disciplined, it's very easy and you want to be
in control and especially for young women and in all of the poor girls have that have
eating disorders at the moment and people that have them when you are, especially during
COVID, there's so much out of our control and what we eat is one thing that we can control.
So, I mean, it doesn't surprise me that that's been the statistic also not being with your
friends, not just not having that normal life is it's so hard on everyone and not having
school.
Like I just, I can't imagine.
And then on top of that, I think, I mean, for me,
I was 19 when I joined Instagram and, you know, you'd think I would be mature enough at that age.
And these kids are so young and vulnerable.
And for me at 19, I was still affected, let alone, you know, being 13, 12, 14, however young
kids are when they join social media.
I think for me and Steph as well, it was, it's definitely a journey.
It doesn't kind of fix overnight.
And the most important thing, I was lucky I got through it with kind of support.
And for me, it was a realisation that what I was doing, lucky,
I never got to the point where my health was at risk and I was able to realise myself,
what I was doing was not, I decided that my value was so much more than the way that I look.
My value is in everything else.
Our value is not in the way that we look.
And that for me was how I was able to work myself through it.
But for younger women and if their health is affected, I think the most important thing is to
reach out to someone to help a psychologist, a medical professional, because it can
get really serious really quickly.
And it is so scary, especially in this time in COVID.
Yeah, it feels like a perfect storm at the moment.
It's for all those reasons, as you said, taking kids out of school, having them locked at home and
then looking constantly at images that often aren't real.
Is that getting back to your conversation on Instagram?
And again, I know you've put out a lot of positive messaging exactly around what filters mean and
how unrealistic that is and trying to, I suppose, navigate that path again is the term that comes to mind.
You're also an author in that space.
A Girl's Guide to Kicking Goals.
Is that part of the mission for you is to try and give this inspiration and be the glass half full
positive voice in this world?
Yeah, so our book actually, it came out three years ago now.
I got a reminder on Instagram the other day.
So it's been quite a while since that came out.
But that book, the reason that we wrote that is it's so aligned with our mission of Keep It Cleaner and
just supporting that book is very much female skewed.
So for young women and all of the things that I think, especially through high school,
that maybe we aren't taught things like confidence, things that the fact that, you know,
the way that we look does not matter.
And especially navigating, I suppose, after navigating social media, we just wanted to put something
together for younger women that, you know, may be struggling now with with all of the comparison.
I can't imagine growing up the way that, you know, the teenagers of today growing up.
There's so they're just looking at images of things that are edited and as you said, not real 24 7.
And so and I mean, especially.
Things like the the filters now on social media and Snapchat and and all those things.
And then it's getting to a point where, you know, some young women are filming themselves on the filters 24 7.
And then I suppose it would be really hard.
These filters, they change when I did a video recently and it changes the shape of my nose, which tells me that the
filter that's called beautiful girl or something, I'm only beautiful when my nose is half the size and I'm only
beautiful when my lips get bigger and my my jawline gets bigger.
It's more whatever you call it, chiseled, whatever you need to do.
And that is such a dangerous message to be sending to young people.
So that's the book was really to talk about things that we weren't navigating social media and growing up.
But yeah, it's crazy.
That was three years ago. It doesn't feel like it.
Yeah. And I think as a parent of a parent of four, Laura, I've got three boys and teenage daughter.
She's our second eldest. She's 16.
And, you know, it's just an interesting experience trying to be.
As consistent and that love and support.
But that seems to me to just be so different to the boys and what they experience.
And and, you know, we're lucky she's such a brilliant, healthy and active and connected young girl.
But it's still terrifying at some stages to look and see the pressures that teenage girls are under.
How are you? I'm looking for some parenting advice.
So how are you with your parents through those teenage years?
Was it challenging?
Do you look back on that and think there was some landmines there?
Oh, I think.
I mean, I was pretty confident as a kid, as in in my body and all those things I did.
I had a very strict mom and my parents separated when when I was 12.
And so I spent most of the time with mom and my mom was so strict.
She would have to if I went to a birthday party in year 12, I would have to walk in with her.
She would walk me into the party and check for alcohol.
So I then sometimes went and it's funny, one of her best friends now actually was one of the moms that would be like, don't worry, Laura, you can sleep.
So, I mean, I was I kind of rebelled a little bit because my parents were so strict and my mom was really strict.
But I think for me, I really for me in year 12.
And I mean, it's definitely something that for younger kids and especially those that have had their year 11 and 12 in lockdown, it's so important to remember that your ATAR, you know, is not your everything.
I think in year 12, you're kind of taught and it's drilled into you that.
If you don't get a good score, you know, you don't have a good future.
And, you know, this is the be all and end all.
I think if I went back, I would tell myself that, you know, it would be OK either way and maybe to not have put as much pressure on myself as I did, you know, to get my ATAR.
I think that's something that probably would be good for schools to talk about a little bit more.
And it's not not to not push kids to, you know, do their best because it's really important to be disciplined and study because you learn so much in doing that.
I think it's just there's a lot.
Right.
And there's a lot of pressure and especially for kids coming up now with a lot of pressure on them coming from all angles with social media.
They're in lockdown.
It's probably a little bit too much.
That's probably something I would I would have told myself back then.
How about when you look back and you talk to your mum?
Do you sort of feel as though that was was was helpful?
I'm a bit inspired, to be honest with you.
I picture me walking in with Sienna and she's like, you're a loser, dad.
There's no way you're going anywhere near the door.
I think that would be the response I would get.
But did your mum think?
In hindsight, did that serve you well, that strict parenting, do you think?
Or would you rather have been a bit more relaxed?
No.
Well, I mean, actually, first of all, my sister's name is Sienna.
It's a beautiful name.
So that's so nice.
My mum was actually I am so grateful for my mum and the way that that we were raised and my parents.
My mum raised me.
And I think being the I suppose the leader that I am today in what I'm doing, there is no way I would be doing what I'm doing without my mum.
We actually had a sticker on the fridge growing up that a man and the sticker said a man is not a financial plan at my mum's house.
I saw that when my parents separated, when I was 12, my younger sister was six.
My mum had been out of the workforce.
I think she'd just gone back part time.
But when you have kids and often the mum will stay home and look after them.
But what I saw as a young person was that, you know, my parents separated.
My mum then didn't have.
I had a really stable income and it wasn't, you know, we had a lot of financial pressure and stress on us because it wasn't a lot to support a single household.
And so I looked at that situation and my mum, I think my gender is as really now I've seen why there is a lot of gender inequality in the workplace now.
But at that time, I saw my gender as something that it kind of almost pushed me to be like, you know, I have to I want to be successful.
I have to set myself up.
I have to set myself up for financial freedom, create my own opportunities and not, you know, rely on anyone else because I could end up and my mum is she's absolutely fine now and she's happy and everything.
But I think seeing her going through that really made me realise that, hang on, I'm not just going to, you know, marry someone and just rely on them to, you know, look after me.
I want to look after myself and be independent and be able to, you know, create opportunities for myself.
Without my mum, I definitely wouldn't be doing what I do.
What a brilliant message.
A man is not a financial plan on the fridge.
That's, you know, what a great, that obviously stayed with you because, you know, to see what you're doing now, as I said, 28 years of age, you're the CEO of an incredible business.
You've got a huge following.
And do you think that that message subliminally was there?
Has this been part of the plan for you, Laura, the way it's eventuated or is it a bit of a surprise to you?
I think for me, I grew up thinking and I want to say as well, my mum really taught me that hard work.
Hard work is the most important thing.
And I prove that to myself in year 12.
I'm not naturally, you know, the kids that just get through everything.
They don't need to study.
That wasn't me.
I had to study my butt off to pass, but I studied my butt off and I did really well.
And so that really taught me that actually when I work hard, I can achieve things.
Obviously, I know as well now, it is so sad.
There are so many people that in the world that work so hard every single day and they're still earning minimum wage.
So I,
I acknowledge that I have a lot of privilege in being able to work hard and create opportunities for myself.
But I,
I feel that, yeah, so with high school, that's, that taught me that.
And then, I mean, in what we're doing with Keep It Cleaner, we've at the start, before we started the e-book,
we just were so open to any opportunity.
And I feel you have to work really hard to get there.
And I feel at the start when you're trying to grow, you kind of feel like you're in a dark room and there's no light
and you'll knock on every door.
And no one opens the window.
And then all of a sudden, 10 people will say yes.
And opportunity kind of then creates more opportunity.
But you just have to work to get there.
And I think as well, because I didn't have a backup plan, I suppose this was, you know, what we wanted to do.
And I wanted, I just have that ever since I've young, that I've wanted to create financial freedom for myself and independence
and also create a path for myself that when I am after, you know,
maybe we'll still be doing Keep It Cleaner when we're 80.
And I don't know about doing squats when we're that old.
But I suppose enable myself to have the opportunity to then be able to help young women,
especially, I suppose, with confidence in being able to grow in their career
and especially underprivileged people coming up because I feel really lucky to, I suppose,
have been as privileged as I was to work hard and be able to create opportunity.
And I really am passionate about wanting other people to feel that way as well.
I can hear the passion.
It's fantastic.
And Keep It Cleaner is a six-year, you know, maybe past the startup's age to getting towards that sustained success.
But what people often think is the overnight success.
You read about it.
You see the profile now.
And you and Steph have got a great story to tell.
But can you tell us maybe about some of the dark room you just spoke about and being knocked back?
And were there times where you thought, this isn't going to fly?
We're not going to make this work?
Yeah.
I mean, there were so many times.
Because it's so interesting looking back now and reflecting.
I think we just really believed in what we were going to do, what we were doing.
So we just kept going.
And I think for us, being naive was one of the best things in the world.
Because I think if we knew what we were in for and the experience of other people in the industry
compared to our very limited experience, we probably would not have done what we're doing.
So I always say that naivety for us was a superpower.
At the start.
And I mean, also that confidence that I had in myself instilled that I could do this.
And I believed in myself.
And just our gender didn't hold us back and all those things.
When you have nothing to lose, really, and you get a no, it doesn't really matter.
You just keep trying for a yes.
But I think for me, it's been really interesting because my confidence has actually got probably worse the bigger that we've got.
Because I think if I look at what Keeper Cleaner is now as a business, I see it.
And I'm like, hang on, that's a really big business.
I can't run this business.
You know, I don't know how to do it.
I've only been doing it for, you know, six years.
And it's interesting, I suppose, which is a bit of imposter syndrome.
And I think it's interesting because I kept thinking the bigger we got or the better that we did and the more goals that we ticked off,
the more confident I would feel.
But it's almost been the opposite of that.
And I think at the start, it's just, it's honestly, it's faking it.
And until you make it, really, that's a really good saying.
And it's true.
Like, I remember one of the first times Steph and I were pitching Keeper Cleaner, we were trying,
we thought another way that we could generate revenue in the business.
This was really back at the start.
We started with the e-book and then we, with the money that we sold the e-book with,
we then made a website, which was so basic.
It was $6.95 for a subscription.
And back then, subscription wasn't really the norm.
It was very new.
There was no Netflix or anything.
It was three very basic recipes and a workout filmed on our phones with a PT, random every time.
So, that's what we were doing.
And we thought, you know, how can we build this?
Let's go, maybe we can get a partnership as we grow our brand.
And we had contacted, it was, the business actually doesn't exist anymore,
but it was quite big at the time.
And they said, okay, yep, come in and present to us.
And I remember we walked into this, I'd never been in a boardroom before that was this big.
It had like 12 chairs and they're all really big.
Two of the male execs from the company that were, you know, 40 to 50 years,
Steph and my senior were sitting there and I had no idea what to say, what they wanted to hear.
And I knew we probably weren't big enough to be pitching what we were, but I thought, you know what?
We literally have nothing to lose.
Let's just, let's just be confident.
And I think what I learned in that time, and I mean, we got a partnership with them and it was fantastic.
And what I learned from that is that, you know, if you believe in yourself, that's the most important thing as a leader.
You have to believe in yourself.
Yeah.
It's like, if you go to a job interview and you don't believe you're good enough to get the job,
how on earth is the stranger interviewing you going to believe that you're good enough?
You know, you have to believe in yourself first.
And so that's something that I've always stuck to.
And even in moments where I feel extremely insecure and like, I'm not good enough to be there.
I just repeat to myself, fake it, fake it, fake it.
You're doing a very good job.
If that mantra is working for you and I can picture the, you know, the two of you walking in and you've got
male execs with experience and that's intimidating for anyone.
Has that been challenging for you, you know, and Steph to overcome that as, you know, young execs you are
and CEOs and running your own business?
Have you been surprised by the reception you've got?
Have you had bad experiences?
What's it been like?
We've had some interesting experiences, I suppose I would say over time.
I think one of the biggest learnings we've had is that you can't trust everyone.
Steph and I really trust.
Trusting of people.
And I think the most important thing to me is in leadership is, you know, leading with openness, transparency and authenticity.
And that transparency led to a few contract negotiations that we've been in where we've thought that, you know,
every single person that you go into business with has your best interest at heart, which has been a huge learning.
That is, it's obviously for anyone that is experienced listening, they'll know that that's absolutely not the case, unfortunately.
So we've learned that the hard way a few times.
But I think one thing that I have really acknowledged in myself and I really I want to work on is as a female in most circumstances where it is in a kind of male dominated room or space, you have to prove, and I do feel this quite often, you have to prove why you're there and why you should be there and why you deserve a seat in the room.
And for me, curiosity and asking questions is how I learn.
It's so important.
But I find when I'm in an environment...
That is really male dominated, I will apologize before I'm asking a question or saying something.
I have to apologize for speaking in a room that's to do with our business.
So I have, you know, I have every right to say something just as anyone else does in the room.
And another thing that I that I know that we do as women is we when we say a sentence, we try to make people feel more comfortable.
So if we're voicing an opinion, I do this all the time.
And it's so funny because I talk on podcasts about it.
I still do it.
So I need to start not practicing what I preach.
But I'll say, you know, I believe in, I don't know, a calendar.
And instead of just saying, I'll put a question at the end, because putting a question at the end then means that if anyone doesn't agree with me, I can then kind of backtrack because I've posed it as a question.
And I think as well, another thing that I have really identified that I do myself and my male counterparts don't often do is if I...
Yeah.
And it comes back to a confidence thing in women.
There's an amazing TED talk.
It's called The Science of Women's Leadership.
I really recommend that anyone listening that's female, anyone watches it, and they speak about how women in leader efficacy, we are so much,
less confident and even though we are more skilled in there was a study that they did and it was
between I think 18 to 21 year old school or university students and there was more women
in the leadership course than there were men except when the peers in the class were questioned
on how confident they were in their leadership the women were made way less confident and it's
really interesting because it's like this inherent kind of lack of confidence that that we have and
I think one of the main reasons for it is as women and this is something that I really struggle
with is that you want to be liked it's something it's like something that we just I don't know why
it's like it's genetically put into our brains that we need people to like us and I think
if you were to write a list of the traits that makes a good woman it's kind of kindness you know
all of those things caring and then if you were to do the same for a male it would be you know
strong
driven all of those things and and it's really hard because I think leadership traits are actually
probably more um towards traits that we would qualify as as a good man and so for a female to
be you know if you're in the boardroom and you're pushing because you have to have difficult
conversations in leadership and when leading a company otherwise if we didn't if Steph and I
avoided difficult conversations we would not be where we are now you have to fight for your
company and so you're so often kind of found to be you know
emotional or you know too over the top or aggressive because you have an opinion whereas
I don't think it's the same for for males and so I think for me it's this it's always this debate in
my head when I'm in these rooms like I don't it's kind of like I almost don't like the person that I
am but yeah I think I only think that way because it's the stereotype of how I should be and I think
we really need to change that and I think we all have this subconscious bias of these gender
stereotypes and it's not it's not fair especially if you're a woman and you're a man and you're a
in the leadership space and there's there's not enough women in the leadership space as there is
and we need to work on that and I think we really need to like look at this bias that we have that
it's not conscious it's not on purpose but it's just the way that we think yeah beautifully said
and thanks for sharing that so openly Laura it's a really powerful thing that that you just said
and and really it goes to the core of why I'm recording this podcast in lots of ways because
what we really are saying and what I really am passionate about is that there is a shift Laura
I'm sure it is away from that male-dominated hierarchical I'm the boss how do I you know
exert my ego over a group of people and then get them you know through command and control to do
what I say and I've got this sort of essence of confidence really below a lot of those males in
my experience is a real lacking in confidence and they overcompensate with but the brilliance
of what you bring is what the best male leaders are now doing which is self-reflection and
self-awareness and openness and vulnerabilities.
The the term of the time at the moment you know and I've seen this in the sporting world that I
came through Laura where we grew up with coaches that were just aggressive and abused and berated
you as the only way they knew and that was their experience but the new generation they build great
relationships and they're connected and in sporting organizations you know I'm lucky enough to sit on
the board of the old footy club I play and Kylie Watson Wheeler I interviewed on this podcast is
our CEO and Fiona McGeckney our board has skewed more femur not only are the girls but they're
smarter but they bring a presence that is so much more effective in in in my experience that's not
to diminish you know they've all got incredible experience so I'm glad you're identifying that
I'm glad the world is because it's not tokenistic in my mind it's just effectiveness and and we're
learning so much more because it's hard for us you know we grew up as males not being vulnerable
was was that you were weak and you weren't able to do that so I'm hoping that that's that's the
brilliance of what you're saying is that you are the new generation of male leaders and you're
of leaders and and I hope the 16 year old girls I hope we get some the teenage girls open my
door she won't listen to me but hopefully she listens to you and and inspired to say yeah you
might be scared you might be nervous but as you're proving you can be very effective too can't you
Laura I completely understand what what you when you say that you know the way that it's looking
at sport for example my dad actually was um he played for North Melbourne and he was coached
under Ron Barassi and I have seen a few videos of him he was the coach wasn't he Ron Barassi was
famous and uh you didn't get in Barassi's way and and uh and that's some of the old audio that
exists and what was your dad's first name Ross of course I had no idea that was yeah that's my dad
so what there you go and what a great history at North Melbourne but he would have been on the
receiving end of some Barassi's praise yes exactly and it was kind of the I've seen some of the video
and it's crazy
not concentrated your body not switched on properly now you get over and try and mind
the body forward pocket okay and it's you know it's changed so much now and I think as you were
saying it's fantastic and and I hope down the track we don't even have to talk about female
leadership it's just leadership and we don't have to talk about women in business because it's just
people in business because you know everyone there's there's equality and that's exciting
to go especially especially Australia as as a country the the statistic for where we are in
gender equality has it's dropped uh it's since I think it's about 2000 since 2003 or 2006
Australia's dropped by about 16 places so I think we're 29th now or something which is not
obviously not great so there is there is a long way to go for us but it's awesome that you're
having these conversations and it doesn't mean that you know women are smarter than men or
anything that's a good thing but it's also a good thing that you're having these conversations
it's absolutely not the conversation or that men it's not that men are smarter than women either
it's that think of all of that untapped talent pool that we just haven't accessed because you
know we didn't think that you know women are able to be CEOs because they need to have children and
then stop working like the amount of times I've been told it's so it's I just sit there now and
kind of laugh to myself but oh Laura you'll want to have kids soon like you won't want to work like
this you know this that's not what you want and I'm I'm kind of sick of being told what I should
want you know I can decide what I want to do and I'm kind of sick of being told what I should want
what I want and if I want to work um and you know and have kids that's okay and if I don't want to
work and have kids that's also okay so I think it just comes back to again those stereotypes
and as you said I I love that the kind of the way you speak about leadership in that it's not
hierarchical hurry up I can never say that and kind of it's like a boss and then I don't like
the word boss because it kind of infers that you tell people what to do when you boss them around
and I think with with good leadership and from people that I've seen lead the the best people
that lead are the ones that are leaders and you can't be I don't think you're a good leader if
you're a boss because then you're not empowering your team to kind of you know to grow and and
learn and be better and and all those things you're just telling them what to do and I think
for me our our Keep It Cleaner team now they are so fantastic I can't take credit for a lot of what
we do at Keep It Cleaner because our team do most of it and I think it's a really good team and I
and I'm so proud of of all of them and they're so good at their jobs and I cannot imagine
you know bossing them around and telling them what to do because
it would make no sense because we're all a part of this journey together and we're all equal in
our contribution it doesn't matter if you know you contribute to the social media or if you're
an engineer developer or if you're a senior marketer everyone contributes to what we do
and you know the journey that we're on together and it's I think that's what why I hope I hope
it's a leader for them but that's really important to me I'm going to pick you up because you're
doing it again Laurie said I can't take credit for the fact that we've got a great team you have
you're the CEO you're driving that culture and uh you know your humility comes through in a
beautiful way but I can imagine that the environment that you're creating with that with
your partner and you as the CEO uh Steph would be would be something really special I've got so many
things I want to ask and there are a series of questions about leadership I want to get to but
one of the things to the health and well-being space in itself is is an interesting and
sometimes conflicted world too Laura there's all sorts of different diets and regimes and people
get protective over whether you should be vegetarian or there should be paleo or this
is how you meditate or not how have you waded through that world with keep it clean and I
suppose what what does health mean to you if you describe it so I mean the the biggest thing for
keep it cleaner is health is holistic and health is all about balance and my personal I think for
us it's been it's been great from a business perspective because we've never yes we have
recipes that are allergen friendly so people that follow gluten-free vegetarian pescatarian
you know whatever they follow vegan but we've never ever ever pigeonholed ourselves into and
that's because it's not what Steph and I believe in into a certain way of eating you know keto
whatever all those things that because for Steph and I it's restrictive and I think because we
came from that the background of restrictive eating and us having a very unhealthy relationship
with food we've really tried to step away from that in the app
we don't have any mention we have a dietician obviously that checks every single recipe and
all the calories and nutritional profiles of every recipe are calculated but you won't find that in
the app because we don't want that to be the focus it's all about balance and you know health is not
eating fish and vegetables every single night for dinner and you know especially for families
the you know the parents having to eat a different meal to their children because they're on a diet
and then the kids are eating something else it should just be sustainable changes and
maybe someone has been keto or whatever it might be for their entire life good on them but I think
for most people sustainable changes in your health that you can actually you know start tomorrow and
then still be doing when you're 75 80 years old they're the ones that incorporate balance and
they're achievable they're not expensive they're not time consuming it's just really really simple
changes adding a little bit more vegetables into your diet you know kind of working out five because
I feel like we all end up making the same recipes every day so I think it's really important to
every single week because you just that's all you can think of but making those recipes healthy
ones and teaching yourself you know how to cook healthily and then finding exercise that you
actually enjoy and finding exercise that you can fit into your day you know if you're a high level
exec or even you know if you're a mum working from home mum you have to manage home school you have
to manage your work you have to then try and exercise it's not going to be realistic that
you're going to do crossfit for two hours a night because you don't have time so find something
that's going to be realistic and that I think is what health is about.
It's knowing that every single person's journey is different it feels different for everyone it
looks different but you just need to find things that you can sustain like for me I love running
I know a lot of people hate it it's literally the worst thing ever they don't have to do it that's
okay find something else that they love because you just you have to find things that you can
sustain because we you know the we don't without our health we don't have anything and it's
something that we take for granted so it's really really important you know next time if anyone's
listening and they're thinking of making a healthy change or switch in their life I think it's
their life don't go on a fad diet for five days and have shakes because that is not going to get
you know that's not sustainable you're not going to eat have shakes for the rest of your life
make change and it's hard work you know to make those changes at the start but then they become
normal. Yeah sustainable I love that word and the successful people you tend to speak to have great
daily habits and routines don't let it stick and they're able to make that as you said really
easily part of their life and things they love things they enjoy doing. Now I've got a handful
of questions for you. I've got a handful of questions for you. I've got a handful of questions
that Laura been trying to ask we have been asking all the leaders and and loving the different
perspectives from Justin Langer as the Australian cricket coach to Steve Biddulph who's you know
spoken and written about raising you know boys and girls and written great books and so the
different perspectives but the way people approach leadership so please be as expansive as you like
or or as brief as you like self-leadership Laura what does that mean to you when I ask you that?
Yeah it's a good question I've loved I've listened back to a lot of your episodes I have
to say I'm very humbled to be on. Oh I'm very humbled that you agreed Laura thank you so much.
Thank you. I think what self-leadership means to me I think it's for me it's knowing that I'm
always growing and developing as a leader and I think that's not for me that is for my team I
think I can always do better for them and if I'm not developing myself how can I expect them you
know to develop themselves in their career as well and I think as well it's being very very clear on
my personal values and I mean it's being a the founder of Keep It Cleaner with Steph our personal
values are very much intertwined with the company values they're almost identical and so I feel very
lucky in that way that I'm so clear obviously as we all are in our personal values and of course
very clear on the Keep It Cleaner values because they're so similar that's really really important
as a leader in being so clear on your vision and your values because then it's so much easier to
be decisive which is obviously extremely important and then you're able to lead with
authenticity and purpose because you know why you're doing what you're doing and so I think
with self-leadership it's always coming back and realigning with those values and at kick in in our
time even though it's only been a short time any of the times we've gone off track away from what
our core is that's when we've seen I suppose the the more detrimental effects of that whereas when
we're clear on our purpose and our goals that that's when we've seen them come true.
And did you and Steph actually sit down and write your values together so you had them
consistently do they do they change and and if you've got an example as you said when we've
gone away from that we've had bad experiences is there something that comes to mind?
Yeah so I mean when we first started we weren't that serious about it we didn't know that you
need to have company values so I think that's why the business has really formed around our own
personal personal values I mean one of them kindness is a really big one especially because
what we we do in our offering is our Facebook community so it's a place as I've said it has
to be safe for young people and or for all people and we actually it's it's funny I shouldn't say
young people because we have I mean really I'm it's because I think everyone is young but we do
have people up to 60 and about I think 65 in the Facebook community that kindness is is really
really important there so that's the value that crosses over I think with the steering away it's
it's more from a business perspective you need to be clear about what you're doing and what you're
on who you are as a business what your differentiators are we're very very clear on
that now and not trying to be everything for everyone I think that's where we've kind of
gone a little bit off track because we were trying to do a hundred things and when you try and do too
many things you don't do anything well but we can do you know the things that we do very well and
so that's what you know we it doesn't mean that you were not open for opportunities but I think
you just have to be very clear on what the right opportunity is.
Positively impacting others.
What are your thoughts on how you go about that?
Oh I mean it's it's so important especially I feel like that is for me one of the biggest
roles as I said we've got an awesome team now that do so much of of the great work that you
see on the app and so a big part of my role now is I think well for me I feel it's bringing that
positive energy to our team. I think as a leader a really really important thing is setting the
tone for your team and of course there's times when serious conversations need to be had so it
can't always be.
100% positive and happy but bringing that to every meeting that I'm in I don't think you can expect
that of your team if you're not going to lead by example and be that way so I think that's really
really important and it ties into believing in what you're doing if the leader doesn't believe
in what you're doing and isn't positive about the journey and the goals of the business then
how can you expect your team to be?
Yeah have you got you know it sounds like it's been something you had to work on the
the authentic conversations is that something that as you said you can't survive.
Can you in business you have to call out when things are there is that come easier to you if
you've found that better as you've got on? Because Steph and my social because of our
social media and our we're very open with everything online we are then I think it's
forced us to be authentic with with our team and I can't say any other way because I show most of
my life on social media and I have pulled back a little bit as I've gotten a little bit older
but I've gotten a little bit older and I've gotten a little bit older and I've gotten a little bit
older but our brand and kick and who we are is built on authenticity and that's what I really
hope with my social media obviously we've spoken about how social media can be so negative but
I really try as hard as I can that I you know I feel so grateful to have a following and so if I
can influence them in the right way and showing you know realness and being authentic that's so
important and I mean probably an example that comes to mind is I am I'm quite an anxious person
which is something that's built more and more as
you know I've been in the business for a long time and I've been in the business for a long time
and I was really scared to talk about it because I thought that it would mean that my team would
think that I was flawed and I wasn't good enough you know to be their leader or for them to work
for and it's funny because when I opened up about it and and I ended up opening up and about it
because I thought you know I've got 250,000 people following me on social media and if I can make one
person not feel alone or flawed in you know themselves because anxiety is so common and
there's definitely more than one person that follows me that that experiences it
then I you know I'm doing I feel like I'm living my purpose and what I need to be doing and then
in turn obviously anyone I mean it was just public knowledge that that's something that I lived with
and my team do not treat me any differently absolutely not they do not think I'm flawed
but that's an example where I think social media and the responsibility that I feel to the people
that follow me to be real push me to be more authentic but I think now I'm yeah I'm
pretty much open about everything so yeah well said probably too authentic for the team
too authentic that's uh that's an amazing quality how about when you talk about the vision that you
guys um have uh have created how do you go about sharing your vision we've actually just worked
through we had an amazing consultant come in and work with us at the start of this year
and her name's Gabrielle and she worked with us on really clarifying our revisiting our goal we've
had company vision goals all those things but we've had company vision goals all those things but we've had
revisited them and really clarified them for the team and we presented them and it was actually
especially with the I think with our company goals especially in values while that's not
really I suppose essentially the vision it's still a very very big part of it because I think
if you're setting goals for the company and what you can do with it you need your team needs to
feel first of all a part of the story and a part of the journey but then also they need to feel
connected with why you're doing what you're doing you know if it's just to make money why would
you care or give you know give any more of themselves and so we did this activity we we
finalized all of our company goals we ran through all of them and then we got everyone to paint we
we're in a common it's called the commons and I know the common yeah that's yeah in South York
it's fantastic and they've got an art room there and we thought let's use it so we went in there
and we all painted how or maybe we I can't remember we painted all these um textures how we saw the
company goals kind of within a picture and then we all explained it and it was so interesting
because every single person while we'd run through the company goals at the start of the day and it
was really clear on what they were the interpretation of them was so different in every
single person of the team and I think that's I mean that's such a great example of why you can't
you know you have to as a leader ensure that you it's not that you change when you speak to each
team member but when you're communicating with them you need to communicate how they communicate
you know that's why dictatorships and it's not the way to lead because you you're not you're not
really putting yourself in in the other person's shoes and how they understand things and how they
like to communicate and hear and listening to them and so that was really a really good exercise
because I think while everyone did an amazing job it gave me a different perspective on our company
values that I didn't understand before and I would not have got that if we hadn't have opened up the
floor to the entire team it didn't matter what their role was in the hierarchy of the business
or on the org chart where they were and I think that's a really good exercise because it's a really
everyone offered such such a great perspective on that yeah it sounds like you do these things
so naturally because of of who you are and the way you are and heard you earlier on mentioned
curiosity and that's the way you tend to learn in meetings and ask questions can you explain a bit
more about that with one of the dimensions we talk about of leadership is curiosity and then
how that affects your learning oh I think I mean asking questions is how you learn I remember in
grade five my teacher said to my I think it was in an interview that
Laura asked sometimes she she said something like she asked a lot of questions and sometimes
it's very annoying but I think it's a good thing and I'll always I'll always remember that and I
think now I one thing that's really important so often there's people I don't think it's very
productive to sit in a meeting and not understand things and be okay with asking you know what does
this mean because you're not expected to know everything if we were expected to know everything
you wouldn't need a team you could just do it and you know you're not expected to know everything
do it all by yourself which would be very sad existence but it's so important to ask questions
and I think a lot of people don't ask them because they're worried that it it shows that they don't
know enough or they're not intelligent but asking questions I think it shows that you know you're
interested in what people are doing and it's how you understand especially for me as I said a lot
of in my university as well a lot of studies things didn't come naturally to me so I had to
ask questions to be able to understand it better and without that I'm not going to be able to
I wouldn't have understanding on things so curiosity and asking questions is so important
I think it also shows for if anyone doesn't like you asking questions and they're probably not a
good teacher but I find when my team asks me questions about things that I'm presenting for
me it's a compliment because it shows that they're interested in what I'm saying they're listening
and they're trying to understand it themselves and that's fantastic yeah it takes courage too
to put yourself out there isn't it you're always hoping that that hits the mark but as you said
it's always well received isn't it if you are trying to understand what people are saying
something regardless of the nature of it communicating with clarity is something
we're talking about a lot in leadership how does that work for you oh it's so important you I mean
especially on the vision of the company you can't expect again your team to buy into this
kind of story and journey that you're on if you're not clear on what it is I know you've
spoken about this on the podcast a lot and it's great because as a leader you don't need to have
every single answer and it's okay to say you know I don't know I don't know I don't know I don't
know but there's someone else in the team that's really good at that and they do that or I don't
know but I'm going to find the answer but this is something that I've learned I think being a law
student you have to be very clear in your reasonings and I remember my first assignment
that I did I think it was a lot of the law exams they give you a big problem and then you have to
go away and try and solve it and come back with maybe 2,000 words and I'd written 4,000 words
and I had no idea on how to cut it down because all I knew
was how to write these really wordy sentences and and what I've learned throughout my degree
is that that is not always effective or efficient in getting I kind of used to fill as many words
as I could because then hopefully within it it would be the right answer but you know that's
not the best way to communicate it's really really important to be clear and concise I think
the more ambiguity that you leave in the way that you're explaining things it's not great because
sometimes people it's there's more I suppose chance for things to be
misinterpreted so being clear is is really really important and that's something I think
in leadership is probably one of the most important things in being able to communicate
clearly and concisely. Clearly you're a collaborator and collaboration that's coming
through in everything you do with your with your business partner Steph as well but do you actively
think about collaboration and what does that mean to you? I think it's it's so important again it
comes back to that the whole idea of not really focusing on the hierarchy in a business I think
if you are a business partner you're not really focusing on the hierarchy in a business I think if you
only think that for example ideas can come from senior individuals then you're not tapping into
your entire team and empowering them so what we do it's really really important that we do
brainstorms within teams all the time to make sure that everyone feels heard and understood
and that they can contribute and often you know ideas will come from everywhere it was like when
we did that exercise with the company goals the perspectives were so the company values the
perspectives of all of the team were really really interesting and you know I think it's
it just it for me I just kind of stood there and I was like wow this is the power of collaboration
and and listening to everyone and also making everyone feel valued I think as a team member
the one of the things that can is the hardest to be an environment is when you don't feel valued I
mean in any relationship or part of your life if you don't feel valued it's really hard to show up
so I think in collaboration within that a really really big part is ensuring that every single
person in your team feels like they are valued and they are valued and I think that's a really
big part of the team. Sounds like a great place to be keep it cleaner with the values and the
vision and the way you speak I think it's I speak about that often there's nothing sadder than
watching people feeling like they have no voice at all in whatever they do whatever environment
as you said home life or the workplace for sure. How about this question Laura I've been asking
to everyone who's come on who's the greatest leader in your life? Oh my goodness that's
I knew it was coming.
Such a good question I think I mean for me my mum's had a huge impact on me as I've said
and then the other person that's had a huge impact on me recently is Gabrielle the consultant her
surname's actually famous it's a pretty cool name. Gabrielle famous that's a hard name to forget.
And she's consulted with us she's now the CEO of Vamp but for the first kind of four to five
months of this year we had her working with us at Kik and it was fantastic she helped me develop in
my leadership so much.
And she really instilled in me a lot of confidence I think it's it's very as a young leader and I
suppose as a female leader it's really easy to lose confidence as we've discussed and it's quite
rare for someone to come in and really instill that in you and make you feel really empowered
and I think having that time over the past four months has given me back this confidence that I
lost a little bit last year. I think confidence is not a sure thing.
It's it comes and goes and you have time when you're super clear and then times when you're not
but working with Gabrielle over the past at the start of the year for kind of four to five months
was incredible and yeah she's had a huge influence on me as a leader. Yeah and there's so many great
bits of wisdom that you've shared today Laura I really appreciate it I'm looking forward to the
the TED talk the science of women's leadership. I love the sticker on your fridge it's inspiring
man he's got a financial plan I as I said I'm thinking through the eyes of
of my teenage daughter a lot talking to you and and and wanting to to get more of that
inspiration out there it's an incredible story that you've created along with your partner
Steph congratulations Keep It Cleaner what's to come where do you see yourself in maybe 15 or 20
years? Oh goodness no idea that's such a hard question I think I mean we have some huge goals
for Keep It Cleaner and our vision with that especially in terms of international expansion
there's a lot of
areas that I can see huge growth for us and and potential in what we're doing we truly we truly
believe with our product and what we're offering it's it's one of the best or if not the best on
on the market and I think that the more people that we can get in front of the better so we've
got huge goals with that and then I think as well something that I'm extremely passionate about is
is empowering women to feel confident and believe in themselves more especially in their workplace
and I think for me I will just continue to try and tell as many people as I can about that and
what's important for companies to get women in I mean in especially the statistic for CEOs in the top
200 ASX companies it's very low and there's so much so much we can do there and I think one of
the biggest things we need to do is get women into senior leadership because that is where they are
promoted from so while I don't really know how I'm going to help with that at the moment I hope
in 20 years I'm doing something to contribute to that as well. I wouldn't doubt you for one moment
Laura Henshaw great inspiration great story check out Keep It Cleaner we'll give all the links that
we can to to get behind Laura's passion and her project and as I said thanks again for your time
today I really enjoyed it. Thank you so much for having me Luke. Empowering Leaders was presented
by me Luke Darcy produced by Matt Dwyer with audio production by Darcy Thompson. To start your
leadership journey I encourage you to go to elitercollective.com take our Empowering Leaders
Indicator tool and understand the impact you have on your business.
Join us as a leader to learn lead and collaborate.