I hope you enjoy this episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast with Peggy O'Neill, the first
ever female president of an Australian rules football club, the famous Richmond Tigers,
who she helped steer to win three premierships in four years, one of the most successful
periods in the history of the game.
Peggy teaches us a lot, and certainly me, about being calm, always positive and clear
thinking, but I wouldn't underestimate Peggy's determination to succeed and find a solution
to be the best in whatever environment she is, whether that's president of the Richmond
Football Club, she's the current chancellor at RMIT University, an incredible leader with
some great lessons and wisdom to share.
It's leaders like Peggy O'Neill who inspire the work we do at Alita, and I'd love you
to have a look at our Alita Connect signature program.
We bring together bespoke groups of five to six people in a facilitated forum, and the
opportunity to learn and connect with different thinkers.
We really know and believe it's a valuable asset in life.
Love you to check it out.
Head to alitacollective.com.
You can book a call, and we'll jump on the line and explain to you more about the work
we do and are passionate about in a world of collaboration, inspiring connections at
Alita.
Get online and have a look.
The Empowering Leaders podcast proudly presented by Temper, a mattress like no other, and we
know from talking to incredibly successful leaders like Peggy O'Neill that they all understand
the value of sleep.
And investing in the world's best bedding, NASA approved, is a decision that you will
not regret.
Peggy O'Neill was born and raised in the now abandoned small mining community of Killarney,
West Virginia.
She comes from a family of coal miners and was the first in her family to go to university
studying law at the University of Virginia.
Peggy became the first female lawyer at her legal firm in Charleston in the company's
100-year history.
After moving to Australia in the late 1980s, Peggy's incredible career has been a part
of her leadership success story, including becoming the first female president of an
Australian rules football club with Richmond in 2013, helping steer them to premiership
success in 2017, 2019 and 2020.
Peggy has a lifetime of community and business achievements.
She's currently the Chancellor of RMIT University, was made an Officer of the Order of Australian
Recognition for her service to football superannuation and finance law, and for the advancement of
women in leadership roles.
She was named Melbourneian of the Year in 2021.
And in 2022, was appointed Chair of the Commonwealth Games Organising Committee.
Peggy, it's great to see you today.
Thanks for taking some time.
Oh, you're welcome.
Good to see you too.
Hey, Peggy, I love your life story.
It's fascinating to me growing up in a tiny mining community, as I said, in West Virginia,
a coal mining family, to go on to break new ground for female leaders and to hold some
of the most significant leadership positions in Australian public life.
Can you cast your mind back to being a young girl growing up in America?
Is it hard to imagine where you've ended up?
It's impossible for me to have imagined this, considering where it started.
But here I am, and I think it all sort of goes back to in those small towns, I had parents
who really encouraged me, and even though they weren't educated, and thought that my
sister and I should have the education that they didn't have.
Yeah.
And along with that, and their sort of encouragement, I just had this curiosity about the world.
And right away, if you're in a small town, the world seems so big, and there's so much
going on.
But for me, I thought, oh, I want to see some of that.
I want to do that.
And I had a wonderful childhood.
And when you're in a small town, you don't realize that you might be missing opportunities.
But I just thought, I just want to learn and experience as much as I can.
But I was 21 before I saw the ocean.
So it was way up in the mountains, and pretty landlocked.
And then I didn't know anyone who had a passport, but I got one, and I started traveling.
And here I am, I ended up in Australia, where I've spent most of my adult life and working life.
So I'm interested in your sister, Peggy.
So you've gone to as far away as you possibly can from West Virginia.
Did she travel?
Did she have a similar trajectory?
No.
She was very bright.
She's a veterinarian.
And she's a veterinarian.
And she is a small-town vet.
So she went away to one of the Ivy League schools in New York for undergraduate school.
And then she went to vet school at the University of Georgia.
And then she and her husband, who's also a veterinarian, bought a practice and have lived in a...
It's not as small as where we grew up.
It's got about 6,000 people, as opposed to 200 people.
But no, she still lives over there.
She's been to...
Australia and we've...
Now that she's traveling a bit more and we've met over in Ireland and thought about her family history and those kinds of things.
But I'm hoping or planning to go back to the U.S. in May.
It'll be the first time I've been there since the pandemic.
So that'll be interesting.
I've got a bit of business to do over there and I'll go down south and see her for a couple of weeks.
It's a long time away from your home country, Peggy.
And it's an interesting place, America, at the moment.
On a whole range of fronts and talking leadership at the moment.
We've just seen the former president arrested in recent times.
How do you feel jumping back into that world?
Is it something that you struggle to align with at the moment?
What's your thought on leadership in your old country, the U.S., at the moment?
Well, you're right.
I have a bit of trepidation about what it might be like.
I think once you're outside looking in and you've sort of lost contact.
Because before the pandemic, I went at least every nine months or sometimes a couple of times a year.
And so you sort of felt like you had a finger on the pulse a bit better.
But I think now it's looking from afar.
You think, how did it get to this point with the great divisions in society and people giving credibility to someone who seems so lacking in credibility?
In most of this business life.
So I'll go back and see.
I'll see what it's like.
I suspect that if you live there, you don't feel the same way about it as we do outside looking in.
Because I think that, and not just because I'm a dual citizen, I have two passports.
And it's not just because I grew up there.
But lots of Australians have said we always look to America for leadership across the free world.
And then once that vacuum was there, all sorts of horrible things have been happening and extreme views given.
As if they were legitimate views.
So I think that that vacuum of leadership, because even though we have a president there now who's perhaps a bit more functional in getting some things done,
you'd have to say there doesn't seem to be a pipeline of inspirational leaders coming through on either party.
And you think we really need someone who thinks long term.
And I think every government might be the same thing.
We need more than that short termism, just get reelected sort of stuff.
So I'm very interested.
I don't think this will be my last trip ever to America.
I have not.
But just got to think, well, maybe we'll meet somewhere else if it becomes so difficult.
But I'm looking forward to going back and seeing my family and my friends.
And Peggy, one of the challenges that I see and I follow the US with interest, like I think we all do,
because we take a lot of the pulse of America here in Australia and it dictates still a lot of our world down here.
But one of the things I find alarming now, Peggy,
is the search for what actually is factual and true.
And we used to have trusted sources where you felt like that was, you know, journalists reported on the facts.
They didn't have alternative facts.
And suddenly it feels as though we're cut into this corner now where really we can't even agree on what's factual.
Even when something happens right before your eyes, you can stand there as a leader and say, no, it didn't happen.
How do we put that genie back in the bottle?
Oh, I think unless, you know, the public demands it and maybe through voting, something might happen.
But but I agree is how can you not believe what you see?
How can you not believe?
But I think you're right.
It goes back to where the trusted sources anymore, because more and more it's become across the media landscape, the soundbite, the short term.
Let's make something sensational.
Even though a sensational headline, even though it might not be sensational story, just so we get someone to look in, because that's how we judge ourselves now.
Not not on the investigative side, not on getting to the facts.
And there's some that do that, but they don't get the airplay or the or the space in newspapers that some of the others do, because it doesn't sell in the same way.
I think our attention span and our willingness to read long.
Form journalism or to listen for half an hour about one story, it just isn't there anymore.
And media doesn't give the time to that either.
So so I don't know how that would ever be solved, but you have to look far and wide and you have to almost do your own balancing act about listen to some of this, because we all like to listen to things that reinforce what we think.
But to find someone who can balance it out for you, you got to search and before that.
It used to be a bit of even handedness, I think.
But now I think one of the disturbing things, too, is there might be a minority view, say, that represents five percent of the people, but sometimes that's given equal time as if it represents half the people.
And so I just wonder if those extreme views being given airtime is for ratings, too, and not because it's a legitimate view.
And so that kind of analysis and.
Tutorial control seems to be missing as well.
So it's a huge problem.
But you're right. Where is there a source of truth?
And and it's and maybe we're all in it for ourselves, which is putting a lot of we don't have the resources that the news organizations have.
Yeah. And the clickbait world, as you described, is is where the money is, isn't it?
And those algorithms are driving that that narrative is why I love this forum, Peggy.
It's a chance to sit down.
With someone and and have time to be able to get your thoughts.
And I hope there's a swing back to that.
If you want a trusted source, you can actually listen to Peggy O'Neill and find out what she what she generally thinks.
I wanted to change tech type slightly because I know you've you've been on the receiving end of mainstream journalism as well.
And I'll ask you about it in a moment when you take these big public roles, all of a sudden Peggy O'Neill becomes in the spotlight.
But I want to quote your former current CEO of Richmond, Brendan Gale.
Who's a champion player in his own right and the CEO throughout the whole time of of your presidency at at Richmond.
And he said this about you said he praised the brilliance of your leadership.
He said Peggy did never get angry.
She got determined.
She didn't panic in a crisis, but instead she pondered problems in the pursuit of a solution.
She has left a powerful lesson for us that there is another way to win.
Can I ask you, Peggy, was that a conscious way that you approach that that role, that big public role?
Or is that just you?
Being you?
Well, I think some of those are my natural attributes.
I didn't think they were anything special.
And sometimes I wonder if that's why I was attracted to the law, because you go, Hmm, I always found that in negotiations, if someone lost their temper, they usually lost the argument.
You know, the business judgment went out the window.
But it's not something that I think too much about.
But I've come to realize that I'm I don't anger is not my first emotion.
And, uh, taking time and being patient.
I think sport teaches you a lot about being patient as well, more than I probably realize.
So I think it's a bit of just who I am and there are other ways, but that was my way.
I also thought that that gave me a chance to respond in a more thoughtful kind of way.
If I needed to respond.
If I needed to respond to things. And like you say, I must have been naive.
I was still surprised when my becoming president of Richmond, the story lingered for a very long time, perhaps until we won the first premiership.
So it's about four years. Richmond might be better if she wasn't there.
And that wasn't so explicit. But there was this, you know, what have they done?
And so I thought, well, I can't second guess myself. I can't worry about that.
I was elected to be president of Richmond until someone else gets elected. I'll just do it my way.
It was it was a pleasure to work with Brendan. And we look back and say, as I was finishing and said, you know, even the bad times, we learned so much and we solved problems that that was rewarding in itself.
You don't know that it's going to end up with, you know, the wonderful result that we were able to achieve.
During those years. But you think if you bring the right sort of mindset and that the goal is the same.
And once you say the goal isn't to make sure I stay in my position, the goal is to do the right thing by the football club.
I think members recognize that. And I think that that's a motivation that everybody can respect you for, even if they don't agree with what your decision is.
And Peggy, you were the first female president in Australian rules football history.
Consequently, we've had several others.
I get to spend some time with one of your friends, Kylie Watson Wheeler, who's doing an incredible, incredible job.
But going back to, you know, perhaps what we'd seen in the past and what Benny was alluding to in leadership in football was that aggressive thumping the desk and masculine sort of leadership that was all that we knew.
I mean, you've been a great champion of women's leadership and the qualities that you bring, as Benny described, that more feminine approach.
You know, less.
You go less aggression.
I mean, clearly it's it's a it's a different approach, but it seems more sustainable and more successful.
Do you feel like we've just we overlooked that for so long and it took the world a long while to understand the strength in the type of leadership you bring?
Well, I think that all the sport, not just, you know, Australian rules, but a lot of sport had one model.
And that was usually the male model of how leadership, how coaching, how.
All of that, because that was all everyone knew.
Women's sport was very secondary and no one had a lot of experience.
But when I became involved with Richmond on the board in 2005, I thought my skills as a lawyer.
But I also started thinking, well, what are the skills you need to help your football club be successful?
And and while there had always been this idea, sort of the amateur idea, which was which was.
The case for so long is that you had to play, you had to know the people in the area.
But now as football clubs have moved on, what you need are people who have business skills, people who have some of that sporting background, need a variety of things around the table.
And just because you were a great player or a great coach didn't necessarily mean you were right to run the football club.
So I sort of saw my being an outsider as of time to be a benefit because I.
I didn't know anyone.
I didn't know where the, you know, the bad feelings or the good feelings or who was married to whose brother and who had played and how many teams together.
But it was more just, well, what do we need to do next?
What's the what's the plan here?
And you don't have to play to sort of make that happen.
Now, it might it might be easier because, you know, everyone.
But that doesn't necessarily mean you're going to make the right decision.
And I know early on, Brenda and I talked about.
If we just make the right decision more often than not, then that's going to set us on a good path.
Just don't just try to avoid making bad decisions.
So make neutral ones or make good ones and we'll keep moving on.
So so I think that with the as we as you said, the the number of women who are taking president roles and executive roles in football clubs now show that we need a skill and the gender of the person.
It doesn't really matter.
And I guess that over time, I started to think of it as perhaps a strength for Richmond.
And and there I was.
But again, as I mentioned earlier, I think I was a bit naive about how much attention it would draw.
And I started to really understand how outside the loop I was.
And as you said, Peggy, what a great strength in so many ways.
And I think we're understanding that better now, isn't it?
When you haven't got.
The history, you can make a more independent judgment at times, can't you?
As I said, when you don't know where the bodies are buried, to use a maybe more brutal phrase, you really are thinking about it purely from what's the best outcome for the Richmond Football Club.
And we see that in the work we're doing in the leadership space, Peggy, around the brilliance of bringing together someone and diverse thinking, because you don't know what you don't know, do you?
And if you're all the same and, you know, I grew up and played in that industry, Peggy.
And you start to sound the same.
And act the same.
And it just happens with time.
When you put someone in from a different background, there's some real superpower in there, isn't there?
Well, I think so.
I think the real motivation is wanting success for your organization or your team.
And the other stuff is what can you contribute?
What can you help us achieve?
And you don't want everybody from the same background, whether it's a playing background or a sports administration background.
You want people.
You want people who have a lot of new ideas.
And I often said the Richmond board, I see that what is it the board is unique?
What is it the board can do that nobody else can do?
Because otherwise we've got a fantastic management team and Brenda's brought together to great people.
What do we add over and above that?
And I came up with the phrase, we bring news to the outside world.
We bring news of the things that are happening that might help our club.
Either through technology, through connections to other businesses, to introducing new people into committees and people into the pool of executive talent.
So I always think that the board is a bit of the outside and we need to bring that into the football club.
And Peggy, you've got a great calmness about you and I always sense that in your decision making.
Anytime we heard from you across that period of time.
But as is the nature of the way that the media works, there was personal attacks that came your way and staggeringly in my mind, someone had contributed in volunteering their time like you were.
And there was a famous line, and I've heard you quote it before, that someone once described you as, you being president of Richmond is a bit like a bear on a bike.
It just didn't seem natural.
I mean, they're nasty, horrible things that were there.
It was part of how you had to deal with it.
I mean, was it hard to cope with that?
Did you look back and think you wanted to fire back at some stage or?
Oh, you know, you can't help getting your feelings hurt when you think, well, then it's then.
But then this person doesn't know me.
They're just, you know, creating a part for me.
They've got some narrative and this is just a highlight that I don't know what I'm doing.
But I did say to someone, you know, I always rode a bicycle pretty well.
And so I think you just got to put it in perspective.
And I just stopped listening to that and saying, would you really take that opinion about anything else in your life?
Like even what car to buy or what to get in the supermarket?
Do you think a person's opinion matters on things so mundane as that?
Then why do you think their opinion matters on you as a person when they don't know you?
Which is a great bit of a life lesson to share, isn't it?
Because that, you know, with the.
Advent of social media and our youth now, Peggy, who are bombarded with this on a daily basis.
You can find a skill like you just described then.
And it's so true, isn't it?
I mean, really, someone that doesn't know has no history or why would you even consider taking that on board?
But it's it's easier said than done.
Perhaps a little bit more public on that.
Peggy was 2016 and the famous infamous challenge of your board.
And there was a group and there was some, you know, heavy.
Hitting high profile past players that were part of that, that wanted to take over the board just before the success took place.
You went on to win three of the next four premierships.
You won the premiership the next year.
And part of their mission was they were going to sack the coach, Damien Harwick.
Have you ever had the time to ponder and look back and think what would happen if they had have succeeded at that time?
Oh, well, you know, it's all speculation.
But we had a lot of.
Things going on behind the scenes.
There was momentum building.
We sort of had had a strong feeling or almost, I would say, knew that 2016 was going to be a difficult year for the football department and for us to take that next step.
Because we we had gotten into final three years in a row.
You might recall we didn't win any.
We thought, well, this is probably about as far as unless we make some changes to personnel.
But this is about as far as we could go.
But the one thing we knew and we took a lot of time to think about this as a board.
And we got lots of input and analysis from Brendan and Dan Richardson was head of football at the time.
And the two of them analyzing, is the coach the right person?
And the one thing we did know is he was the right coach.
So there are other things to change.
But that's one of the things that always surprised me around any kind of sport is if you change the coach, we'll all be OK.
You know, it's this sort of one person makes all the difference.
The coach is very important.
Important person.
But that's not going to guarantee success.
So we were committed to finding the things that needed to be changed rather than just changing stuff and finding out afterwards.
Oh, that was the good part.
We've changed a good thing.
And that's that's not right.
So I guess with spec speculating, we didn't know we would win in 2017, but we thought it was coming together.
And then Damien is, you know, has been reported, went to Harvard and did a lot of work on leadership himself.
And how he could be a better leader and came back and decided it was going to be fun and play to your strengths and all those things that now seem to be across football everywhere.
But I think it was him deciding the kind of leader he wanted to be and having some additional tools on personal development, because so much of football and sport had been about professional development.
You know what the latest gadget, what's the latest training technique?
But the real.
Success is often those connections and those personal relationships.
And and and the course that Damien took was helping him identify when was he at his best and how far is that off what you've been doing?
So so that made a big difference.
But back to your original question, I don't think any of us.
Well, we wouldn't have been there as a board.
I doubt that we would have had a CEO who would have stayed and Damien would have been gone and we would have been starting all over again.
Because I kept thinking if we every five years we change, we'll always be starting all over.
And at some point you've got to stop starting all over because you've got to figure out what's good and what you can build on.
And and so we brought in some new people in administration.
We brought in some new assistant coaches.
Damien applied himself in a different way.
Trent Cotchen was maturing as a captain.
And and then we had a great trade season.
And got.
Out of the the core of a of a good team and some position.
So there were a lot of things that had to come together, but we were working on them.
And there are things that you can talk about until they come to fruition.
And for example, we were already talking to Neil Baum.
And so he came in to assist us and, you know, as a champion Richmond player.
And but there were lots of things going on.
And I thought if this happens, then we'll be gone and they'll have to deal with all the change.
That's going to happen.
And it's really hard to come in with this wholesale board changes when you don't have the corporate history about what's what what's been tried before and what didn't didn't work.
So so I don't know for sure what would happen, but it wouldn't have looked like our twenty seventeen, eighteen, nineteen to twenty.
It would have been a different thing.
And in effect, I believe starting all over.
Yeah, and I think it's great credit to your leadership and to Brendan's leadership at the time, as you said.
Probably the history of your football club in the thirty seven years after the previous premiership was that it did change every five years.
And I find this fascinating conversation for you, this obsession in sport around sacked the coach, sacked the coach.
We frame a market at the start of the year on which coach is going to get sacked first, Dan.
Where's the pressure?
Yeah.
And you think these are people, well, you know, and you see it and you think, what if every CEO in the country got ranked every January?
But which CEO is going to make it to the to June?
Who's going to be gone?
Who's who's vying for that job?
But but also with twenty sixteen, you know, the lawyer in me came out as well and it's like I've been elected to do a job.
And if someone else gets elected to do this job, I will.
Well, we'll all leave.
And there's an election every year and three three positions turn over on the board.
If you run for election and you get elected, we'll work together.
But the lawyer in me went.
I can't legally even turn over my office to you.
So there was a bit of go on, get your legal advice and run for election.
And no one ever ran for election.
And I love, you know, going back to Brennan's quote about you, you didn't get angry.
She got determined.
And and we just saw a little piece of that then.
And, you know, for all the people that love the Richmond Football Club, which is tens and tens of thousands, it's been a golden era.
And you can say and I love just the strategies and finding out.
And where to make change, not change for change sake.
And, you know, and also like the empathy of the people.
We know those people.
A lot of them face ridiculous scrutiny and pressure.
And we've seen horrible outcomes for for senior coaches in this indigenous game we play in Australia.
It seems a bit out of and out of hand at times.
I love Peggy that I never hear even when you it sounds like you're fired up.
You don't ever say anything negative.
I can't you know, my research going through, I was looking for some moment where you might have said, you know what?
I've had enough of that person.
I mean, is that is that your upbringing?
Is that your nature?
Or it's it's it's a brilliant practice.
Oh, I say plenty negative, maybe just not on the record.
I mean, to me, but I also sort of think, well, people have said plenty of negative things about me and I don't want to be one of those people.
People said a lot of wonderful things about me, too.
And I think, you know, I think everyone's mother said to them, if you can say something good, don't say anything at all.
And maybe that sunk in.
But.
I think it's better to be silent than to say something negative and then find out that you've said the wrong thing or you've hurt somebody unnecessarily or it's not really who wants to battle something out in the media or in a public kind of way.
So, so, no, I, I, I can't believe that you look to see if you find something negative, I said, but but it's been it was a pretty good experience.
It's been a pretty good run.
So, you know, there wasn't a lot of negative to talk about.
It was an amazing, amazing period of time.
And can I ask you, how does an American born lawyer who moved to Australia fall in love with this unique, strange sport?
You always find when I'm talking to Americans, it's the hardest sport in the world to describe.
The Americans don't tend to get Australian rules football.
And what what made you love it so much?
Well, I've always loved sport, you know.
Where I grew up, it was so remote and so poor, and there would be like one field for gridiron and basketball and baseball in the springtime and all that.
But, you know, it's like small towns anywhere.
The big social element of those small towns is sport and the church.
And so even though girls weren't allowed to play any of those things and there wasn't space for them to play,
it was, you know, predominantly boys growing up.
I loved, you know, I was the tomboy.
I loved playing.
I was a pretty good quarterback.
I like kicking the ball at basketball.
I loved my dad.
It was just me and my sister.
But my dad played as a softball pitcher in the local leagues until he was 50.
And so so I was the one that went along with him to do a lot of those things.
And even growing up, I wrote a column for the university newspaper on.
Girl sport and, you know, who had played and all that sort of thing.
So I just loved it.
And and even though I was never an athlete, I always went to everything.
You know, I was a great spectator and I'm still a great spectator.
And so when I moved here and, you know, I live with inside of the MCG and I always have and I live in Richmond.
And so I picked Richmond as my team and because everyone seemed to have one.
And that's what everybody talked about.
Yeah.
Talked about all the time as their team and the results.
And so I thought, well, I got to have a team.
And so Richmond was just coming out of the Save Our Skins campaign.
And and and people would say to me, oh, you should have been here when they were good.
And I thought, oh, they'll come good again.
I didn't know I'd wait another 30 years.
But that was sort of, well, once you pick it.
And then I went to first match the the what was then the new Great Southern Stand had just opened.
And it was an April afternoon.
It was gorgeous.
And just to see how big the ground was and because I listened on the radio, but I hadn't been to a game and and I just loved it.
I loved the fact that it was such a big part of the community of Melbourne.
And and so I joined a tipping competition to force myself to learn a bit more about the game.
And and then I just became a sort of priority to get to the game.
So maybe it was a relief from, you know, being a partner in a law firm.
And having that that, you know, a lot of people find their the sort of relief of of going to a sporting event is a is is just part of what you need to manage the sort of stress of your job.
But that I just loved it and started doing more and more and and realized that over time that if you paid more, you got better class and membership and you got a better seat.
And if you paid even more, you could go to these auctions and buy things.
And so I remember one of the first auctions.
I went to I bought dinner with the captain and coach, and it was when Campbell and Danny Frawley and we did that for three years.
And so I became very good friends with them and, you know, it was very sad about Danny a couple of years ago and and all that.
But so it just and I thought, oh, they're nice people and and I enjoy this and and then I wasn't on the board at that time.
And then I went on the board and got a bit more distance from from that.
But I still hear from Wayne, you know.
And Sarah Campbell quite a bit.
That's what I love, Peggy, the community of of anything, I suppose, and I picture myself, you know, perhaps going the other way and dialing into what life would have been like in West Virginia.
I suppose you try and find community, don't you?
And that's the community I've grown up in.
And you mentioned those names where we're all close.
You know, Wayne's an incredible person.
We had some good rivalry in our time on the field and loved Danny and working with with Danny.
And so it's, you know, from you.
I love it.
It's you come to town, you move into Richmond randomly and, you know, you end up being Melbourne into the year.
You end up now as the as the Commonwealth Games organizer for the city of Victoria in 2026, the chancellor of MIT University.
It's a it's a it's a great contribution you've made to come into a foreign community.
You must have incredible pride in what you've done because it's a it's a fascinating and an amazing contribution.
Peggy, I wanted to.
I love talking to different leaders.
There's about what we think are really common traits for leaders in different settings.
And you've brought such a unique perspective to to the world that you're in.
And we think one of those dimensions that we start with, it's hard to ignore is a sense of self-leadership.
It's hard to be a leader of someone else unless you've got that sense of self-leadership.
Does that resonate with you?
Yeah, I over time, it's when people ask me questions like this, because usually when you're going about your day to day,
life, you don't reflect on these things.
But but over time, I think that self-awareness about who you are is what you really bring to the leadership role.
And if you're trying to be somebody else, then you're never going to really succeed because it's not you.
It's not who you are. So I think that self-awareness, that idea about what do you want to do with?
This leadership role, why do you want to be a leader?
I think coming back to even the basic motivation about what is this?
What do you think leadership is? Why do you think it's something that you want to be attached to?
As we all know, having a title doesn't make you a leader.
We know a lot of people who have a title and nobody follows them.
I often say, you know, the first thing about being a leader is do you have any followers?
And I think that comes from that self-awareness about are these people with me or are they not or why?
What am I trying to do?
Yeah.
What am I trying to achieve and am I communicating because communication, I think, is important, but listening, I think, is really important.
And it's all those self-awareness about the traits that galvanize people to want to join in whatever you're trying to, whatever goal you're trying to achieve.
But I think it all starts with that self-awareness about who you are.
And that means some things you need to work on if you want to achieve certain things.
But to listen to the feedback.
And to listen to the feedback that you're getting about, but I often just think, why do you want to be a leader?
Why do some people want it more than others?
Why do some think they are a leader when they aren't?
Why do we just naturally go to some people for guidance who may not think of themselves as leaders?
But I think if you have a real sense of yourself, you can tell whether people are with you or not.
And it all sort of goes back to you got to have some followers.
Yeah, it's a great thought to share, and I appreciate you doing that.
And we're really passionate about that sense too, the title, Don't Make Leadership At All.
And you can be on your first day and have as big an impact in a place as someone who's been there for 20 years just by the nature of what you bring.
And I think for us, that sense of not having to wait to have an impact as well is really important.
And I love the way you described that, that sense of self-awareness.
And I think moving on to, we see people in positions like yours are really conscious of how they positively impact others in their environment on a daily basis.
And that's a thought that they think of regularly.
How have you gone about positively impacting others?
Well, a bit of it's what we've already been talking about is what's natural to you.
I think also that constructive criticism is much more helpful.
I think that's a good point.
It's much more helpful that you want to help people get better at what they do to understand what you're trying to do.
So I think the positivity is helping people find out more about themselves and about their capabilities.
It doesn't mean that you stick with things that aren't working, but that you give people a chance and that you feel you've been fair.
And I remember early on when I had, I was a partner in a law firm,
and I had to,
accept the responsibility of some people aren't going to work out and some people on my team I'm going to have to have those terrible conversations with.
And I thought, if you can put your hand in your heart and say, you know, you've been fair and they're going to be no surprises because if it's me, I'd want to know where my shortcomings were along the way.
And I was given a chance to fix it and it could be this job isn't for everybody.
But I think that's part of helping people develop and helping them understand that, perhaps,
what they're doing isn't their real strength and they need to look somewhere else.
So I think it goes back to being somewhat easy to get along with, not getting angry at people for something that is usually about you more than about them.
And I think that we all like to work with people that seem to like us.
Yeah, great, great answer.
And I love your description is that sometimes you have to make hard decisions when you're in positions.
And you've done that all your life in the legal firms you work with, I'm sure.
But often if you do that with empathy and kindness and a sense of fairness, it's a very different way to go about it rather than, you know, some of the brutal environments that we've all seen and decision makers that don't have empathy.
We know the lasting effect of that.
Creating and sharing a vision in a clear way is a dimension of leadership we're really seeing as a common trait.
That's played out for you a lot.
I mean, we've talked a lot about the Richmond Football Club.
It was a really clear vision.
And there was some, you know, the industry sort of mocked a bit of that vision at the start.
I remember Brendan coming out and talking about premierships and, you know, large membership bases.
I mean, how have you gone about that in your life?
I said, whoa, Brendan, whoa.
Think about that a minute.
I think he took us with him too.
So, anyway, sorry I interrupted you.
No, that's good.
I mean, was there some  he came out at the time.
He said, we want to have 75,000 members and win two premierships in a pretty short space of time.
And the industry laughed at Richmond, didn't they?
I mean, were you a little concerned at the time or?
Well, I knew Brendan didn't think they were just words.
You know, this wasn't  but at the same time, we needed something to energize, something to get all the Tiger Army who had been very loyal.
People talk about it.
They haven't been.
We weren't winning anything and we still kept getting record memberships.
So, we needed something to spark a new Richmond.
And this was something for us to work toward.
And we talked about it at a board level and measured ourselves all the time.
And, oh, well, you know, we've retired dead a year earlier than we'd planned.
And we've made finals, but we haven't made  you know, gone beyond it.
And membership kept creeping up.
And I remember the first year when I was on the board, I think it was about 20 years.
I think it was about 2006, I guess.
We actually made like a $4,000 profit.
And it was like, oh, my goodness.
We actually have made money.
So, those little victories along the way.
But I knew that Brendan came in as the new CEO, Steven Wright having retired for health reasons.
And Brendan came in and very much wanted to jumpstart.
Jumpstart the club again.
And he talked to us and walked through it.
And it's like, well, we're going to give it a go.
We're going to try this.
And then after we were  we did pretty well in the first five years of his 10-year plan.
And then it was sort of parked, you know, and nobody really thought about, oh, that was a 10-year plan.
And then when we're coming up for our third premiership and if we win this, we have won three premierships in 10 years when we started from nothing.
And hadn't even been in finals in, I think, 11 years at that point.
So, it was  yeah, I think it was necessary.
And it made us all have a lot of energy about trying to achieve something for the club.
Yeah, and 100,000 plus members is the current number.
It was  yeah, as you said, it was a vision that was shared really publicly, wasn't it?
And you felt when it started happening.
Great credit to you.
And backing in the CEO to fulfill it.
It's been an amazing success story all around.
We see curiosity as a common word when I sit down and talk with different leaders, Peggy.
And through that curiosity, they're constantly learning and developing themselves.
Does that resonate as well with you?
Well, it does.
But I'm one of  I'm someone who loved being a student.
And it's sort of a  you know, you get to the point you're not doing formal education in the same way.
But you're meeting new people that, you know
You're meeting new people that you learn from if you let yourself.
And I think that goes back to understanding a bit more about the kind of person that you are.
And I think that my curiosity about people and places is really sort of the theme of my life.
And I often think that if I didn't take on some of the jobs that I have now, that I'd love to go work on a Ph.D. in something.
And everything is just wonderfully  I'm curious about it.
It's just a wonderful experience to meet someone new, to get the new ideas.
And whether  I'm sort of more in the arts kind of thing rather than science.
But I can be fascinated by science too.
But I just think to meet someone who writes something wonderfully or a musician who does something that creates beauty in the world.
And how little we know  or how little I know about that whole process.
And who these people are.
And more and more sometimes this information overload is how many people are doing things out there that would be exciting if we knew more about it.
And so every day I learn something new from someone or about someone.
So I think that that means you're never stale.
That means you never feel like you've arrived.
And that you can continue to be excited about new experiences.
Peggy, we see
Lee is really conscious of how they communicate with clarity.
You've got some big roles.
Chancellor of RMIT.
A big job with the organizing committee for the Commonwealth Games in 2026.
There's some high public profile roles again that you've had.
How have you gone about your communication?
Well, both of those are  because of my curiosity about them.
It's not as if  it's sort of like walking into Richmond and going,
oh, I want to learn about this.
Both of those roles when I was approached to sort of assess my interests, I thought, are you sure?
I don't know anything about this.
And then, again, it was a bit like the Richmond role is, well, you don't have to have spent a lifetime in it to understand it.
And so take your time.
You're going to learn a lot.
You're going to meet a lot of new people who are doing a lot of different kinds of things.
There's going to be good times and bad times.
But, again, going back to I think I am the kind of person that can understand the big picture eventually.
I'm not going to understand the minutiae of anything.
But I do like working with people.
And I often have said if you don't like being on committees, you don't want to be on a board because they're just committees.
And there's one decision that's made, and we all have to get to the point that we can agree with that.
And I think I can do that.
I've always enjoyed working with groups of people to achieve things.
When I was a lawyer, I had a great team of people and we're still friends, even though I don't practice law with any of them anymore.
So I think that all of those kinds of elements go into running anything at that board level.
I'm not the CEO or the CFO or the execs who have to do that.
I'm not the execs who have to know the intimate detail.
What I have to do is to get people to come together and make decisions, as I said, hopefully make more good decisions than bad decisions.
And that leads to the last dimension I wanted to talk to you about, which is the sense that collaboration now is something that leaders are really conscious of and seek out.
You mentioned that a board is effectively collaborative.
When you get on a committee, you have to be collaborative.
How important has that been to you?
Well, I think it's what interests me in being on boards.
And the ones who, the boards that function the best doesn't mean that everybody agrees, but everybody has matured discussions and brings something to the table about another perspective, as we were saying earlier.
So I just think it's great to work with a group of people and to go in with one point of view and through discussion find out that, oh, well, that wasn't the only point of view.
Right.
And now I need to think about it some more.
And if you're on a board that has those people with those attributes, some days you just think, gee, we've done good work today.
And sometimes if you're spending all your time on a board or a committee working with difficult people who don't have that same idea that it's a collective decision, you realize that it can really hold the organization back.
So it's a fine line to walk between.
Groupthink, which no one wants, and then having people who are just there to argue all the time because only their view is the legitimate one.
But I enjoy it.
I have some, I've been on some great boards and RMIT and the Commonwealth Games are shaping up to be great boards too.
I'm really enjoying my time there.
Peggy, ask these questions to all the community.
To all the great people I've had the privilege of sitting down with.
And I've loved this conversation.
I always feel like I learn an enormous amount about your positivity and patience and clear thinking and calmness.
It's inspiring.
Who has been the greatest leader in your life?
Well, I think all the public figures.
I don't know.
You know, when you think and always think, well, that's what we see.
But.
But I guess if I would think of who's inspirational in that way, I've been on a number of not-for-profit boards.
And when I see what people do with so little to make changes in society, I think, no, there's a real leader.
Unsung for the most part.
Working really hard on behalf of people in need or a cause that needs to be addressed because, you know, we'll all be better off for it.
Those are the people that I really just applaud.
You know, and think that I would like to be regarded as that kind of person.
Someone who just works hard for the cause.
You're mine.
Initially, I felt Peggy went to a few public inspirations.
Was there any, you know, and was there anyone specifically in the social venture and the not-for-profit space?
Is there any names that spring to mind?
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
No more recommendations, Mmmm.
I'm on the Board of Women's Housing that builds social housing for women who are destitute,
women in domestic violence situations, women coming out of prison.
And the CEO of that has dedicated her life to improving the lot of women in those dire
circumstances.
you'd never know who it is but who she is but she works tirelessly for that and then sometimes I
look back and think about in those small coal mining towns and my mother was one of these people
the volunteers who just make things work and who never did it for themselves but to but to benefit
someone else and whether that was you know volunteering to put together Christmas baskets
were needy families I used to say to my mother people would have thought we were a needy family
she said but we were so much better off than everybody else so she would be the one going
around and helping everybody and getting somebody to drive them to the doctor and getting all those
sorts of things and I think we really rely on volunteers and people like that who are community
minded to to achieve so much in this world that that we take it for granted sometimes and most
of them are women.
Yeah great credit for you for uh for giving that a a positive mention in the way you did and you're
right isn't it's the unsung heroes that make our whole community thrive and and the as you said the
women element to that is uh is off the charts uh in the spirit of collaboration we're really
obsessed with uh collaboration and you've got so many diverse interests and uh so many different
roles is there been one person who's got to collaborate with them on you know whatever it
might be you mentioned a PhD before or a musician.
Or uh another lady you've thought that's the person I know I could do something special with
is there any can I prize a name out of you Peggy?
Well uh this is sort of uh way out there but I would love to have been a collaborator with the
Beatles. I don't know the the recent um I think it was last year the documentary Get Back uh the
long where they're in the studio and the way they made great songs again it's that miracle of
creativity that I have none of that.
And if maybe you can collaborate and maybe bring some of that along um there's uh and and figures
in history I mean I would think um I don't know if it's collaborate but to make change like the
suffragettes who are but look what look what they faced and look what they did and uh and now we
find too often people take the vote for granted where people all over the world are still dying
for the right to vote.
So so that's.
That's sort of a bit of a that way but I would love to have been able to learn how to play the
guitar and been there in the in the Beatles sessions when they were putting all their albums
together.
That would be a special uh collaboration to to sit on wouldn't it?
Not so serious but I I would um have been in awe.
Well Peggy thank you so much for taking the time and uh and for your contribution to
community that served me incredibly well from a young age and and
being on the other side of the fence and growing up and really wanting to be in that from uh from
the age of of five to see what you've been able to do and the the leadership and the you know as
as Benny Gale said so uh eloquently you you've shown a different way a a humble and a a caring
and a kind way to achieve success and I think it's a great lesson that has been left behind for
for lots of us in in an industry that can be combative at times to to the extreme so thanks
Peggy for uh for all of your your efforts and your work.
Your achievements and your and your humble successful way.
Oh you're welcome Luke nice to chat with you.
Thank you for listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast powered by temper a mattress like no other
and to make sure you don't miss an episode click subscribe wherever you get your podcasts.