How do you make a decision earlier in your life of where you want to be
and how do you follow that passion?
G'day, it's Luke Darcy.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership both on and off the field
has been a lifelong passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective
and have had the privilege of working with thousands of leaders
in education, sport, industry and the arts
that have helped shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership
where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
I sat down with the founder of One Earth, Lindsay Boyd,
to chat about adapting your passions amongst the pandemic,
finding your purpose in wanting to make a difference
in a new platform that creates an entirely new form of collaboration.
Our next guest needs the full introduction
because it's an extraordinary life that she has lived.
She's a visionary leader.
Lindsay Boyd is a woman known for building famous brands
and speaking on the world stage
about her passion for leadership.
She's here to create the face of the modern world.
She's also a best-selling author, serial entrepreneur
and founder of Bob, which is about to undergo a rebrand.
I want to ask her about that.
By age 24, Lindsay had set up and sold two businesses.
Her second company was sold to Caterpillar
and her third business, Surgery,
championed some of the most well-respected brands known today.
Lindsay now works in the enterprise market.
She's teaching entrepreneurs how to build a famous brand
for bigger valuation and to scale to make impact in the world,
changing the way modern business,
operates and creating the face of modern business.
She launched the first purpose-led platform, Bob Earth,
which will soon be One Earth in 2020,
which connects people to unite, learn to grow and trade
with positive impact in the world.
It is an extraordinary life that she has lived
and very excited to speak to Lindsay Boyd.
Welcome, Lindsay.
Thank you for having me today.
I'm excited to be on your show.
Thanks for your time.
You were born in Leeds and doing some research
just to find a bit of your background.
You've got two older brothers, I understand.
Can you describe yourself?
We've been from a rag-trade family with grandparents
who worked in fashion and manufacturing,
even though your father was a dentist.
But I think the first place to start is at the age of 15,
you decided school wasn't for you.
That was a pretty big call, Lindsay,
to go home and tell the parents.
How did that go down?
Yeah, well, as you can imagine, my dad was a dentist,
so he came from an educated, you know, university background.
And at the age of 11, I stood in the kitchen with my mum
and I said to her,
do you know what, I'm thinking of leaving school, mum.
And my mum was like, Lindsay, what are you going to do with your life?
And I said, well, I think I'm going to be as big as Oprah Winfrey.
And my mum looked at me and really like I had two heads
and I'd lost the plot at this point.
And at the age of 15, I did leave school with no qualifications
and I had this mad, deep, burning desire
that I could do something impactful in the world.
And I'd seen Oprah.
And she'd inspired me to believe that I could build something,
not knowing what that was.
And so I did leave school.
And at the age of 18, I started in retail.
You heard that I came from the rag trade
and my grandparents, both sides were tailors.
And so I bought my first retail shop in Leeds,
in the north of England.
And I brought diesel and replay into the north of England.
And I don't know if there's any like big football,
but I had a very famous footballer's wife work for me.
And it gave me my first taste of what celebrity and fame
could do for your shop,
because literally my clothes used to walk out of the shop.
And so it was a very successful shop.
And then I sold it at 21 when my friends were going to university.
And I set up in my second business,
which was the footwear manufacturing business.
And we spotted a trend in the market for fashion sneakers,
and I then, we sold 150,000 pairs of shoes in the first season.
So at the age of 21,
I had a business turning over nearly 5 million pounds.
And we had seven distributions set up around the world,
had the shoes in the design museum in England,
in London, next to Evian bottles.
And as you heard, I sold the business to Caterpillar
when I was 24.
So it was a bit of a crazy journey for me,
but I did it.
It was a great journey for me.
My first early years of my life,
because by the age of 24,
I was onto my third business when my friends were still at university.
Remarkable story all around.
And there's so many places to go there.
I've got to ask you two questions.
One, the fact that I love that,
isn't it?
I'm going to be as big as Oprah is a,
is a profound thing to say as a teenage girl or boy or anyone.
And then who was the footballer?
Who was the footballer's wife that sold the clothes?
I can't reveal the name,
but he was a very look,
just remember Leeds United.
It was Gary McAllister,
Gary Speed,
Vinnie Jones,
Eric Cantona.
It was all the biggies.
And so look,
I knew all those guys because one of them were one of the wives worked for me.
So I was 18 and I,
you know,
it was a crazy time.
Some of the biggest names ever in the round ball game,
you know,
Vinnie Jones and Eric Cantona,
who can forget his,
his influence as well.
So you,
you had a,
an inkling in terms of what a celebrity and,
and profile could do,
but you must've had incredible self leadership at that age to be able to work your way through the complexity of buying and selling businesses and learning on the job.
Where did that come from within you?
Look,
um,
both my sides of my family were,
were entrepreneurs.
So,
um,
you know,
my grandpa on my grandparents side,
my dad had his own company.
My brothers have got their own company.
So nobody really,
and either side of my family had ever worked for anyone else.
And I think it's just inbuilt,
in me,
that kind of drive and determination.
And I've always said,
you don't have to be the cleverest or the smartest to be the best.
And you really need that grit and determination and that vision.
And when everybody and everything is failing around you,
it's that grit and determination that you get up and you pick yourself up off the floor and you continue on.
It's a great term.
Great.
Is it a brilliant book too?
That's Angela Duckworth wrote a book about grid and studied,
uh,
the data of that term.
It's a,
it's worth reading.
And,
and clearly if you've done what you've done in that space of time,
you must have been able to cope with and push through,
uh,
some challenges and hurdles on the way.
Do you look back on it?
And was it,
was it fun?
Was it stressful?
Was it a bit of the,
all the above?
Okay.
So my second business,
the footwear business was one of the most stressful periods of my entire life.
I was 21 to 24.
I had no mentor.
Um,
I had to learn how to set up,
things like letter of credits and foreign exchange set up distribution channels.
We had two huge distributors in Japan.
I was manufacturing the shoes in Korea.
I was 22 in a factory in Korea with all men.
And,
um,
and then obviously we were selling these shoes all around the world.
So I was incredibly stressed.
Um,
but at the same time,
it was probably one of the steepest learning curves I've ever had.
And when I,
when I transitioned into my third business,
um,
which was a business that I then transitioned all my knowledge into building other
people's brands.
I started with a man called Mark Newsome and you may know his name because he
designed the,
I watch for Apple,
great Australian designer,
but I came with Mark to Sydney for the Olymp for the millennial.
When he did the Sydney opera house,
I was with him and I traveled around the world with him.
I launched his car and his book and his watch and his bike and everything with him.
He was a fantastic guy.
And,
um,
and then when I transitioned my knowledge as well into a brand called Pringle of Scotland,
that was a golfing brand.
And I brought it back to be a brand on Bond street,
which is one of the most famous streets of London.
Um,
I brought in David Beckham.
I brought in Sophie Dahl.
I did some big celebrity projects and turn the business around.
That was when I really made my name in the game because I kind of worked with Mark Newsome.
And I turned around and renovated this brand Pringle of Scotland.
And I did a big collaboration with a brand called dry shot and come to gas on.
And I started to make my,
my name in the game from building my other business stride,
which was the footwear brand.
People started seeing me then as building other people's businesses.
Yeah.
I want to get to,
to all of that.
You wrote the book brand.
You wrote the brand famous and a bestselling book and your business is business of brand.
That,
that,
that is you.
I suppose there's a question that is nagging me at the moment because you're,
you're now a mother of two.
What do you do if one of your kids at 15 comes to you,
Lindsay,
and says,
uh,
not for me,
I'm out of school.
How do you handle that one?
Look,
I thought about this a lot because,
you know,
I was very driven,
um,
and very determined.
And with that,
you know,
comes a bit of a,
not a rebel girl,
but you know,
she's got her own mind.
And,
you know,
I've definitely got two kids,
particularly my daughter,
but the apple hasn't fallen too far from the tree.
I have to say,
and,
you know,
I loved performing as well.
So acting,
singing,
and that was the other route that I wanted to go down.
So look,
if either one of them comes to me at that age,
I will let them follow their dreams and their journey if they wanted to leave school,
but they have to work and they have to either go and do work with someone,
to learn a skill or a trade or,
and they have to learn business.
So they have to learn how to grow and scale a company.
And then,
you know,
I'm a big believer in people following their dreams and doing what they want to do in life.
Lindsay,
the Empowering Leaders podcast is really based on this premise that we're passionate about is this shift in leadership.
As we see from the old way of hierarchy and command and control into this more collaborative and self-reflective approach to leadership,
which to me reflects people exactly like you.
We've been talking to you and I look at your life and I see someone who's picked trends ahead of time and from the youngest possible age and even bringing brands like diesel and replay down to leads that I'm assuming back then weren't well ahead of really where they ended up becoming.
You're now in this space of heading businesses towards purpose.
And you say the words purpose is the new currency,
not just commercial gain.
What are you saying?
What's the trend that you're so passionate about in terms of purpose?
About 12 years ago,
I started really looking at building businesses,
not just for commercial gain,
but for commercial and cultural gain.
I've been building businesses for over 27 years at that point.
And I recognize that when I was building my businesses with my third business and I built some of the most famous brands on the high street,
look for 19 years,
I worked with pretty much,
everyone from celebrities,
very famous celebrities to very famous brands,
G star,
super dry,
Wrangler,
Lacoste,
Aldo,
Urban Outfitters,
all these brands that everybody recognizes.
I either built brands,
renovated brands or refreshed brands.
And that we always talked about brand as your business,
not as a branding exercise.
So how you built out the whole of the business model end to end,
and then 10 to 12 years later,
I recognize that I couldn't do this anymore.
I couldn't just build businesses for commercial gain where people were lining their pockets,
but they weren't giving anything back to the world.
And so I moved out of the world that I'd worked in since the age of 18,
the world of famous brands and celebrities and consumer.
And I moved into the world of enterprise and in the world of enterprise,
my priority was,
I,
I would give people every single bit of knowledge that I knew on how to build
and grow and scale a business and increase the value and,
you know,
all the good stuff that comes with a commercial business,
but they had to lead with impact and they had to lead with purpose.
And it couldn't just be a marketing strapline.
It had to be driven into absolutely everything.
They do an ethical business model.
And what I saw 12 years ago was that purpose was going to be,
be the new currency.
The next generation,
our kids were going to want to build a business.
It wasn't going to be a business.
It was going to be around what they could do in the world.
So when I hung out with some younger kids and I,
and I actually got the privilege of speaking on stage to about 500 people with a
16 year old girl.
And she got up on stage and said,
I've got a sweatshirt t-shirt range,
and I'm working with Donna Karen,
the most famous,
one of the most famous fashion designers in the world.
And I said to her after,
how are you working with Donna Karen?
And she said,
well,
every time I sell a sweatshirt or a t-shirt,
I give a school uniform to somebody in a developing country.
And I said,
well,
how many of you,
those have you given?
And she said,
650,000.
Wow.
And so,
you know,
the trend even back then was the fact that our next generation,
our kids were going to lead with purpose and impact.
And we needed to,
you know,
we needed to,
we needed to transition our businesses,
to understand how to lead us into a new era of trade,
to be a guru,
but somebody that was able to be from a commercial and cultural space,
and be able to drive purpose into everything that they do.
Lindsay,
you're often talking about the next generation.
They really care about where a product comes from,
its carbon footprint,
and you know,
whether it was made in ethical,
and sustainable way and the businesses they work for,
the values are really important to this generation that you picked 12 years ago.
And effectively you're saying to businesses,
you know,
stop selling,
start building communities.
Is that a too succinct a way to describe it or not?
I did a very big interview for a very famous newspaper.
You can probably see it if you Google me and it was in the UK and I,
and I got quoted,
stop selling.
I was like,
I'm not going to start leading with the human response.
And during the pandemic and the recession,
it was exactly what I taught businesses to do.
I had over 2000 businesses globally come around me during the pandemic.
That was in the first 10 weeks because we had been teaching businesses over five and a half thousand businesses with my business.
In the business schools that we ran around the world.
And because we were teaching them how to lead with purpose, and impact,
and not the commercial sales side,
when the pandemic and the recession hit,
I actually had hundreds of businesses around me and I started saying to them,
stop selling and build communities,
lead with the human response.
And the businesses that were dropping 90 to a hundred percent in revenue.
I mean,
there was some scary times for some people started to record record sales,
not just from that year,
but from all the years that they were trading because they said,
I'm not going to do this anymore.
And they started to build communities and they started to actually put impact and purpose into these communities.
And when the world started to come back online again,
that was when they built loyalty.
They had they'd created leadership in their community,
not just in the business community,
but in their local communities as well.
We had a guy Sav in Australia.
If you Google him and go onto my,
it's YouTube channel,
you will be able to see Sav.
And he got himself on channel seven news for putting his arms around the community,
giving pizzas,
setting up an online TV,
YouTube channel,
and actually just helping the community rather than selling to them.
There's some fantastic stories in that,
in that space.
I was thinking of the thank you social enterprise that I'm not sure if you've seen their story.
It started with thank you water,
young Aussie called Daniel Flynn.
He was reading,
that four and a half thousand children around the world died daily due to waterborne disease.
And he decided to have a look at the bottled water market.
$140 billion globally annually is the bottled water market.
And he started with a thank you water.
And amazingly because of the community that he built,
he was able to go to the biggest two supermarkets here,
Lindsay and Coles and Woolworths.
And so his community demanded that thank you water be on their shelves and almost impossible to compete with the multi nationals that have got their products on those shelves.
But the community,
he won the day and he's since got out of bottled water because of the single use plastics part of it.
But that thank you brand and what it's been doing to,
as you said,
purpose driven organizations are having this incredible impact.
Is there other stories that spring to mind that you can share with us?
Well,
you know,
interestingly,
you spoke about Daniel and we in November,
as you know,
cause you were a guest at the summit,
we decided to run a 24 hour live stream summit and the United Nations,
opened it for us and we ran it for 24 hours.
And Daniel came and spoke at the summit and I had the pleasure also of interviewing Daniel and his story really laid laid a lasting impression for me.
But there's another gentleman that also spoke at my summit who I've now become a very good friend of David Katz and David Katz.
You all want to Google him.
He's from plastic bank.
And he is all about.
Turning plastic into gold.
And he has now has a mark.
You can see it.
Actually,
when you go into some retail shops,
they've got his plastic bank mark on their carrier bags.
People can trade their plastic in all around the world and poor and people that are underprivileged or poor,
they don't have enough money can go to the plastic bank and trade in their plastic for a digital currency.
And they make money from picking up rubbish.
Yeah.
Amazing success,
isn't it?
I mean,
the issue is,
you know,
we've got to get rid of plastics in our oceans and to as you said,
the brilliance of turning that into currency and digital currency.
David Katz,
as you said,
check out plastic bank.
It's it is fantastic and credit to you,
Lindsay.
I mean,
as you said,
you had this shift in yourself,
I suppose.
I'm not going to continue down the path of just commercialization and what you've done with your platform,
which is really shifting the world to use your language around purpose.
And I understand you're obviously the branding expert and you've changed now.
It's Bob Earth,
which was Bob standing for business of brand.
You're about to rebrand to one earth and that platform which I have had exposure to.
You've got a brilliant way of synthesizing what seems like complex ideas into really practical,
certainly benefited what we've been trying to do in the leadership space in a brilliant way.
Can you share with us a bit more about how that works and what this platform is all about?
Yeah.
So look,
I genuinely had an epiphany moment and I woke up one morning.
I was in Mallorca.
My in-laws lived in Mallorca.
And I and I said to my husband,
do you have a pen?
And I got up and I sat on a sofa for four hours and I drew out what I'd been gifted from above.
And it was a platform,
a purpose led platform.
And I drew the whole thing out.
I've still got all the drawings on my iPad and and I saw this vision of one earth and I just and the vision was to create this place.
One earth.
Which is now what I've rebranded to,
which was always what I saw when I when I sat down.
And it was a platform that you could connect people all around the world to unite and then they could learn together to grow and then trade with each other to impact change.
And so a few years,
it took me a number of years to get this platform live.
It was a gamified platform that I saw.
And it's an earth and on the earth you come on.
And you create an avatar and you build your own house and your house represents your business or you and you come on.
And instead of being a business saying I'm a commercial business,
everybody on the platform is talking about their purpose.
So we have people on there that's all about architecting your own health,
finding the cure for cancer in dogs and becoming the voice of women's wealth,
all different purposes.
And everybody's profile is their purpose.
On the platform,
as you go into the learning area,
you learn together in a classroom environment,
a bit like Google Classroom.
And in that classroom environment,
you understand people's purposes and you understand how to grow and scale your business.
And once you come out of the classroom and you're certified with your purpose,
then you can trade with each other.
And this is the fun part.
You can either trade time,
knowledge or money so you can just give somebody some of your time without anything in return.
You can share knowledge for the same value without having to pay for it or you can pay for somebody's service.
But every time you do that,
we give education to somebody that can't afford it.
And that's through our foundation.
And so we've been able to give hundreds of people actually during the pandemic as well that could never afford to come on.
And educate themselves the education because people have been able to support that.
And we've supported that through a bursary.
It's extraordinary.
And speaking of leadership,
it is an amazing,
I suppose,
ambition that you've got and you've created it already.
And there's a program that you run called Personal DNA that I want to talk to you about,
Lindsay,
which is,
again,
brilliant.
And I have to admit it challenged me and I've been through it because whenever someone spoke about personal brand,
I felt squeamish in the past.
It was like,
why would I,
be worried about that?
Why would I care what someone thinks of me?
But as you point out correctly,
we all Google each other now and we've got a digital footprint,
whether we like it or not.
And then you'd go through that nauseating experiment of actually Googling yourself.
Oh,
wow.
That's what people are saying about me as someone who didn't have a social media account for 46 years of his life,
but has joined in recent times.
And I suppose what it did,
the penny dropped with me to think,
well,
okay,
what do you stand for?
What is your purpose?
And how do you communicate that?
And if you're doing something purpose driven,
of course,
you want to communicate that.
I think in the past to me to always been,
why would I want to put a picture of myself out there?
Didn't necessarily sink in,
but talk,
talk us through your passion for this personal DNA and where you want to take it.
My passion came from my very first company,
that retail shop when I was 18 years of age and then drove through every single company because I've worked with building pretty large celebrities as well as businesses.
I recognised the power of fame.
And what that could do either for your business,
for your life,
for the world.
And then what I started to teach people was that fame was just a state of mind.
And it was the biggest limiting belief that people could do.
People would say,
I provocatively used to get on stage and say,
who wants to be famous?
And people would be like,
she's just asked me if I want to be famous.
Oh no.
You know?
And then,
and then what I'd say,
is who wants to be known in the world for making a difference?
And,
you know,
when I do these talks around the world,
sometimes 500 people in the audience,
I'd say 90% of the hands went up.
And then I'd say,
who wants to be known outside their industry for making a difference?
And I'd say about 70% of the hands went up.
And then I'd say,
who wants to be known in the world for making a difference?
And I'd say still about 50% of those hands would go up.
And so,
when I said to them,
fame is just a state of mind.
And I would specifically ask,
what do you want to be known for?
And how do you want to show up?
And at that point,
people would sit there and they would say,
what do I want to be known for?
Whoa,
nobody's asked me that question.
And then people started to recognize that you could build a profile around what you wanted to be known for.
And you could lead either,
your community,
your business,
society,
an industry,
or even the world into a new era.
And I always used to say to people,
look at myself as an example.
It's not necessarily the biggest people that end up being on the stage.
Everybody has a role to play in life.
And if you can really re-remember who you are,
why you're on this planet,
what you're here to do,
then everybody's role is important.
It's not,
it can be somebody that does something in their local community.
It can be somebody,
I have a beautiful lady,
Julie King,
and you look her up and she moved from having an agency to now shifting the whole of the travel tourism industry.
And people can,
when they get confidence,
when they believe in themselves,
when they believe I can,
if you understand what you want to be known for,
and how you want to show up,
then you can lead into a new space.
And look,
you know,
I turned it into a board game called the race to impact the world.
And I am teaching kids in my board game.
It comes out next year.
I'm teaching kids how to understand how to have a profile online and how that wants to show up.
Then how to build a profile around shifting an industry and buying impact businesses.
And then,
the game is all about becoming a guru,
creating a foundation and leading into a new era.
I know you've got a passion about the next generation and particularly in schools and sitting here in Melbourne,
Australia.
And unfortunately,
we've got the record as the most locked down city in the world through the COVID era.
And it has spawned an epidemic of eating disorders,
particularly in the teenage girl bracket.
It's horrible.
The numbers that are coming through,
are really tragic.
And as you know,
I've spoken to you about this before,
which is young girls not really understanding who they are and what they value and what they stand for.
It's not really taught at school.
And unfortunately,
now looking at these images that are unrealistic on your phone that we know of this perfect storm,
you're isolating young girls and then you're training them to their phone.
I suppose that to me,
I love the idea of teaching all of us,
you know,
what do you stand for?
What are your values?
What do you want to be?
Everyone has got that answer within themselves.
And I think that's what we need to do.
It's a brilliant idea to get it into schools.
I know you're passionate about that.
It's interesting.
Look,
I obviously,
you know,
and I didn't know you'd done my personal brand curriculum.
That's fantastic.
Thank you.
I'd love to speak about that offline.
Look,
you know,
I have a curriculum and I teach people how to not only build the business out,
but also build themselves out as a brand and as an asset.
And look,
I worked in the fashion industry for many years,
from the age of 18 to the age of 30,
to the age of 38.
And,
you know,
being a young girl in the fashion industry,
myself and my friends had eating disorders.
You know,
it was part and parcel really of being in the fashion industry.
And I recognize that young girl.
I can speak firsthand from that young girl.
And yet I didn't have social media around me then.
When we were growing up as young girls and I did work in the fashion industry and so forth,
there was enough pressure on being able to look the way
that you looked and be and perform and all the different things that come on.
And it's not just about young girls.
I have to say many boys now are in the same space.
It's both genders.
And I've seen a massive upsurge of boys as well in this space.
So what I recognized and one of my passions,
and obviously I've been teaching businesses,
but a huge passion of mine,
as you know,
is youth and kids predominantly because I left school at a young age.
And I felt a bit,
a bit let down by the schooling environment.
They didn't teach in the way that I think that they could teach now.
Like you've just said,
being able to empower kids in a different way.
And the second layer is that you've got these young girls and boys and they're on the internet.
And what I'm teaching them is,
and what I've taught my own kids and my son,
who's a very big sports person,
he's 13.
And as you know,
he's going,
he wants to,
his vision is to be a GB climber.
And I said to both my kids,
you can go on the internet,
you can have your own Instagram and so forth.
What are you going to be known for?
What do you want to show up as?
What are you going to post online?
It can't just be around synthetic fame.
I'm just going to post things and have a laugh online.
It has to be around what you care about.
And everybody's DNA is already in them,
as I described.
So somebody might be slanted more towards art or drama or,
you know,
sport or whatever it is that is inside them,
their DNA.
Then think about that and put that out into the world.
Think about what you're known for,
how you want to show up.
What do you stand for?
And then that way you start to craft your own brand,
even at the age of eight or nine,
and it sits with you.
And then as you evolve as a child into a young adult,
that DNA,
that strand will grow with you.
And then when people look at your profile online,
you will be the one that will get recruited quicker,
because people will see this confident person that's sitting
with their purpose and not just online because of synthetic
fame.
And, you know,
we all know what that does for our own self-esteem.
I love it.
It's such a powerful message of leadership,
talking leadership,
isn't it?
Finding your purpose and sharing that,
It's a lost art.
And I know it's something that you're,
you're personally doing a great job in,
in bringing that back to people,
whatever age it is.
And then by extension,
so I love the idea that it gives people a voice,
something we're passionate about in your work environment.
If everyone understands what their purpose is,
and if you can connect together and collaborate,
even in big companies,
isn't it?
It's a,
it's an opportunity,
isn't it?
If the people that work around,
you know what they stand for,
and you can find some common ground,
there's,
you know,
commercial channels that work well with that,
as well as making people happier because everyone understands,
where they're coming from.
Lindsay.
Interestingly that you've now touched on what I describe as brand culture.
So now we're into the employees that are all people that work inside
organizations.
And this is a real speciality that I work on.
I've recently just worked on a beautiful client of mine that I've worked with for
over three and a half years.
They're engineers and they came in my business school and they were,
you know,
sat there crossed arms.
I'm an engineer.
And that's what I am.
And I peeled back this onion,
peeled it back,
peeled it back and got this guy,
Gary,
bless him.
I know,
you know,
if you go on again,
my LB presents YouTube channel,
you will be able to watch his interview,
Gary Elliot would anyway,
he sat there and he went,
and I said,
Gary,
what is it?
You know,
You are,
what do you want to be known for?
I peeled back this onion and eventually I got into a space and he said,
okay,
we're here to engineer a better society.
And I went,
Ooh,
what does that mean?
And he went,
well,
we're all about revealing the unseen,
seeing the hidden asset.
But what we're really about is building impact into all our engineering.
So that goes down to the materials that we use.
And he talked to me about a community that he really cared about where they
designed this bridge.
And he said,
the bridge wasn't about just engineering.
The bridge,
but about connecting the two communities on either side of the bridge.
And I went,
that is so inspiring.
And we then looked at how to rebuild his business.
And I said,
what if you had a coworking space where you could have an Academy and
teach all your engineers that were coming out of college,
how to be impact engineers.
Anyway,
last week I went to his coworking space with the Academy and all the
engineers in it.
And he has created his Academy and he launched his first coworking space
three and a half years on.
But the project that I then started working with was all the people inside
his organization.
And I had 25 of them around me and eight weeks on a program.
And they all sat on the very first program.
We're engineers,
we're efficient.
That's what we do.
And by the end of the summer,
we're all working together.
And so,
at the end of the seven weeks,
I went into the coworking space and I ran the session with them.
And they all stood up at the front of the room for Gary.
And they announced their purpose.
Every single one of them.
I nearly cried because not only was that purpose around what they really,
truly cared about and every single purpose was different.
They were now running this as a campaign,
which we designed with them to go out externally into the market and talk
about what they were.
Known for.
They are now using it as a recruitment.
Videos so that they can recruit people in all around purpose.
Each one of them is designing their own purpose,
project off their purpose.
And they're driving this now through 180 people inside of their company.
They're running the project through every single person inside the company.
So it just shows you even engineers,
but sit there with arms crossed and I'm just an engineer.
And.
turn into massive purpose impact people. Worth looking up Elliot Wood and having a look at
the vision video that I know you were behind creating as well, Lindsay. So we'll put that
details in the show so you can check out transformation, isn't it? The stiff engineer
into a purpose-led organization is a fantastic story. There's a bracket of questions I want to
ask you, Lindsay, which we're seeing is a bit of a common thread of iconic leaders like yourself
and picking up the patterns and the habits. But what we're seeing is the dimensions of great
leaders like you who are really taking leadership into the 21st century. I want to start with self
leadership, Lindsay. What does that mean to you? Everything. And this is what I try and instill in
my kids because I've always been extraordinarily driven and self-leadership for me is the thing
that's got me to places when actually most things would fail.
And sometimes people look to other people to lead them. And that's that's OK. That's good as well. You know, everybody needs guidance and leadership and so forth. But your own intuition, your own belief, your own leadership, your own knowing, as I describe it, is the thing that will get you there in life.
And really, truly, if you listen to your gut, you know, your stomach, your third human brain, as you describe it, then that inner leadership that will drive you, you do know the answers.
People think they don't know. You do know the answers. You just need to look within.
That is a brilliant answer, Lindsay. And it's interesting. I've heard so many people on this podcast describe it in different ways.
We had a great author, Steve Biddle.
Talk about the super sense, he calls it.
Tuning into your super sense is where the great answers and intuition comes.
And other leaders talking about exactly that.
When they've gone away from listening to their gut instinct, that's when they've made bad decisions and finding a way back to there.
The other dimension we want to talk about is how you go about positively impacting others in your environment.
That's a great question.
Look, we've all been through a pandemic and a recession.
And I would say when the when the boat, you know, when you're in that boat.
Right. And it's rocky. And, you know, you know, for me, when you went through that pandemic and the recession and I had firsthand of having thousands of businesses around me that were in that boat, you know, and also my own business.
You know, my my own business was in that boat where I had to pivot very quickly to be able to support, you know, over 2000 businesses in 10 days.
When we.
We had business schools running offline, not online.
And so when you're in that space, you need to become you need to be confident and you need to really be lead from the front.
And that means but you still need to bring people with you.
That's the most important thing.
So that means that when you have confidence and you're going a certain direction and people are scared or they're feeling anxious about something or they're in fear.
You need to bring them into a space of love and into a space where they feel calm, where some people freeze.
They don't know what to do next.
And so in that space, when you're in a leadership space, really what you want to do is people feel assured.
They know.
Yeah, she's got it.
You're going in that direction.
This is what's happening right now.
There's a confidence.
There's an air.
But you also have people.
You have them around you and you bring people.
People with you.
That's the most important thing.
Now, I described you in the intro as a visionary leader, and you are certainly that.
And you have big visions, including the earth, the one earth that you're creating around really shifting the world.
They're big ambitions.
They're big visions.
How do you go about creating and sharing those visions?
Look, to stand in front of your mom at age 11 and turn around and say, Mom, I'm going to be as big as Oprah Winfrey.
And my mom and dad are not.
I'm not from that world.
You know, you know, my dad, you know, the academic, more academic space.
There's something innately in me anyway.
And I I have the gift of sight.
So I was born being able to see in a psychic space as well.
And so I've always been able to see what's coming up next or what's happening or trends or things that are future.
And, you know, that's that's a gift that I.
Was born with.
And so I have always said, and you'll have heard me say this.
I'm here to shift the world into a new era through the eyes of brands.
I believed that I was here to create a quiet revolution that was built from a space of love.
And think of this, the biggest quiet party that the world has ever seen.
And all of a sudden, one day we all pop out and go, surprise.
And my belief was that it's the small.
It's it's the it's the individual people.
It's my engineer.
It's my travel tourism lady.
It's my influencer.
It's my wealth person.
It's all these people that if we can have one earth with one billion purposes, then each person's purpose will lead us into a new era.
And I've always believed that you need world leaders, industries.
You need industry leaders, societal leaders, business leaders, community leaders.
You need all the different layers and they all come together.
And that was where to shift the world into a new era came from.
I've always been very good at being the woman kind of behind the brands.
The woman that's kind of the orchestrator, helping people to understand how to build, grow, scale a business, but also to impact change.
And also to be behind.
And teach them around how to be known, what that looks like.
And so if we all come together and make that positive change, then my whole thing around standing for the face of modern business and the face of the modern world means that everybody has the right to be seen and heard no matter where you live or the demographic that you live in.
You don't and nobody.
Everybody.
Doesn't have the right to be commercially successful.
You need to put work in that.
Everybody has the right to be on the same playing field, to be seen and heard.
So to create the face is all around everybody having a face and a modern world or a modern business means we're moving people from 20th century thinking to 21st century thinking, where people can genuinely become a guru or a guru.
A modern day person where it's more of the spiritual and the commercial and people are moving from competition to collaboration and they're coming together and shifting industry or society and they move from an I conversation to a we conversation where we can come and do this together.
Well, yeah, I think I just felt that vision and you couldn't have explained it any.
Better.
Clearly, you know your vision and you know how to share it.
That's a spectacular answer to clearly something that is just part of who you are.
We talk about curiosity a lot as a dimension of leadership that is clearly identified in leaders who are, to use your terminology, 21st century leaders and then curiosity as a way to approach learning and development.
How do you approach curiosity in your world?
Oh, isn't curiosity the crux of it all?
Isn't that the kind of cornerstone milestone?
Curiosity, creativity.
Do you know that creativity as a skill will move from number, I think it was like 22 to number three in the next 10 years?
Because curiosity and creativity is really all you've got.
And when you're curious and when you allow yourself to be in a creative,
creative space to get those juices flowing, then truly anything is possible.
And, you know, I sat there and when, you know, I was gifted with, you know, a vision down to say, create this one earth.
But, you know, I sat there and for a few years, people went, what you want to create an earth with three platforms in one, a community area, a learn area and a trade area.
And you want it to be gamified and you want it to have its own currency.
And it's like, you know, people think that you're mad.
And and so that curiosity and creativity is the thing that will drive you and lead you because it links with purpose.
And when you have that and you stick with that and you have a true belief that anything is possible, if you put your mind to it and then you can succeed, then, you know, hold on to curiosity is what I say, because that will get you into places that you may not have imagined.
Maybe didn't think was possible.
Yeah, beautifully said.
Again, I'm looking forward to your answer on this because I think you do it brilliantly.
And that is, you know, the area of communicating with clarity.
What are your thoughts on that?
I come from a comms background.
So what I always talk about is your language patterns.
And I believe that people stop themselves from getting to places because of the language patterns that they put around themselves.
So I can't.
Aren't limiting beliefs that are put in the way and people use language that actually people then hear from what's coming out of somebody's mouth and puts people off.
So what I always say to people is think about every word that comes out of your mouth and try and replace the word with a positive word.
So my kids will say, you know, I can't.
And they'll always laugh because they'll say.
I'll ban something for a week.
And I try and get them into a space of not using that word, but using a different word.
And if you have seven days of not using that word, but using a different word, your brain then re engages into a new space.
And that then links with positive thinking, because what you say is your actions of what you do.
So if I'm saying and I do this with myself.
I do this with my kids all the time.
I have a parking space.
Thank you.
Thank you, universe, for the parking space.
And then all of a sudden a parking space appears.
I'm putting a positive intention out to the world and then creating manifesting something to be to bring it into being.
If I'm constantly saying I'm bad, I'm not worthy, this, that and the other.
I'm never going to get a parking space.
I'm never going to get that job.
Then I'm just putting that out into the world.
So what you speak is what you make a reality.
Yeah, well said, isn't it?
It's incredible how powerful that is.
And then retraining those negative thoughts.
I think a lot of people get into that habit where you don't even realize that you are imposing negative thoughts on people around you.
And it becomes isolating in the end because people generally don't want to be around that too often, do they?
And you can retrain your brain.
And as you said, we're about this world of collaboration.
And we see collaboration and leadership as really what people.
Like you are doing brilliantly.
What do you think about collaboration?
Well, our whole thing and through one earth is all about moving people from competition to collaboration.
And it sits at the heart of our business model.
So genuinely, I believe that people, even in the purpose space, we're still saying my purpose.
This is what I stand for.
And actually forgetting that if you move from.
Just my purpose.
If you connect your purpose with somebody else's purpose, we call it the purpose footprints.
How do you connect your purpose footprint with somebody else's purpose footprint?
And then together you grow.
And when you move from collaborate from competition to collaboration, people have been in an old school mindset that, oh, no, they're the competition.
I can't work with them.
I can't let them see what I'm doing.
And actually our business model.
It's an open business model.
So we will reach out to people that are in the same space as us and look at it and go power in numbers.
How do we create and collaborate to be able to shift the world into a new era?
Because we know that when you bring people together, you'll make that happen.
And in industries, we now work with specific industries.
So we work with engineering, accounting, finance, travel, tourism, health.
We're manufacturing all the different industry sectors, and we're now bringing industries together.
So as I mentioned, Julie King, she's in the travel industry, and we're bringing 180 people advocates from the travel tourism industry, and they're all coming together.
We're teaching them how to switch over their business models to 21st century thinking to lead with impact and purpose.
But the main thing is that.
But they're all going to be taught how to campaign together.
And when you learn how to campaign together around a cause and a purpose, that's when you really make the biggest change.
Yeah, what an impact that will have.
You think of how affected the travel and tourism industry is.
And I love the work that you're doing in that space.
A couple of final questions for you that we've been asking regularly all the guests that have come on the Empowering Leaders podcast.
And the one I want to start with.
Who's the greatest leader in your life, Lindsay?
My kids.
Really?
Yeah, because when you watch your children and you watch them go through all the things that they go through, oh, my gosh, you learn so much about yourself from watching your children.
It's a great mirror, isn't it, Bec?
It's a great answer.
I always try and claim the, that's definitely me, that one.
That's definitely not me.
That's yours, Bec.
If we can pick.
The traits that come through.
You mentioned about the teenage years and, oh, my gosh, hold on to your hats.
That's what I would say.
They will be my biggest leaders and learners of that period of time.
And it's really coming up now.
Yeah, incredible, isn't it?
You do learn so much, don't you, through watching them grow and develop.
If you could collaborate with any person in the world, who would you collaborate with?
Elon Musk.
Why?
He's one of the most visionary.
He's one of the most visionary people that I have ever come across.
And I'm putting that out there, actually.
I did this with, I wanted to collaborate with the United Nations.
And every single school I used to teach and I used to say, you know, we could be working with the United Nations.
And I would put it out there all the time that I wanted to work with the United Nations.
And then, obviously, they opened and I've been working with them for the last two years.
So, Elon Musk, if you are listening to this podcast, I would like to collaborate.
And the reason why I would like to collaborate with you is you are one of the most visionary people that I have seen in the world that I think looks beyond the realm of what's there and what's possible.
And I know that having the brain that I have and the visionary space that I am in, I'd be quite interested to see what we could do with impact and purpose and put those two brains together to really collaborate.
And I know that having the brain that I have and the visionary space that I have and put those two brains together to really collaborate.
And that would be a collaboration that I would like to hear the transcript from your energy and your vision, Lindsay.
An extraordinary, you know, what he has done, isn't it?
You think of pushing through the car industry to electric when it was sitting there for all of the car makers forever.
And he, as you said, has quite an extraordinary way of living for sure.
Lindsay, I've loved listening and learning and hearing all of your incredible vision.
And if you want to hear more, please do.
Thank you.
If you want to hear more of it and see more of it, Lindsay, it's available on so many platforms, lindsayboyd.com.
Go and check that out.
Have a look at the book, Brand Famous.
Check out One Earth.
At the moment, you might have to check out it under the name of Bob Earth, but coming in the rebrand is One Earth.
And having seen it and used it and benefited from it firsthand, Lindsay, it's a fantastic, incredible thing that you are doing.
It's brilliant.
It applies to almost everyone.
And, you know, more power to you, more strength to your arm, as they say.
You're doing incredible things and inspiring many people.
And it's been a great pleasure to talk to you.
Thanks for your time.
Thank you so much for having me.
And, you know, you are a true inspiration for all as well.
And congratulations with everything that you're doing.
Thanks so much, Lindsay.
Really great to speak to you and look forward to hopefully doing it again sometime.
Thanks again.
Thank you.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me, Luke Darcy, produced by Matt Dwyer, with audio production by Darcy Thompson.
To start your leadership journey, I encourage you to...
You go to elitacollective.com, take our Empowering Leaders Indicator tool and understand the impact you have on your environment.
Join us at Elita to learn, lead and collaborate.
Listener.