A Leader Connect is passionate about inspiring connections and creating a world of collaboration.
We curate groups of five to six people from non-competing backgrounds who come together
to learn, connect and collaborate.
Leaders from the arts, from the business world, social venture and sport coming out of their
silos to share life experience and best practice in their own unique worlds.
Our Leader Connect panel here at Semwood at Sport Next in Melbourne is a group of coaches
who have achieved extraordinary success.
Second from the left is Mike Dunlap, coach to the Michael Jordan-owned Charlotte Bogcats
in 2012, becoming the only coach in NBA history to triple a team's win total from the previous
season.
Mike's most recent success, as you can see on the screen, was with the Milwaukee Bucks'
historic NBA championship win in 2021.
John Aloisi next to Mike is a legend of Australian sport.
His penalty kick that put the Socceroos into the 2006 World Cup was voted by the sport.
Australia Hall of Fame was one of the three greatest moments in Australian sporting history.
John is the current head coach of A-League Club Western United, a team, as you can see,
he coached to win the championship in 2022.
Andrew McDonnell next to me was appointed as the head coach of the Australian cricket
team in February 2022 after a long and distinguished career.
In his short tenure, he has guided Australia to retain the Ashes, a World Cup win in India
in the most spectacular fashion and an almost unprecedented run of success.
Alongside Andrew is Craig McRae.
A triple Premiership winning player.
He was an extraordinary player and he coached Collingwood, as everyone knows, to an incredible
four-point win in the 2023 AFL Grand Final delivering the Magpies their 16th Premiership.
I'd also like to acknowledge Anthony Seybold, a legendary coach from Australian rugby league
and rugby union who unfortunately can't make it here today but is an integral part of this
group.
The Elite Connect program, I'm going to ask two questions to the panel and they sound
like this.
The Elite Connect program has created a forum to allow this group to share openly with other
world leading coaches from different sporting codes in regular online meetings.
This group get together on a monthly basis.
I want to ask them how it's helped them and have they got any specific stories or hacks
that they've been able to add to their life or to their own team.
I want to start with Ronnie McDonnell alongside of me.
Your commitment to the program, Ronnie, has been extraordinary.
I understand that these guys turned on their laptops, you were walking through customs
in India.
You had your pants over your shoulder, still found a way to dial in, you weren't going
to miss a meeting.
It's an incredible commitment to the group.
Can you tell us about your experience with this group of gentlemen alongside of you?
Yeah, thanks, Darce.
To start off, it's been an incredible experience but I'll take it way back to the start when
Matt first rang me and I was really sceptical around it and I pulled out of one group and
I was like, oh, and he rang again and he was relentless in the pursuit and I was lucky
that I missed out on that first group and that's no disrespect to those people that
were going to be in that but to be able to tap into the minds to the left of me here's
been a wonderful opportunity and it's helped me immensely in basically problem solving.
One thing you learn as a leader is that you're all going through a similar thing and to be
able to bounce it off these guys, work our way through it and even to the point midway
through the World Cup, jumped on a call and we were two and two, I think we had an awful
start and just to have people on the outside to be able to bounce ideas off and just get
clarity in thinking and to really appreciate that we all go through a similar experience.
But getting back to that challenge of getting online, we're in all different time zones
and there's a lot going on.
And yeah, we've made an incredible effort to jump on and yeah, I was going through the
airport security and the phone went through and these guys were patient enough for about
five minutes as I went through security, so I appreciated that.
Alongside you, Craig McRae, on Sunday 1st October 2023, your coach calling into a famous
Premiership victory, your daughter is born the morning of grand final day, Maggie.
That's a pretty big day by anyone's estimation.
Coincidentally you have an Alita Connect morning the next morning after grand final and no
one on this panel is expecting to see Craig McRae after he's won the grand final.
You turn up with your one day old daughter.
You're on your lap.
Such has been your commitment to learning and sharing.
Can you tell us a bit about the experience, Fyfe?
Yeah, thanks, Darce.
And similar to Andrew here, it's been an incredible journey the last two years with this team.
You've seen Johnny win the championship and then winning Ashes and World Cups and riding
the bumps and Mike's just a wealth of knowledge and his experience has been incredible for
all of us.
Yeah, on that day it was, I couldn't let the team down.
I had the baby and my wife says, have the baby, she needs some sleep.
And then I thought, oh, I've got to have the baby.
She needs some sleep.
And I thought, shit, I'm on this Zoom call and I got there a little bit late myself.
But you know, we've got a strong connection and we ride bumps together and we enjoy successes
together.
It's been great to be part of.
Mike Dunlap alongside you is a legend of world coaching, flown in from Singapore.
He's had 2000 coaches under his tutelage and I understand that Mike dialed into a meeting
on the Milwaukee team bus on the way into the stadium and the group got to experience
an NBA pregame in real time, live, Mike.
Through your laptop.
And through you telling them the story, tell us about connecting with this group of coaches
and a leader connect and what it's meant.
One of the famous coaches in the United States who's now passed, John Wooden.
And also there's another one called Pete Newell.
But the bottom line is, is that as somebody who transported coach Newell around so he
could do clinics when he was 88 years old, I was the one who had the privilege of, of
traveling with him.
And he said, the one thing you want to do is be a lifelong learner.
Regardless of whether you retire or not, or somebody asks you to leave the business.
And the key point is, is that to always take a macro view that life is good and it's going
to be okay.
And what are the lessons learned?
And I would say in the Alita group, all of these guys bring a particular view to things,
which isn't necessarily my view.
And if you keep an open mind, you'll be a sponge and you'll pick it up.
Yesterday, I met with Jason Smith, who's second in line now.
For all.
And he was a big fan of the Atlanta Hawks.
He was a big fan of the Atlanta Hawks.
And he played for basketball on the female and male side.
And he played for us at a small school.
And he was drafted by the Atlanta Hawks.
And right before he went to camp, he snapped his, his patella tendon and it changed the
direction of his life.
He played for the flag several times.
And then his last 15 years, he's been in the corporate world dealing with people's accounts
that have a hundred million and up for a particular bank.
And now he's made the choice to come in, help his country and develop.
And so the essence of what we do.
It's not what we think we do.
It's about relationships and not things.
There are things we have to pursue, but the most important thing to remember is, is that
what are your priorities and how are you going to raise your family and what kind of example
you want to be?
Because when that drives you, it has a tendency to have you make great decisions.
And the best decision I've made in the last two years is to be a part of this Alita group
because they challenge your thinking, they give you stories and they re-reference some
of some things that you've done.
Yeah.
That's what you would do, which is what I would call nuance.
And that's why Alita has been so good for us.
Thank you, Mike, for that incredible description.
John, I always see everything that John does tends to turn to gold.
And we mentioned one of the great sporting moments in Australian history.
John's famous for it.
But I know your dedication, John, to coaching and you take on a new A-League franchise and
you win the championship in 2022.
But you've got this team in your corner all the way through that.
Tell us about that experience for you.
Yeah, it was a great experience.
Yeah.
One thing that I learned about winning the championship that Mike said, celebrate, enjoy
it because they don't come around too often and make the most of it.
And they're the stories that we speak about, about the experiences that we're going through.
Also we were talking about the selection process in terms of captains or retiring players, how
we've dealt with it in the past.
And we all want to keep learning and that's the most important thing.
So when we go online, this is the first time we've been online.
It's the first time we've been together in person, but when we get online, it's story
after story.
It's what would you do in this situation or what have you done in this situation?
And it's good when you're winning.
When you're losing, you really tap into them a lot.
And it's sort of like a therapy session for me because as a head coach, you end up being
a little bit isolated at times and you've got different sorts of pressures from your
board and then from supporters, from media.
Yeah.
And then, you know, when I chat with these guys here, you know, they make it that it's
a lot more, you know, you can get through this, there will be something around the corner
for you.
And, you know, just six weeks ago, we were on call and my team hadn't been getting results,
but I was so excited about the young players that we got coming through.
And Fly said, you know, just make sure they harness it because you can do a lot with these
young players.
And we've gone on a run now.
And, you know, the younger players are really believing and it's incredible just from, you
know, a little chat that you can actually bring that to the group.
So it's been, for me, it's been amazing and I love every time we get together.
And there are not many spaces you can go when your leadership can be lonely at times.
So the opportunity to speak to someone who's got a very, even a non-competing sport.
Johnny said something interesting, Fly, celebrate.
He got advice from Mike.
I didn't think you're allowed to celebrate, Fly, in recent times.
The world of pressure comes to everyone.
I understand that.
Yeah.
I understand.
A lot of these conversations have been private from peer to peer, but I believe some of Andrew's
talks on leadership and how he approached the leadership of the Australian cricket team
really influenced your decision-making at Collin.
Can you share that story?
Yeah, I can.
And I'm disappointed because this is the first time we've been together in the same room
because we've been on Zoom for two and a half years and we're going out to dinner after
this and you don't have a game and you're over, come from overseas, you don't have a
game and I'm going to have to leave early, I've got a game tomorrow.
But yeah, it's been a great connection of relationships.
And yeah, the story you're talking about, at one stage last year, we were transitioning
our leadership from Scott Penelbury, who'd been a great leader for such a long time and
chose to move on from that role.
And I just asked to the group, have you gone through a leadership transformation before
and what did you do?
Just looking for experiences and stories.
And then Andrew shared the story only probably six months earlier that what they did with
Pat Cummings.
Taking over.
Yeah.
And the transition of that.
And I said, do you have any things you would change?
And I don't want to speak for you, but I will.
Or do you want to share what you shared with me?
I just recall the way that if you had your time again, you would take others on the journey
for this decision making.
Now the board and certain people had decided that Pat Cummings was the guy, but then there
was a ripple effect from the likes of Steve Smith and David Warner and so on and so on,
had aspirations that they thought they could be.
Yeah.
They thought they could be the guy, but there was no process to take them through when the
decision was made.
They were sitting there going, well, what about me?
What happened here?
So from that conversation, which happened just before Christmas, the first thing I did
when I got back in the New Year was to grab all the people, the aspiring leaders that
I thought would have, even if it was just this much inspiration to be a leader or thought
of in this capacity, was to get them in one room.
And there were 16 of them in total.
And some of you go, really?
But most of them all had at least this much thought that they could be the guy.
And then we talked through exactly what we're going to do in the process, and then what's
required amongst that, how we're going to vote for it, and the criteria everyone was
going to be involved in around that.
So without this guidance, that wouldn't have happened.
And then from that, we then had 16 people that were all invested in the outcome and
realised they'd been taken on a journey for the outcome.
And while that was happening, the other 30-odd guys were in a room with our young, young,
young, developing leadership group, working out how they can support the change of leadership.
And it was a really thought-out process, thanks to the guidance of this leader program.
Yeah, I love that.
We feel like we've been in silos a lot in the world in recent times, and that just chance
to share with like-minded people at the same level is exciting.
Ronnie, I look at the World Cup win and what you've been able to do in recent times in
India as one of the great sporting moments in Australia, without exaggerating too much.
But not without a few hurdles on the way, Glenn Maxwell falls off the back of a golf
cart.
I'm assuming not many people can relate to that.
Things happen in life and in sport.
Are they the sort of things that you can bounce off a group like this?
We've probably all been in a situation similar to that.
I'm not sure many have had a person fall off a golf cart mid-World Cup and concuss themselves,
but we can use that as an example.
Just the ability to, I mean, every team takes on challenges at different times, and you're
going to have different friction points across the journey.
Yeah.
And just to be able to share what you're feeling in a non-judgmental way with this
group of people, and there's no agendas within it, and just to be able to bounce ideas off
it, it feels like a safe environment.
When I first went into the Alita program, the first three or four sessions, I was really
doubtful around how we were connecting, and it didn't feel like there was any rhythm to
it.
And then once we got the trust and it opened up and we were able to share anything without
judgment, and as Mike said, we don't always agree on it.
But to be able to come at it at different angles, you get off the call and you always feel as
though you've got a path through anything that confronts you as a leader.
So it's a really nice moment when you've got that to be able to draw upon.
Mike, as you said, lifelong learning is one of your philosophies, and there's an enormous
amount of wisdom that you're able to share, but you're seeing a new generation come through
that react differently, and a new generation of young athletes they're dealing with.
What have you taken away from this panel alongside of you?
Well, I think the most important thing is as you're recognizing your workforce is younger,
and they're coming through.
It is that their parenting was different, and instead of doting on the fact that the
parenting is different, the good, the bad, the ugly, it's more important to stay in the
day of how the young athlete listens, what drives them, and to have information from
them of who they are so that you can lead, and better state it so they can lead themselves
and remand them back to themselves.
So I think it's really important that you have something like an I am sheet, so if somebody
comes to you and they're new to your company, or they're new to your team, or they're young
and you're going to put them in a position where they've got to perform now, you see
that they have talent, well, the best thing you can do is get information first, an I
am sheet, and you can make it up, and you can say, hey, favorite thing that you would
take to the moon, worst tragedy that you've ever experienced, your nickname that you like,
and you go through these questions.
You can make them up.
They could be anything that you wanted, and I will promise you, if it's two or three pages,
you're going to read things about them that you couldn't find if you were doing it haphazardly
in 10 years, 20 years.
Give it to your spouse, and you create your I am sheet, and I would guarantee you that
you'll only get two-thirds right, no matter how long you've been with them.
So the revelation is that be an information seeker before you decide to codify and put
them in areas where they've got to lead, and you're depending on everybody.
And the last thing I would say in team is everybody spends time with the star, but you
have to understand is that the role player is the one that makes it so the star can do
their job.
And if you don't have those people that grind and grunt and get the job done, and you don't
spend your time with them, and you don't acknowledge them, then your team is going to be paper
mache.
Well, it's wisdom.
When Mike Dunlap speaks, and we're really grateful to have Mike out from the US for
this panel here at Sport Next in Melbourne.
I just wish I'd had Mike this morning, because we just picked selection, and we've dropped
a role player.
You make me feel guilty.
Yeah.
And I am sheep.
Oh, God.
Sorry, Flay.
Can you expand?
That's a meaningful, live example.
I mean, I'm going to pick up on that.
Can you expand on that?
I mean, you're a learner.
You're always, I know you absorb things, so where's your mind gone to there when you're
listening to that?
Oh, well, I'm just listening to exactly that.
We nourish our role players.
Everyone knows who the stars are, but the role players quite often get missed, and you're
constantly trying to reward those behaviours within the team, because you need those players
to execute.
And we've dropped one this week, and just because we want to get, they can't all fit
in.
And there needs to be change after, well, there doesn't need to be change, but we've
decided to change a few things up, looking for a spark or a different version, but we've
let one of them go.
And I'm not doubting it, but I'm going to make sure I've got to follow up more than
what I already have, because they're going to be important.
They certainly are.
I think Nick Dacos is safe.
I think he's more than a role player.
Yeah, yeah.
If you're listening live, you'll be okay.
Jonny, you've always approached learning in a really professional way, and when you
put your mind on something, it tends to take all of your focus.
Have you got a specific example of a hack or a strategy that you've taken and implemented
into your life or into your world of coaching?
Yeah.
Discussing with these guys here about the beginning of the season, or was it last season,
that it's funny, when you're a coach, that it's probably the only profession that everyone
has an opinion of what you're doing, right or wrong.
I would never go into a surgery and tell a surgeon how to operate.
We've been involved in the sport, I've been coaching over 10 years, and Mike's over 40?
45.
45 years.
And so we know what we're doing, but either your board or your chairman, they have their
ideas, and when you have a board meeting, they might be saying, why did you make this
sub and why did you do this and why did you do that?
And I was discussing it with them.
And they said, well, take them on the journey with you.
Take them with you.
What about if they come into one of your analysis meetings?
What about if they come into one of your team talks?
What about if they see the way that you're actually engaging with the group and why you
made this change?
Because every day we get a wellness of how the players are feeling.
We get their data on fatigue or how they're going.
And so a lot of that, a lot of thought goes into when, in soccer especially, when you've
made a substitute.
Because you can see if a player's tiring before they even know they're tiring, and then there's
the risk factor of injury.
So I did that with my chairman, and it was quite funny.
We didn't win that game, but he came out of it and he goes, that was so good.
He goes, that was good.
I can actually see what you're doing.
And so when we went through a bad spell, he was with me.
And I don't think if I went on the journey with him, he would have just probably lived.
He probably listened to, because what happens is they go to a barbecue or they go to their
friend's house and they start telling him, this guy doesn't know what he's doing.
You need to get rid of him.
But because he was there with me, he understood what I was trying to get from the group.
And that will take a little bit of time, but the process is there.
And Mike, over 45 years of coaching, you've seen it all.
You've been through all of that and been in teams.
And I mentioned off the top, you have a record winning season, effectively, at the Charlotte
Bobcats, but you're not there the next year.
So you've experienced it all.
Is it still that process?
You can say the next day.
The next day.
No, I hate it.
Let's go ahead.
Yeah.
You're still learning.
You find that there's still things that surprise you, even with all your wealth of experience.
Yeah.
I just think the most important thing is that envision yourself when your career is no longer.
And a lot of times we adopt what we do as far as how we make a living as part of our
identity.
I think you need to embrace that, because that's where you spend your time.
But also is, if you're looking ahead, you have to say, okay, what will fill my days?
And it doesn't have to be right.
It just has to be the fact that you visualize those next things.
So people ask me, hey, I've been retired since June.
What are you doing with your time?
And I go, I don't know, I'm here.
The point being is that I thought I would come back to Australia.
The Alita group stimulated me.
We're going to have this function today.
And I said, well, how can I incorporate that?
And be of some use for Basketball Australia?
I feel like I owe them, because I lived here.
My daughter was born in Adelaide.
So I said, well, I'll volunteer my services.
And they asked me what my charge was, and I said, there's no charge.
I owe you.
And so this is wrapped around the fact that this was my target.
And I've just finished a whirlwind nine or 10 clinics and workshops, and I'm here.
And that all was because I got invited.
And so my point is, is that don't ever worry.
Don't worry about telling people about your own self-worth.
You don't have to do that.
You just have to know it.
And as Mr. Rogers would say is, we are in a very loud world.
But when are you seeking peace in a given day where it's quiet, where you can reflect,
and you're doing it with intent?
Because at some point in time, you're going to wake up and be irrelevant in terms of when
you leave your job, you're going to feel like, well, now what do I do?
And it's probably one of the least.
Most important.
Most important things if it's directly connected to things.
You identify yourself with things and things, as opposed to, this is who I am and here's
my purpose.
What a great message, isn't it?
Not identifying yourself with the actual job and with a round of applause.
And I did want to jump in at that moment because sitting at the back, there's
an incredible connection and trust with this group that's been developed over more than
12 months and a special bond, it's such a humble group, very hard to drag out some of
of the the stories that i know are there but i thought what we might do given the connection
and we'll start with mike mike has just donated his time to australian basketball don't worry
about paying me he's flown through singapore and just done a master class for 2000 coaches on the
way down so i thought i'd ask the rest of the panel and we're going to go down the panel i'll
start with you john tell us about your experience with mike dunlap and and what you've learned and
from him and his wisdom well i think it's been over two and a half years that we've been going
online together mike comes up with a book every time that means i over talk
so yeah there's so much knowledge with you know sometimes uh i'm just sitting there listening
the whole time because um i just want to take it all in and you're trying to you know make sure
that you don't forget anything you're writing down notes and um and so that we we get so much
from mike because mike's been the head coach and then when we started this mike was the assistant
coach so
you know i was the head coach at that time and then you know explaining how his role is within
that team and uh and so which is important because you know at the time i think we're all head
coaches except uh sieves was assistant to eddie jones with england and then he ended up taking
on the head coaching role so it was that was important to find that also his experiences as
a head coach um experiences with some big stars and and you know that you know i think that you
know
we underestimate how big they are over there and and how they they um they you know talk to them
how they deal with them and and you know and we i still remember when you know we're in the he was
in the change room preparing for the games on his phone and you know i'm trying to see you know what
what place in the background to see if i can see anyone so yeah mike's been amazing amazing to
listen to and uh you know we're always you know getting great knowledge from him great book
recommendations uh from mike i'm trying to catch up to the miracle morning uh
one of mike's worth a read we'll maybe send that out to the community mike's uh
must read material as well craig tell us about uh your experience with mike i've got the winner
within book from pat roley which i'm reading and using consistently now about you know success
continuing and why you do it and why you don't so that's that's been a great help um i just love
your energy your energy you're always up and you're in a different time zone and you even
your text messages have energy i'm just reading them with you you're just uh you are you're a
great person and i'm really happy to be here with you and i'm really happy to be here with you
amazing he would say that because i was with hawthorne yesterday
i know i'm gonna get clubbed later on no you're dead to me you are dead to me but
um no you you just you're just really insightful you've got so much energy and then and so much
wisdom like i just i was trying to tell my wife yesterday a story about you know you talk you're
talking about like um celebrating wind you he says drink the whole thing and then when it's empty
drink it again you know and i did yeah
uh ronnie tell us about your experience having mike dunlap uh in this group with him
energy enjoyment but uh the one thing for me that strikes it sticks out is curiosity after 45 years
in the game um coaching worldwide to still be that curious is a skill in itself and the endeavor to
do things better and to continually learn and and not preach either learn off others and i think
that's the one thing he's got he's a great listener as well and he absorbs that information and
takes it and is able to come back to you with with something that you can take away from it so it's
it's not it's not it's not it's not it's not it's not it's not it's not it's not it's not
just about him it's it's about the others around him making them better he's probably the godfather
of the group yeah he is every group needs a godfather fly but i'm going to continue down
the panel and mike i'm going to ask you john we see uh someone you had a connection with for over
two and a half years i didn't realize it was it was that long tell us about your experience of
what you've found with john well i i would uh say and i can shorten this and that'd be a good thing
for everybody but uh you raise your children in a certain way so there's a culture of
of australia which because of living here i know a smidge about now and so i would say they're
byproducts of uh superior education it was important uh and as they've come through the
system they're uh they're they're humble they share with their acclaim you you don't hear a lot
of i in their vernacular and that's stunning to me in the way they defer to the story and wanting
to impart knowledge so that's a tribute to the people that are sitting out there in the audience
and then the other thing is is that they're very much people that rarely will even get into do as i
say not as i do they're examples by motion of what they do and they've all been in pivotal competition
and where the pressure's on and one of they they say is it's easy to be a good person when you win
but what are you going to be like when you get dropped and you know that a whole year you've
gone by and i've experienced this and you lose a national championship and i would say their
behavior is exemplary in the fact that it's not what you do as you lose or you win it's what you
do afterwards and they're get up people they're get up people they get up and they're ready to go
and they're in competition such that you could be owing to at this juncture but it
has a lot of value to it and i think that's a great point and i think that's a great point
nothing to do with the outcome and what that's going to be it's going to be lessons learned so
they have you know in their own way imbued in me that you may be retired but stay alive and stay
moving and stay going because they've been invigorating to me and i can say it with action
because i'm here because of these three and also anthony anthony was in vegas two weeks ago playing
in a competition i went over and watched him practice and was with siebes and did all of that
and then we had coffee in sydney a couple days ago so those relationships are ensconced because of
this meaningful connections uh mike uh craig tell us about collaborating with john lewis i was um i
was a new coach so i'm just starting out and and johnny's there and then watching johnny have
success and the storytelling of what what it's taking to be successful i love every time we get
together there'll be something that comes up and then you watch and it comes to life within your
coaching and it and it is
really inspirational whether it's a challenge of losing games in a row and then there's a
turnaround and how did that happen and you talk how you got out of the dip and
and then the lots of different layers to things that um i've had to live after you've already
lived it yeah so i'm gonna you're doing that and then i'm listening to it and then here it comes
and oh johnny told me to do this and then there's so many different layers of those things but i
great admiration for somebody who's probably in the most cut throat of all of us you know
soccer can be really ruthless
and and uh in particular but the way he's just he's seen such level um with his approach to all
of it so thanks great beautifully said ronnie collaborating with john lewis he's always a man
with a plan for me like he's always clear and concise um he knows the direction he's heading
in and he's got a vision and a long-term vision he's had some challenging times um had that spike
at the start and he's going through a rebuilding um phase obviously at the club at the moment but
he's clear on where he's heading uh he's always got a plan and yeah i just love that you're going
to keep rolling down the path and i'm going to keep rolling down the path and i'm going to keep
rolling down the path and i'm going to keep rolling down the path and i'm going to keep rolling down
the path and i'm going to keep rolling down the path and i'm going to keep rolling down the path
great mccray has changed the face of coaching a bit in australian rules football for me john and
has uh left the mark already in a in a unique way what's it been like connecting with him the way
you have i love when he tells us how he's you know approaches a team meeting and um one time i think
you dressed up i can't remember what you dressed up as but i've dressed up a few times and i and
i'm just picturing myself dressed up walking into the change room i go maybe my group's not ready
for that yet um yeah just just all those
And, you know, Fly is very, he's wanting to learn.
You talk about energy, you've got energy.
You've got energy and abundance.
And the thing that I noticed straight away was when he became the head coach,
it wasn't about winning or losing.
It was about the process and made sure that his club was going to be like that.
And I think that, you know, we spoke about shaking hands maybe on one of the first calls.
And you said that the first media conference you went into,
you shook everyone's hand and, you know, people that didn't like Collingwood,
I know you're here, Eddie, there was a lot of people that didn't like Collingwood,
but they ended up loving Collingwood because of Fly and the way that he comes across,
the way that he speaks to, you know, people in the press and then, you know, his playing group.
And so, you know, that really sticks with me whenever I hear him talk, but they love him.
You know, he dropped the player today.
He probably still loves him, that player, you know,
because when you're picking,
you know, we have a squad of 23 and I know that 12 players are going to be pissed off with me.
It's just part of it.
But it's the way you do it, you know, and you can see that, you know, he does it the right way.
Mike Dunlap, tell us a bit about Craig McRae.
The best part of him was on Mother's Day and they had a match
and he had a mother of one of the players come in and give the pregame.
Remember?
Number one, that took courage and number two is it was spellbinding
and it captivated the group because in what you do and it's violent
and there's a physicality to the sport, but yet there's a tenderness underneath
and that's the human factor of all the athletes in there.
And so it just goes to show you can be fierce, but you also can be sensitive and sincere.
And humble and that act in and of itself, I brought it home to my wife Molly and I showed it to her
and it just stunned her and stopped her because in a male world of sport,
that connection with your wife, your family and all that is really hard.
So really what he was saying to his team is that it's a whole, it's not just what we do.
You impact your family name and he brought it to the fore
without being didactic and having to lay the lesson in front of them.
It was absolutely brilliant.
So that's what I can tell you about it.
Thanks Mike, what a beautiful moment that was and great we all got to share in it.
Ronnie, talk us through your relationship with Craig McRae.
He challenges the norm and that comes with incredible risk at times.
I think clubs are stooped in history along with organisations
and to take it in a different direction comes with its risk.
But I've taken a lot away from that.
Like,
I think it's the way to go.
I think coaching has been done a certain way in the past,
but that doesn't mean it should be done that way in the future.
But as I said, that takes a lot of risk and he has changed the face of coaching,
I believe as well, in AFL football in particular.
Craig, I'm going to go back and we're going to talk about Andrew McDonald now,
who could not have landed more success for the Australian cricket team.
We know how competitive an environment that is and so much scrutiny.
Tell us about what you've learnt from him.
Can we just talk a bit more about me a bit more?
I'm blushing, I'm blushing.
No, I'm a massive critic.
I'm a cricket nuffie, so I watch all the games.
And so when I'm getting the inner sanctum stuff of all the cricket,
I start and watch the Ashes and the World Cup
and I'm riding every ball with the games.
And then to see the insight and hear the storytelling
and hear the inner sanctum stuff, I've been very fortunate with that.
I think he's a leader in so many ways.
Probably the biggest thing I see that we only caught up in the MCG
only a couple of weeks ago,
the amount of work that goes into how many different
travel teams that you're part of.
Like they're playing 2020s into one days, into test matches, all like that.
It struck me when you said that we have a different vision for every team
or a different cultural values or something like that.
Remind me of that.
Yeah, different layers, different, yeah.
Yeah, and it astounded me that you're going to have a different,
like Pat Cummins comes into the 2020 game and then he goes to one day
and it's like this one, I'm going,
oh, don't you have the baggy green?
And we're all in the baggy green all the time.
So having different layers of doing things really,
opened my eyes and ears,
hence that it doesn't always have to be the same delivery.
See what I did then, I used cricket for the analogy.
But I think in terms of leadership, we're all so different.
And I think you bring a level of consistency in one way,
having to evolve so many different,
you're coaching three teams really with the one coach,
which is a challenge in itself.
Mike, did you get to know cricket in your time here in Australia?
It's a unique sport.
And have you found the coach of the Australian cricket team?
Well, enough to know that it stretches your attention span and I'm ADHD,
so you got to be ready for the moments because to me,
it's a game of moments.
The thing is that when you start to learn on these conference calls,
Zoom, that it's messy what he does because of where he goes.
He has different layers of teams and player combinations.
He has to deal with circumstance of your opponent.
So,
you have in your pocket your plan and they say work your plan and you have
your tenets of what's going to drive your success and I find that Andrew's
very nimble with hard and fast rules and he understands how to shift gears
quickly and you know companies and people that do that you can still not
lose your way with your compass but you have to understand is the world's messy
and those that adjust quickly and not radically but can hold their identity
and he holds his identity and the other thing I told him is he ever loses his
job that voice is made for radio commercial acting all of that he's got a
beautiful voice I'm jealous John I wish you tell us about your experience with
Andrew McDonald yeah I just see that Andrew is very calm and you know I think
it was one of the first tours in Pakistan and there was a few issues and
and you just you know made the group embrace that and and and how they could
you know be better for it and you know I think it was one of the first tours in
Pakistan and there was a few issues and and you just you know made the group embrace that and and and how they could you know be better for it and
then you know they remember that because it was a difficult situation I
can't recall that the whole story and I was like wow you get in the group to buy
into you know that the end no problem we're in this together and then we'll
come through stronger together and then it reflected a couple of years later
when you played in the the World Cup final in India and you know how many
people hundred so yeah hundred thousand not expected to win but you you had a
game plan and you knew that you would win and then so that was the belief that
he gives the group and you know you can just see it in the way the players you
know step out onto the field they got a belief in the game plan they got a
belief in what they're doing and no matter if it's t20 or you know the 50
overs or test match and then you know even when they're dealing with difficult
situations you never see him flustered and then that that goes a long way
because we know how much pressure there is on the cricket team you know everyone
follows the Australian national team and they want them to do well when they're
not doing well
they get scrutinized pretty quickly we are just about out of time you can see
there's a deep connection now here on the panel I could go for another three
hours if time permitted but I believe there's some questions from the audience
we might just take one given time and I'm going to pitch this to Mike Dunlap
who is full of wisdom this question is coming from the audience here Mike at
Sport Next in Melbourne thinking about how we can apply your best coaching
practices to our business world what's the single most important thing you do
to coach a winning team
to make sure that you use your eyes to see what you have because whatever your
plan is if you go away from the collection of talent you have and getting
to know your talent
you're gonna go down the wrong path so you are the people that you surround
yourself by and the greatest thing that a leader does is pick those people be
selective who gets in your house we don't let everybody in your house and
you have your own standard so you can win a lot when you pick the right people
because the winning is in the picking.
And so I would say that really focus and take your time.
As they say, hire slow, fire fast,
kind of that little cliche that people use.
But more importantly, the sub-point of that is do your homework.
Put your hands together and thank our panel,
Andrew McDonald from Australian Cricket,
Craig McBride, Mark Dunlap, and John Elowisi.
Thanks for joining us here at Sportnet.