This episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast features a legend of Australian sport, Liz Ellis.
Very lucky to call Liz a friend.
And we talk about the month that we spent in Delhi, India in 2010 working together on the Commonwealth Games.
And how she threw me right under the bus by handing me a phone when I was standing at the bar
that put me live on air in Melbourne radio that just about cost me my job.
Liz also shares her story and her journey from being hyper-competitive to learning to be a person
and her words that describes just being able to stop and be.
She also shares her fight and the instinct she had to constantly try and succeed
as she's done in almost everything in her life when really struggling to conceive her second child.
She talks with me about the language we can use to have better conversations around fertility and miscarriage.
And there's a link to her book, If At First You Don't Conceive, in the show notes that's worth checking out.
We also talk about the lessons she learned when she bought into an ice cream business that ended up failing
and she reminded me of an amazing quote about
never being able to succeed without taking risks.
I hope you enjoy this conversation and laugh as much as I did catching up with the great Liz Ellis.
It's people like Liz that inspire the work we do at Alita.
We are really privileged to have Liz Ellis in our Alita Connect group
and I love the diversity of thinking in her group.
Paul Watterson from Australian Venue Co, Brad Johnson from the Bulldogs,
Brendan Lader, Premiership AFL player and Dylan Flavel as well.
Diversity of thinking and Liz is an incredible contributor and thinker in that world of Alita Connect.
Thank you.
If you want to learn more about it, head to alitacollective.com.
We curate groups of five or six like the one Liz Ellis is in and you don't have to be an Australian legend like Liz to join our world.
We'd love to connect with you and start your leadership journey today.
Huge thanks as always to the team at Temper Bedding.
Jason Nicholas and his team are great supporters of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
We really appreciate them supporting conversations like this one with Liz Ellis.
We know that great successful people value sleep.
A third of your life is spent on a mattress.
You may as well invest.
You may as well invest in the world's best bedding.
That is Temper.
It's a mattress like no other.
It'll change your life.
Liz Ellis is one of the most respected names in Australian sport.
A remarkable 18-year elite netball career that included two Commonwealth Games gold medals,
three world championships, four National League titles, four MVP awards, and an Australian
record 122 test matches played.
In 2018, Liz became an Officer of the Order of Australia for her distinguished service
to netball.
As an elite player and coach, through support and advocacy for young women as a contributor
to the broadcast and print media industries and to the community, Liz is a lawyer by trade,
experienced broadcaster, media personality, host, and the most recent winner of Australia's
version of I'm a Celebrity, Get Me Out of Here, which is incredible, Liz.
She's also a very sought-after board director holding positions on the Australian Sports
Commission, the Sydney Olympic Park Authority, and the New South Wales Institute of Sport.
Liz, it's all right.
It's always good to see you.
Oh, thanks, Luke.
And you too.
What you didn't put in there was that, you know, I couldn't have done my netball commentary
career without having Elle Darcy holding my hand at the start.
Well, I'm sure we're going to get to that because that was a very enjoyable chapter
of, well, maybe let's start there because I thoroughly enjoyed that time.
I do remember getting the call from Channel 10 saying, we'd like you to host the netball.
And I was like, no fucking way in the world.
I'm not equipped to do that.
That's the worst idea I've ever had.
And then I stand next to you and I couldn't have had more fun for two years, mainly because
of you.
Oh, thanks, Luke.
It was heaps of fun.
And what I loved about it was that you were so nervous, but you went away and you did
your work and you took it on.
And when I, since like, since then, and you've gone on with all your other media stuff, you
can sort of, like, I do feel a little bit of pride in you because I'm like, oh my God,
when you started, that's where you learn how to do ball by ball commentary.
And then you go in and do it with football and you're so good at it.
So, but those two years were funny.
And like stuff that we can't talk about with a microphone on, funny and just naughty.
And it was so enjoyable.
Well, you made me feel relaxed straight away because you're doing a sport you know nothing
about.
And it's the people that love that sport must be looking going, who is this boy?
Why is he standing there?
But standing next to you immediately gave me some maybe small credibility because you
embraced me straight away.
And I always talk about going to Delhi with you and that gold medal match in 2012.
That is still close to the best sporting event I've ever been to.
Double extra time.
And your reaction post that game, I'll never, ever forget.
You were so filthy Australia lost.
You couldn't hide it.
You refused to cooperate.
It was just extraordinary.
If they hold on, it's going to be gold.
No, no, Gerard, the man's broken.
There is 15 seconds left, Gerard.
It's a throw in.
So, McMahon.
Unbroke.
Turnover to New Zealand.
Long ball goes to Van Dijk.
He will go the way of Van Dijk.
This is phenomenal.
Should this go in, we will go straight into extra time.
To Taish.
Missed the last one.
This to draw level and go into double extra time.
We're waiting for a signal from our time kickers here.
It's 58 all.
If we get the call, the flag's up.
We're in double extra time.
Now we need, or the winner will be the first team to get up by two goals.
So, you're looking to score, but you're looking to break.
Can you believe it?
Double extra time here.
The final gold medal.
Oh, it's a turnover.
It was amazing.
And, you know, I just couldn't believe that Australia had lost a game that they should have won.
And, you know, I'd been in Commonwealth Games finals in a double overtime final where we won.
So, to see players who I was still really close to not get up and win, it hurt me.
Thank God you were there.
But that was amazing, wasn't it?
That whole Delhi experience.
And, like, I look back at it now and I just laugh because it was one of the greatest sporting moments of all time.
It was in a stadium in Delhi and we were surrounded by army guys with machine guns who our security people from Channel 10, they were just so worried.
They were like, oh, my God, their gun security is not good.
We were like, oh, I don't know what's worse.
And, you know, and they used to, remember they used to man the security?
And you know how we used to have to go in and you had makeup in your bag?
And they'd pull the makeup out.
And they'd pull the makeup out every day and laugh at you.
And you had to explain that it was for television.
It was just so much funny stuff.
And then you get this amazing game of netball.
And remember we went away and I always talk to people about this, about preparation.
You know, I think that was, we did a really good job of calling that game.
But we sat down the night before and went through, okay, what would happen if it was overtime?
How would we know if it was double overtime?
Because it's not a hooter or anything that goes for double overtime.
So, when it happened, it was like, wow, we prepared for this to sound really natural.
And that to me is part of the success of the call is that you think ahead about what might
happen and how it might sound.
There's so many stories from that very fun and memorable trip.
We had a month in Delhi, which I love, but because of security, they'd shut down the
stadiums at the start.
So, we would be out at that venue for the whole day and starving by the end of the day
and going, are you prepared to eat the non-vegetarian shish kebab, Liz?
Because if you do, I reckon that could be interesting for you.
And I, as we walked into the studio, really,
Rosie, who I worked with for 11 years doing Breakfast Radio, reminded me of a moment where
you put me in, and I deserved it because I'd been allowed to go and commentate on the basis
that I would dial in to Breakfast Radio.
And I decided that I was going to have a few beers this particular night.
And I said, oh, look, I can't make it.
I'm otherwise occupied.
I'm snowed under over here.
So, they rang you.
They did.
And what did you do?
I was happy to talk.
I was like, yeah, yeah.
And they said, oh, yeah.
And I said, oh, look, how's Das?
Is he all right?
He sounds like he's really busy.
And I was outside the bar, and I'm like, no, he's just here.
Das, there's a phone call for you.
I might have had a couple at the time.
As you can imagine, that conversation is just outstanding.
You just couldn't believe that I was handing you the phone.
I think there may be audio of that, which we'll try and find.
Oh, look, I've ditched Luke.
And it's good to hear that you've ditched Luke from the show, actually.
I'm seeing.
I'm looking on the other side of the bar from him, and he's telling lies to someone.
So, it's good that I'm here, and I can tell you the truth.
A couple of things.
Now, he is a monkey.
So, a few days ago, we actually have to go into the netball together.
And every time we go through the security sort of area, they confiscate something of ours.
So, I always get my hand wash confiscated.
The other day, I got my makeup confiscated.
Oh, no.
Luke has as much makeup as me.
Didn't confiscate his makeup because they were too busy killing themselves laughing
at a man carrying that much makeup.
So, please feel free to ask him how his makeup is going.
And he needs as much makeup as he can because he's the most palest man on television.
But yesterday, a BBC cameraman was waving his arms around at the IBC and wasn't being
allowed in.
Made a mistake of waving a little bit too hard.
Got mistaken as a monkey mating ritual, and he got attacked by a monkey.
That was nearly a game changer for me on a whole range of issues.
Now, Liz, going back to the start, I look at you, and I think,
everything you do becomes successful.
And I'm not surprised, you know, that you win.
You tell me you're going on, I'm a celebrity.
Of course, you're going to win it.
But what are the traits, do you think, that have helped you to be successful in what you've done?
Oh, that's a good question.
I think when I look back at, like, me as a little kid, I was never the most talented,
and I was never, you know, had the most skill.
But I was always the hardest worker in my junior teams.
I always worked harder.
I always did the fitness.
I always made sure that I could.
If I wasn't.
If I wasn't the fittest, I could keep up and do enough.
I used to work hard on my skills, and I never, ever felt that I was the chosen one.
You know, like, you know, coming through juniors, there's always someone who's really outstanding
and awesome, and that was never me.
It was always somebody else.
So I was quite happy just to sit at that next level.
Well, I wasn't happy about it, and I wanted to be the chosen one.
So I'd go away and work really hard and harder than anyone else.
And then it's kind of you to say that everything I touch is successful.
I just don't talk about the stuff that's not successful.
I keep that nice and sort of on the down low.
You know, every time something does fail, I really try and look at it and try and figure
out why.
What did I do wrong?
What could I do better?
And that really then informs the hard work to become successful next time.
So, you know, you talk about those four premierships that we won.
They were all late in my career.
Early on in my career, we were pretty average as a team.
And one day we got in the bus and we'd been flogged.
And we said to our coach, yeah, we're not very good, but we're the funniest.
You would remember Julie Fitzgerald.
She was coaching when we were commentating and she just went off ahead of us.
And she really made us understand that that's just not acceptable.
Like, yeah, have fun by all means.
But what comes first is what you're here to do.
So I always have felt that I'm always, I'm prepared to work harder than anyone else.
And then you get into a situation like I'm a celebrity, which I never, I was always,
I'm never going to do reality TV ever, ever.
Anyway, I needed the money.
So I did it.
And, you know, I just thought I'll have to go in there.
And you can't.
You're in front of cameras 24 seven.
You can't hide.
And this is the other key I think to success is to not try and be someone that you're not.
I've never tried to be, um, any different to what I am.
What you see on camera is what you get off camera.
And sometimes that's, um, that's great.
Sometimes it's really annoying as you will be able to attest.
And the thing that really drives all of that is I'm an inherently awfully competitive person.
As you know, I hate to lose.
I still can't.
I still can't believe that I lost to you in the celebrity match.
You were genuinely filthy about that.
I'm not a good loser.
And, you know, I've always said that show me a good loser and I'll show you someone I don't
want on my team, which is not very PC, but I'm really competitive, but that competitive,
that competitiveness has to be backed up with, with hard work and the preparedness to work
harder than anyone else.
And you mentioned that a night before the Commonwealth games, gold medal, it was you
sitting down, Hey, come and catch up.
These are the scenarios to play.
And you were the one with the detail on the preparation at a, at another level.
I like to do my homework, but that doesn't surprise me.
But there's a couple of things to pick up, pick up on.
I read your mum and dad described you as a bit of a clumsy kid.
You're a bit of a, a bit of a bookworm.
Is that, is that right?
That's so true.
So, um, I really only started playing netball by accident.
One of mum's friends rang her and said, and her name was Sheila, because all netball women
have great names like Sheila.
And I get up and thank Sheila every morning for my life because she rang mum and said,
would Liz like to play netball?
And mum said, no, she's a bit clumsy.
She's a bit of a bookworm.
I don't think team sports for her.
Sheila rang back about a week later and said, Margaret, you won't believe it.
I've just read that 95% of kids who end up as juvenile delinquents have never played
team sports.
So mum was hooked after that.
She was like, okay, well, Liz can play or Elizabeth, as I used to get called then, can
play on the proviso that when she wants to stop, she can.
So it took me 27 years to stop, but that was a really good lesson to reflect on.
I didn't understand it at the time because I was eight.
But now when I look back at that, I think so often we get told no and we go, okay.
But what Sheila taught me was that that no is just like the initial salvo.
It's actually, when you hear no, don't accept no, go out and find a way to get back to yes.
Now I've got no idea if she had read anything like that or if that was a spiel that she
gave to every parent who said no to her because she was a housewife in Western Sydney with
five kids and you wouldn't have looked at her and gone.
And she's a leader, but she's responsible for a whole generation of kids playing netball
and rugby league.
That's what her kids played.
And she thought that every kid should play team sport.
And that was how she went and got kids by guilting their parents and thinking they were
going to be juvenile delinquents.
So it was just luck.
And like I say, I do often sit down and I think about her because I think if she hadn't
have made that phone call, I would have gone on to achieve academically and do all that
sort of stuff.
And, you know, you mentioned I've got a law degree and I probably would be working in
a legal firm.
But I wouldn't have all the joy that my sport has brought me and I wouldn't have the
opportunity to do so many other things.
What a legend Sheila is.
What about mum?
Not for Liz.
She's reading her book and we'll keep her there.
You mentioned the law degree and I look at you and I think you're a constant improver,
constantly wanting to do something to better yourself.
So you do a law degree at the same time as playing sport for a living.
You take on a lot.
Is that true of you?
The constant never ending self-improver?
Yeah.
Which is good and bad.
Now I've got kids and, you know, we live in the country and my husband is often saying
to me, just stop, just slow down.
And sometimes I have to force myself to slow down so I can be present with the kids.
I'm not, I think my whole mindset is, okay, I'm always thinking of the next thing and
whether that's improving or whether that's planning a holiday or what I need to do in
the garden.
But I really do have to work hard to be mindful.
So there is a balance there.
It's great to wanting to continually improve and look for the next challenge.
But as you get older, particularly, and now my kids are young, they're 12 and seven.
I started a bit later than you, Dars.
I used to laugh at you with your 300 children having to get up early and get flights back
home.
I remember it.
Because now I'm like, no, that's me.
I'm on a 6.30 flight out of Melbourne on Sunday morning so I can get home and be with Matthew
and the kids.
So, but I think it's like wanting to improve yourself and looking for challenges is, I
think it's a really good trait, but it does need to be balanced by the ability to stop
and just be.
You married Matthew, who's a ripper, an elite rugby player before he hurt his back, and
then two beautiful kids, Evelyn and Austin.
What are you like on the home front as a mum and a leader on that front?
Sometimes I'm a pain in the ass and my daughter's just going through puberty, so she'd probably
highly agree with that.
This will not surprise you.
I like everything organised.
I think five meals a head.
So at the start of the week, I know what I'm cooking for the rest of the week.
And when I know I'm going to be away.
I leave meals frozen.
So when I was going into the jungle to do Celebrity, I had 30 frozen meals.
You didn't, did you?
I did.
Because I knew that Matthew was like, he's a farmer and I, like he can cook, he's great.
But, you know, kids sport, I knew he was going to be out all the time.
And, you know, I show my family I love them by feeding them, by cooking for them.
And so I was like, if I cook for them, then they'll know that I'm thinking of them, even
though I can't talk to them while I'm in the jungle.
So, and what else am I like?
Oh, you know what?
I.
I like to think that, um, I like to think that I'm fun, but I also, you know, I don't
let them have screens during the week, um, which they hate, but I'm like, well, we've
got 160 acres.
You've got dogs and chooks and cows and bikes and bulls and get out, get out of the house.
So my mum always tells me I'm too hard on my kids, but by the same token, like I love
reading with them.
I spend time with them.
Um, and I always tell Matthew that I'm a top smiths.
Some days he agrees.
Some days he doesn't.
Yeah, and bad luck when he doesn't.
Yeah, exactly.
Well, I, you know, he's good looking bloke.
So I like to keep him on the farm.
We're the only women he sees at Bovine.
He's a good catch, Matty.
One of the great, uh, people.
And I, I, a lot of people talk about, um, balancing life.
I think you just go and do it and make decisions.
And I remember talking to you when we were working together, you know, all those years
ago, more than a decade ago, how are you going to move out into a farm outside of Byron?
And you go and do it.
And I'm going to take 12 months off, which you've just done and get in the caravan and
take the kids around.
Australia.
How do you make those decisions and just make them happen?
Oh, look, uh, I make, I tend to be very decisive without often thinking through the pros and
cons of a decision.
Like it sounds very great.
Yeah, I'm really decisive.
I go and do it.
But, um, whereas Matthew is the opposite.
He is not a decider.
He likes to look at things like it took him seven years to ask him to marry me.
So he really had a long, hard think about it.
So, um, look, I think I tend to go with my gut a lot, which isn't great.
Um, but then sometimes I feel like you can really get paralysis by analysis.
So we're a good pair.
And I think if you, if you like me and you like a decision, just make the decision and
go, it's good to have someone who's your partner, whether in business or, you know,
personally who says to you, well, hang on, let's just weigh up the pros and cons of this
and work out.
And so, you know, one of the failures that I had, particularly in business was years
ago, a friend of mine and I bought into an ice cream franchise and, um, it failed miserably
and I didn't do my homework and I went, yeah, this would be great.
This is a gut decision off we go.
And we lost a significant amount of money, but I learned from that.
And I learned that if you're going to make a large decision like that, you've got to
go and speak to people about it.
So, you know, sometimes it's good to make decisions, you know, and when we're talking
about moving up to the country, we'll just, we, we talked about it a little bit.
Matthew was a farmer when he was younger with his father.
And then he went to Sydney to play football and was very successful in business and he'd
sold his business.
And it was like, he was talking about maybe one day wanting to go back to being a farmer
and we're at Gold Coast airport.
Had a few wines, which is when the best decisions are made and because our plane got delayed
and he said, you know, one day I would, I'd like to move up here.
And I said to him, well, people who say one day, just don't, don't get, never get it done.
One day is, is always sometime in the future.
We either do it now or we don't talk about it.
And so we sat and made a list of all the things we needed to do.
And the first thing obviously was put our house on the market in Sydney and I woke up
the next morning and before he could change his mind, I just rang the real estate agents
and come over.
So that's probably a really good example because, you know, I speak to people now and they're
like, oh, I wish we could do it.
And anyone can do it.
There's no laws to say you can't sell in the city and move to the country.
It was easier for us because we didn't have kids.
But I just sort of knew that if, if you talk about one day doing it, those days just like
when he's one day, so you put a limit on it and you go and do it.
And, um, you know, and it was a bit similar with the holiday last year.
It was something that I always wanted to do.
And that took a lot more convincing for Matthew to do.
Yeah.
And someone said to me, you know, I was working for channel nine and I've been there for five
years and I loved it.
And someone said to me, I can't believe you're walking away from your broadcast career when
it's really at its peak.
You know, I was commentating netball and I was on sports Sunday and I was doing some
other things.
I just said, my priority is my family, my kids.
And I know that they're going to grow up and have their own life.
And I want to have this, this year with them now.
So I think decision-making, good decision-making is about being really clear about your priorities
and what's important.
And for me, I've always been really firm in what's important to me is Matthew and the
kids.
And that is the thing that all my decisions are filtered through.
And they talk about, uh, the, the trip around Australia.
One of my best mates in life who I've, uh, interviewed on this podcast, Craig Ellis,
who founded Triangle Bikini and we played footy together.
And I'd still hear a story from his trip around Australia when he was eight.
He's still coming up with them to this day.
It's like, mate, it gave him this whole perspective.
He loved travel on the back of it.
Was it as good as you thought it was going to be with the kids?
Yeah, it was.
So my parents took my sister and I out of school and did the same trip in 1982.
So in 2022, it was, we left nearly 40 years to the day after that.
And that was really significant for me because I thought it'd be nice to just mark that
anniversary.
You know, my dad's not alive anymore.
So it was nice to think about him in that regard because he really drove that trip.
But I knew from that trip that it had really opened my eyes and opened my horizons.
And I realized from then I was.
Maybe eight, same, same age as your mate, just about how big Australia is and how amazing
it is in the history and the culture that's out there and the geography and the science.
And I thought I really wanted to give my kids that experience, but I also knew that it brought
our family really close together.
So when my dad was dying, you and I were working together at the time, I'd go to the hospital
and we'd often have conversations about that trip or about experiences that we had.
And it was so nice.
Like on your deathbed, no, like I didn't want to, dad and I didn't want to talk about how
hard he'd worked or, you know, his journey.
Yeah.
We talked about our family experiences in that holiday and a few others.
And I thought, I want to bank that for our kids and our family.
And I realized when we were doing it, because I thought initially it was about getting to
know your kids and being part of their lives.
But what they got was to know us because Matthew and I at home are really capable.
We know what's going on.
You know, he's a farmer.
He's on top of all of that.
But they saw us have no idea about what we were doing.
We had a, we don't fight very often.
We had a massive blow up one day because we'd left the caravan.
And I found that we're on the Gibb River Road, which is like, it's in the Kimberley.
It's really rough.
And we left the caravan and packed the tent to drive up to Mitchell Falls.
And the road was terrifically rough.
And I said to Matthew, did you pack the butane containers?
And he goes, no, for the stove.
And I'm like, right.
We're eating raw pasta and raw sausage.
And I went off my head.
And kids just sat there and they were like.
But it was so good for them to see us lose our, lose our shit and then work together
and then figure it out.
And what happened was that Matthew, who is inherently shy, got to the campgrounds and
he went and asked around and had to swap our cold beer for butane cans.
I'm like, we don't have any beer.
But they saw us work through that.
And I think it was so good for them to see us have no idea what we were doing for nearly
12 months.
I'm thinking of another great friend of mine, Bob Murphy, who's as hopeless as me.
I would be, I'd need to take Matthew on the trip around Australia.
And he bought his camper van, first stop, tried to drive through a bottle and took the
whole top off the bottle.
Stop it.
At their first.
Oh my God.
And if you know him, you know that that was always a chance to happen.
That's like a nightmare scenario.
It's incredible.
I'm going to come back to the ice cream business and that not working for you.
How did, how did you cope?
And tell us a bit more about that.
I didn't cope very well actually, because I'm so used to succeeding and no matter how
hard I worked, the business was so poor that it didn't matter.
I could have worked in there 24 seven and it made no difference.
And, um, it took, it didn't take long.
It didn't take very long for us to figure out that we'd actually made a huge balls up
and my business partner took her a little bit longer to get there.
And, uh, I sort of went through like the seven stages of grief, like anger and denial.
And I went through a stage.
I didn't want to even hear about it or talk about it or think about it or go down there
because it was in manly.
Um, and then when we realized that we just had to get rid of it, it was about cutting
our losses.
And I, it just showed me everything that I didn't do.
I didn't do my market research properly.
I didn't know how to do it.
I didn't understand the ins and outs of a commercial lease.
I didn't understand the franchising model.
I didn't, there was so much I didn't understand.
I loved what we were serving, but the actual food component is such a small part of it.
It's all the business that sits behind it.
And, you know, I've got a lot, I thought I was, I was overconfident.
I've got a law degree.
I can read it, but I didn't really take the time to sit and understand the ramifications.
And I actually never, before we went into it, I never sat and thought about if all this
goes pear shaped, what does that mean?
And so there was, we lost a lot of money.
And fortunately I was in a position where like it was, it ended up, you know, you get
past that and you move on.
And it wasn't the money that hurt.
It was the fact that I'd been in charge of something that failed.
And it really took me a long time to speak about it and to acknowledge that we'd had
that business and it hadn't gone very well.
And, you know, it taught me about businesses that like buying a franchise into a franchise
is okay, but it doesn't really give you the scale that you need to what I thought we'd
get.
So, you know, you'd need to be prepared to buy two or three or something like that.
And there's various business models out there, but it also showed me the value of growing
a business organically and being able to control it and understand it and learn as you go.
So jumping in that deep end was awful and it cost me a small fortune, but I just learnt
so much from it.
And I learnt the questions that I should have asked and which now when I get presented
with things that I do take the time to ask and understand.
We don't like the hard lessons at any stage, do we?
No.
But they are the best ones in the end, aren't they?
You end up with this incredible, you know, the detail that you would approach other things
that you wouldn't have previously.
Well, there's a great saying, you often find out what we'll do by finding out what we'll
not do.
And he who never made a mistake never made a discovery, right?
So if everything in your life that you touch turns to gold, you actually don't learn that
much.
You learn so much more from failure about the questions you should ask, about the understandings,
about your relationships as well.
Yeah.
And I love if you don't take a risk, then you don't get to anywhere at the same stage.
And it's great to share those stories.
Because you read the headline and the bio and you go, that's just a blessed life.
But in reality, we've all got these hurdles that come up.
And you're an author as well, Liz, a book about fertility.
If at first you don't conceive was the title of the book and talks openly about your troubles
with fertility or challenging time in your life.
Can you share a bit about that?
Yeah.
Bloody Austin, he took his time.
So I'm in love now.
But look, we had no trouble falling pregnant with Evelyn.
You and I worked in Delhi and Matthew and I went away to Europe after that.
And we're like, right, when we get back, we'll try and have a child and see how we go.
And we're pregnant within six weeks.
We're like, oh, this is so easy.
And we used to joke, we had more sex getting her out than getting her in, right?
Is that too much information for your podcast, Luke?
It reminds me of working with you.
Oh, the stuff that you shouldn't say in front of a microphone.
Anyway, stop blushing.
I'm midway through my story.
And then we had Evelyn.
And we went to the...
Obstetrician, he goes, well, you need to start straight away because you're old.
So I was 39.
I thought to myself, we'll be fine.
And we were pregnant really quickly again after that.
And then we had a miscarriage.
And then nothing happened.
So we started through the journey of fertility drugs and IVF and fell pregnant a couple more times.
And the last time on IVF, we fell pregnant.
And we got to about nearly the 12-week mark.
And we'd seen the heartbeat on the ultrasound.
And then we get to the next appointment and there's no heartbeat.
And that...
Like, speaking of failure.
I really struggled with that because I was so used to my body doing what I'd asked it to do for all these years.
And suddenly, it would not grow a baby for me.
And, you know, I was old.
But when I had my last miscarriage, I was 41, maybe 42.
And I thought, well, that's it.
It's all passed me by.
And mum kept saying to me...
She kept telling me these stories about people who had stopped trying and fallen pregnant.
And I'm like, mum, I've never achieved anything in my life by not trying.
Right?
So I'd have these big spits at her.
And God love her.
She puts up with me.
And then, funnily enough, we stopped trying.
Because we thought, we're focusing so hard on this kid that we don't have.
We're actually not focusing on the kid that we do have.
You know, Evelyn would have been three or four by that point.
We thought, we're really lucky.
We've got a healthy, beautiful girl.
That's it.
We'll just sit back and enjoy her.
And then one night we had a bottle of champagne and one thing led to another.
Too much information again.
Yeah.
And we fell pregnant with Austin.
And we're like, that's just his personality.
He doesn't do anything until he's ready.
So, but that whole thing was about like writing that book.
I actually had a massive pile of papers in my office and I went to throw them out.
And I thought, there's actually a book in this.
Not so much collating this, but getting, having all this information and then relating it
to what happens in the real world.
And I wanted to write a book that was like your best friend holding your hand, pouring
you a wine and saying, right, I'm going to talk you through this.
So I do make lots of jokes in the book about vaginal discharge and erectile dysfunction.
And then all that sort of stuff.
Are you happy you don't work with me anymore?
But it's science, Luke.
It's science.
So I write about this stuff, but then I make jokes about like, you know, like I've got
a pure old sense of humor.
So I just make jokes all the way through the book.
But I want it to be really like what happens when you go through infertility.
A, no one ever talks about it or miscarriage.
No one knows the words to talk about.
And so many women miscarry.
And we never have a conversation about.
And then so many people are going through infertility or fertility treatment and don't
know how to talk about it and often don't know how to talk about it to each other.
So I wanted to provide in my book a bit of a way to work out language, to speak with
each other.
And people often talk about the cost of IVF.
And so like I did a bit of a budget, but I also did an emotional budget, which is these
are the things you're going to face.
And these are the things you should talk about before you go into it with your partner so
that when they happen, you've got the language ready.
And I've heard from people who said it saved their marriage because they knew how to talk
to each other.
They knew what was coming.
And the hardest part for the book for me was writing about what to do when, if you don't
get a child at the end of all this, because I got my baby and I found this woman in Perth.
It was amazing.
And she really talked me through the process that she went through.
And at the end of the book, she shares an email that she sent out to all her friends
and family banks, basically saying what had been happening.
And, you know, this is what.
I don't want to talk about.
This is what I do want to talk about.
And I think there's great merit in explaining that to people.
I've tried ever since to have conversations with people about miscarriage and fertility
and that sort of stuff.
So when I went into, um, into, into the jungle for celebrity, we had a conversation about
miscarriage and that conversation has continued since we've got out with, you know, Deb Lawrence
and I working with a group called the pink elephants, um, about helping women through
and families through miscarriage.
Um, because there's lots of things that we just, it's a bit hard to talk about.
It's a bit sort of like, it can be awkward.
Yeah.
How do you do it?
Well, you're the perfect person for that.
Cause there's no awkward, uh, with you and it's a great super, and you're authentically
you in every situation and that comes across.
And I think, uh, if you're going through it, you'd be happy to share even, you know, if
it makes people like me uncomfortable, as you know, which happens so easily, uh, I tell
you what, it's been great.
I'm really connecting with you, haven't seen you for a while and really appreciate you
being part of our Let It Connect, uh, space, which we're really passionate about, you know,
this idea that we felt the world's got a bit siloed and people are retreating back into
their spaces and connecting groups of great people like you together.
How have you found that, uh, that space of Let It Connect?
I've loved it.
And the thing that I've loved about it is not just the meetings that we have with our
group.
It's the thinking that you do for days and days afterwards.
Someone says something and it sparks a thought.
And I found that I would go back and look at things that I was doing in a different light
and particularly around for me at the moment, my leadership is a bit sort of, um, fuzzy
because I don't have a leadership position.
I don't have a badge that says I'm the chair or I'm the leader.
I'm the CEO.
It's really within my sport and within women's sport.
I'm just someone who I try to lead by, um, keeping people talking about the issues and
it actually gave me a really good way.
To think about how to do that a little bit differently.
I've been banging on about it for 30 years.
Luke, at some point you've got to do something differently, but you know, it got me thinking
about different ways of doing things and just the things that I need to work on.
Like there's times when I think people are, the person I'm trying to convince is not listening
to me and rather than thinking, which I do, it's their fault.
I'd actually got me thinking about, okay, this is how I need to address my communication
with them.
So it was so valuable.
And the little group that we've got is great.
And I'm really looking forward to sort of continuing to connect with them into the future
because we're all so very different.
So yeah, it was, I can't tell you how much I enjoyed it.
So yeah, we love, and you're always going to be an amazing contributor, but I think
that's a great point Liz around this idea.
People think we need a title or I need to be, you know, a current captain or I need
to be CEO to do that.
But every moment we've got a chance, having on the home front with our kids or, um, our
friendship groups.
There's a chance for us to learn from each other on how, you know, it sounds a bit
altruistic around living a better life essentially, isn't it?
Totally.
It's a, it's a constant thing that, isn't it?
It is.
And you know, um, the first person that taught me that was, you know, Sheila, the woman who
got me into netball doesn't have the badge.
And, you know, I think about her a lot actually as a leader, because now I'm coaching the
under 12s headland dolphins team, my daughter's netball team.
It's so stressful.
Anyone who's coached 12 year old girls would know the pain that I feel on a week to week
basis.
But like, I do really feel the responsibility that I've got in my hands.
I'm holding their, like their netball experience in my hands.
And I feel that responsibility deeply.
And even the stuff that we did with the Alita group, I took it back to my coaching of them
to make sure that I was doing it in the best way possible and, and allowing them to hopefully
one day having someone in that group to pay it forward.
And I see them now stand up and they umpire and they work at the canteen and I'm so proud
of them because they're learning leadership, you know, from all.
All these older women around them in our little netball club and they're now doing it and then
they'll pay it on one day too.
So it's just phenomenal.
And that, I think that's one of the great things about sport.
And it's the genius of someone like you going back to junior sport and doing it consciously
and making sure it's good for everyone in the team.
It's another one of my great, uh, hobbies here, Liz, is the craziness of junior sport.
I don't know how mental it has got and, and parents going ballistic at the sidelines and
screaming at 12 and 13 year old umpire.
Have you seen that?
I haven't, I haven't seen it, but I think everyone's too scared when I'm around to behave
like that, but I certainly do hear about it.
And well, I'm in the country, right?
I'm in a little, a little country sort of group, but I've have seen it a little bit
when the kids have gone on to state champs and things like that.
And I, I see it creep into netball because suddenly my sport is professional, right?
So parents really have ambitions for their kids.
And I just think, I always think back to my parents.
They were so laid back about my netball career.
They were.
I was a bit surprised.
Like even when I got selected for the diamonds, dad goes, Oh, I didn't think you were that
good.
I'm not saying do that to your kids, but understand that their sport is their dreams.
It's not your dreams.
And like you and I can understand that because we've been there, right?
You know, you've played your AFL career.
I've played my netball career.
I don't need my kid to do it, but there are, I do understand there are people who have
those dreams for their kids, but also understand that if you go too hard on that, your kid
is likely to walk away.
Yeah.
It serves the opposite purpose to what you're trying to do.
So, you know, at the start of the season, I do say to the parents, can we make sure that
we're encouraging and that, you know, that we're, even when you get home in front of
your kids, try not to speak disparagingly about another kid in the group because they'll
carry that with them to training.
So again, that's about like when I talk about my book or anything else, it's about the language.
Like before you even start, think about the language you're going to use and hopefully
it's sort of coming through.
Okay.
Listen to Rod Campbell's podcast.
That I had a great conversation, learning life through sport.
It's exactly your language, Liz, is just teaching kids leadership for life through sport and
good respect and respecting the umpires and their teammates.
And I know it sounds easy, but it feels as though this world has got a bit crazy on that
front now that is not helping kids at all.
And it should be the happiest place.
Junior sport for everyone should be the place where they go and be happy.
Liz, we had someone in our world use the term success leaves clues.
What does that mean to you?
It means a couple of things.
It means, um, I reflect on my behavior often.
I think self-reflection is really important.
And when I was in a team and a leader within the team, I'd often reflect on conversations
that I'd had or things that went wrong or went right in the game.
What was my role?
How can I do that better?
And I've always been a bit harsh on myself in that regard, because I think that's where
you like, you've got to be honest with yourself.
And if that means being hard, then so be it.
Sometimes I think my self-talk could be better, but the last thing I, and the world needs
is me with a bigger ego.
So, so, you know, I, but I do engage in a lot of self-reflection just at home or, you
know, when I'm on the plane or driving somewhere.
Um, and I think to me, a lot of people who are successful do that because, you know,
one of the great things that sport teaches you is you can,
you can blame the umpire, but then you lose control of changing anything.
So actually look at yourself first.
So that's where I started with self-reflection.
And I'm really careful about, um, I don't know that you can achieve balance because
you always have crazy moments, but I'm really careful about having, um, nice things to look
forward to, right?
Because that makes you a better leader because you're more centered.
You're able to focus on the moment because you know something good's coming, which, um,
drives Matthew insane because I'm always wanting to book holidays, but like, it's just about
looking after yourself.
And allowing yourself to be in a happy place because you've got a few other things under
control.
And the big thing I've learned, especially since having kids is the power of saying no.
I used to think I had to say yes to everything, especially when I left the law firm and went
freelance.
I was like, oh my God, this job could be my last, but I've survived, I don't know, 25
years doing that.
So now I understand that I can say no, especially if it doesn't suit what I'm doing with my
family.
And that makes me a better leader because when I'm there or wherever I am.
Um, I'm actually really invested in it because I know that I've given myself space to be
with my family and to do the things that I like to do.
You've got some clarity on that, Liz.
I love it.
I'm a bit like you too.
I'm the same.
It's got to be something coming up in the next 24, 48 hours that I'm really looking
forward to.
Otherwise I get a bit, uh, edgy.
I'm a bit in our house booking holidays all the time as well.
Uh, and I think, yeah, that's almost like a club for me.
Self-reflection is that there are a group of people that that's not really who they
are.
And, um, it seems as though you're very, very clear.
We see leaders are really conscious, Liz, on a daily basis, how they have a positive
impact on other people from moment to moment.
How do you think about that?
There is no, I think, shame in being kind to people.
And I really try that.
Like I know I've got a sharp tongue and sometimes I have to think about that.
As you know, Luke, I'm like, oh, I shouldn't have said that.
Go back and think about it.
But, you know, just being kind.
I think that you can have a positive impact every day on someone by being kind to someone
who you don't have to be kind to.
Holding a door open.
Or saying thank you.
Like that doesn't cost you anything, but it has a massive impact on someone's day.
And I really do try now, I've been guilty of not doing in the past, but I do try now
to lead with kindness and show that you can actually be a strong person and a decisive
person, but still care about people who you come into contact with in your day.
And I, I try and do that with my kids as well.
And Matthew and I have always said through our marriage that, you know, you hear some
people who are married speak to each other.
And they're like, and then they'll say mean things to each other.
And then they'll go and be nice to someone who they don't have to be nice to.
Whereas we have always said that we are, we're nicer to each other than we are to anyone
else in our day.
And that sets the tone in our household.
We try and do that with the kids.
And even when they drive me insane, I really do try and take a big, deep breath and explain
to them why I'm, I've got the shit.
Sometimes that doesn't work.
And sometimes it does work.
And sometimes I just yell.
But that's okay.
And I engage in self-reflection.
But.
I think if you start in your immediate circle with kindness and being respectful and the
way you run your close relationships, that sort of ripples out into everything else.
Yeah.
Beautifully said, isn't it?
The kids, you know, often, um, you can talk to them when they're older about what you
think values are like, but they observe every minute thing.
Everything.
And that forms really their own sense of what relationships look like.
And I think Beck and I have articulated it quite like you and Matt, but certainly how
we feel, isn't it?
Yeah.
See us spending time together and talking to each other the way that we do, then it's
got to be a positive impact.
And it's an easy thing, isn't it?
Like the, the, the opportunities are there all the time.
Uh, leaders who are conscious about how they go about creating and sharing a vision for
whatever they do.
And you've had so many things in your life that you've gone and tackled.
And it seems like you've always got clarity on that when you're needing to achieve something.
How have you gone about creating and sharing a vision?
Um, I think I've always got like, I've, I've always.
I've always had a vision and always known what, what needs to be done.
I think where I've been guilty of not doing things properly is not enunciating that properly
with my teammates.
Like I just assume we're all going in the same direction.
We all want the same thing and we all know, but then you speak to people and I'm like,
oh, right.
Well, we've got a different idea of what this looks like.
So I've always tried to make sure learning that has made me ensure that you just have
conversations.
I think the key part of leadership is communication and that's not telling people what to do.
That's listening to what other people's ideas.
And I had to learn that as a leader.
Like I initially, I was like, it's my way of the highway.
This is how we're doing it.
And that worked for a short while, but it's exhausting and it's unsustainable.
So I soon learned that you had to listen to people and get their buy-in and let them tell
you where they wanted to get to and then work out a way to make that working with what the
team needed.
So for me, that clarity has always been there in my mind.
The challenge has been to be able to bring everyone else along or to make sure that everyone
else that works for them as well.
So, you know, I think listen.
And it was interesting, you know, in our, in our leader group, it was really interesting.
We had Brendan Laid and he just is so good at that.
He listens and he thinks, and then he says something a long time after that, that takes
you back to that conversation.
Whereas, you know, there's people and I'm one of them.
I listened to you and I started to think about what the next thing is that I'm going to say.
So like I'm clear in my mind, but what I need to do is listen to you or anyone else and
go, okay, what do you need to know that you have this clarity as well?
Yeah.
The great gift is having someone like a lady who I've known for a long time is a big farmer
from Kangaroo Island.
And yeah, it's the quiet ones that listen well, that often know everything, don't they?
Because they're not in a race to, and when to say something, but when they do, it's often
more profound than anyone else.
It's a great lesson for me too in, uh, in that I'm scarily like you, Liz, as you talk, as
you're talking, I'm going, God, that's a bit of self-reflection for me.
Um, we see leaders are really curious and through curiosity.
They approach their learning and development.
Does that resonate with you?
Yeah, it does.
I'm probably not as curious as, as other leaders might be.
You know, I really like, I worry about the chaos that curiosity can cause.
So I'm like, sometimes I'm like, no, I don't want to know about that because I really,
I'm really focused on getting to this point rather than taking the side road.
Whereas I learned through that ice cream shop experience that, um, it's not just curiosity,
like being a kid curious, it's actually curious about understanding everything that you need
to understand.
That's really important.
So.
So it's probably not a natural trait.
I'm really curious about, like, I like to read widely and about all different things
and understand lots of things, but I need to be more, I, and it was really through the
process of doing the course with a leader that I understood what curiosity, curiosity
means in leadership.
So I feel like I'm a curious person, but I need to be more curious about the decisions
that I'm making and how I'm leading and what the potential impacts are.
And that for me is something that I've taken away from this that I need to go away and
learn on.
And, and learn about and think about.
I love that you know yourself so well though, Liz, you know your strengths and you know
the, the parts that you want to spend some more time on.
You, you are a great communicator.
You always have been.
And we see that as a common trait to communicating with clarity and whether it's captaining the
Australian netball team or working in a law firm.
Is that something you've given thought to?
Yeah, but I do like a lot of people.
Um, and it was interesting again, doing this course with a leader that, um, we're all very
quick to talk about what we're not good at or what our focus is.
What our failings are or what we don't do, which was really interesting.
And I think a good leader does that, has understanding of that.
Um, and for me, I'm a good communicator.
I've, I've always in trouble for talking in class.
There's a surprise.
News flash.
Um, but the challenge for me around communication was the flip side and that's listening.
And I think communication is important.
The ability to sell a vision to people and the ability to articulate what that looks like.
Um, really clearly set out what the behaviors are and then very clearly talk about the
accountabilities is really important, but in getting there, you actually need to learn
to listen a lot to your team.
And that to me has been what I've had to work on over the years.
How important has a collaboration been for you Liz?
Yeah, super important actually.
And again, I tend to be someone who is really decisive in my decision-making as we've talked
about, and I want to get out there and do it, but I've had to learn again, it's all
the learnings about, um, about collaboration.
Collaborating in leadership and letting go of things so that that collaboration can
happen.
I think when you're a leader and you, and you try to collaborate, you, you do need to
understand that you can't do everything.
And that was a real lesson for me, but then in terms of doing what I'm good at, which
was playing netball and, and being a teammate, that collaboration was really easy because
I learned very early on, especially in my sport, not one person can do it all.
And that's what frustrated me about being a lawyer actually, was that I don't think
law firms do collaboration particularly well.
Or they didn't when I was practicing.
In what way?
Um, it was very much, um, so every part, there was a series of partners who were all part
of this business, but they all had their own business within the business.
And they were really focused on their business because that's where the profitability and
the money came from.
Whereas I think if law firms and not just law firms, but certainly businesses look to
collaborate with, within the businesses, things would get stronger and information would be
shared.
And I used to think that that didn't happen a lot.
Because there was this real, well, I'm going to keep that for myself because that's my
competitive advantage.
Yeah.
Yep.
The, uh, the challenge of hierarchy in that world is a big shift.
We think in the way great teams work now more than ever.
Who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Uh, I've had, I've been really fortunate.
I've had lots of great leaders, but I'd have to start with my parents.
You know, they set a really good example of what a great relationship looks like.
I've, um, you know, I've since found out that their decision-making prism was, um, or the
filter was, can we include them?
Can we include our kids in this?
Yes, we can.
Well, we'll do it.
No, we can't.
Well, we won't do it.
So, you know, they really set a great example for me of the sort of parent that I want to
be.
And I, I feel like that's like, regardless of all the corporate stuff and all of the
business, your family is your basic unit.
So to me, that's so important.
So mum and dad really, um, were great leaders in that regard.
You know, getting exposed to someone like Sheila, Sheila Ether was her name, and she
was just amazing in the way that she got people into sports, seeing how that one person can
be so powerful in a community.
And then going through my netball career, Julie Fitzgerald really stands out to me.
She was a great leader because she, um, she never played like above C grade at Karingai,
yet she was a great coach because she was the, she's the queen of collaboration.
She goes and gets the answers from her players.
And so you feel like your, your input is valued.
And so you buy into the game plan because it's part, partly yours.
And so she was, has been successful over such a long period.
And when I watch her coach now, she still gets excited.
When someone does something well, as she did when I was, she had me in under 19s and like,
so that was like 30 something years ago.
So she's still got that great passion, but I really think her strength is that she doesn't
pretend to know all the answers.
And a lot of leaders could learn from that.
Um, you know, and then when I was in the, in the diamonds, you know, Vicky Wilson was
very much a lead by example.
She wanted to be the biggest and the baddest and the strongest, and that was her solo leadership.
And then Kath Harvey Williams was very similar, but she was, um, you know, much more able
to bring, or she was also, she had her other team.
Her strengths as well, which was, um, you know, working really well with the coach in
a really collaborative manner and getting the best out of her, which I thought was interesting
with her ability to manage up and then send it down to us as well.
So, you know, I think every leader has good or bad, has things that you can learn from.
And I've had leaders I've thought were not much chop, but rather than going, they're
not much chop.
I've actually looked at them and gone, how do I learn from that?
How do I learn from what they don't do well?
So that when it's my turn to lead, I will do well.
Yeah.
It sounds like you've grabbed pieces from everyone along the way.
I was in preparation for this, watching some videos, Liz, and there's a great pictures
of your mum and dad sitting at the netball and, uh, you know, I remember, you know, meeting
them both and, uh, they've been in your corner every night.
And you're right, starting there, isn't it?
If you've got this gift of that example in life and, and you're obviously passing it
on, you and Matt now, it's, uh, like winning the lottery in lots of ways, isn't it?
For sure.
If you could collaborate with anyone, we love the spirit of collaboration and the work we're
doing at a leader.
Is there been someone you thought, you know, what could be, I know you've got a range of
different passions in a whole heap of different areas.
If you thought that's the person I'd love to connect or collaborate with.
Um, I got to work a few years ago with Kate Jenkins, who's a federal, was a federal sex
discrimination commissioner at the time.
She's so smart, like being in the room with smart people.
And I just chit to chair, we were doing a state of the game review for netball and she
was on it.
And I was like, oh my God, I am, I am the dumbest person in this room and I've got to
lead them.
So that was like a real challenge for me because she's so smart.
Joe Pollard was on that.
She was really smart.
And like.
Really cluey.
Um, and I just look at women like that and I go, God, they're so like, they're so across
their field.
I sometimes feel like I try to do so much that I'm not really across deeply into whatever
field I'm doing, but they are.
And particularly Kate, she's so across her field.
So collaborating with her was just amazing.
And, you know, at the start I was like, I'm the dumbest person in this room.
How do I lead them?
And how do I chair this group?
And by the end of it, we'd worked out a really good way to work, which is I just listened
to them and do what they told me to do.
Uh, but yeah.
Um, I just, I don't know that there's someone who I, I'll probably walk out of this room
and think of 10 names and I'll ring you up and I'll go, Luke, Luke, what are, there's
this person, there's this person, there's this person, there's this person.
Um, it's hard to single someone out because every day I meet really interesting people.
Like just doing the, the, our little group with Alita was so good to be able to collaborate
with those guys.
And, you know, I had a few side conversations with Brad Johnson around his business that
he's got at the moment.
And that was really interesting and trying to figure out a way to get him into gladiators.
Um, which was the show that I was filming at the time, the channel 10, because he's
got, you know, that protective gear.
So there's always, I feel like every day presents an opportunity to collaborate, um, with people.
And to me, that's probably where curiosity comes in.
And that's one of my favorite moments ever.
The first time I've seen you lost for words is for even just a second.
I'm glad that, uh, I, uh, I got it.
It's taken, uh, more than 20 years.
You are a legend, Liz.
I feel very, uh, grateful to be able to call you a friend.
It's always great to catch up with you.
And, um, it makes me laugh and, uh, great to see that you're going so well as you always
are, but, uh, maybe better than ever and appreciate you taking the time today.
Thanks Luke.
Always great to catch up.
Thank you for listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast powered by temper, a mattress
like no other.
And to make sure you don't miss an episode, click subscribe wherever you get your podcasts.