It's one thing to lead a team on the right path to winning a premiership
or building a workplace that encourages growth and sustainability.
But what if your team is an entire city?
How do you generate a positive environment for over 6 million people?
G'day, it's Luke Darson.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership,
both on and off the field, has been a lifelong passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective
and have had the privilege of working with thousands of leaders
in education, sport, industry and the arts
that have helped shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership
where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
I was lucky to be joined by the Lord Mayor of Melbourne, Sally Capp.
Leadership is something that she does on a daily basis on a pretty grand scale
and we discuss the importance of valuing input from others
and being able to embrace your failures.
Well, this is always an honour and a great privilege to sit down
with the Lord Mayor of Melbourne and an inspiration in every sense.
Sally Capp, thanks for joining me today, Sal.
Thank you, Luke.
What a lovely introduction.
Well, in terms of your history, we're going to talk a lot about leadership today, Sal.
Your history in leadership is quite extraordinary,
from the youngest possible age.
Where did you get the drive from?
Well, I'm really comfortable in the have-a-go mode.
I know that probably sounds a bit simplistic,
but I've been brought up that way.
And when you're in have-a-go mode,
you do appreciate that there are going to be consequences,
humiliations and embarrassments and failures, frankly.
But if you're comfortable in the have-a-go mode,
it means that you'll keep having a go
and you're not daunted by those situations.
And I think there's a lot about leadership,
about really stepping into the unknown or the undecided
or the opaqueness of so many situations.
And let's face it,
it's rare that you get an easy yes, no, go, stop situation.
It's really about managing the 49% to 51% situations
where there are pros and cons both ways,
but you've actually got to step into making a decision.
And to me, that's a lot to do with leadership.
But what's really helped me is that I'm really comfortable in having a go.
Can you give me an example, Sal, where we've gone for,
I don't know, but I'm just going to have a go.
Yeah.
Hmm.
Well, so many, as you've said, and I do get nervous, of course.
One of the things that really stands out for me when I was younger
was my father saying to me, nerves are the sign of a champion.
And it's all about how you channel those nerves, that adrenaline,
that fear into something better or more positive.
So that was very early advice that I have.
And I think that that's really underpinning of being willing
to put yourself out there and take risks.
But even if I think about the decision to run for Lord Mayor,
for example, which has been one of the biggest changes in my life,
in my family's life in 2018, and it was very much that sense of passion
and wanting to make a difference and seeing something
that I felt I could really add some value to,
but it was really more that I wanted to see change.
And I had no qualifications in local government.
I'd never really even considered local.
I didn't consider local government seriously in many
of the activities I'd had previously, particularly in business.
I hadn't had a lot of interactions.
And again, I've never seriously been involved in policy development.
Or maybe I'm talking myself out of this job at the moment.
But there were all of these things that go through your mind,
as well as the taking on public roles like this
and putting yourself out there in an election.
It is one of the scariest things I've ever done.
It's really hard.
And all of those things ran through my mind and my husband Andrew's mind
and my family's mind.
And I think that's really important.
We like to do things as a team.
That's always great.
And ultimately, we made the decision staring at the ceiling
late on a Sunday night where we just said,
this is something we're going to do.
And it was that even with the considerations of all the downside,
that sense of passion and purpose really driving that decision-making
to take the risk to go into a situation that seemed quite daunting
and scary at that time.
But knowing that even in having a go, and this was the thing
that unlocked it for us, even in the having a go
and putting up a different proposition for Lord Mayor,
somebody that was quite different, that that would make a positive impact,
that really unlocked that decision for us and away we went.
Yeah, awesome story.
That's success anyway, whether the outcome is what you wanted,
which you've been elected twice.
No one else as a female Lord Mayor has ever been publicly elected twice.
I just want to go back because I love what you said before,
you know, the words from your dad.
I went,
the great pleasure of meeting too, Brian Capp, and what a legend.
Talk about someone.
I occasionally walk past him outside Kooyong and he's driven
and I can picture him having a go.
But nerves are for champions.
I remember hearing the great Tony Lockett,
who's the greatest goal kicker in the history of AFL,
and had the pleasure or maybe displeasure of playing against him at one stage.
And he was so nervous pre-game.
It literally would make him so sick every game.
I think, God, if you're that nervous,
because you scared a lot of people out there, Tony Lockett.
He was a fearsome.
He was a fearsome character.
But as you said, if you can harness that energy,
it becomes real positive and it's a power, not a weakness in the end.
Yeah.
It's also very humanizing, I think,
to realize that other people are in the same situation.
And mostly now to help me manage my nerves,
I do also reflect that there are many people in the audience
that would empathize with the situation
and would know that I'm feeling that way.
And mostly in my life,
I've found that people want to be supportive
and they want to provide advice and guidance
and they want to share those sorts of situations with you in a positive way.
And I really lean on those thoughts and that energy
to help me manage those fears.
That might sound quite esoteric,
but I literally can look at the audience
and think a lot of people out there have been in my situation
and they know I'll be feeling nervous
and they will be willing me to be successful.
I might be deluding myself, but that's what I say.
And I really harness that energy as well.
And when I look out at those situations
or even if I'm standing in front of a media pack,
I really honestly do bring it back to human to human scale
and that really helps me move forward.
You've had so many firsts along the journey
and glass ceiling you've smashed through.
It's probably a few concrete ceilings really to think what you've done.
And the first female agent general for Victoria based in London.
And what you did in that role expanded it to other regions.
First female board member of the famous Cullingham Football Club.
First ever, as we said, publicly elected female Lord Mayor.
I love what you said.
Have a go.
I'm going to take this on.
I may be nervous, but there are a lot of firsts.
I mean, when you look back,
how challenging was it to do that so often?
Well, I think I don't consciously look for those sorts of opportunities.
And most people would say that.
What I'm always looking for are ways to add value
and to be able to do that.
And gain value.
And I actually look for that in the people that I might employ in my teams
or I might work with in partnership.
Because in any sort of situation,
you have to have a mutuality to make sure that it really binds
and that you've got that shared purpose and goal.
There has to be a value on both sides.
So for me, I'm always looking at what have I already learnt or done
and that experience that I can feel confident
that it's going to make a difference.
to a role I'm going into.
But also what's new about that that really challenges me
and means that I'm still learning and developing.
And I guess that's part of feeling comfortable
in being outside your comfort zone because I welcome that.
And when it comes to those firsts,
every single one of those times has been that as the underlying element.
And then I also look for not just the one step forward,
but the 10 steps forward, whether that's for me personally,
whether that's for the organisation,
or that's for the role, or in some cases it's been,
what does it mean for women in leadership as well?
And where you can add those dimensions in,
then that's extra special.
But a big part of it is, firstly, I've had lots of bumps
against the ceiling where it's hurt my head more
than I've made much progress.
And two, I know that in taking on those roles,
there are risks and I'm really comfortable with,
I wouldn't say failing, nobody sets out to fail,
but if I need to be vulnerable in those times to say
that I've never done this before, or this is new,
or it's new for the organisation, or it's a difficult environment,
I'm really comfortable to call those things out.
And again, I think it makes it also easier for the people
around you to respond as well because when you go in as the first,
so I remember that first Collingwood board meeting
in the old Victoria Park social club upstairs in the legendary ballroom
that has a fist punch through one of the walls
and cracks in the glass doors and carpet that your feet stick to
on the way through, you know, the bar area.
And I remember how nervous our fellow board members were as well.
Ed, very welcoming.
But I was new into that culture and also being the first female,
that was something completely different,
not just somebody that was from outside the little group there.
So I remember so distinctly that one
of the things that was necessary to do was make the other board members
feel comfortable with me being there and so really putting it out there
that there were many things I didn't know and I was keen to learn,
but here are the things that I thought I was pretty good at
and where I could add value and that immediately gave them a sense
of where I was going to play even if that was initially
and where my focus areas were going to be
and we started up a bit of a common language.
I remember Kevin Rose saying that he'd purposefully,
reduce the amount of F words he said in the meeting as a result,
all those sorts of fun things.
But you do need to find that equilibrium and being first should be
as good an experience for everybody around you as it is for you,
particularly when you know you're going into something that's new
or uncertain or potentially difficult and really building that rapport
so people can work together is important.
Yeah, and picking up on what you said,
so we're talking a lot about,
empowering leadership and I love what you said,
it's a value add both ways.
So if you're employing someone in your Lord Mayor's office
or likewise if it's someone who's supporting you on the campaign,
there's got to be a value both ways and I suppose that's something
that we're really passionate about is there is a bit of a shift now
that people are looking to that.
It's not just there's a hierarchy and the old school leadership
and you would have come up through that with,
I often speak about the big corner office and you know what,
you get your set tasks.
When you haven't got a voice,
do you think that that is the way forward now
where it generally has to be a collaboration
with the people you work with?
How good is that?
Yeah.
I mean, what were we even thinking in the old days?
I remember as a young lawyer going to a meeting
with a senior partner, very senior,
and it wasn't I lucky to be in that meeting
and I'd been asked to prepare for it.
So being diligent, I did that and I read up all the regulations
and I was ready and during the course of that meeting,
the client asked a question.
And because I'd done all that preparation,
I stepped into the conversation at that point
and I gave an opinion based on my research.
When we got into the lift after that meeting,
the senior partner looked at me with venom and said,
I don't give an F what you think.
Never speak in a meeting.
Wow.
And I was so put back in my place.
Look at me.
I'm even blushing to think of it because of the emotion of that.
I was definitely being,
put in my place.
No discussion of whether what I'd added to the conversation
was valuable or not.
And I think to the circumstances now where I can play a really big role
in this and that is valuing the input of other people
and knowing that whether it's people with less experience,
so they're bringing new eyes, people with more experience,
or people with different perspectives,
that that diversity of thinking actually gives you a better result,
whether it's internally or externally in your organisation,
to really embrace that.
Embrace that is powerful.
And it does mean, of course,
that it adds a complexity to your decision-making and your processes.
But from my perspective, that investment has been paid back in spades.
And so it is the new way of going forward.
It's a new way of leading.
It does have some challenges to it, but they're absolutely worthwhile.
How old were you when that happened?
Oh, 22.
So how do you pick yourself up from that?
What did you do next?
Well, exactly.
And there were more of those situations as a young lawyer
in that very hierarchical world, particularly, I've got to say,
particularly as a female, than now.
And another great lesson from my parents was,
it's an old adage, what doesn't kill you makes you stronger.
So just gathering every single one of those experiences
and learning from them.
And even if it was only to build up my own resilience,
because I don't agree with any of that.
Of course, it taught me the sort of leader I didn't want to be.
So there's even value in that.
You can tell I'm an optimist and very positive.
So I'd like to turn it around.
Did I have moments of sheer frustration and anger and emotion?
Yes.
I even had a meeting where I burst out in tears hysterically
in a professional meeting, which was completely inappropriate.
And I picked myself up and walked out and got some tissues
and fixed myself up.
And I...
Went straight back into that meeting room.
So lots of lessons along the way, what I can do better,
how I can be a better person.
And, you know, we all put up with difficult situations
and I think you've got to embrace those challenges
and keep moving forward.
But if we all accept those and we continue them,
then that's terrible.
But if we go through those situations and resolve to do better
as a result of them,
then that's good.
And it's always been one of my...
If you're a have-a-goer, you know you're going to have lots of failures
and make mistakes.
But it's what you learn from those situations
that gives you the 10 steps forward I was talking about earlier.
If you actually take the time to recognise it,
get the value from it and move forward.
It reminds me more recently of a meeting I had with an investor in Israel
where I went to do a pitch and, of course,
I had a...
I had a slide pack that had all of the brilliant things that I'd done.
It wasn't long, Luke, but, you know,
the slide pack with the things that I had done well
because I was seeking, you know, the support and investment
of this leader, business leader.
And as I started this slide pack, he interrupted me
and he said, now, have you got slides in there
that tell me your five best failures?
I was completely taken aback.
And I said, no, of course I don't.
I'm here to do the sell job on you.
And he said, well, the sell job for me is for you to tell me
your five best failures and what you learnt from them
because that gives me confidence that you can drive deals
and companies forward and when you're faced with challenges
that you've got good experiences and self-awareness
to be able to deal with them.
Has that resonated with me in the years since?
Yes.
I am.
I absolutely love that and I think more of us should embrace that
because this sense of whether it's tall poppy syndrome
or undermining people because of failures is something
that really holds us back as individuals and as a community
and we need to really push beyond it.
Yeah, and it's unfortunately an Australian thing sometimes,
isn't it?
The tall poppy doesn't resonate when you go to other countries.
I always think of the Greg Norman quote he often spoke about,
if you're lucky enough.
If you're successful enough to buy a nice car in America
and I don't like all parts of American culture,
someone's likely to say nice car and he said in Australia,
someone's likely to run their keys down the side of it
and we have got that issue a little bit around how we treat people.
I've got to ask you the question, memorable failures then?
What did you say on the spot then?
Oh, gosh.
What did you go with?
Yeah, so many.
Well, the first one that really came to mind was when I decided
to leave the law and you get to a point where you go,
you're going to keep advising, which has lots of benefits to it,
a lot of variety and intellectual stimulation, et cetera.
You're going to keep advising or you're actually going to go out
and have a go at the things you've been advising other people on
in all those years and I decided to make the move and so funny
because when I look back, I realise that in making that move,
I put together a business case, another slide deck.
I walked up and down, you know, the main street to,
meet with lots of potential investors because I needed shareholders,
I needed capital to get this new business going
and I just kept getting no, no, no and what I'd done
with this slide deck is that I assumed a lot of things.
Everybody that I went to visit, of course, I started with the people
that I'd been working with as a lawyer because I felt they knew me
and they knew my skill set and that they would automatically want
to support this new venture of mine and I completely underestimated the fact
that I was going to be a lawyer.
I was going to be a lawyer.
They knew me as a lawyer but they didn't know me at all
as an entrepreneur or somebody that wanted to start up a new,
I called it adventure capital rather than venture because it was so risky.
Was this the private equity business you started?
Yeah, the private equity business.
So I kept getting no's and no's and no's and I had to really go back
and rethink and I had a business partner, Tony, and we agreed.
We had to go about it completely differently and that was
to still identify the opportunity but really highlight the risks.
But also talk about what we'd both done in our lives that we felt
could bring success to this new venture and really de-risk us
as a proposition and it's really something I've taken.
It's one of my career rules actually that I've taken forward from then
and that is that I have a responsibility.
Everybody says take risks, take risks.
That's great.
But the corollary of that is you've got to find ways
of de-risking yourself so that other people can take
a risk with you or take a risk on you.
And so I spend a lot of time now preparing ahead of big decisions
or big interviews that I'm doing or big opportunities I'm pursuing,
looking really across other people's perspectives,
understanding the circumstances and then presenting in a way
that de-risks, whether it's myself or the issue or the proposition.
Yeah, great thoughts, Sam.
I'll tell you a step back.
There'll be people listening.
They'll listen to this and they'll say, all right, I understand that
and I understand there were some failures, but Sally Capp's a freak.
You know, she was first-class honours and, you know what,
she might have had a few steps along the way, but she just was something.
How could I ever be like that?
What do you say to young girls and I suppose young boys as well
who might be listening who want to get to the point where they are
in leadership and they can create things that you've done?
What's the advice you'd give them?
I don't think anyone's called me a freak before, Luke.
So that's a new one.
No, so I'm racking that up as a first.
Term of endearment that was to the Lord.
Yes, no, I get it.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Look, I really have a very strong work ethic and I share that with lots
of people in my family and around me, including my husband
and what we're doing with our family because it's,
there's the saying, aptitude gives you height but attitude gives you
the pinnacle.
It's something like that.
I've got that completely wrong.
I need Andrew around me.
But it's really, it's about your attitude, not your aptitude.
It's, you do, you can have talent but unless you apply it and you're
willing to work hard at teasing out all the elements of that and making
it relevant and applicable and achievable, then it's a waste.
And so for me, and I was a diligent student.
I was one of those sucks.
But I was a bit naughty but, you know, my main focus was
on really achieving in that way and yet most of the feedback
from my parents would still be, you know, are you working hard
enough at that?
Was there still something more you could have been doing?
And I guess that still drives me forward, my mum and dad,
Brian and Sherry.
Yeah.
Like most parents have been a big influence on my life and I do
think that even today.
I mean, I have busy days.
And I'm across lots of issues but I am driven by is there more I could
have done and is there something else I could have fit in and could it
have been better?
And a lot of that sense of how it can be better actually comes
from your personal effort.
And so I really encourage everybody that there are no rules.
There sort of are no barriers if you're willing to work hard enough.
Now that seems easy to say.
When I sit back looking at my career, which I've absolutely loved
and a very happy, happy family life.
So I've had so many benefits in that way.
There's no doubt a lot of fantastic role models and I haven't had
to worry about too much, let's be frank.
But I've also seen through some of those rarer experiences,
some very raw personal experiences, as well as some
of those professional failures that if you stay focused
on what you're doing, you're going to be able to do a lot more.
So if you're still turning up every day, still trying your best
and really putting the effort into that hard work and that ethic,
then it's amazing what you can achieve.
Yeah, have a go and then the work.
I mean, it sounds simple, isn't it?
But you combine that together.
I did want to touch on the family because to me that is another
amazing element to your story and lucky enough again to have met
the family.
Nicholas is 22.
He's just graduated from Melbourne Uni.
William's at university.
He's at Yale University as the ducks of his school and, you know,
talk about passing on the high achiever gene.
And your husband, Andrew Sutherland, is one of the most extraordinary
people I've ever met in my life.
He's the most engaging, passionate.
When you walk out of a, if it's five minutes or 50 minutes,
I feel like you've had your batteries charged up for the rest
of the day being around your husband and you are a great team together.
So how do you get that, you know, I suppose to achieve what you've done
and have the family life at the same time,
you guys have nailed it.
Well, it seems that way.
I know and I think so.
I think so.
But I guess I would say again, you know, when everything seems fantastic
that usually behind the scenes there's an incredible amount of effort
and emotion and dedication and patience and commitment that's gone
into this and it has.
It's been a real juggle and there are some really big decisions
that you make along the way and I think that's another reflection
for me.
There have been times when I've really been tormented
about decisions because it's that juggle and that balance
and particularly when you've got children and you want to be able
to spend really great quality time with the kids but you want
to be able to pursue a career as well.
Those sorts of difficult balance decisions come up all of the time
and when I look back, I really feel that where we've gone forward on the basis,
of things that are value-based, that are what's most important to us,
where we've had discussions, Andrew and I, about really what those priorities
are at the end of the day, what makes us happy, what brings us joy
and making sure we have that focus on relationships and family,
whether it's family or it's friends as well.
When it comes down to it, they need to be the priority
because they're going to be the most lasting, the most fulfilling,
the most satisfying and I think we've managed that balance pretty well
but there have been some really stressful times when you're considering
what's in front of you and what's the best way forward.
Changing tax cell for a little bit, there's so many areas to go with you
but I'm interested in now you're in this incredible leadership role,
high profile in Melbourne, there's so much that comes your way
but then you've got this element of social media that everyone's got
to deal with now too.
And to me, it's a disgrace.
Female leaders in particular seem to get absolutely attacked on that basis.
I mean, a lot of people are dealing that every day.
Teenage kids, most people have got that.
How do you cope with that?
It's a really good question because being in public roles as well,
so there are two elements here.
Public roles seem to mean that there are no rules even of normal civility
that apply.
Yeah.
To people in public roles.
I've found that really confronting and also social media, as you know,
just seems to give permission for people to say anything they want to
with absolutely no consequences and that's really disappointing
and more of us need to stand up to say that's unacceptable
and I see more of that sort of conversation and discussion coming through
as we go forward.
Of course, you have to have a very thick skin.
There's no doubt about that.
And there are times still, and that's where I lean on my team a lot as well,
of sanity checking and support in those moments.
But it does also, and I think the last 12 months have particularly highlighted
this for me, you have to have a resolve if you want to be a leader
and if you want to be involved in these sorts of discussions and debates
and let's face it, there are highlights and there are lowlights
and if you want to be involved in important issues,
and progress in our community, then you really have to be willing
to have that resolve to keep going even when it feels like everybody
around you is telling you that it's wrong or you're doing a bad job,
criticising, undermining, attacking.
You have to have that centre in yourself of that resolve.
Part of that is being willing to admit if you've made a mistake.
I think that's really important.
And part of leadership and having the resolve to do that.
I can tell you I've had to do that and it's tough,
but if you think it's the right thing to do, you must do it.
And same if you think something's the right thing to do
and everybody's telling you it's wrong, then just keep going
because even in doing it, you're making a difference
no matter what the ultimate outcome is.
And so I've become much more focused on that.
But I will say I am a team player
and I think building a team around you
who can have different views to you
but will absolutely stand behind you when needed
and that's both in your personal life
and in professional life is key and absolutely necessary.
I think what you said about owning the mistake that is yours
feels a bit like a lost start in 2021 to me
and particularly I can't understand
and walk in your shoes in political life now,
but there seems to be,
there seems to be that advisors are saying
whatever you do, don't accept responsibility.
Whereas to me, it's the most human thing to do, isn't it?
A disarming thing to do is, and clearly part of your makeup.
Is that going to always stay with you?
Absolutely.
And I think it's a testament to you, Luke, as well.
And I do look for other people and leaders that,
to me, that's a standout characteristic.
It's a differentiator.
And I like to work with people.
I like to work with people like that
and learn from people who have that approach.
It's much more relatable.
I think it really drives much more empathy as well
and understanding of what you're going through.
And it's actually one of the toughest things you can do.
So if you do, do it.
But it also creates the environment for other people to do it.
Now, what we find in culture so much
is that deflection or avoidance, distraction or cover-up
because people don't want to admit mistakes.
If that's the sort of culture,
you have danger, danger, warning, warning.
Much better to have a culture where people feel comfortable
to call out mistakes or to say sorry
or to identify issues and be open to that as well
so that you can keep moving forward.
Because let's face it, we all do it.
It happens every day and it has to.
In the pace and complexity of life these days,
we know that these things are going to happen.
So the sooner you fail and the more open,
you are to mistakes and to moving forward from that,
the more effective you can be.
And I remember actually just back to the campaign
when we set up the first campaign in 2018,
had no idea what we were doing, Andrew and I,
which we worked out in about five minutes.
We set up a team around us to support us
and frankly lead in many ways.
And one of the first things I said is,
please know I am going to make a lot of mistakes
because I've never done this before.
And I need you to point those out to me
as quickly as possible so that we can respond to them
and deal with them and move on.
And a wonderful person, Nicole,
who was our campaign manager,
looked at me and said,
that's the most brilliant thing you could have said
because I'll make mistakes too,
even though I've done this many times
and so will other team members.
And so it created a very constructive culture,
which we had to form instantly
because we only had three months
to pull the whole thing together.
And it was really set a pace and a momentum
to what we could achieve as a team
because that was one of our underlying principles.
Yeah, I'm really conscious, Bec and I,
parenting-wise as well,
is to just occasionally,
more than occasionally as it turns out,
and go, hey, geez, I got that wrong.
And it's pretty disarming for the kids to hear that as well,
to look at you and go,
yeah, I think I maybe pulled the wrong rein there
and maybe lost it a little bit on that occasion.
And you're fine, you can then move forward
and allow them to have conversations as well,
being great.
So you don't achieve what you do
and have the family balance,
I'm assuming, without some pretty good rituals
and routines and habits.
Is there anything you can share with us on that front?
What a good question.
Wow.
Routines and habits, very good.
I like to,
I haven't, nobody's asked me that for ages, Luke,
so good one.
I try to be very organised.
So in the chaos of life,
I do really like to have a diary
that's,
that's been well thought through
in terms of what's on for the day.
And I rely on other people to help me completely with that.
I like to really stick to time.
I value your time, you value my time.
So I really like to do that.
I find that the more organised you can be
on the things that you can control,
the more receptive and agile you can be
to the things that are beyond your control.
So we really focus on those elements of our lives
that we can control personally and professionally.
And then that sets us up for,
for the unexpected and unpredictable things
that happen in life.
We always have people that can catch the balls
that we might have missed.
And that's been absolutely key,
particularly for juggling family and profession.
So I have been so lucky with family,
my parents-in-law, my parents,
sisters-in-law particularly,
and my siblings to know that there are people
that can catch the balls.
And I think that's a really good thing.
And even in primary school,
when I was really working so hard
to get that career moving to the next level,
to know that I could rely on other mums,
I was straight out to other mums to say,
hey, I'm going to need your help.
And the great thing when I said that,
and the perfect one was first day of school
for young Will, we dropped him off in the morning
and all organised to pick him up at the gate at 3.15.
But I got the call at 12.15 from the school
to say, your son is going to be in school
and your son, Will's here.
He's the only child still here.
And I said, what do you mean?
And they said, the first day is a half day.
So I completely dropped the ball
and knowing that somebody could be there
to help in those urgent situations.
You've got to know, and it's the same in your team.
You've just got to know that you've got each other's back
to be able to step into those situations.
But the routines is very much around feeling organised
on the things that you can control.
We've been talking,
a lot about in the work I've been doing
about the dimensions of what makes a great leader.
So what does self-leadership mean to you?
Self-leadership means accountability.
And I mean that in a very positive way.
Another word that a lot of people don't necessarily like,
but is discipline.
And I really like to have discipline.
Having said that, and maybe it really plays
on the discussion we've just had,
is that I like to be spontaneous.
I like to be a little bit crazy at times.
Hard to believe, Luke, I know.
I like to be a little bit naughty,
whatever naughty is for me.
And you've got to allow yourself those moments
to let off steam and be yourself.
And so that's important for me.
To me, that comes back to the maybe overused term,
but it is about authenticity.
If you are,
not being true to yourself,
and in doing that,
allowing other people to see the true you,
then not only letting yourself down,
because who wants to live a life with the stress
of trying to be something that you're not,
but you are letting everyone down around you.
And the richness of life experiences
comes from being open to that.
So being vulnerable.
To me, vulnerability is powerful,
and to being completely authentic.
And that means that you can have failures and humiliations,
but you can also be there for the triumphs and the accolades.
They go hand in hand.
And I don't ever intend to live a one-dimensional life.
And so really bringing all of that to the fore
is important to me.
But I do have those sense of discipline and accountability,
particularly in my interactions with other people.
Beautifully said.
I'm interested in what the naughty Lord Mayor does.
I won't go there,
but I can see that spark in your eyes.
I know you do like a good time when the opportunity provides.
How do you think about positively impacting others in your environment?
It's a really good point.
And I think one we should all explore more
because you can have a positive impact in a very purposeful way.
So when you,
you decide and you determine that there are ways
in which you can use your powers and influence
to be supportive and make a positive impact on other people.
And I think in many ways,
that's the more obvious and easier thing to do.
And I do take time to think about that.
But what we should be more sensitive to,
I think, is the way that you can have positive influences
that the coincidence,
the dental or the unintended
or the things you're not necessarily conscious of.
And the reason they're more difficult
is because they happen in moments
where you're not deliberately thinking about it.
It's, it's, it's your, your aura.
Let's say it's your halo.
It's, it's the unconscious everyday things
that can make such a difference.
And one of them for me is the word, thank you.
Yeah.
And I know I've just said they're the,
they're the sort of more unconscious,
conscious moments.
If it becomes so much of,
of an ingrained part of what you do to be grateful
and to say thank you,
then that they're the little things
that can happen every day
that can make a positive influence,
can be positive on people's lives,
to be grateful for the value that they're adding.
One of the most humbling experiences for me last year
was when I would come into work
because I got to go to work every day,
which was, was great for me
to see the teams getting organized in the morning
to go out and clean our city.
And they were people that had been chefs at the MCG
or had been front of house
in one of our magnificent theaters
who had found themselves out of work
and ineligible for other support.
Who said, I will put myself forward as a city cleaner.
And that in doing that,
they were also helping our community
in such an amazing way.
Very humbling for me.
They had a positive influence on me at the same time.
As us organizing those programs
to be able to provide that support for people
who needed work and a sense of team
and a sense of purpose in, you know,
one of the most extreme situations
we've gone through in our lifetime.
So it goes both ways.
And I think being deliberate
about how you have influence is important,
but also being mindful of it's the other moments
that can make just as much of a difference.
Yeah, what a great story.
I wasn't aware that that happened
in the city of Melbourne,
that people actually volunteered
to repurpose themselves and clean the city.
How do you think about creating
and sharing your vision, Sal,
with the team you work with?
Oh gosh, that's everything
from using the complete force
of my personality and passion
to see things through
to being conscious of
how do you actually galvanize
and motivate people behind something
that is an outcome of yours,
an objective or a project.
And I think inclusiveness is really important.
I think a lot of times
when I was coming up as a young worker,
leaders would only try and tell you
the good bits of what was coming up
and not so much talk about the more challenging
or difficult or complex parts.
And even today,
I think people respond with such cynicism
if you don't give them the full story
or you try to deflect.
So I think in terms of building teams,
it's important that people
can see the full spectrum
of what's coming up,
that you share the detail
of what's going to be challenging
as much as what's going to be positive and fun
and that you get that input
into projects early
so there's a sense of ownership
over not just the outcome
but also the process
on how we're going to get there,
that those elements are really important.
And it's something you've reminded me actually
in this conversation
that I don't do enough of
and that is really celebrating
at the end of the day.
And I think that's really important.
At the end and reflecting back on the team
because the pace at which we all work these days,
it's so easy to move on to the next thing.
And we do need to find those spaces
to celebrate and to give feedback.
And I receive feedback as a gift.
Can you imagine how much feedback
I get in this role?
It's a lot.
And I mostly receive it as a gift
if people have felt so incensed
or passionate about something
that they're actually
contacted me to give me that feedback.
I take that on board.
I might not use all of it,
but certainly I take it as a gift
and I want to give feedback
as a gift as well.
And if we think of cultures
and conversations
that we challenge each other to improve,
then that really turns the paradigm
on how we interact around
giving constructive or negative feedback
as much as positive.
I love the way you frame that.
It's just, you know, feedback's a gift.
You know,
receiving it and delivering it.
It's such a better way to think about,
you know,
for what some people find
the hardest thing, isn't it?
You know, because it's still
always challenging, isn't it?
You know, it might be a gift,
but sometimes you're not sure
you want to unwrap it right away.
And I love what you just said
about celebrating as well.
And I often think a lot of my analogies
come from the sporting world.
So as a fanatical Collingwood
former board member,
you'll appreciate this.
Nathan Buckley is one of the greatest
players at your club ever
and a great person.
I think there's a quote
from him.
He might've even written in his book
that he didn't enjoy
one moment of his career
because he was told all the way along
until he won a premiership,
he couldn't enjoy it,
couldn't celebrate.
It's one of the saddest things I've ever,
this is a guy who achieved more in sport,
is a great person,
a great leader.
And then I saw firsthand in 2016
with the club that I play,
Luke Beveridge,
just changing that paradigm.
Every time something good happens,
let's celebrate.
And they were dancing and partying
and all the old school people in media,
you know, crusty old people like me,
you can't do that.
You know, like it's,
you know,
and the fun and the momentum that created
was the best.
And they, you know,
really broken that stereotype,
which has got to be a good thing.
Communicating with clarity,
so how do you approach that?
Communications, absolutely fundamental.
And the communicating with clarity,
I think is a lot to do
with simplifying messages
so that it really goes to the heart
of what,
you want to,
you want people to hear, frankly,
and to understand from it.
Now, I'm a lawyer.
I love words.
This has been a tough one for me.
And even now,
I get a lot of feedback about my answers,
sort of dancing around the topic
until I actually get to the point.
So this is a development area for me.
But I think the other part of this,
apart from the simplicity
and really getting to the point,
is to think of other people's perspectives.
Because what we say
isn't necessarily what people hear.
And if we put effort
into other people's perspectives,
what will they be looking for?
What will they be wanting to hear?
Or what is the element of your message
that is of most interest to them?
It may be that you actually change
that communication,
and you should for different audiences.
It may be that instead of doing
one big message to a whole lot of people,
you chunk it down
and you make the effort
to actually get to the point.
You actually go around to smaller groups.
It can mean more time
and it's more of a commitment.
But actually,
if you're focused on getting the message to them
and frankly receiving also the feedback,
then putting that effort in is important.
So I think communicating with clarity
is about simplicity of message
and getting to the point.
But it's also about thinking of the audience
and their perspectives
and being as prepared as possible
to deliver it in a way
that they hear what you want.
That's what I'm trying to say.
Well said.
Collaboration,
I know it's a huge part of you
and what you do.
Do you think about it consciously?
How do you incorporate it every day?
I'm naturally a collaborator.
I love people
and I love spending time with people.
And I can come out of a conversation
and people say,
oh gosh, that was so difficult.
And I think, I loved that conversation.
That was terrific.
And I really value difference
and the contribution.
But I've also seen the absolute support
that comes from collaboration as well.
We've talked about a lot of those themes today.
And I think that people underrate collaboration,
coordination, cooperation,
all of those words,
because sometimes it's just easier
to get on and do it.
But a lot to do with preparation.
How key is preparation
to the success of the final outcome?
To me,
preparation, it goes to that being organised
and that sense of discipline and accountability.
The more prep you can do,
not always possible,
but the more prep you can do for me
includes that collaboration.
Who are the stakeholders?
How are we involving them?
How have we embraced and communicated with them?
What level of knowledge do they have?
What level of action would be required?
And how can we get everybody on board
from the earliest steps possible
is,
a really big part of creating
that foundation for success.
And as you know,
the stronger and the broader
and the deeper that foundation,
the bigger platform you have to leap forward.
So to me,
collaboration is one of those key elements,
sort of in everything,
infused in everything these days.
One of the great things about social media
is you can reach out
in all sorts of different ways.
But to me,
it goes to one of those essential elements
of preparation for success
is collaboration.
Final question, Sal,
and we value your time enormously
and really appreciate you being so generous today.
If you're thinking of a leader in your life
who's been the greatest inspiration,
can you name one?
I've mentioned my parents a lot, et cetera,
but somebody else who's been an absolute leader,
and I've been so lucky to have her
as part of my personal life as well,
is my aunt, Ros Kelly,
who was one of the first women into federal parliament,
who was one of the first women
to break the ceiling about becoming a minister,
to sit around the cabinet table,
who was actually the first woman
sitting in parliament.
She wasn't literally sitting in parliament,
but a sitting member of parliament
to have a baby
and everything that that meant.
And somebody who has stepped into
really big issues like climate change
way back in the 80s and 90s
and stayed dedicated to issues like that
throughout her life following politics
and has still made time for friends and family
with the strength,
the strength of relationships
that have endured decades.
Ros has been somebody I really admire.
She's had an amazing impact on my life,
but also on many others
as a leader in her professional career
and somebody who's had a big personal impact
on lots of people.
So I feel really lucky
to have had somebody like that in my life.
And do you still run things past her today?
Oh, yes, of course.
I mean, she would say,
she can't believe I didn't get into,
even though it's local government,
local government politics sooner,
given the sort of influence
she's been on my life.
But I've also saw firsthand
when I was much younger,
the toll that public life can take on people.
And she really put in a massive effort to that.
But Ros was one of the first people I called
when considering the Lord Mayor role, for example.
And I actually rang thinking she'd say,
you've got to be joking.
But when I rang her to put,
this idea to her,
she said, absolutely, positively, go for it.
And it's that sort of positive energy
and passion that she's had on me.
I picture the 22-year-old lawyer in the lift
with the senior partner telling you to be quiet.
And I just think, you know,
the impact you are having on so many people
and sharing what you're sharing today,
the change and that shift around,
it just is going to impact so many people's lives.
So thank you so much for sharing your wisdom.
And it's always an inspiration to speak to you.
Thanks again.
Thanks, Luke.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me, Luke Darcy,
produced by Matt Dwyer,
with audio production by Darcy Thompson.
To start your leadership journey,
I encourage you to go to elitacollective.com,
take our Empowering Leaders Indicator tool
and understand the impact you have on your environment.
Join us at Elita to learn, lead and collaborate.