How do you bring empathy, care and vulnerability into the elite sporting world of the AFL,
which has been dominated by alpha males and old school mentality, to change the way we
now think about coaching forever?
G'day, it's Luke Darson.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership, both on and off the field, has been a lifelong
passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective, and I've had the privilege
of working with thousands of leaders in education, sport, industry and the arts, that have helped
shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership, where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
In 2016, Luke Beveridge coached the Western Bulldogs in the AFL to their second premiership
in the club's history, ending a 62-year drought.
He has twice been recognised by his peers as the Outstanding Coach of the Year in 2015
and 2016.
Last season, 2021, he coached the Bulldogs to just their fourth grand final in close
to 100 years in the VFL-AFL competition.
His playing career extended over a decade and more than 100 AFL games.
Luke Beveridge is universally respected for his sense of purpose, his vision and his leadership.
Bevo, it's always great to spend time with you.
Thanks for joining me on the podcast.
It's a pleasure, Dars.
Thanks for having me today.
Now, Bevo, I feel fortunate enough that I crossed over with you for a few years in the
early 90s.
That's the start of my career.
And you'd been drafted from the Melbourne Football Club to our club.
And I don't think I've had this conversation with you, but I wanted to start here because
there are a couple of moments that have always stayed with me from the impact you had on
me as an 18 or 17 or 18-year-old at that stage.
And this sense of presence I always felt you had.
And there's two moments that I thought of in preparation for this chat.
There was a time, and I don't know if you remember this, but first-year player, you
think you're ready to play.
You're not getting a game.
I remember being really down.
I was thinking that perhaps that wasn't an opportunity that I was going to be able to
fulfill.
And you came and sat next to me and you just said, hey, mate, you're going to be a really
good player.
In fact, you're going to have a great career and you're going to be fine.
And I remember thinking, geez, how did he come to know that that was a time I really
needed that?
There were more senior players and guys that had been around.
And there was a second occasion.
We won a reserve grand final that year, one of those years, you might remember.
And I remember at the end of one night, late at night, I had a couple, might have been
carrying on a bit.
I was in a round with the coach and you grabbed me and said, hey, mate, you're better than
that.
And you sort of pulled me aside.
I remember, and it stuck with me, I'm thinking, not many people at 2.30 in the morning have
the presence to have a conversation like you did.
And it stayed with me for a long time.
Do you remember having that presence?
Do you remember having that impact on people even in the early days of your career?
I think I might have remembered you looking at me like you wanted to snot me that night
when I pulled you.
I don't think we were probably in the right state to be being too serious.
I'm not too serious about life, but I think, you know, the journey that I was on and some
of the struggles that I'd had probably in the early parts of my career and learning
to persist and persevere and probably being on the edge a lot of the time, I think I understood
what some players were thinking and what they were going through.
It was a daily and weekly emotional rollercoaster.
And I don't really remember.
You know, not many of my ex-teammates have ever said to me, like you just did, and I
really appreciate that.
It means a lot to me to us, that I had an influence because maybe I reached out.
But I like to think that, I think, you know, obviously we're going to be talking a little
bit about leadership, you know, today, but I like to think that I always looked at outside
of my own sphere and thought about other people's emotions and what they were feeling.
And for me,
I think that's where really powerful, impactful leadership starts.
You know, that's always been my belief.
I've always, you know, trying to describe you or summing up Bevo is almost the impossible
task.
And I don't know if you sense that as well, but to me, you've always had this great emotion,
great connection, great empathy for people.
And perhaps those stories that I shared before are evidence of that.
You always, it always felt to me like you were thinking about how other people were
going at any particular time.
Yeah.
And how they were going at any particular stage and a great love for people.
You know, I use that word love on purpose because not many people in our era would have
felt that way, but you also, if you cross the line with you Bevo, there's a line and
you can be pretty direct when that line's crossed and maybe even a little bit brutal
when that's the case.
Is that a fair way to describe it?
Yeah, maybe.
I think my default is to love and care for people first.
I give people chances.
If there are accidents or unintentional outcomes where people's best intentions were there.
But I must admit, I don't give people many chances when the early read is that they're
not a good person or that they're selfish and they won't hesitate to do wrong by people
around them.
I don't tolerate that.
And unfortunately, I think what happens is 99% of the time, you're a good person and
you're a caring person who wants to help others whenever you can and on the odd occasion
where maybe there's some emotion and it is a bit edgy, that's sometimes what you're remembered
for.
And I'm sensitive around that because it's still a part of me and in what I do now, I've
got to be really careful that there's no controversy.
Yeah, it's a fascinating insight, Bevo.
I mean, to me.
I think that's as great a part of you as any part, the care and the love comes out.
But I love the fact that people around you know exactly where they stand and always have
done.
I think even from that really young age, knowing you at that time, you could stand pretty clearly
on where you're still with Luke Beveridge.
Is that something that you try and soften a bit when you get older or it's just that's
your DNA and that's who you are?
I think I've matured like all of us.
You know?
I've made myself a little bit better.
I'm fortunate that I've been lucky in life, you know, in different stages of my life.
I've worked hard and not just in my working life, but in my relationships with my family.
I've had stability.
I'm fortunate in many, many ways.
And I don't think I was, I think I believe I was a later mature.
I had that.
I had that for quite a while.
But my personality was probably a little bit volatile for too long.
And probably until, you know, into my early 30s, I think that was when I really came around
and coaching really helped me with that.
Because you're not only technically and tactically in control of something, you're a manager
and you've got to make sure that the human resource and what you're trying to achieve
with managing personalities and emotions is on point.
And that hastened, I think, my maturity at that point in time.
But it was a bit late.
You know, I wish I was like that in my early 20s.
And I definitely cared for you, Luke, and my teammates and everyone that I've ever played with and been involved with in sport.
But I think in totality, I didn't grow up enough, you know, in my 20s.
And you think that sort of volatility, which is pretty common for young competitive, you know, players, alpha males, I think we all had that.
I can put my hand up and, you know, hopefully soften as you get older as well.
But part of it was probably needed in that environment as well, do you think?
But you look back and think, God, if I had a better handle on that like I did in my 30s, I might have had better outcomes earlier, is it?
Yeah, possibly.
There's no doubt that when you reflect, there's sliding doors moments in your life and in your career where, at times,
you say your football career could be over.
I always used to think if I got suspended, my position at any of the clubs I played with wasn't secure enough to endure too many things that were undisciplined.
I feel like I played the game hard enough, but I really, as far as being disciplined in the game, I was pretty good away from it at times.
As far as a confrontational aspect, I wasn't.
So.
So good.
But I think I, because I was so sensitive to that, I generally made good decisions to prolong my career and sustain what I was doing.
Could I have handled and managed relationships, especially managing up and, you know, with coaches and out?
Definitely.
You know, because I just, I wasn't mature enough in my thinking to understand.
You know, where they were coming from at times.
But I've really got no regrets with any of that.
I just, I just feel like if I understood my surrounds and my environment better, and I didn't spend enough time to do that.
Yeah, it's an interesting reflection.
I want to come back to some of that, Bevo, because I'm fascinated by your thoughts on that.
But I wanted to change tack and jump into a story that you've spoken about, but to me is still under.
And I think it's a good thing that you're saying that you're a senior coach.
And I think it's a good thing that you're a senior coach.
I think it's a good thing that you're a senior coach.
What you achieved at your old football club, St.
Bede's, Mentone, in the three premierships in a row, never done before in Australian rules.
Never done before in Australian sport, really, to take a team from C grade.
You went back to your old club.
You're an assistant coach.
They got relegated to C grade.
You win the grand final.
It was your first year as senior coach in C grade.
Tell me it's one of the great grand finals in football history, 47 points down, and you pull off a remarkable victory.
You're playing at that stage and have a massive.
You go to B grade and win, and then the team goes to A grade and wins the A grade against the side that the collegians, they told me, were on paper the far superior team.
It beat you by 100 points only two weeks earlier.
And we're talking about you doing that with almost the same players.
Eight played in all three, but you didn't go and pay money and recruit better standard players from AFL.
It is truly a remarkable sporting story in every sense.
When you look back on it, what are your memories and what do you think?
Yeah, my overriding thought is always how grateful I was for guys like Matt Beasley, the president, and those eight players that played in all three who just totally committed to what we were trying to do on and off the field.
And all the volunteers and helpers around the football club, that is always my overriding sense and feeling.
I'm really grateful for, in particular, the players.
Because they've essentially...
Provided the opportunity that I've had at AFL level and where my coaching has gone.
And I never lose sight of that.
They were just amazing.
And in the A section, premiership team, 20 of the 22 were St. Bede's alumni.
They were former students.
We had five under-19s.
Sam Anstey, who wasn't part of the alumni, was teaching at the school at the time.
And the other guy who didn't go to St. Bede's...
He's Jamie Maddox, who's now our development manager at the Western Bulldogs, which is an interesting irony.
So that was amazing when you think of the amateur nature of the game, you know, with the Vafa.
And, yeah, talking about sliding doors moments, you know, in that C section grand final, at one point, it was 21 goals, 12 to 21 goals, 11.
And, you know, can you fathom that?
Yeah.
And I think it was just amazing to see that score line, for there to be a point at the end, the difference was just amazing.
So I am very grateful.
I do feel fortunate and lucky in some ways.
I mean, if that game is two points the other way, the Ajax boys have got it over us.
But it was an amazing time, Darson, I think, when I'm really fortunate to be in this collaboration or the collaborative forum with...
with some really influential coaches.
And when you listen to Ange Postacoglu and Brian Gorgian and Eddie Jones and Neil Craig talk,
one of the things that comes through is they really believe in what they're trying to achieve, who they are, what they do, what they stand for.
They're prepared to take risks.
They coach on the edge.
And when I think back to those early days of coaching,
that's what I did.
And so in times of when you're challenged and there's some struggle in convincing people at different ends of the spectrum,
the belief in yourself and to stay true to what you believe in, it's just absolutely imperative.
And those guys I just mentioned, they just epitomize that.
And it's been great to listen to them because it's a reminder to me that, yeah, stay, you know, continue to believe in what you do.
Because it's, you know...
It's fostered some success, notwithstanding amazing contributions from a lot of others.
You'll love to talk to you about that in a moment as well,
the collaboration that is a passion of mine through the work we're doing with my great friend Matt Waterwitz and Alita and the Alita Connect program.
But I just want to go back to some beats for a moment because I rang a couple of your old teammates in preparation for this.
And I just want to get a sense.
I've read about it.
I've heard about it.
I've spoken to you about it.
To find out from their point of view and the words that sort of came up were,
this was the best three years of my life.
The way that Luke Beveridge made me feel through that time, I've never felt better about myself as a person.
You know, I might have been a 6 out of 10 player at best.
He made me feel and play like a 9 out of 10 player at the time.
And, you know, in an amateur setting, you've got people going to work.
Like, it's something amazing, mate.
It's really an incredible story.
It's, you know...
I love that the emotion runs freely with you, mate.
And I could hear emotion in their voices when they were telling the story, just how special that era was.
You know, how does that make you feel?
Yeah, emotional, mate.
It was.
It was an amazing part of all of our lives because I suppose the game, you know, we grew up loving.
For it to culminate in something like that was just, you know, incredible.
And, you know, the connections.
And as far as the friendships and the relationships, the things that endure and are long-lasting and they still remain.
We had a great social environment too.
We'd celebrate victories as well as anyone.
And I'm a great believer in that, you know, how do you measure success?
How do you identify and celebrate little successes or milestones along the way?
I mean, whatever it is, you have to make sure that you do.
You recognise your achievements.
It's not all about winning the trophy at the end of the year.
It's about what happens during the week and that week in competition.
And we definitely didn't miss out on an opportunity to bond and connect through small achievements,
which to us were just great, great moments in time.
And I think, you know, even this weekend, it's the anniversary of Paul Brennan's passing.
Paul was our ruckman in the game.
In the C and the B years.
And Paul was one of four boys who came to us from Udith Vale Aspendale, including Chris Jamerson and Sam Anstey,
who I mentioned before, and Anthony Scafidi, who was Andrew Scafidi's older brother.
And Andrew was already playing with us.
And those four young men in particular, it was only four players.
They had such an impact on the football club just through their personalities.
They weren't all senior players.
And Paul was overweight.
He was at the time and he wasn't fit.
And he just knuckled down.
He worked his, you know, he just worked so hard to be a part of the team.
And he was.
He was only six foot two and a half as a ruckman.
And Brezza was a police officer who, yeah, who took his own life.
But so this, the boys meet at the pier in Mordialloc.
And as a ritual, they jump off in memory of Paul.
And I've only really just been caught up in it last year.
And now, and I got a text yesterday to say, hey, we're doing it again.
And that's a sort of, you know, triumph from tragedy, sort of the whole thing.
But yeah, it was when, if any of the boys, obviously one of the boys said it was probably
some of the best years of my life, it definitely was for me.
And I think that's the, I'm lucky again and fortunate that after that experience,
it didn't matter who I coached.
Because I was.
I was satisfied.
You know, I was full to the brim with the game and I could have walked away and not
been a part of it, but I love it too much.
And so now in times where it's not going so well, the memories of, of what we all went
through and now with what we've been through with the Bulldogs, there's so many great memories
and positive things to reflect on that they override, you know, the challenges and, and
the negatives.
And it's pretty easy to reflect on them and, and turn your state of mind in the right direction.
I think the incredible thing, Bebo, for me is that you've been able to take that same
essence now into the professional environment and create those same relationships and that,
and that same feel.
And a lot of what you did when you first took on the senior coaching role in 2015, and I'll
talk about, you know, your impact at Collingwood and Hawthorne as well as some beads at some
stage over this chat.
But, but really, you know, we weren't allowed.
We weren't allowed to celebrate prior to you bringing that in to AFL football.
It was frowned upon if you were seen to sing a song too loud or a particular, if you're
a club like the one you coach and I played for that we love, that's why they're no good.
Look at them.
They can't, they've never won anything and they celebrate.
You changed so many of those things that were, were set in stone.
Was that a conscious thing or is that just you being you?
I think a combination of both.
Um, I don't think it's too difficult.
I think it's too difficult to work out that unified outfits, you know, whether it's teams
or groups of people are more a chance to achieve something significant, um, if they're bonded
and, and, and if they want to do things for each other and what greater opportunity is
there than after winning or achieving something together that you actually really celebrate
the contributions of, um, of your peers, of your teammates, um, of your fellow workmates
right on, right then and there, you know?
And, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and,
and make sure that, that you recognize and thank each other for, for what you're doing.
And, and if you walk away thinking, oh, well, we've got to focus on the next one, you've
just missed out on one of the golden opportunities to, to make your establishment, make your
organization even stronger.
So I've always felt that it was critical to do that.
Um, you know, there's some, I think there's some literature, well, I know there's some
how we can get it wrong when we don't acknowledge, you know, little successes, you know, whether
it's our children or, or whether it's our, our players and we're all in need of a pat
on the back and we, we're all looking for affirmation, positive affirmation and, and
we have to continue to search for opportunities to, to recognize and, um, and make sure people
feel good about themselves because they're, they're doing their best and, um, you know,
I think alcohol, alcohol is obviously a drug that, um, is a bane in our society in moderation.
I think it can really facilitate in the right, in the right, um, you know, amounts can, can
start the conversation as long as you, as long as you jump off, you know, step off pretty
early.
Um, and, and there's no doubt that sometimes even back then at St. B's, we probably took
it too far and got it wrong at times because intoxication.
Isn't the right way to end up and, and that happened here and there.
But, um, yeah, I consciously went after it and, um, and, and I must admit probably selfishly
as well that yearning to be part of a club environment that, um, was, was special at
the time.
You just didn't want to leave.
And, uh, and I think we all got caught up in that and, you know, the game at this level
now, the professional national level, you can't do that.
And, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and,
and unfortunately, um, you know, you, you're fragmented, um, and, and you, you go away
and you sort of, you subgroups and now, cause there's a lot of night games, there's not
an opportunity to do it too often, but when there is again, you know, we really pursue
that where we can at the Bulldogs cause it can be really powerful.
Sounds such a simple thing, isn't it?
To celebrate those small moments, but it is a great legacy of your leadership.
It wasn't, uh, allowed, you know, in the space of Australian rules football and I think you
really brought that to the forefront along with many other things.
Changing tack again, so many things I want to come back to Bevo that you've said, but
I needed to ask you, I wanted to ask you about your, your, your grandfather, the legendary
Jack Beveridge, who was part of the, the machine, the four premierships in a row in the 1930s
at Collingwood.
And I was reading your story again in the last 24 hours at 27 years of age, he moved
to the West.
It was depression era.
So to support the family and financially they go to Western Australia is an incredible impact
on the West Perth footy club and changes so much.
So much about them.
He then goes to Launceston as captain coach, wins a premiership, uh, Horsham the year
after and, and, and wins a premiership, incredible, you know, legacy of success.
And, and, you know, they talk about him as a voracious reader and learner and someone
who was really interested in how he can impact the world.
It feels like a lot of that DNA is in you.
Can you tell us a bit about your relationship with him?
Yeah, he actually finished at Colerain, I think in the end too, you know, and they,
yeah, he, he got knocked out at the start of a grand final, which was interesting.
Um, um, they actually won that grand final, but he, he was a publican too.
He ran the Colerain pub for a fair while and, um, and Jack and Mercia, his wife, uh,
they, uh, they had great relationships with, with the locals and, um, and I managed to
take dad back there a couple of years ago and just have one last beer.
Um, dad's, you know, probably nearer to the end than the start, as we know.
And I think it was good for him to, to get back there and experience that.
But, um, my, my main connection with him was usually on a day when I couldn't go to
school, uh, if I need to be looked after, I'd go around and spend some time with, with
Jack and Mercia and he was, he was immobile by then, you know, and he was fit and strong
during his playing days.
But I think, you know, managing a hotel and, um, and dealing with, uh, with different things,
he, both of them became heavy smokers.
Um, and I think I used to probably smoke 15 or 16 cigarettes passively every day when
I was sitting in their lounge room.
Um, but, um, you know, he, he didn't say a lot.
He, he seemed really wise and, you know, he had that really, it was almost like he had
that old Collingwood head, you know, that really wise, you know, sort of Wiedemann type
head, yet it was my grandfather, Jack Beveridge.
So it's been some special times.
I, I remember.
We used to go around there on Christmas day and, and, and play cricket.
They lived in, um, a court in, uh, in Hyatt and I was batting one day in part in play.
He was, um, in his mid seventies, but he came out, he walked out and he, he was standing
in between cover and mid off and, and I, I thought I got one off the middle and he just
stuck his left hand out and caught it.
And, uh, I think I would have only been about seven or eight years old and I spat the dummy
and I couldn't believe the reflex.
I says, oh, I just didn't think he had it in him and he just stuck the mid out and caught
it.
And so there's some special memories there.
Um, actually when he, when, when he, when they, they both passed within about four days
of each other, uh, and when, uh, mom and dad and the estate was wound up and the house
in Hyatt was to be sold, they actually lived next door to a biker gang and, um, and I didn't
really understand.
I was pretty young and, uh.
And, and the auction was about to start and the auctioneer, um, had, had done his, um,
his early blurb and he was about to get into, uh, the selling of the house or the auctioneering
of the house and about six or seven bikers walked out the front of, uh, of the house
next door and you reckon the house got sold?
So it was passed in at a, you know, a moderate price and I think it was sold to the state
government as a commission house.
And, uh, so, uh, the inheritance.
Um, probably dropped off by about 20 or 30 grand, I think, thanks to the next door, next
door neighbors.
Um, can you see the synergy though, Bevo, in, in that story and your eye and my, I spoke,
you know, to you a moment ago about some beads and the incredible story of that, but you
know, you, you went back into the AFL system at Collingwood, they win a flag in 2010 and
you'll be too humble to talk about your influence, but the Collingwood insiders tell me it was
profound.
Your time at Hawthorne, I think there was two premierships in that period of time, you
had a massive impact.
On the whole group and their defense in particular, and, and then we'll get to the Bulldogs in
two years and what, and what you've achieved, but it feels as though that's a very, uh,
similar path to your grandfather's.
Is there, is there a sense of history about that or?
Yeah, maybe a little.
I mean, I, I sometimes, you know, you, you think back in wonder or what, what par achieves
seemed like everywhere he went, they won a premiership, you know, everywhere he coached,
um, and sometimes played.
He, uh, you've just mentioned.
A few of them does, whether it be Launceston or Horsham or West Perth, it's just everywhere
he went and, and obviously the Collingwood machine and the four flags.
And, uh, um, as I mentioned earlier, you know, he, he would sit here and he'd be the first
to say what I said about how gratefully he was back then for, you know, his teammates
and, and how hard everyone worked to achieve something.
Um, but yeah, as far as synergies go and, you know, probably feeling fortunate and lucky
in the game, you know, there's many of, many of us who have, you know, have, you know,
been really involved in the game for long periods of time who just don't taste, you
know, any sort of tangible success.
And I played in some junior flags at St. Peter's, you know, we, we, from under 11s to 15s, we
just used to win every year.
Um, and I played in, um, you know, reserves one with you, Darcy, at the Dogs and played
in some losing ones as well.
But, um, you know, until St. Pete's, you know, I, as far as senior footy goes, it was an
open book.
And, um, for it to go the way it has and to be involved in so much club and team success.
So I just, I feel really privileged and, and I suppose, yeah, there, there is some, um,
some synergy there in that we're, we're probably both really fortunate that the game has allowed
us to experience those times.
Yeah.
Both incredibly humble.
I suspect if, uh, Jack Beveridge is sitting here, I think we'd be hearing a similar type
of, uh, of language.
Um, I wanted to touch on you for me.
You're such a, you're such a, you're such a, you're such a, you're such a, you're such
a unique leader and we're talking leadership and you've had a diverse range of things in
your life from, you know, working at Austrac, which is a government agency that tracks,
um, laundered money effectively, you know, from, from crime and, um, you know, studied
various things at different stages.
I'm not sure if this is true, but I think when you did your business career, you took
a fashion subject just as a bit of an offshoot.
I like to remind people of that.
The youngsters.
Might be the only thing you failed at, potentially, if I can be so bold.
Well, qualifies you to be a critic though.
Why the, how did you end up at Austrac?
I mean, for someone listening to you and your sporting background, a government agency,
I, you know, you, why did you end up there?
Yeah, I worked at the tax office for seven years and they, um, really grateful, uh, they
sponsored me and put me through university and I, I graduated, um, through the union
of New South Wales.
I studied by distance and that was probably the busiest time in my life.
At the end of, um, completing that degree, cause I was, I was on a couple of subjects.
I was coaching some beads.
I had a young family, um, Kai and Noah were born, Dana and I, um, so we were looking after
a family.
I was working full time and, um, so I was studying late at night and I, there weren't
enough hours in the day.
So you had to sort of give up on a bit of sleep and, um, and when I graduated and I,
I'd moved up the, the rungs or the levels within.
I was in the ATO and I'd got to the executive level and, um, and at the time the, um, the
financial transactions act, uh, had been repealed and, and the anti-money laundering counter
terrorism finance act had just, um, reached Royal assent and Austrac were the administrator,
um, the, you know, the government agency that oversaw that out of the attorney general's
office.
So they advertised for some positions.
And cause I was in compliance or investigations, it, it matched, it suited my skillset, but
it was just a different body of legislation.
And, uh, and, but there were great opportunities to teach, um, small, medium, large business
on how to comply with the new legislation.
And, um, and, and, and I needed to change.
I've always either, if I haven't got a new job or a new role, you know, within the sort
of three or four year mark, um, I've moved agencies and, and it, it had got to the point
where the tax office, I was probably seeing it out to finish my degree and time seemed
right.
And, um, the geography is right though, cornered Burke and William and, um, and I enjoyed working
in the city and, uh, and I was looking forward to, um, the challenge of, uh, and, and learning
too, you know, learning more about, um, other areas in commerce, but probably more the finance
sector.
Uh, and, uh, and so I moved on.
Although it's, uh, it's, it's fascinating.
I was reading a book I really enjoyed over the summer called Range and I, and I've got
the author's name off the top of my head, but I'll, I'll put it in the show notes afterwards
so people can look it up if they're interested.
And the book's sort of thesis is that people who achieve great, um, legendary status in
life and, and, uh, and find their true meaning and, and great to sample a range of different
things.
To me on the outside, you're the most unlikely tax office compliance officer in history,
but when you hear you describe it, there's great.
There's creativity in that.
And someone who's incredibly creative as you are, you know, to be able to delve into that
world and then have the other pursuits that you've had in the sporting life and your family
life and other areas that have, uh, did you see that package has sort of come together
now, you know, to, to form the person that you are and doing a role feels to me like
you're born to be a coach.
You're born to do this, but you've sampled a lot of things along the way to, to get there.
Is that, does that make sense?
Yeah.
And I, you know, the, the fascinating thing for me is, and I mentioned earlier, I don't
feel like I'm maturity.
Really enough.
You know, I was a terrible secondary school student.
I, I had football on my mind.
I wanted to be an AFL player, VFL at the time.
And, um, I, I lent on a great mate of mine, Anthony Lance, who was studying, um, the right
subjects to be a physiotherapist and him and I were both studying mass science.
So he, he really helped me at the end of year 11, his notes were on point.
Um, and I figured I'd do the same in year 12 and, and it didn't all come together.
I, I, I definitely couldn't.
Yeah.
I graduated okay.
And I started off, um, pursuing an environmental studies degree at Rusden, but I, I just wasn't
a good student.
I pulled the pin and it coincided with me playing senior footy at Melbourne, um, as
an 18 year old.
So I'd kind of had enough and I went, went, went over and, um, started mowing some lawns
and became a gardener for a little while.
But I, I, what happened when, um, I finished my AFL career at 29, I needed to get busy
with a career.
And the, the tax office had just advertised for many, many positions, um, the implementation
of GST was about to occur and there's a mobile education workforce that was about to hit
the road.
And I wanted to be part of that purely because of the opportunities and the pathway forward
for me.
Uh, I managed to, um, land one of those positions, um, and ultimately when I realised there was
an opportunity to study at tertiary level.
Through the tax office, I, I pounced on that as well.
And I ultimately, I was probably the perfect remote student.
I was that paranoid about failing anything that, that, you know, possibly the, the degree
would be over because I couldn't see myself coming back to it.
It was all or nothing.
Yeah.
And I studied extremely hard.
I, I was probably the model tertiary student, you know, as, um, I was self-driven, I was
willing to sit down at night, open the books.
I was really interested in the law.
And it was a law based, uh, a law faculty degree, but I, I, I really, you know, I enjoyed
the fact that I was achieving something different and I was now good at something that I wasn't
good at as a, as an 18 year old.
And I think, and that's where my appetite and capacity, capacity to read started to
kick in.
Cause beyond the law books, I started to have an appetite for different types of literature,
um, broaden my knowledge.
I started to have an appetite for different types of books, you know, and that helped
me, you know, as I was, as I was, uh, teaching the, the conversation of the law, the book
I was making out of, the, the, the, the book I was making out of, um, um, the first book
that I'd published in edition, um, I started to keep track of the content.
I'd put out the books that I'd made out of, um, the book I was making out of, and so,
so, um, I, I read it and I, and I, I made it more short and more meaningful, more, you
know, you know, more sophisticated.
And I, I learned a lot from that, um, this, this, this, this, you know, the, this, this,
you know, and it, I, it was just, it was an amazing experience.
Yeah.
story, isn't it? For me at 29 years of age, you're coaching some beads, you're studying the law,
you're working the tax office, and you mentioned Noah and Kai and Dana, your beautiful life. We're
all in love with Dana, I think, when you were younger and your childhood sweetheart. How do
you manage? I love talking to leaders about managing all that. How do you get that right
without one of those wheels falling off? And even just family life in general, how have you managed
that through your work and family balance? Yeah, I was fortunate that the boys were really
young at the time and they were low maintenance in a way. And so my number one priority was
I didn't miss out and they didn't miss out on the father-son stuff. And that's why the books
wouldn't come out until they were in bed. And so nothing was really compromised. I was able to fit
everything in and probably my sleep patterns went from eight or so hours a night to maybe
six, sometimes five and a catch up later on in the week. And I think I haven't really ever gone
back to the eight hour pattern, even though you probably need to have a bit of a sleep in here
and there or get to bed early. But yeah, I think just prioritizing, getting the balance right.
The kids were never less important than anything. They were always at the top of the list and Dana
as well, making sure that she was okay. Dana's a nurse and she took,
some time off work and she's an unbelievable mother and life partner for me and making sure
our relationship was always strong. So I think the balance was right and the footy was,
probably thankfully Dana really enjoys the game and the boys, you want to expose them to it
because it's important that they play team sports and the boys have always loved the game as well.
So,
um,
in the,
early parts of my coaching,
it was easy to expose them when they were really young to,
and take them down to the club and,
and Dana would,
uh,
you know,
involve herself here and there.
So I think on balance,
I got it right.
It's just that the work commitments at times,
um,
you know,
they,
they were pretty measured.
I suppose always on a level where you could,
uh,
and predictable that it was,
wasn't going to encroach into some of the other priorities.
Um,
changing gears slightly from that,
uh,
Bevo,
I caught up with Marcus Bond and Pele,
who's the captain of your team at the moment,
the Bulldogs and,
and,
um,
you're going to be an iconic player if he's not already at 25 years of age,
I think Marcus is still.
And,
and I asked him about you and,
and,
uh,
and I'm paraphrasing here and he said,
he said,
Bevo to me is the person that has asked himself the big questions in life and he's comfortable with the answers and comfortable in his own skin.
Does that sort of resonate with you,
Bevo?
Does that make,
make sense?
That that description?
Uh,
well,
I think it's a great compliment if,
if he thinks that way,
he,
um,
and that's where,
you know,
talking about gratitude and how fortunate we are to,
to work and,
um,
relate and be friends with,
with different people now in our lives.
He's just a high end,
um,
individual in person,
you know,
his integrity,
his character.
And,
and I,
I think that's part of the,
um,
the challenge with,
with many of us who are searching for who we want to be and how we should manage our own personal space.
It's recognizing when sometimes people are just a better human beings than others.
And,
uh,
and he's,
he's just a,
an incredible human being and,
um,
allowing him to be autonomous in what he does,
but also learning,
you know,
he's,
he's going great benefit from also the collaboration that you put together for,
for him,
you know,
with him being able to relate to guys like Pat Cummins and Rob Sitch and,
and some of the other people in there.
Andy Lee.
Yeah.
You know,
in that forum,
it's allowed me,
because part of the early part of his football life,
I missed his first year,
Marcus,
but it enabled me to,
and it challenged me to,
um,
to guide him a little bit and,
and help him with his thinking in different ways as,
as it did with,
with Bob and Easton and,
but they were in a different,
um,
stages of their lives and,
and,
uh,
and their footy careers.
But it got to a point with Marcus where,
um,
you know,
he was,
he was really exploring,
you know,
his own influence outside of what anyone else was thinking.
And,
and I think the,
him being able to speak and listen in that forum and different things he's exposed to at the moment have really shaped him even more.
And,
and he's got a,
an inner confidence that,
um,
that his about life balance is right,
but,
but he is influential and he's comfortable with himself.
I think if he says that I've asked myself the questions and,
and I'm comfortable with the answers at the,
at the tender age,
I think he's 25 now at,
you know,
I reckon he's almost done the same.
And this is what I'm saying about,
I wish I was more like that when I was his age and I was nowhere near it.
Um,
so it's respecting that,
acknowledging,
acknowledging that and allowing him to be powerful because he is not allowing him.
I don't need to allow him.
Now,
if I tried to stop him,
he'd quickly barge through it,
um,
because he,
he should,
and he would,
and he could,
uh,
because he's just so highly respected.
So,
um,
I'm really comfortable now that,
you know,
he and I work more in a partnership,
um,
than,
than say,
uh,
um,
you know,
him being the two I see he's,
he's,
he should be more,
influential than me as far as how the playing group pursues the behaviors of both him and
I.
And he definitely,
he is.
And,
and sometimes he's unsure about how far to push that.
and that's the,
the humility in Marcus Spontanpelli.
And,
and I think he gets the balance right.
Yeah.
It's remarkable to hear you say that,
uh,
you know,
Bevo,
that you're allowing,
you know,
the hierarchy of coaching that we,
um,
experience would never have even thought of talking about being in partnership.
And,
you know,
as you said,
you get a once in a generation type of person.
He's a special,
special human being,
that young man.
And to,
to have that and,
and clearly that relationship with you is,
uh,
is unique.
And I,
again,
mate,
I love it.
I can hear the emotion in your voice.
My wife always says to me,
I don't think boarding school was your friend,
didn't allow you to,
uh,
to experience emotion because it wasn't your friend then.
But I,
I love how comfortable and free you are with,
with your most.
Thanks for mentioning the,
the Alita Connect space because,
you know,
we're really passionate about,
um,
my old friend,
Matt Waterwitz and I,
and can I ask you to talk a little bit about it?
You mentioned that,
that it's been positive for Marcus,
but for you with,
with Eddie Jones from English rugby and,
and Neil Craig,
who coached the Crows and,
and a high performance background,
uh,
at the elite level in every,
every sport just about,
and,
and Ansh Poster Collier is doing incredible things at Celtic.
Amazing.
As the first Australian coach.
Yeah.
Um,
I remember talking to you about it and,
and as always,
you always like to think things through,
but it feels like it's been a real,
a real positive for you.
Oh,
it's been such an,
an ear opener,
an eye opener,
you know,
to listen to their experiences and,
and,
you know,
there's,
there's various throwaway,
um,
key messages to take away from most of our discussions,
you know,
but the,
probably the overriding thing that comes out of everything is if you're in your comfort zone,
you're in the wrong zone,
you know,
you're always on the edge and,
um,
and there's a lot of differences in,
in what we do based on whether it's the international stage or,
um,
and,
and ownership of,
of different organisations,
and,
you know,
Ange is obviously coaching Celtic and the ownership,
all right,
is very different to a,
an AFL club,
um,
that's really owned by the members and it's a non-profit organisation and when you think about Brian Gorgian and,
and the owners of the different basketball teams that he's coached and,
um,
and what's,
what is really clear is how challenging the coaching and the educational piece has been in China for,
for Brian when he,
you know,
he coached for about 10 years in China when you think you're standing in front of your whole roster and they can't understand what you're saying,
and you've got interpreters there,
what,
what an amazing,
enormous challenge that would be and,
and he's talked about that and,
and Ange similarly when he's coaching Yokohama in Japan,
the,
the language barrier is significant.
Uh,
he,
he must be so relieved that as much as the Scots have got pretty hefty accents,
they still understand,
you know,
his,
his English and his Australian,
um,
angle.
Uh,
so it's probably a bit of a relief that he doesn't need the interpreters,
although he's brought some Japanese boys over,
uh,
he's doing an amazing job.
And,
and when you think about the pressures of coaching national teams,
Brian's just,
you know,
experienced coaching,
um,
the Australian basketball team to the bronze medal in Tokyo.
And now,
you know,
Eddie Jones coaching,
the,
the English rugby union team.
Oh,
just fascinating.
You know,
to,
to listen to them talk about,
you know,
who speaks to them about the expectations and,
um,
and how they stay in their,
their own,
um,
right positive headspace and who they talk to.
And that's where Neil Craig's such a great confidant for,
for Eddie,
because he's,
he's,
he's a custodian of,
um,
of Eddie's,
wellbeing as much as anything.
And he's an advisor and he,
and he helps him,
um,
find context and perspective in different things.
Uh,
but it's just been really,
really rewarding and,
and they're,
they're very wise men,
uh,
very experienced men.
And so it's been great for me to listen to them and,
uh,
talk about their experiences.
And the idea initially,
Bebo was,
you know,
to have this forum with,
uh,
like-minded people.
And clearly you guys share commonality,
but it really potentially private.
And the conversations are yours and,
and,
and yours alone and initially facilitated,
uh,
by Matt,
but we're excited,
you know,
people are listening to,
to people like you talk about it.
And so,
geez,
that'd be something that would be beneficial in my life.
And we're,
we're curating these,
these groups now of,
uh,
diverse people in different areas.
And,
and,
you know,
to me,
the idea of,
you know,
it's,
it's more corporate term,
but having like your,
your own personal board there for you to reflect with and learn from and create,
we're,
we're excited about what that looks like.
Do you,
do you see merit in it beyond the elite sporting context for people to be able to form these
forums and collaborative groups?
A leader connect is what we're doing.
The,
it under the banner.
Do you see,
do you see merit in that?
Uh,
absolutely.
Absolutely.
And it's quite simply,
you know,
you,
I mean,
the,
you don't know what,
what you haven't exposed yourself to or what you don't know and,
and listening to others talk.
And sometimes,
um,
you know,
you hear examples or you see examples that are very similar to things that,
um,
you've experienced in your life and to hear different perspectives and,
and understand the way that successful people have gone about it.
And even,
even to listen to the failures and the,
and the disappointments is,
is a great opportunity to learn,
um,
you know,
what to do or what not to do.
And sometimes,
you know,
you can get a lot of things right and still ultimately come up short.
And that,
that's,
that's a really important,
um,
leveling message to,
to all of us,
you know,
and I,
but I think there's a real power in us,
um,
it being together and,
and,
and the group think and,
um,
and sharing and even the support,
support aspect of it.
You know,
we,
we quite often communicate and there's,
there's the essence of,
of,
of the friendship and,
and having each other's back is there as well.
And I think there's a great power in that,
especially in times of need when you're not so sure of yourself.
Yeah.
Brilliant,
mate.
It's,
uh,
it can be,
I'm assuming a lonely job at times,
isn't it?
When you're at the helm of a very public sporting,
uh,
organizations and,
and,
you know,
sort of digressing for a moment,
uh,
you know,
probably been an issue.
If you look at AFL,
a lot of,
uh,
the mental health of,
of some of our senior coaches has been a huge challenge and probably in
sport around the world,
never more pressure applied on one leader in one role.
Is that,
is that something that,
you know,
you're aware of and concerned about?
We seem to have overlooked just how,
how stressful it's been for a lot of people in the role that you do.
Yeah.
What's evolved over the years is the reaction and the impact on people around
you.
And,
and,
and how that impacts you more than the criticism of your own performance.
Like I,
I can quite easily deal with,
um,
whatever the assessment will be of,
of my performance,
because I know,
you know,
most,
uh,
you know,
99.9% of anyone who reports on sport will pick something apart and,
and take a really,
um,
uh,
you know,
take a magnifying glass,
to,
to your performance and,
and pick out where,
you know,
the improvements need to come from.
But,
but also,
you know,
that the same population will jump in and praise when the time is right as
well,
you know,
and,
and I understand that.
And occasionally there's someone who's more on the negative side than the
positive side.
And I think that's something that stands out every now and then.
Um,
so I can always process that for me,
but what people around you,
in particular family and friends,
they'll react,
you know,
in a,
in a really emotional way to any negativity towards,
towards you.
And then you've got to go and deal with that.
And,
and so sometimes,
you know,
you,
the less you say the better,
you know,
and,
and I,
and I think this is a thing with clickbait and how the headline doesn't
match the,
the content of the story.
Um,
there's a reaction to the headline and some,
well,
have you read the story?
And then a lot of people don't read the story.
and that,
so,
and it's only there because you've spoken or,
you know,
and,
and sometimes now,
you know,
you,
you're,
you're reluctant because you think if I speak,
there's going to be six articles.
I don't know what they're going to say.
I don't know what the headline is going to be.
So I think as far as your own headspace and your own wellbeing goes,
uh,
yeah,
the,
the support around you and the,
the positive,
um,
interaction that you get from not only your own staff,
but definitely,
I think you look for it from people you manage up to,
uh,
really feeling that support and being probably less judgmental at times.
If you've got that,
you know,
you're really fortunate.
I've had,
you know,
mostly I've experienced that,
but there's times when you don't feel supported.
Uh,
and they're probably the,
the most challenging times.
Cause if you feel like,
uh,
you're slipping away from your own organization,
then you,
then you know,
you're in a bit of trouble at that point in time.
And,
and to arrest that slide,
it's,
it's sometimes just too much of a slippery slope.
Now moving towards a series of questions I've been asking all the guests,
but before I can't believe,
uh,
and I can't leave this interview without talking about 2016.
Bevo,
and I'm biased because it was one of the most enjoyable days of my life being
there on the ground,
uh,
working on the day and,
and,
and what that day meant to so many people,
as I said in the intro,
62 year gap,
you take over in 2015,
um,
the so-called experts,
in,
uh,
the industry is saying the Bulldogs have never been further away from success at
that time.
Uh,
the captain is disillusioned with the club and he asked to be traded and he's
traded to GWS.
There was 700 games experience walk out.
There was all sorts of turmoil and drama going.
You walked into an environment that needed a lot of care,
you know,
to,
to say it was a 501 chance that you would win in two years time is probably,
um,
underestimating it in some ways.
And then you,
you achieve that in two years.
You look back,
I mean,
I know you move forward in this industry really quickly,
but what do you think when you,
when you look at that achievement?
I'm ultimately very proud of,
of what,
what everyone achieved,
you know,
during that,
um,
you know,
that little snapshot of,
of the last,
uh,
seven years.
Um,
the,
when you think about the complexion of the,
the Bulldogs team and it was a little bit piecemeal and,
um,
so system wise to be able to implement,
to be able to champion it as a group and for the players to totally buy in and,
and push it in,
in such a,
um,
meteoric direction was,
yeah,
it was,
it was unbelievable.
it was brilliant at the time.
And I,
and I think that,
you know,
post the 16 year and the challenges that we've faced,
um,
you know,
behind the scenes and you,
and you mentioned,
mentioned the mental health.
Um,
we talked about the mental health earlier to us.
These are the hidden things that,
that can affect performance.
And,
and I think one of the things that we can really be proud of now is we,
we never really wavered from,
you know,
strong beliefs in,
in the core of what we do.
Um,
and a lot of our people,
you know,
have just been so stoic and,
um,
I mean,
the playing list has turned over,
turned over significantly,
um,
through that,
uh,
through the,
through recent years.
But,
yeah,
I mean,
the overwhelming emotion is,
is,
is a great sense of pride.
Um,
and,
and I still,
I've mentioned it a couple of times.
I think if you see,
if you look at the,
the looks on the Bulldogs players,
um,
faces at the end of the 16 grand final,
it,
they're not ones of satisfaction and jubilation.
I don't think that to me,
they look surprised.
It's like,
you know,
that just actually happened.
You know,
and I think that was the,
the look on most of,
um,
the,
you know,
anyone,
whether you're a supporter of the club or whether you're directly involved,
you know,
in a work capacity,
there was a significant element of surprise.
Yeah,
the emotion in the MCG that day,
even the neutral supporters could just sense that there was just something
historic and special.
It was an energy in that stadium that I've never felt before.
Clearly biased because it's something I wanted to see my whole,
uh,
sporting life.
But,
uh,
it was just a unique,
extraordinary achievement and,
uh,
more to come on that front.
But,
well,
dimensions of leadership is something we're,
we're passionate about seeing if there are some common traits with leaders,
uh,
diverse from,
from different areas of,
of sport and industry in the arts.
But one of the things we're identifying is the idea of self-leadership.
If,
if I ask you about self-leadership,
what do you think of when I,
when I pose that to you?
Uh,
is this,
this will sound like it,
it's not off the cuff,
but I,
I often,
Rachel Robertson,
um,
is a,
is a fine author.
And she says that,
uh,
leadership isn't a title.
It's a,
it's a set of behaviors and,
um,
and I,
and,
and essentially that's it for me,
you know,
self-leadership for me is,
is having,
because there's,
there's always,
we can be leaders in many ways or what type of leadership is it?
You know,
is it a toxic type of leadership or is it a,
a really positive,
um,
influential,
not even influential is not the right word.
Is it,
is it a positive,
um,
is it in the right space type of leadership?
And if you get,
if the set of behaviors that personally you,
you live by and the,
you know,
we always talk about values and behaviors almost in the same context.
If they're all in the right spot,
um,
if you're going to have any influence on,
on yourself,
uh,
or anyone else,
then it can only be positive if you,
if you get all that right.
So,
um,
self-leadership for me is to make sure that,
you know,
day in,
day out that I'm,
I'm true to who I,
who I believe is,
is a good person and,
um,
and making sure that you behave in a way that society expects you to.
Yeah.
Beautiful,
uh,
answer.
And I think anyone who's had any time with you would not question that in,
in any way,
shape or form.
It's the essence of you.
And,
uh,
you know,
for me from the youngest possible age,
um,
you know,
I've seen that about you.
We,
we see leaders really consciously thinking about how they positively impact others in
their environment.
And that's another,
uh,
essence of you.
But do you consciously think about that positive impact on others?
Yeah,
I,
I do.
And I,
I think it,
you know,
the essence of,
um,
use the word essence again,
but,
um,
leaders sometimes can be really outspoken and,
uh,
and we,
we need to be at different times,
but the listening aspect is critical,
you know,
and,
and ensuring that people feel enabled and,
uh,
and that they've got their own space and that they can be influential.
And if you don't,
um,
listen and contextualize and,
and just nudge and guide rather than tell and,
and push,
uh,
then you're not going to allow others to become who they should be in a positive
way.
And I'm sensitive to,
um,
not just our,
well,
our playing group are critical in that space,
but,
but our,
our coaches and people who we work with,
um,
listening and,
and seeing what they want to do in their own influential space and,
and helping them on their way is,
I think is as critical as,
as me,
um,
taking something in a direction.
Yeah.
Brilliant answer.
How do you go about,
uh,
creating and sharing your vision?
I know this is a real passion area for you about how you do it.
Can you share a bit about how you go about,
you know,
creating and sharing that vision?
Yeah,
I,
I think we,
we got some,
um,
and if you,
if you talk to people in,
in different,
sectors of,
of commerce,
um,
you know,
the,
the old death by PowerPoint,
um,
you know,
will come up.
I,
I went through some horror years at,
in,
uh,
in government agencies where,
you know,
new initiatives or,
um,
things that needed to be executed,
were being rolled out in,
in an educational sense.
And,
and you'd get a PowerPoint presentation,
um,
come across your,
your shared drive and you go and look at it and it's 90,
uh,
slides.
How's this going to go?
You know,
when you,
if you've got an audience of 60 people and you're going to tick through 90
slides,
what's their capacity of that?
And,
and so,
but the question back then,
because the understanding of,
um,
effective learning and,
and the right way to get messages across,
it isn't considered well enough in,
in,
uh,
in different sectors.
We don't really understand how important it is to get it right.
So as far as,
um,
I usually try and take a bit of a different angle and,
and it's mostly around,
um,
the power of connection and,
and also the,
some of that metaphoric language and the escapism.
And it's okay to,
for other,
for things that are sort of a bit abstract to resonate with you,
if it gets the most out of you and other people.
And,
um,
and for,
it's okay for the,
you know,
whether it's music and,
and movies or,
or literature,
it's okay for that to be the connector,
for that to be the medium that brings us together.
It's not artificial.
It's what we enjoy.
It's what we love.
And there's a real power in that.
And so I probably try and do it,
you know,
in,
in ways that are a little bit left field than,
than,
uh,
than the words and the,
um,
and the historical language around leadership.
Yeah.
It's a great,
uh,
strength of yours.
And,
you know,
as I said,
the authenticity comes through when you,
when you hear your ideas and your thoughts on it.
Um,
you know,
curiosity is something where it seems a common trait in leaders.
They're,
they're curious and they approach their learning and their development often
through curious.
And you listen to your life and,
and you love absorbing material and content and,
and reading.
Do you,
do you think about your learning through,
through being curious?
Yeah,
I do.
And I love the word curious.
There's a,
um,
a great book called the explorers.
Um,
and T.E.
Lawrence is,
is Lawrence of Arabia.
You know,
when I was a young kid,
you know,
there were all these old movies and Lawrence of Arabia kept,
um,
showing itself on,
on,
on a channel,
um,
at some point in time.
But in this explorers book,
it talks about curiosity being one of the seven traits of the great explorers.
Um,
and,
you know,
essentially if you are,
um,
a great explorer or an explorer in,
in any sense of the word,
you're trying to get out of your comfort zone and,
and then explore new things.
Um,
and so,
being ever curious about,
um,
what's out there,
what you might be able to learn from or use or,
or even the life experience and the physical aspect of being in the ocean or,
or what the different,
um,
what different environments can throw at you.
I,
I think it's,
it's,
it's a word that really resonates with me.
And,
you know,
we,
uh,
we don't talk about internal themes and messages too often,
but,
um,
you know,
part of the historic,
um,
message around,
you know,
I think a lot of people were inquisitive about salty dogs,
back when we won the flag and,
you know,
that,
that internal theme and the text,
um,
uh,
you know,
in the,
in that book is about facing your fears and,
um,
and,
and being curious and being okay with that.
And even if it doesn't work out for you,
and I think that's the thing,
um,
is feeling okay about it not working out,
when you've explored your curiosities.
Yeah,
it's,
it's brilliant.
And,
you know,
as you said,
they're,
they're private,
often the internal themes,
but,
uh,
generous enough to open up about that.
And,
uh,
and you share with me a copy of that book,
which,
which I loved,
uh,
for those listening,
you know,
to have,
players armed with something that's meaningful from you and,
and,
and that bonding,
it,
it seems abstract,
but it had massive impact on me reading it.
And then looking back and understanding what,
what you created,
it's,
it seems as though,
you know,
it might be left of center,
but there is a connection that works with it.
Uh,
is it hard to land for you?
I mean,
do you,
do you ever not land them?
Do you ever,
do you ever?
Absolutely.
Yeah.
And,
and I think,
you know,
some of our best,
um,
ones,
yeah,
cause you can't reuse them.
Um,
I don't think I've ever reused one,
but,
uh,
some of your best ones just haven't,
haven't worked out.
And,
um,
but I think young Sam,
uh,
Sam Darcy,
um,
Marcus,
and,
and this is part of,
you know,
he's influenced,
but,
he,
he presented the new seven players at the club with,
with the Salty Dogs book a couple of weeks ago.
So Sam's,
Sam's got a copy.
It's part of the indoctrination of our new players.
And to understand,
hey,
we need you to do this.
It's okay to,
um,
to feel uncomfortable about it.
But essentially from here on in,
you,
you step into,
you know,
a bit of a new world.
And if you're not,
um,
exploring outside of your own comforts,
then you,
you're probably not,
um,
getting the most out of yourselves.
And you,
and it's,
and ultimately,
um,
you know,
you're not,
you're not doing what the team really needs you to do.
And so I imagine it's a pretty quick read.
Um,
but I'm hoping that all of our new players who received that text,
um,
it's,
uh,
it's probably to play somewhere,
whether it's in a drawer or whether it's,
you know,
stored away.
I'd like to think that they know where it is.
It's a simple message.
Um,
but yeah,
ultimately the,
the week to week angles that we take.
Yeah.
You always take a risk.
Um,
but I,
I,
I'm a great believer that you've got to put the work in and you've got to make sure that,
um,
it's fresh.
Um,
it's real,
it's new.
It's,
um,
there's a creative aspect that doesn't go too far that,
that your players and your team appreciate.
Um,
but,
but ultimately you've got to bring it back to them and,
and the team.
And,
and there's a way to do that.
And yeah,
I'll put the hand up.
And so I haven't always got it right.
Yeah.
For those listening that don't understand,
there's a unique sort of history going on for my son's 18 and Sam,
and he's just been drafted under Bevo's care as a,
as an old teammate and now going full circle Bevo and,
and,
and then seeing it from a parent's eyes and hopefully is there in the background to,
to support and,
and he's going to live his own chapter,
however that plays out.
But I loved it.
If you don't mind me sharing this,
uh,
I felt the first cup,
different era we played in and,
and even to get a word with a senior coach or I felt even for them to know who you,
who you were or anything about you was a stretch,
but,
probably understandable given the time.
But one of the first things,
uh,
you did was,
was pick him up and take him to dinner at your house with Dana and,
and Beck and I,
my,
we,
we love this because to me,
I would have been that nervous about going to senior coach's house and I wouldn't think
about what I,
what I was going to say.
His main concern that night Bevo was that there's two things he doesn't eat,
pumpkin and bananas.
He said,
what if Bevo serves pumpkin soup?
And I said,
it looks like you're eating pumpkin soup,
my,
uh,
my young friend.
So,
um,
new generations,
they think differently.
I'll,
I'll move on to,
um,
to the next dimension of leadership.
There's a,
there's a couple more communicating with clarity is something we're identifying with leaders.
Do you think about the way you communicate?
Yeah,
absolutely.
And,
um,
yeah,
setting the scene and providing context,
um,
is,
is absolutely critical for,
uh,
for all of our,
all of our people.
Um,
but I think it gets back to,
you know,
the learning mediums,
and to continue to think about,
uh,
how do you,
in a group,
in a group setting,
how many can actually process the spoken word?
You know,
is there,
if you speak for 10 minutes,
what are they going to take in?
Most of us,
I think,
have got a real appetite for the visual mediums,
you know,
whether it's pictures or videos and,
and it's such an effective way to get your message across.
And,
um,
and the,
the physical side of it,
you know,
actually,
whether you're working with people,
walking through or demonstrating and,
and,
and being physically active,
which you can't always do in a,
in a normal workspace.
Um,
he,
he's really valuable in what we do,
obviously,
we're,
you know,
in a high skill game sense,
um,
type discipline.
But,
um,
but yeah,
so as far as the communications go,
exploring the,
the best mediums,
um,
reminding people how they can do it better.
And,
uh,
and that constant loop of feedback,
especially with our coaches as they think about this,
you know,
understand your audience.
Um,
because the one-on-one,
um,
connection is a little bit simpler.
It's just when you,
when you've got a group catering for all is,
is,
is the most challenging.
And,
um,
and I think,
you know,
I probably,
as far as the spoken word goes,
I,
I've always been,
uh,
somewhere between a mumbler and,
and a reasonable orator.
Um,
and I get,
you know,
you can,
you can get lazy,
you know,
and,
and I think I'm,
I'm,
I've become more conscious about pronouncing,
um,
my words a little bit better because I,
I,
I've,
I've been,
I'm pretty laid back most of the time.
And,
and I think that can be construed as,
um,
you know,
almost being a,
um,
it starts to connect to connect you with your history.
And if you,
you come known as,
as a skateboarder more than a coach,
you know,
so,
uh,
I,
I've become a little bit more mindful of,
of pronouncing my words and,
and,
and making sure that,
um,
I get the message across in a fluent way.
We're seeing leaders really value collaboration,
Bevo,
maybe more in this generation than ever before.
How do you view collaboration?
Oh,
that,
it's interesting when you consider with,
you know,
what we do as coaches and,
and managers,
we've all got some kind of ego.
You know,
we've,
we're all come from a,
um,
a self-belief platform or premise at times and,
and collaboration for me is really understanding or,
or acknowledging that you definitely haven't got all the answers and we really
need to listen and open,
open ourselves up to,
um,
conversations.
And,
and I think if you've got a really intense,
um,
sort of self-absorbed and overarching egotistical,
egotistical way of doing things,
you're going to be less collaborative,
um,
and you're going to miss out.
So,
you know,
I,
the,
we mentioned these really influential coaches like Brian Gordian and Ange and
Neil,
um,
Neil Craig and,
and Eddie Jones.
And there's a,
there's a deep seated humility in their personalities.
They don't think they've got all the answers.
They're willing to listen.
They're willing to talk.
And it's a reminder to,
to me and to anyone who,
who,
uh,
who wants to better themselves that you need to go in with an open mind,
contribute where you can,
but really learn from others.
Uh,
I just think it's absolutely critical that you park the ego,
um,
and,
and you have a good time with it and you,
and you really take away the nuggets,
write your notes,
um,
take an angle from what someone else has said,
as is there's so much to benefit from,
from other,
what other people's experience has been and what they've got to say.
Yeah.
Beautifully said,
uh,
again,
mate,
two final questions.
We've been asking,
uh,
all the leaders I've been fortunate enough to sit alongside and enjoy this
experience.
Who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Greatest leader in my life.
Oh,
what's your second question?
Can I come back to that one?
Yeah.
A bit of think time.
Uh,
if you could collaborate with anyone in the world and it could be on anything,
Bevo,
it could be your love of surfing.
It could be coaching collaboration where we're interested in.
If you could collaborate,
it might be in a rock band,
Bevo,
who would you collaborate with?
Well,
right at this point in time,
I'd say Peter Garrett.
Is that right?
Yeah.
I've been thinking a lot about Peter Garrett and I've always admired him fiercely.
My,
my interests,
my desire to,
uh,
be more influential in,
in the first nations space and recognition of,
you know,
indigenous rights and reconciliation has,
has really escalated over the,
the last few years.
A good friend of mine,
David Quinn,
uh,
Paul Thompson have been influential there behind the scenes with me.
Obviously Peter has,
you know,
had a huge passion in that space.
He's,
um,
he's want to,
uh,
influence,
you know,
our thinking around the environment.
And obviously a lot of the,
um,
a lot of the songs that Minot Oil have sung and,
and that they've written over the years have,
have been,
you know,
really sensitive to the environment and definitely first nations people.
And his journey for me has been fascinating,
you know,
for him to go into politics and,
and not last a long,
long time at federal level.
I'd love to sit down and talk to him about why not,
because for me,
he's just one of the most standup,
um,
characters that Australia has ever,
had the benefit of,
of being exposed to.
And when you think of the diversity of,
of him,
you know,
as a,
as an artist in the music industry,
but then as a politician,
um,
and as a freedom fighter and a rights preserver,
what an amazing person.
So I'd,
he'd be probably number one in the,
in the way I've been thinking recently.
Um,
because I just think he's just such a,
an amazing human being.
And,
uh,
he'd be probably at the top of my list.
And the courage to go on the inside and go through the path at his age.
And he could have had,
you know,
toured around the world and,
and kept doing that.
That would have been a pretty hard thing to give up.
I suspect,
you know,
mid-air at all for that period of time.
But I'm going to go in and try and,
unless it changed from the inside and then the hand grenades got thrown at him everywhere.
But the humility of his exit and the class with which he,
you know,
with all sorts of mud being thrown his way,
it'd be,
it'd be a great conversation.
I'd love to hear.
Absolutely.
A transcript of you two getting together.
So I've given you some think time,
mate,
on,
on the greatest leader in your life.
Is there anything or anyone,
or is it a handful of people?
Yeah,
I mean,
so many influential people on the way to us,
but the guy who stands out for me is a guy named Neil Jensen.
Neil was the one who set up the financial intelligence units in Australia.
He,
he was CEO of AUSTRAC,
but the Australian FIU and the Canadian FIU were the most powerful financial intelligence units in the world.
Now he was involved in helping other countries,
set their own up,
um,
where essentially,
you know,
the,
the data capture and the analytics around trying to detect money laundering,
um,
and the mechanisms that surround that.
He was the one who was guiding and influencing,
um,
AUSTRAC really has got two main offices or back when I worked there,
and one's in New South Wales and one's here in Melbourne.
And,
and Neil happened to be based in,
in Melbourne at the time.
And,
um,
and what struck him?
What struck me was he would walk the floor as a CEO.
He'd,
he'd talk to everyone.
He'd shake hands with those he could.
He knew everyone by their name and he'd call them by their name.
And he,
he was at pains to make sure that anyone new to the agency would feel welcome.
he was a CEO.
Other people could do that,
but he felt it was important for him.
And this is a government agency.
This isn't a private,
um,
entity that he owns or runs.
Yeah.
He,
you might say,
well,
he,
it's not part of his roommate,
you know,
but he,
he thought it was absolutely critical.
And there was a real power in that because people knew he cared.
And so as far as,
um,
the influence from the top down and the relationship piece,
it was really strong.
There were great connections there at AUSTRAC.
And,
and the reason why he stands out so much is he retired.
And during the,
uh,
transition into,
the new legislation,
they recruited a lot of senior management from other government agencies.
And there was a new CEO who came in and the whole environment changed.
And that personable,
um,
caring aspect of the organization went within the space of six months.
And,
and I realized how much of an influence Neil Jensen had on AUSTRAC as an agency.
And for me,
it was just so tragic that that agency now was in the,
the state that it was.
And I experienced the change and that even the toxicity that now existed,
um,
in some of the teams because it wasn't being led well.
And,
uh,
it was fascinating to me to see the two extremes.
And,
and so,
yeah,
he was a great example for me of how to do it right.
That strikes such a chord,
Bevan.
I'm glad you shared that story because it goes to the essence of what,
you know,
I'm really passionate about and we're really passionate about in this leadership space is that your ability and the way you described that,
it's not a,
a really big thing to do to know people's name and shake their hands and make them feel special in that moment.
But your ability to impact people and change their lives,
we spend so much of our time at work.
So for those people then to have that removed,
then it was probably someone who just didn't have the leadership skills or the understanding or hadn't put time into or may have been well-meaning,
didn't understand the impact,
but you can cause misery by the environment you create.
And for a lot of people feel trapped there and that affects their,
their family,
that affects their relationships,
affects their kids.
It's a massive flow on effect because we're not sharing the idea that we can be better in this space.
So I'm glad you shared that story.
It really,
it's the essence of what we're really trying to capture.
Absolutely,
Darson,
you know,
just quickly,
there's no doubt,
Neil Jensen saw the worker and the person,
you know,
his empathy and his range took over when he was talking to Luke Darcy as a person rather than Luke Darcy as the administrative clerk or whatever your role might have been.
Yeah,
he was more interested in how you were and how your family was than he was in you doing a good job.
And,
and that meant that the,
that worker was compelled or felt,
you know,
some responsibility and drive to do a good job because he knew or she knew that the CEO cared about them.
Um,
and I think that's a challenge for people in authority or in senior positions.
If they haven't got great depth,
um,
emotionally,
they need good people around them,
to help them with that or to help the staff with that.
Um,
and,
and recognizing that in any organization is,
is a critical starting point.
And,
uh,
but Neil did it right.
I went to school with,
uh,
um,
a young fellow named Matt Connell and Maddie and I don't,
we don't see each other anymore.
And the most humble person I ever met in my life.
And he never wanted any credit for,
for anything.
And,
and I think he,
he taught me a lesson as a,
as a young fella around,
you know,
when to step back and,
and when to step forward.
And,
um,
and he was,
he,
he was the epitome of,
of almost being too humble,
you know?
And,
um,
and I look for that,
that humility in,
in leaders and,
um,
and dispersing recognition in,
uh,
in good times,
but the willingness to,
uh,
to,
you know,
take responsibility when,
when things don't go so right.
Um,
and,
and so I,
you know,
I,
at the moment I,
like in my life,
I,
I don't know,
there's probably not been one standout,
uh,
person,
but if I,
you know,
I think about it,
you were on the political spectrum and you,
you think about,
say Jacinda Ardern at the moment and,
and she just seems to me like a very strong woman who's got the balance right,
um,
in that regard.
Um,
also,
um,
I've gone down a political,
political angle a little bit here.
Um,
but it,
but it is a,
it is something that I,
I really look for in a great leader is,
is that humility.
And,
um,
there have been some outstanding ones and,
I just wish I could spit them out at the moment.
Could I ask you to go childhood friend?
Why don't you see each other?
Is it just the evolution of life and.
Yeah,
essentially.
I mean,
we,
after year 10,
sorry,
after our secondary schooling,
we,
um,
yeah,
we just parted ways and,
and Matt went off and studied and,
um,
and yeah,
we just don't see each other anymore,
unfortunately.
And,
uh,
he,
it's interesting that I think all of us felt the same way about Matt and for him to be,
he was such a,
um,
as far as football goes,
he was such a hard in and under type physical player.
And then off the field,
he was,
he was such a,
a generous caring type person.
And my,
my,
my father,
John,
um,
brought me up on a appetite on a,
on a menu of,
um,
mean Joe green who played for the Pittsburgh Steelers.
And Joe green was famous for being just such a great and beautiful human being off the
field and,
uh,
being caring and generous in,
in what he did for others,
but on field across the white line.
And it's,
he's,
he's a different,
different person,
a different customer.
Um,
ferocious in the way he played the game.
And,
uh,
and that balance of,
of on and off field has always resonated with me.
And,
uh,
and so I look for that,
in,
in other people,
the competitiveness,
but the,
um,
you know,
the,
the lighter side in them and that they're,
they're willing to,
um,
show their emotions and,
and reach out and care and,
um,
and definitely praise and,
and,
and make other others feel good about themselves,
um,
at any opportunity.
Well,
I think I said that one stage at the start of this Bevo,
uh,
I found very hard to get the words out to,
to describe you.
Maybe you did it yourself with Joe Green.
I'm not familiar with his work,
but that empathy,
that care for others,
being a great human being,
but also fiercely competitive and loyal.
Uh,
I look forward to reading more about him because that is who I'm staring in front of a unique leader in every sense,
mate.
I've always,
uh,
valued the fact that we crossed over and,
um,
I love spending,
uh,
any time with you.
So thanks for joining us today.
Very flattering,
Darcy.
I appreciate it.
And,
um,
you know,
what you're doing,
uh,
in this space is,
is really influential and,
uh,
and I'm really grateful to be a part of it.
So I really thank you.
Thank you for that.
And,
um,
I've really enjoyed the chat.
Empowering leaders was presented by me,
Luke Darcy,
produced by Matt Dwyer with audio production by Darcy Thompson.
Start your leadership journey.
I encourage you to go to a leader collective.com,
take our empowering leaders indicator tool and understand the impact you have,
on your environment.
Join us at a leader to learn,
lead and collaborate.
Listener.