I really loved the conversation this week on the Empowering Leaders podcast.
It truly was a great pleasure to sit down with five-time Olympian
and the 2010 gold medal winner, Lydia Lassler.
Listening to Lydia's story, hearing about her attitude towards excellence
was incredibly insightful from her early years making the tough decision
to give up a sport she loved to then move into a completely new area.
Her attitude towards parenting and now her thoughts on business
and entrepreneurship, incredibly insightful.
Her documentary, The Will to Fly, is brilliant and was labelled
by the Huffington Post as 2016's most inspiring film.
This crossover between sport and leadership is something that I have been exploring
at the business I co-founded with my great friend Matt Waterwitz called Alita.
It's a place where leaders can collaborate and learn from one another.
We've been fortunate enough to work with some incredible leaders
in our program, Ange Postacoglu from Celtic, Arsenal's Mikel Arteta,
the Milwaukee Bucks assistant coach Mike Dunlap, just to name a few.
And if you're interested in this space, you don't need to be a global superstar coach
to be part of it.
You can find all about it at alitacollective.com.
I encourage you to check out our signature Alita Connect program
to understand how people like Lydia are collaborating and leading in their world.
Lydia Lassler was awarded the prestigious The Don Award by the Sport Australia Hall
of Fame for her gold medal winning performance in the aerial skiing
at the 2010 Vancouver Winter Olympics.
Four years later, in the Olympic final in Sochi, Lydia became the first female ever
to attempt a quad twisting triple somersault known as a back full double full full,
a feat at the time that was only considered available to the men.
And despite not landing that jump, her courage was rewarded with a bronze medal.
Lydia's brilliant documentary about her life, The Will to Fly,
has motivated and inspired many with her courage.
Perseverance and dedication.
Lydia, it's always great to see you.
It's been a long while and nice to see you on the line from Finland today.
Yeah, it has been a while.
Thank you for having me.
It's great to see you as well.
Now, Lydia, I loved going back and watching your story again.
The documentary is just brilliant.
I encourage everyone, if you haven't seen Will to Fly,
it's easily accessible on Apple or lots of platforms.
It's just incredibly inspiring to watch it again.
But I didn't realize, the youngest possible age, Lydia,
you had in your mind about being an Olympic champion,
Olympic gold medal winner.
Tell us about where that came from.
Oh, it started early.
It was probably around six years old.
So, and I, we were on a family trip to Cyprus where my dad's from.
And we're sitting in this beach cafe in the 1988 Olympics we were on at the time.
And I was just, you know, kind of transfixed to the TV
while we're eating our tarra masalata, you know, in the beach
and just looking, what the hell is this?
What's this race?
You know, they're swimming.
And there's running and there's all kinds of sports.
And, yeah, that was probably my first introduction to the Olympics
and just watching these athletes standing on top of the dice and crying
and, you know, the idea of, I guess, the best competing against the best
in something, you know, just really, it drew me in.
It really did.
It's something that I've always fell in love with, you know,
the Olympic movement.
But, yeah, I think from that early age,
I really believe that was something that I was meant to be.
You know, I was meant to be in some kind of sport.
I didn't know what at the time, but I wanted to stand on top of that dice as well.
And, yeah, I think individual sports probably were more appealing to me.
But, yeah, just to be that individual, you know, having stood up on that dice is,
yeah, it was really compelling.
For a young kid that just didn't really know anything about structured sport
and didn't have the background.
Gymnastics was the early passion.
You're an outstanding junior gymnast.
And then you got injured.
How unlikely was it from that moment on, I think it was around 16,
that you would go on and become an aerial skier?
Look, so many unlikely things have happened in my life.
So I'm just, you know, living in Finland at the moment.
And who would have thought I'm living in Lapland, the North Pole?
So.
So strange things happened.
And, you know, it was like those sliding door moments, I suppose.
But, yeah, I didn't make it as a gymnast, which was gutting, I think, for me,
because I knew I had the potential to.
But long story short, you know, I just missed opportunities there.
And then, yeah, got injured and just had to make that call,
which was horrible because, you know, you're young
and you feel like your whole world's kind of crashing down
because that gymnastics was up to that.
But at that point, my passion and my life, you know, I really loved it.
And it was my community and growing up with three older brothers,
it was a way for me to just get away from my brothers
and do something different as well, you know,
and be able to just stand on my own on something.
They wouldn't let me win anything else.
So it was an important part of my life.
And I just always knew, like, I had what it takes, you know,
to be the best.
And so for that to be kind of a non-event and to just not happen
was pretty gutting for me.
So I had to make the decision to stop because I was also realistic
and I'm like, it's not going to happen.
But I was looking for something else to do.
And at that time, I had, you know, as a gymnast,
I had a pretty good skill set in a lot of different areas.
I was very strong and disciplined and motivated.
So I looked at something.
I was kayaking at one stage and even rowing and loved the beach
and loved, you know, spending time at our holiday house down in Lawn.
So I loved surf lifesaving.
I grew up watching, you know, the Uncle Toby series
and wanted to do that as well or surfing.
So there was lots of, like, options of, like, where can I go?
What can I do?
I still want to be an athlete.
And at that time, the Olympic Winter Institute had this really great idea
of recruiting ex-gymnasts.
They were first in the world to do so, recruiting ex-gymnasts
and seeing if they had the skill set or if we could develop the skills
for them to convert into aerial skiers.
So it was innovative because we, in Australia,
we didn't have a large pool of, you know, skiers.
It's not our main sport.
It's a short winter season.
But we do have a lot of ex-gymnasts.
And at the time, there actually wasn't much of an avenue, you know,
for us to go into.
Like, the college gymnastics wasn't really a thing.
And I did have a call from Cirque du Soleil at the time,
and they were just starting out.
So it wasn't big yet.
Like, it wasn't big at all.
And I had a call and they said, oh, look, we know you've retired and, you know,
would you be interested in, you know, coming to join us?
And I'm like, what?
I'm not a circus freak.
No, thanks.
No, I'm not joining the circus.
Like, I'm better than that.
I could do something else.
And had I known it was going to be a really good career option,
and it is what it is today, I might have said yes.
But, yeah, so I turned that down.
But, yeah, so the Olympic Winter Institute got in touch and they said, Lydia,
you know, we know you're retired.
Do you want to come and have a bit of a ski at Mount Buller and come
into the office and we'll introduce you to the sport of aerial skiing?
So I went in for a meeting and they put the VHS tape in and showed this
highlight.
And I was like, oh, my God, this is the highlight reel of what aerial skiing is.
And I was just like, what is this?
Like, I had no concept.
I was not a winter person and hadn't skied before.
So it was so foreign.
But it looked so cool.
You know, these amazing athletes, you know,
flipping off these huge jumps and doing all these acrobatics in the air.
And, of course, it was a highlight reel.
It didn't show any crashes and it didn't show any hard hits that were to follow
pretty soon after that.
But it looked amazing.
And I think at the time, you know, seven, I was coming to, you know,
being 18 years old and the idea of, you know, gallivanting off to the mountains
and that time it was off to Canada and to Whistler Blackcomb and, you know,
and experiencing real mountains and real winter and this kind of adventure
was appealing because I'd, you know,
been this disciplined gymnast stuck indoors for quite a while and told what
to do.
So it was like liberating for sure, the idea of it.
But really it was just, you know, just mentioning the Winter Olympics
and I was like, hmm, this is cool.
Yes, please.
I didn't really ask too many questions after that.
I mean, and then two years later you're in an Olympic final in Salt Lake City.
It's an incredible ability to get there.
And, again, watching back and watching your dog,
you had an incredible level of confidence at that age.
Yeah.
And, you know, you told people what you were going to do.
And, you know, senior people in the sport, you were getting stuck into them.
I mean, where did that come from?
Where did that full self-confidence come from?
Yeah, it's tricky.
Like I was – I think I was progressing really fast and I saw, you know,
a lot of weaknesses in the programs, like in the way competitors trained,
the way – I mean, it still didn't have much structure.
So freestyle skiing was pretty loose.
When I started, still, like people rarely warmed up and the gym was just a thing.
And, you know, they were, you know, having a good time on the weekends.
And so it was actually, yeah, pretty loose.
And there was a really big gap between, you know,
the females and where the males were at when I started.
And I could just see those opportunities.
I saw them as opportunities.
I'm like, oh, I want to close that gap, you know, want to fill that hole.
Because I couldn't understand why there was such a big gap
and why there was such a big gap.
There was such a big difference in skill level at the time.
It didn't – it doesn't – it's not explained by physical strength.
Like a lot of other sports, you can kind of easily say, well,
men are stronger than women or whatever you want to say.
But, like, it just – it's not that kind of sport.
It's very skill-based.
And, you know, you had six-foot guys doing these amazing tricks
and you had five-foot three guys doing these amazing tricks the same size as me.
So, you know, so it wasn't really based on any kind of physical, you know,
body set or anything like that.
And so I just saw opportunities.
And so I was a bit, you know, cocky.
I was very cocky at the start and just saying I'm going to be –
I've really believed that I'm going to be the one that's going to close those gaps
and I'm going to be, you know, setting a new benchmark, I suppose,
for the female aerial skiers.
And that was the mission.
That was like, right, that's the job, you know.
And that's what I wanted, you know.
I wanted to win everything.
But I also wanted to be a groundbreaker.
I think even more so.
Like I think that's what really drove me every day, training with guys,
making sure my quality was at the same, you know, standard
or nipping at their heels as best as I could.
So with time and, you know, and I guess if you look at the program's evolution,
like when I started it was very unstructured and myself
and my teammate that was chosen at the time as these, you know, rookies
or basically guinea pigs to see if this process of turning gymnasts
to aerial skiers was going to work.
It went from being quite loose to then now, you know, 20-something years later,
like it's so structured and it's beautiful, it's meticulous, you know.
There's processes in place for our athletes.
There's training facilities in Australia.
They've got all the services they need.
There's medical support, which, you know, we didn't have when we first started.
And psychological.
Psychological support and, you know, to see all that kind of change over the years,
it's a beautiful process to witness.
Come back to the groundbreaking part of what you did and it's fascinating
that you had that, you know, such an early part of your career in a sport
you knew nothing about.
You'd never skied before, but in your mindset you're going to, you know,
break new ground.
I find that incredibly fascinating.
And as you said, they show you a tape of the highlight reel.
They don't show you how many times you're going to fall down.
Now, again, I watched.
I did it again last night.
I had seen it before, but it just reminded me of how ridiculously courageous
you and your colleagues are to sit at the top of that mountain.
You know, you've blown ACLs out before.
We'll talk about that.
To know, I still couldn't watch the replay last night.
You know, having done an ACL play footy before, I still find it hard to watch ACLs.
Same.
Let alone saying, okay, I'm in an Olympic final.
You know, I've had surgery.
There's a massive chance if that goes wrong,
I blow my knee out again.
Tell us about how you found and some of the crashes.
You had in training were just ridiculous.
You know, like it just looked like you were going to kill yourself at some stage.
I mean, how did you find that mental toughness?
What sort of practices did you get to get that resilience and mental toughness?
I think at the start of my career, like, you know, we talk about being a bit cocky
and probably mostly it was more to do with naivety, I suppose.
It was just, let's face it, the less you know, sometimes the better.
But, yeah.
It probably started with my coach at the time, his German coach.
And I was just learning how to ski.
And he said, Lydia, Salt Lake City Olympics are in less than two years.
If you train really hard, there's an opening for you.
Because it wasn't like four women get selected onto the team and, you know,
there wasn't enough women.
So I'm like, right, you know, it's on.
Yeah.
And so it started, the recklessness started there.
Let's just call it recklessness.
Because it wasn't really monitored and it wasn't, I was just all go.
You know, I had some great things going on.
I was determined.
I was improving very quickly.
I had come in with a good skill set.
I had great balance.
I had great feel and all of those things, good acrobatic skills.
So, you know, it was a nice, smooth transition.
But on top of that, I put the work ethic in, you know, and I had talent.
So you mix those two.
You mix those two things together and you've got a good recipe, you know,
for success.
And so probably my biggest asset at that stage and my biggest downfall was the
amount of volume that I could pump out in terms of repetition,
in terms of hours on the hill, and had this ability to do enormous volumes
without getting bored.
And so my first jump to my 60th jump of the day would be the same or maybe even
better, whereas, you know, people kind of trailed off at about 20, you know,
and couldn't do the volumes.
So it was great because I improved really quickly and in no time had the skills
to compete in the Olympics.
But I didn't rest and I didn't, you know,
periodise and I didn't have any recovery and I didn't have any physio and, you know,
like I just burnt my body to the ground without realising at that point that it's going
to need to carry me another 15 years, you know.
So I was injured probably most of my career and in pain for a lot of it.
And it started early.
And so, you know, going into Salt Lake City, I was,
I had a cyst in my spine.
My left leg was going numb.
So I was going crooked off the jump because I couldn't feel the same balance
on my two skis.
You know, I had a torn shoulder that, you know,
slapped lesion and slapped hair in my shoulder that needed surgery afterwards.
I was an absolute mess.
But here I was believing that I could win a medal there.
I honestly went in thinking, nah, I can win a medal, you know,
and I had no business being there.
It was my first ever year competing actually that year.
And so I made the,
I made the finals and finished eighth place and my teammate,
Elisa Camplin, who was at the peak of her career, you know, won.
So a crazy kind of self-belief, which I have no idea where that came from,
and a good ability to block out pain and the fear associated with that.
Because at the time I remember being really frightened for my life,
actually, because I was really struggling.
I was, you know, skiing off crooked off the jump,
which.
Is not good in the air because then you're landing, you know,
crooked and then you're landing heavy on one leg and, and then, you know,
you get really quite beaten up on, on, you know, lopsided almost, you know,
so, so body was just in terrible shape.
And it took me after those Olympics,
it took me a good two years to iron myself out and kind of get straight again.
And, and even now, if I don't look after, you know,
that back injury and, and, you know, knees and shoulders and things like that,
that have kind of come over the years, um, yeah, I'm in trouble, you know?
So self-management is, you know, really important thing these days,
which I didn't really care or didn't really take into account then,
and had no one to really guide me and say, Liv, you, you know,
you're doing a bit too much, let's slow it down a bit,
or I think your shoulder's torn or, you know,
In fact, you're insane, Lydia, we need to give you a break.
We need to, I mean, there was a bit of vision reminding, uh, where you, you,
you had a, uh, pre-Olympic tournament at the Bird's Nest, uh, stadium in China,
and they, uh, they build the, the slope inside the stadium,
and then you look up and there's not a net to the left.
No.
And you think if, if, if you, if you get that wrong,
you're literally, someone's going to die.
Yeah.
And you're catching an elevator up to that height.
I've got an insane fear of heights.
I felt nervous just watching it again to, to, to watch it.
I mean, I'm fascinated.
You say you had a great ability to deal with pain and, and clearly you did.
Great ability to overcome fear.
And I, you know, watching your eyes on the top of those slope, knowing that you've got
those things going on with a torn shoulder, I mean, was there something specific to, is
it just who you are or did you learn some techniques to be able to control that nervous?
Because a lot of people listen to this who, you know, who are anxious, who struggle with,
you know, uh, fear and anxiety daily.
I mean, how can they tap into a bit of Lydia Lassoy?
Yeah.
And I, you know, I was scared a lot, you know, and, and pain a lot and worried a lot, especially,
you know, starting to do these triple somersaults.
And, you know, you go to bed at night and you're like, oh gosh, my knees really saw
or, oh gosh, it's going to be a blizzard tomorrow.
I hope I get through it, you know, like, like those kinds of feelings, um, going to bed
at night, which is not, I don't miss that at all now sitting in the comfort of my home,
you know, a few, few years on and sipping a cup of coffee, like I don't miss that feeling
of being anxious and worried and scared.
Um, but, um, over the course of my career, you know, I wised up.
Like.
I started out reckless and then 2006 Torino Olympics, where I blew my knee at the Olympics
for the second time in six months was the end for me, um, in terms of being reckless,
that was it.
I didn't want that up and down, you know, um, cycle of being injured and coming back
out of it and having to fight back and cause I was good, you know, I was really talented
and really good and I knew I could win an Olympics.
So I reached out for help.
So I think step one, anxious, depressed.
Worried constantly, or feeling like you are not where you want to be, not where you should
be, like don't worry about should or could or what, where you want to be, um, reach out
for help.
Set one, I think like, and I, and at that point I, you know, blown my knee and I, and
everyone else was kind of, well, you know, you get the feeling people are going to start
to write you off after you've blown your knee twice and they start to think, well, I don't
think she's going to have the heart or the.
Courage to, or the, to come back, you know, and be able to be successful and you feel
that.
And, but inside I was like, no, that's not going to happen.
You know, like I know I can do this.
I just don't know what I'm doing wrong.
And I need help.
And so after, you know, 2006 and probably in the lowest point of my career, I just found
I'd, I'd been reading, um, I've been reading some books on, on, um, um, um, you know, um,
like I've read heaps of mental training books just to try and get an edge and to give me
the skillset to be able to calm down in stressful situations.
And you can learn so much.
You learn so much from these days, podcasts, you know, it was amazing.
Like you can learn so much, but I read a lot of books and, um, the book, one book that
really resonated with me was a book called sports mind.
And if you're actually, if you're an athlete, it's a, it's a, it's like a Bible.
It's amazing.
Um, but if you're anyone.
Yeah.
And I read it and I thought that I should read it as a book.
Because I read it every single day when I went to the gym.
And I think so.
I've got, I've read it every single, every single day.
So the book is pretty strong.
I was so, so proud of it, um, but yeah, so, so, and this book talked a lot about that.
And so I did read it.
And what it did for me was I read it and I was like, you know, the most important thing
I'm, I'm, I'm so excited to read this book because it's so, so important to me and, I'm
so, so happy to read it.
I love it.
And I read it.
I have, you know, the funds at the time to engage Jeffrey Hodges,
the author, and he's from Queensland.
He's amazing, probably the most pivotal person in my career
and really focused on NLP, so Neuro Linguistic Programming.
So he's not a psychologist but he's an NLP trainer and, you know,
quite incredible.
And read his books.
They really resonated with me.
He bought his CDs and on the CDs there was, you know, these lectures
but I guess lectures on self-confidence, visualisation,
positive mental attitudes, motivation, like how to do all these things,
like real tangible skills.
And, you know, I just listened to them religiously really
and also with those with daily visualisations,
which really helped me a lot, unpack a day and get ready
for the next one, you know.
And so after Toreen.
I thought, bugger it, I'm going to give this guy a call
and I flew up to the Sunshine Coast and went and saw him
and, you know, took him through what I'd kind of been through
and felt like I knew him already because I'd been reading his material
for so long and listening to his voice on the visualisation tapes
and he looked at me straight in the eye and he said,
Lydia, you've created everything that's happened to you.
And I'm like, you know, how disordinary.
You've just come out of surgery.
I'm like, you bastard, that's really mean.
And, you know, because every thought, you know,
then leads to some kind of action or behaviour and you do that long enough
and it becomes a habit and a pattern.
And he was spot on that I was, you know, a lot of the things I'd done
in the past, the past Lydia, that overtrained,
that had some limiting beliefs.
But, you know, one of them was if you work hard, you'll be successful.
And so he taught me how to change that and how to flip that
and just transform that belief, you know, about working smarter,
not harder, you know.
And then there was a positive shift.
From there it was a change and he taught me the skills on, you know,
there's so many little techniques and when you're standing up on top
of the hill and there's so many distractions that could possibly come in,
you know.
Someone might say something or a bird might fly in front
or someone might crash just right in front of you, you know,
and something bad, you know, has happened just in the jump before
or you've just had a bad crash and you're trying to pick yourself up.
And in those moments, you know, the skills of just being present,
you know, being where you are and understanding your cues.
So, okay, I could think about all the bad things that are going
to happen to me right now or I could actually just focus on the things
that are going to let me do this.
Jump safely and successfully.
So, hit your take.
And just keeping those kind of things really simple, you know,
and you practice that long enough and it becomes habit.
And so when you get into those situations and stressful situations
and rather than being a deer in a headlight, you know,
where you just freeze and you don't know what to do,
you can pull out the, you know, the tools out of the tool bag and go,
right, this one for this one, you know, this one for this one.
And breathe and all of these things that help you just stay present,
stay in that place where you can actually focus and be confident.
You know, it's a state that you can change instantly just
by the way you carry yourself, by the way you talk to yourself, you know.
Yeah, and being able to set yourself up for a good day by asking empowering
questions, not ones that will disempower you.
What if I don't do this?
You know, or I don't feel I've prepared enough or I always get nervous
in front of the crowd or, you know, whatever it might be for you.
Like listen to the way, I guess, you're speaking to yourself
and just try and reframe it.
But there's so much.
There's so much, I think, mentally that we can all learn and do.
But it just, you know, like that make a really big difference
and it just as much as we train our muscles, I think it's so important
that we actually train our minds so it doesn't kind of, you know,
lead us down that rabbit hole and get out of hand.
If there's ever a sport or an athlete to sum that up, you know,
brought to life again for me just seeing, you know,
it's pretty immediate, isn't it, when you've got a ramp
and you're going at 60 k's an hour and you're going to do four flips
and try and land, you know, if you're not, the risk is enormous.
And I love what you said, you know, reach out and get some help
and, you know, very different sport, Lydia, lucky enough to play.
But always when you're out of form and you're anxious about,
geez, am I good enough?
To play and you start thinking about wanting to play this great game,
you're in that space straight away or you can't control that outcome
but you could always go back to things that, you know,
help you to be good in the first place that you could control,
how hard you worked or how hard you ran or how you supported your teammates
or how you used your voice or there are all these things
that no one could take away from you.
And when you're sort of drilled into that, you know,
it tended to make life a lot easier rather than that anxiety around,
geez, if I don't kick five goals, I'm in a world of trouble.
I love hearing it from you all.
You know, sports point of view.
I want to go forward, Lydia.
It's the quad twisting triple somersault.
It just, it looks like the most ridiculous thing anyone would ever think
to attempt in their life.
Busy.
Busy is one word.
I would describe it again as crazy.
And you do it in an Olympic final.
You know, you build up to that.
You're a mother at that stage and, you know,
you're already an Olympic gold medalist so you've done everything you needed to do.
The fact that you had the motivation to do it, but, I mean,
it was such an amazing.
It was such an amazing thing to attempt an Olympic final.
Tell us why that was so big for you.
Look, at the time, it was just on my bucket list kind of thing, you know.
It was something that had drove me through the sport, you know.
When I said before, like, I wanted to jump like a guy and that was,
if I could do that trick, that meant that I had achieved that, you know.
And so my goals, I guess, were, yes, I wanted to win an Olympic medal,
but once I'd won that or actually Olympic gold medal, that's what I wanted.
But after that, it's kind of like, what now?
What haven't I, you know, kind of done yet?
And there's still lots of things left undone.
Don't get me wrong, but that was one of them.
That was an important one, one that when I got to Olympic finals,
prepared to kind of sacrifice everything for, you know.
So it was what motivated me for that quad.
I'd had a baby.
I had Kai, my firstborn, after 2010, after I'd won.
I'd had time off, which I believe every athlete should do.
It just gives you great perspective, have a break from the sport,
find some other things that in life are fulfilling
and that you can see yourself doing after sport, I suppose.
That was really important for me and helped my transition.
But then, you know, I had Kai and, again, people thought,
oh, she's not going to have the heart to come back.
And, you know, it's like being injured.
And I think women are amazing these days.
They're doing all kinds of things, having surrogates and things.
I was like, ooh, that idea did not come into my mind,
but how cool would that have been?
Outsource that one.
I think, yeah, outsource everything.
But, no, it was good growing a baby and coming back from it, you know,
and that whole process was amazing.
And the only reason why I wanted to come back was because I wanted to,
you know.
At that point in life, I had a family and had business already set up.
And so the thing that drove me and pulled me back was the sport.
Being an athlete was what I loved to do.
And this idea of there's something still that I haven't done yet that I want to do,
you know, and it took me a long time to get there because of injuries and,
you know, like the whole ring marole of being an athlete.
It's not like linear.
It's up and down.
And so I was at that point.
I'm like, this is my kind of last push.
I want to get to this trick.
And it wasn't easy.
I had, you know, Kai in tow.
And so I had a lot of help with my mum and my husband, Latay,
and they flew around with me and my mother-in-law as well to help me manage
and cope with being a mum and an elite athlete and, you know,
running a business on the side.
And when I look back now what I was managing at that point in time in my life,
my head kind of spins off because it was a lot.
It was like a lot.
It was a lot of intensity.
And so, yeah, that quad was all about that comeback to the 2014 Olympics was
about building up to this quad twisting triple somersault and being the first
woman to do it.
And that's what I wanted.
And so my coach at the time, Mishroth, who coaches, you know,
one of our athletes still, Laura Peel, you know,
he just bought into my ideas.
He really did.
And I think.
I think that's really important to have that support from your coach
and the team around me.
And so my, you know, Geoffrey Hodges at that point was solidified into my team.
He was part of the furniture and coach and physios and trainers as well at the VIS.
So they all bought into what I wanted to do.
That was really important because I felt like everyone was on my team and,
you know, because I didn't have to do it to win, you know.
And sometimes.
We back down.
We only do what we need to do to win, you know, nothing more.
Definitely not less, but I didn't need to do it, but I wanted to.
And so got to the, you know, to 2014 Olympics.
I didn't have the preparation that I wanted to.
It was quite a difficult season leading into those Olympics with really crazy
weather.
And so being a bit smarter, we had to choose when,
to do this trick, you know, and,
and not to take risks before we actually even get to the Olympics, you know.
And so the opportunity in the window just didn't present itself at our Olympic
training camp.
It was as an average temperature of about minus 25 degrees.
And so it was freezing.
It was cold and, and my body wasn't, you know,
coping and it just wasn't the time to throw this new trick down, you know,
and, and leading into that, you know,
that we just had bad weather days.
And so the opportunity to present itself until about three days before the
Olympics or maybe even two and actually there in training and,
you know, got, you know, used to the new, new side in Sochi.
And, and so that takes, you know,
a day or so and got up to speed in my tricks and was feeling good.
And, and that was the time I looked at my coach and like, I think,
I think we go like, this is now feeling good.
And like the time.
And so it's at the end of the day, I was, I was the last jumper of the day.
It was starting to get dark and I started to, you know,
visualize doing this trick.
And when you kind of visualize and you start doing the movements,
everyone knows what you're doing.
So all the competitors and the coaches start, you know,
got their phones out and started crowding down at the Olympics.
They could literally, they could see you as soon as you got into that routine.
Everyone's going, hang on a minute, it's on here.
And they heard whispers.
That she's going to do it.
Yeah.
And, or that I'd been training it, but I hadn't done it yet.
Hadn't had the opportunity.
And so everyone's like slid down underneath the jumps and I'm like, Oh God,
here we go.
And, you know, I felt green.
I wanted to vomit and, and, you know,
skied in and, and, and relied on all the, you know,
the training that I had done.
So I'd practice it on, on the water ramps.
I'd practice it on trampoline, but it's still a thing, you know,
when you're doing it for the first time on snow,
it's scary and you just hope everything kind of kicks into gear.
You don't forget and do the deer in a headlight.
Anyway, skied down, went off the jump.
I was fine.
I was like, Oh, this is good.
I know what I'm doing.
I could see everything and skied away.
And I'm like, did it, you know, and this is at the Olympics.
I've turned around and every single person, my competitors, the coaches,
this is, you know,
this is the Olympics where everyone is in game mode and it's the most
competitive environment.
Ever.
They're all lined up and just cheering, you know?
And for me, that was like,
the Rocky soundtrack came on and it was my Rocky moment.
It was like, Oh, I did it.
And it was a really cool,
like really cool moment that no one really saw.
Like it, you know, it wasn't, it wasn't executed perfectly.
And, you know, you know,
I skied out of it.
It wasn't perfect, but it was such a milestone, you know,
for me and, and, you know, a lot of the, you know,
the women, you know, as well, and looking in and watching it,
the time and coaches that had all been, you know, part of it.
So for me,
that was one of the best moments of my kind of career a couple of days
before the Olympics.
So then anyway, it was done.
And, and I, you know,
remember going through some video feedback with my coach that night and,
and we made,
we made a plan and, and now that it was done,
like it was just so much lighter.
The monkey was off my back and, and he said, look,
we're jumping well.
And what do we want to, what do we want to do?
If you, cause it, the, the, the,
the competition was in fact a brutal format.
It was a good eight hour competition where you had to go through a
qualifying process and it was all elimination.
And then the final 12 would start,
they do a jump and then it would go to eight.
And then four, and then you jump for the finals for,
for the medals, sorry.
So four people at the end, last people standing,
jump for a medal and you don't know what colour you're going to get.
And so I said, look, if we make it to the four, you know,
I think we should go for it.
And he's like, I think you're absolutely right.
So it was a plan that if I made it to the four,
which is hard enough in itself, then,
then we would never back down.
We would go for it.
So just an amazing moment.
And sport, I love hearing you tell that story.
And it freaked your opponents out too, didn't it?
A couple of days out before, yeah.
They stood and applauded and then it unnerved them all.
They went, if she's got this up her sleeve and she's prepared to do that,
you know, a couple of days out from Olympic competition,
she's next level.
And, you know, this really strong Chinese jumpers, you know,
got off the, put off their game, slightly letting into it.
It's brilliant.
If you haven't seen it, you go back and, as I said,
watch the incredible documentary, The Wheel to Fly,
it captures it, that moment, brilliantly.
And I love, as you said, that high purpose around,
you could have played safe in an Olympic final when you didn't.
You put it all out there and did something no one else has ever done before.
Can I, can I, you know, there's some questions I want to ask you at the end,
but you mentioned Latte, your husband, who was an outstanding skier for Finland.
He represented his country in the 1998 Olympics and the 1999 World Championships
and the men's moguls and his support throughout the journey.
You've had two boys, Kai.
And, Alec, can I ask a parenting question?
Because I love asking this from a leadership point of view.
The boys have got two incredibly disciplined, high achieving parents.
I mean, how does that flow through to them?
And what's your leadership like from a parenting point of view?
Oh, gosh.
It's, look, parenting's tough.
It's not easy.
We, you know, Kai is our firstborn and he's, he's, he's our kind of angel child
that does what he's told.
And we had him and we're like,
oh, we're awesome parents.
And then we had Alec who has a different, different, just, you know,
goes to the beat of his own drum and doesn't really listen to us
and does his own thing and does it his way.
So, and we're like, no, but there's an easier way.
And we know that there is, and you just trust us and do it.
And he's like, no.
So it's about just finding, I think, their strengths, you know,
encouraging them in what they, they like to do and,
and letting them be their own.
And there's, you know, risk in having, you know,
I guess parents that have, you know,
achieved at a high level before and trying to push that then onto the,
onto the children, especially if they're not ready or,
or they don't want it and there's no interest, you know,
and, and we're very mindful of that.
We don't, we instill discipline in,
in them in a way that is easy for them to do, you know,
make your bed.
Tidy up your clothes, clean up, do chores, like contribute.
And if you're going to do something, you know,
put some effort in and do it well and,
and trying to just give them opportunities,
trying to give them opportunities to say they can try different things,
try soccer, try tennis, try, you know, different little,
different sports that, that they're interested in and,
and finding their strengths, I think.
And, and then, you know, supporting them through that,
then, then giving, trying to just give them, I suppose,
as much opportunity as possible.
So that's, that's,
that's what we try and do when, you know, not definitely not try
and make them fit into, you know, a certain mold or our mold
or what we think, you know, they should do.
But I guess it comes, what we do have is the ability
to give them some guidance, especially,
particularly if they want to be athletes.
I think we can give them some really great, you know,
great advice and skillset that I didn't have, you know, growing up.
But what I did have growing up was support.
Um, no one could understand what I wanted to do or why it didn't make any sense
to them, but they, they supported me.
And so, um, yeah, that's what we try to do.
Yeah.
It's early, early days yet.
Um, and they, you know, showing their interest in,
in certain things and we co-parent, you know, there's no good cop,
bad cop.
We co-parent in a really equal way.
Um, Lattes had to play mum a lot and sometimes I play dad a lot,
you know, and it's just this,
this role that's actually, there is no mum and dad.
It's just the same.
We do the same things.
We both work, we both do chores, we both rear the kids, you know,
and, um, and so it feels like a pretty good unit and a really good team,
I suppose.
But yeah, it's a tricky one, isn't it?
Cause like I do watch the kids play sport and, and I'm like, ah, come on,
you know, don't, don't, you know, don't, don't give up now.
Keep going.
Come on, keep going.
Oh, listen, make sure you're listening.
And, you know, like,
and I want to shout from the sidelines, but I don't, I hold my tongue and you
can't, you just can't, you know,
you can't do that because you can't put that kind of pressure on them.
I don't think as, as young kids, they're just, I don't know if they might,
when you do, I think they, they turn the other way and get discouraged.
Leah, I've loved talking to different people with great leadership and,
and life stories like yours.
And we see common traits of what leadership looks like.
Most people, first of all, don't say, you know,
the term leadership doesn't necessarily resonate with them,
but your life has been incredible story.
And we see everyone's got a sense,
the first dimension I want to talk to you about of self-leadership,
this idea of being able to lead themselves first.
Does that term self-leadership resonate with you?
What does it mean to you?
Yeah, I think so.
In many ways it resonates, you know, I'm the leader of my life.
So, you know, we have, you know, yeah,
this life because we've engineered it that way.
It's not happened by chance or,
by, you know, some kind of extraordinary gift.
It's been a lot of grit and hard work and steadfast kind of resilience to stick
to what is important to you.
So lifestyle for me is important.
Being able to work abroad and, and,
and do what I want to do and give the kids these opportunities is important
for me.
So that's something that we've engineered over many, you know,
over many years.
And, and, and so leading your own life,
leading others, you know,
I've run a couple of businesses now for nearly 15 years from,
from overseas, from my laptop, from abroad.
And so I think, I think I'm a pretty good leader.
I'll have to ask everyone later on, but they don't say,
they don't seem to complain too much.
And, and, you know, that whole leading by example is,
is kind of true because, you know,
if I portray self-discipline and then if I give people a go and give them
independence to show me what they can do,
um,
and, and to do their job without breathing down their back is,
as I do my job without anyone breathing down my back,
I think it empowers people.
So I really try to give them the confidence to,
to get the job done, um,
and to,
to develop their skills and to encourage them to develop their skills.
Um, so that's kind of, you know, within, you know,
my remote workplace, that's, that's how I suppose I lead.
Um, I encourage them all to find,
you know, a balanced lifestyle as well.
You know, it's really important if you're happy at home,
you tend to be happy and productive at work.
Um, so balance for me is important and finding,
you know,
and that balance through your relationships and through your own learning
and through performance and career and, and through, you know,
giving back as well, like contributing, um,
I think is, is, is really important.
And so that's,
you know, I mentor athletes as well.
So I, in a way, you know,
I'm leading them or guiding,
guiding them through their own journeys and, um,
and teaching and,
and passing on and contributing in that way,
passing on things that I've learned,
which I believe is a lot about myself,
but also about the process of being successful.
So I really enjoy, um,
guiding athletes and giving them that kind of information.
Um, or, or helping them flesh through their own,
um, their own story, you know, not just story,
but process and,
and what makes a difference to their training and their,
their performance on a,
on a daily basis,
um, and help them find things outside of their sport that they're interested
in so that they can be a wholesome athlete,
you know, and a well balanced athlete.
So I really,
yeah, I think leadership for me,
um, you know,
my dad was,
you know,
ran his own,
he was,
you know,
an entrepreneur in his own right.
So he ran his own business.
And so that was instilled from a young age for me.
I never really envisioned myself working for anybody.
I've always thought I'll just be like dad,
you know,
run my own show and have school holidays,
have a lifestyle.
And,
and in certain respects that has definitely,
you know,
flowed through to me.
And,
um,
and our kids,
you know,
we're seeing it now leading,
leading our children through life,
you know,
they see mom and dad working from home.
Um,
they always have,
they've never gone to a nine to five job.
So they've no,
they don't know anything different.
So they might want to go to an office to work,
but who knows?
They might want to do what we do as well.
So I think you just,
yeah,
I think ultimately,
um,
if you can figure out how you want to live your own life and find that
balance that we all strive,
um,
you know,
start with leading,
leading your own life.
Um,
but it's important to empower,
our team as well,
even as an athlete,
you know,
I was still leading that team of physio and coach and management and
telling them what I wanted to do and how,
and then we all did the little jobs to get there.
No,
I can't replace the physio and I can't replace the mental trainer and I
can't play replace the coach,
but you can empower them.
Brilliant answer.
And,
uh,
sums up what we see,
you know,
people in this type of,
uh,
environment lead in such a profound way.
And your language is,
uh,
you know,
really aligned with,
uh,
a lot of the people we're talking to about empowering other people,
empowering leaders is the title of this podcast.
And you can see you do it in a profound way and body ice that you
create,
you had lots of ice on your body on a long way to turn that into a,
into a business.
As you said,
that's given you a lifestyle and flexibility,
you know,
is another great part of,
of your story.
We see,
uh,
next dimension we're going to talk to you about is really conscious
leaders and how they positively impact others in their environment.
I really think about that.
I mean,
you work from home,
as you said,
you,
you gravitate,
gravitated to solo sports,
but how have you gone about positively impacting others?
I think the,
it's really important to give back in any way you can.
Um,
whether that's for me,
it's,
um,
through our business,
you know,
we,
we definitely,
and you know,
with time over time,
I've become completely environmentally conscious and,
and sometimes climate anxious.
And so I want to do everything I can to be able to,
um,
to help there and,
and,
um,
contribute.
So,
you know,
both of my businesses zone and,
and body ISA,
you know,
we,
um,
contribute to 1% of the planet and try and do our bit and sourcing
better solutions environmentally of our products.
So,
and so that,
that is a pretty big part for me.
We often then donate proceeds to other,
um,
climate action charities and,
and,
and groups.
Um,
so creating products with purpose,
but very conscious of,
of what we're making and whether there's a place for them in this world,
and they're helping let alone destroying,
you know,
and not,
not,
not completely destroying the world.
So,
so that's,
that's kind of really,
um,
important for me.
And,
and even though it's small business,
it's,
I like to think there is some positive impact,
you know,
for,
for what we do in that way.
Um,
not let alone helping people recover from the injuries,
but in a conscious way.
Um,
and then,
yeah.
So the giving back side of things is,
I think,
um,
super important because that's,
that's a cornerstone really like positive.
How do you have positive impact is by leading in a professional way and being
able to empower those around you,
but also giving time and giving space and energy to others so that they can
flourish.
Um,
for me teaching,
you know,
other people how to,
um,
how to,
how,
how to have a,
not how to have a positive impact,
but how to change the state from being a little bit flat and negative to lifting it up to
being turning around to be positive and motivating.
Because if you can change someone's state from being a little bit flat and unmotivated
to motivated and charging like you're doing a bit.
So I do that,
whether it's in my business or one on one with athletes,
um,
and to the broader community that's,
that's having really positive impact,
you know?
So I don't know if that's answered your question.
It did beautifully.
Uh,
again,
I love the way you think about that.
Uh,
you know,
creating and sharing a vision is something we see really common trait.
Your vision to change a sport that you didn't really know about until you're 16 is,
is incredible story in itself.
I mean,
how did you go about and how have you gone in all your other areas when you've got a vision?
How have you gone about creating it and sharing it?
Yeah.
As an athlete,
so important and it was something that was really strong.
Um,
it's a good question.
Because it's actually something that I even,
you know,
today struggle with a little bit outside of sport.
Um,
and,
and I think I play so much importance,
I suppose on,
on being an athlete in sport and,
and having these really strong goals of,
you know,
winning Olympics and being a groundbreaker for so many years.
And that vision was often very clear,
you know,
as an athlete and I did the work and I put all the pieces together to get there.
And the process,
the process is the same in business,
having that same vision and passion for your business,
I think.
And then how,
you know,
putting the people in the places and the roles and responsibilities in order to get there.
So I'm,
I think I'm really good at breaking down vision into like little bite-sized pieces and creating that pathway and plan on how to get there.
So I try to do that in,
in business.
And sometimes I,
I'm not as disciplined to be quite frank.
Um,
you know,
it's,
maybe I don't put as much importance on it because when you're an athlete and you have a time and a deadline and a date to be successful and are used by date as well,
there's so much intensity and pressure and time pressure to,
to put all your eggs in,
into that one basket.
Um,
and so the vision is intense,
but so is the process.
Whereas in business,
I slack off a bit,
probably.
I don't,
I wouldn't,
I'm not lazy,
but it's not as like,
it's just business and I'm not driven by money.
You know what I mean?
So,
um,
I like,
love my businesses and I like that they have purpose and,
and I am passionate about them,
but I don't think I'm as passionate about them in the way I was as an athlete.
If that makes sense to you.
Makes sense.
And,
and I can't imagine lazy and,
uh,
you being mentioned in the same sentence ever.
So I,
I think that might be an overreach,
but I get it.
I mean,
the,
the lifelong pursuit of wanting,
an Olympic gold medal and do that requires a level of focus that,
you know,
very hard to replicate,
isn't it?
In anything that you do outside of that,
I suspect it's,
uh,
not having done it,
but,
um,
for me,
for you,
it has been,
it's just not as,
um,
yeah,
I think in business as well,
like there's a bit of smoke and mirrors,
like,
you know,
there's people that say they can do a role and they don't deliver or,
or,
you know,
it's not all what it,
like,
it's everything not is not as it often seems,
whereas as an athlete,
you can't hide behind anything,
you know,
if you don't put the effort and the work in and have that perfect preparation
and even then still things can go wrong,
but there's no,
the,
and you get the feedback in the sport,
you know,
directly,
and often that takes time in the other parts of your life.
We see,
uh,
people who are leaders and,
and pave new ground like you,
Lydia,
are really curious and curiosity is a common word.
And through curiosity,
they really continue to approach their learning and development.
Does curiosity play a part in how you think about things?
Oh,
absolutely.
And,
you know,
serial entrepreneur,
if I don't,
I,
you know,
love to explore new ideas and,
and,
um,
then I lose focus on others and,
you know,
I'm wanting,
yeah,
I'm curious about a lot of things.
Um,
and,
and I think that's,
you know,
how,
I mean,
I wear a lot of different hats and I think that's how I tame that curiosity
by doing lots of different things,
whether it's,
you know,
property development or running a business or mentoring or coaching kids or
whatever it might be.
Um,
having lots of little things,
you know,
kind of taming that curiosity,
but even still,
like I'm,
I love yoga and I'm probably moving more into that passion and,
um,
you know,
studying kind of Eastern philosophies.
And,
you know,
if I had time,
I'd just send me to an ashram for three months.
Like,
just let me go because that's,
I'm curious,
you know,
and,
and I know that,
um,
yoga for me has really helped me in so many ways and can help a lot of
people as well,
manage their stress and exciting body.
And,
and so I know that the gift that it's kind of given me and longevity gave me
through sport as well.
Um,
so I'm curious about that path that,
that I want to,
I want to explore it.
So I started,
you know,
I've,
become a qualified yoga teacher,
but you know,
basic one,
but I really want to expand that and,
and go deeper,
you know,
into that,
I think.
And same,
it's just the same with lots of things like,
you know,
surfing.
I'm like,
Oh gosh,
I just,
you know,
I really want to learn.
I want to learn how to be a better surfer.
And,
and,
um,
you know,
yeah,
it's just the same in every probably aspect,
I suppose,
like here living in Lapland and I've discovered a thrill for ski touring.
And so now I want to learn and do an avalanche course because I want to be
safe and be confident,
you know,
in my skillset to go off and do this ski touring.
And,
um,
and it's the same,
you know,
with business or,
I've had so many digital marketers in my business over the last probably five
or six years that I've had a gutful of them.
So at the moment I'm building out my own ads.
I'm learning how to do it because I'm frustrated that people haven't
delivered.
This is what I mean in business isn't always,
you know,
black and white and pure.
Like it is sport.
People kind of fudge the lines and say they can do things and not,
not be able to do them.
So I get frustrated and want to learn.
And so I do.
Yeah.
But that spreads you thin a little bit.
I love it.
I mean,
I love that answer.
You went off into eight different directions and I'm sure another hour.
I love that curiosity.
But I'm curious.
You are.
There's no doubt about that.
It's,
it's brilliant.
And,
and you communicate with clarity,
which is the next dimension we talk about a lot,
really,
you know,
systematic leaders about how they communicate.
Um,
you've had to do that in business and in,
in your sporting life.
And,
and every area.
How have you thought about that?
Oh,
I think it's,
you know,
being able to wind down a day,
um,
with three questions.
I generally give me so much clarity for the next day.
And that is what did we do well today?
What didn't go so well?
And what are we going to do tomorrow?
And if you can answer those three questions,
you're moving forward.
You know,
you're kind of with your team,
um,
individually,
it doesn't really matter,
but I think it's,
it's just a nice way to unpack a day,
um,
and keep the momentum moving forward rather than dwelling on what hasn't gone
well in the past or,
or whatever that may be.
And then,
you know,
next day,
what to expect and what you're going to be working on and,
and keeping that relatively simple.
It sounds really simple,
but it helps me.
It's brilliant.
I love it.
Celebrating first,
what you did well,
and then a bit of reflection and then celebrate first.
It's,
it's a,
I love the simplest,
uh,
things are often the,
the,
the best.
It's,
um,
you know,
something that everyone can relate to that.
It's brilliant.
We see collaboration as a really,
um,
sought after trait for leaders now.
They're really conscious about how they collaborate,
who they collaborate with.
Uh,
what does that mean to you collaborating?
Um,
I think at the moment it's,
you know,
really in line with,
in business,
um,
in working out ways,
obviously to,
um,
and,
and choosing.
Um,
I think I was pretty open to collaboration at first,
but then realizing that not all collaborations go very well,
but,
and,
and really picking and choosing who,
who we align with and collaborate with.
And that's both businesses,
body ice and,
and zone,
but,
but also individually in,
in partnerships,
you know,
that,
that I like to support.
I think,
um,
you collaborate with like-minded or aligned businesses or people,
you know,
that are going to put in,
that are going to put in as much effort in that collaboration for you to get to the next kind of phase of your business or the next stage or have a successful campaign or have a successful launch or whatever that is,
um,
in that sense.
Um,
but also in idea sharing.
And I think that's,
that's kind of really important where,
you know,
especially for,
for me and my remote team,
sometimes we get a bit slack in,
but we try to do on a,
you know,
at least a fortnightly basis is to just check in with each other.
And an idea share and brainstorm and,
and make sure that we have all the ideas on the table before we make some decisions,
um,
about which way,
you know,
the business is going,
which way the campaign's going,
which way the launch is going,
whatever it might be.
So,
so yeah,
collaboration is about idea sharing,
you know,
and eliminating,
those kind of maybe nice to have ideas,
but what ideas are actually going to move the needle?
What the ideas are actually going to increase engagement or increase,
be sales or increase,
you know,
our follower base or whatever it might be that we're,
discussing,
um,
at the time.
But,
um,
yeah,
so it's collaborating is,
is designed to bring idea together so that you can then collectively be better.
Isn't it?
So it's,
it's,
um,
pretty good,
pretty good description.
Yeah.
And that's a good place to start and end,
isn't it?
With it,
not all collaborations,
it's successful,
but yeah,
if you're,
um,
as you said,
bringing together the sum of all parts to get a better outcome,
worthwhile thing to pursue.
Listening too.
Um,
we see great outcomes.
Making sure that you are listening,
taking in and giving,
listening and sharing.
Lydia,
you've been asking these two questions,
uh,
to everyone I've sat down with,
who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Hmm.
It's tricky.
I don't know if I've had,
I have an answer for that one.
I'm really,
really sorry,
but,
um,
me,
does that sound stupid?
But I,
I've had people,
you know,
that have been great,
to give me advice and,
um,
to call on and to lean on,
you know,
and across many different industries.
Um,
but ultimately they've given me the information that I've needed to make
decisions for myself or for,
for business or for the direction that I wanted to go.
Um,
so I don't,
I don't know if that's,
it's brilliant,
Lydia.
I love it.
Probably not the standard answer that you wanted,
but I can't put it on one person because there's been so many people that have
inspired me.
Um,
whether they're young or old,
one of my biggest inspirations is a,
is a dear chap called Jeffrey Henke,
who is,
uh,
90,
probably four at the moment.
And it's just stepping down as the chairman of the Olympic winter Institute after all
these years and has helped,
you know,
so many athletes in Australia and,
and helped me,
you know,
um,
and help get these,
you know,
Australian facilities off the ground.
And with that,
he's,
you know,
just dogged determination,
like a little bull terrier and his relationships.
He's taught me how to nurture and massage relationships and never give up,
you know,
and,
and at 94 years of,
of age,
you know,
and so he's been instrumental in,
in,
in a lot of,
in a lot of ways there,
but there's been a lot of people,
um,
that then give me the inspiration to,
to live my life in,
in,
in maybe take steel parts of them and put it in my life.
I love it.
That sense of self for you is,
you know,
an authentic thing,
isn't it?
That you,
you,
you're working with people,
but the idea that you can do it yourself.
I love it.
I love that answer.
It's a,
it's a fan.
And,
you know,
listening and reading and preparing for your story.
I'm not surprised you said it because it,
it,
you look back and think you had this very few people have that sense of belief and a
young age and an idea of what they're going to do and then go about doing it.
So,
um,
nah,
it's brilliant.
Um,
final question in the spirit of collaboration,
which we,
we love the idea of collaboration,
which,
um,
may or may not resonate with you,
but if you could collaborate with anyone on any of your,
your many passions,
is there anyone that springs to mind?
Um,
gosh,
I've been isolated in Lapland for so long,
um,
that,
you know,
I haven't been around a lot of people in a,
in a while.
Um,
it's,
it's comes back to,
I mean,
yeah,
there are many projects that there's,
there are many projects that I still are undone for me that I'd like to do.
Um,
I'd love to,
um,
collaborate a lot more with,
I mean,
doing podcasts,
information sharing and things like that.
If I had the time,
there are certain individuals that I probably,
I'm not going to name,
I'm not going to put them on the spot that I'd love to get together and bounce
these ideas.
and,
um,
and some of them are TV personality.
Some of them are,
you know,
like high functioning CEOs and just superstars in,
in,
in what they do in business.
And,
you know,
others are athletes that in a way I'd love to get this cast together and,
and talk to them.
Talk about how we manage day to day life and collaboration and how we lead and
how,
how everyone else breaks down the process of achieving success in,
in,
in a public way.
I think,
um,
that would be awesome to do.
I've always wanted to do it,
but in the same time,
be able to give back through whether that's helping athletes or,
or,
you know,
certain charities and things like that.
So collectively getting these people together to inspire,
to bring out storytelling,
because I think stories,
everyone's got an awesome story,
like,
and that's what inspires people.
It's not,
you know,
the end game and what they've actually achieved,
but it's how,
how they got there.
And there's many ways to skin a cat and it's un,
unfleshing and unpacking those,
fleshing out those stories is what I love,
um,
to do and finding out how,
how people,
other people tick.
Cause you know,
you can kind of get in your own head and sometimes think your ways is the,
what everyone else kind of thinks,
but it's not,
it's not.
And so,
yeah,
I probably,
it,
it almost looks like a TV or maybe a podcast of bringing these people together
and,
um,
and just discovering,
you know,
what,
how they remain motivated and how they inspire and how they lead and,
and,
um,
how they kind of break down these overwhelming tasks,
seemingly overwhelming tasks into these bite size,
manageable,
uh,
pieces.
That'd be cool.
It's a great segue Lydia,
because,
uh,
I may have exactly the thing for you because this podcast,
to be honest,
has been based on a business we started seven years ago called Aleda,
A-L-E-D-A.
And we,
we,
one of the signature things we do is actually bring together exactly like what
you were talking about,
Lydia,
someone like you with your background with someone from the commercial world
or someone from the arts and that idea that different thinking,
and that some of that thinking in these collaborative leadership podcasts,
and now that world,
I can be talking to you in Lapland today.
And,
uh,
you know,
you can have that conversation,
as we said,
you know,
when you're back home in Lawn.
And so the world has shrunk post the,
uh,
COVID and we now understand that that's the possibility is there.
And so we've been really fortunate.
You know,
we see in some of our groups,
we've got,
you know,
uh,
as high profile as Mikel Arteta,
the coach of Arsenal collaborating with Matt Lafleur,
the coach of the Green Bay Packers,
or,
you know,
someone running a small business that wants to learn from,
an athlete in a different sport or someone at college in,
in,
in America who's connecting.
So the idea of bringing to people to get exactly,
as you said,
for that sharing,
contributing back into the,
into the world of what makes people tick and also learning from different
people,
as you said,
doesn't really matter your background.
Everyone's got a great story and we feel like there's a real gap for when
people get together and share and,
and do exactly what you did today,
Lydia.
And I appreciate so many notes.
I've got books to read.
I've got inspirations at the end of the day.
And I love it.
I'm fascinated by,
uh,
you know,
been great to have met you a few times over the years,
but to go back and watch your story and taken by the courage and the bravery
and the sense of self.
And I love,
I love your,
your answer at the end,
you know,
the,
the greatest leader starts with ourselves,
isn't it?
And,
and you've had a great sense of that.
So thanks so much for your time.
It's been really,
uh,
enlightening and,
appreciate it.
Thanks so much for having me.
It's great to share and I love,
I love what you're doing.
It's,
it's quite,
yeah,
it's amazing.
I've loved it.
Thanks.
All right.
Thank you for your time.
Have a great day.
Bye.
Bye-bye.