This week's guest is Major General Simone Wilkie.
In sitting down with her, you immediately get a sense of her presence,
her leadership and her strength of character.
Having spent 35 years in the Army,
she was responsible for 1,500 soldiers in the combat zone she worked in.
She is truly a trailblazing female leader.
I get to talk to her about leading in combat,
how she was awarded the Bronze Star for her work in Iraq,
the interesting and surprising synergy and crossover she talks about
between her leadership in Army and corporate life.
And you'll hear a lot about her passion for accountability,
stepping up and acknowledging that the Army itself makes mistakes
and taking accountability in life in general.
It's always a great privilege for me to learn from incredible leaders
like Major General Simone Wilkie.
It's the basis for the work that we do in our leadership business, Alita.
And if you're interested in learning, leading and collaborating,
check out our signature Alita Connect,
you can head to alitacollective.com.
Major General Simone Wilkie AM spent 35 years serving her country,
breaking new ground for female leadership within the ranks of the Australian Army,
including becoming the first female commanding officer
of the Royal Military College, Duntroon,
and the first female commandant at the Army Recruiting Training Centre at Kapuka.
Her post-military leadership portfolio is extensive.
Professor of Defence Technology at Deakin University,
Director of the Australian American Leadership,
Dialogue, AFL Sports Ready, the Beaufort Group,
and she still serves as a Commissioner on the Australian Football League.
Major General Simone Wilkie, it's a great pleasure to spend some time with you today.
Thank you.
Nice to see you, Luke.
Can I start back in 1983?
You joined the Australian Army, and at that stage,
it was the Royal Women Officer Cadet School.
Men and women didn't train together at that same stage.
And looking back 35 years later,
you become the most senior role in the Australian,
Australian Army.
Could you have even dreamt at the start that you'd end up there?
Oh, absolutely not.
I actually joined the Army on a bit of a whim.
Sometimes people ask me, why did you join?
And it was actually more to do with one of my friends who wanted to join,
and we went down to the recruiting unit,
and she didn't like it because it was too physical.
And I was at school trying to work out what I wanted to do,
and I was too young to join at the time.
So I went off and did, started a phys ed degree.
So for a start, I thought I was going to be a teacher,
and then I joined the Army a year later,
and to be honest, I was pretty hopeless as a cadet.
I was often in trouble, and after about four months,
I decided that this is not what I want to do,
and I'd gone back to my university, and they said,
oh, you can come back second semester,
and I thought, giddy up, here we go, this will be terrific.
And I didn't bother to tell my parents about that,
and so the Army rang them up and said, oh, you know,
Simone wants to leave, and my father,
my father said, and, you know, sorry, they said to him,
look, we can send her back to Ballarat, or she can stay here,
to which my father said, put that application in the round file,
she'll like it eventually, which is short for,
well, we don't want her back.
So, you know, it wasn't a particularly auspicious start,
and I didn't particularly like it for the first year or so,
and then before I knew it, the decades were disappearing,
and I was finishing up as 35 years later.
Yeah, so.
So, it was a pretty interesting journey.
The resilience to get through that, you know, it would have been,
you know, in the Army, it's a pretty brutal environment,
and the training, and you hear a lot about how tough that was.
Was that part of it at the start?
You thought, this is too much, not for me?
I think it was more around the discipline aspects,
and because I hadn't really thought through why I wanted to join the Army,
so that was part of the naivety element.
But then I realised, you know, it's a bunch of the things
that I really like.
I mean, you talked about the sports industry,
so you're a part of a team, you're learning about yourself,
you get to, you know, in those respects,
you get to live in different places and get to know people
and get to lead teams.
So, eventually I saw the light, and my father was quite right.
I was actually better off to be in the Army at the time
than being a teacher, even though I sort of ended up
doing a lot of education and training.
Well, it's an extraordinary leadership story
when you think of the many glass ceilings that you broke through
in that male-dominated environment of the Army.
When you look back now, what are the unique leadership skills, Simone,
that have allowed you to achieve what you have?
Yeah, that's a good question,
because I think leadership's about influencing people
and setting the environment for people to succeed.
Many of those things are the same.
Actually, they're very similar in the AFL and the Army.
You know, set the direction, set the expectations
and set the environment for people to learn.
I think the military is a bit like a couple of other industries.
Anywhere where you're taking lives or saving lives,
it's all about trust and respect and relationships.
So, I think those things are certainly drilled into you
as part of your leadership and development training.
And the military certainly invests a lot in people and individuals,
making sure you understand where you are as part of that team
and how you can lead.
So, as a woman,
I was reading an article on the weekend
where I can't remember the name of the lady,
but she was basically saying she really enjoyed the opportunity
to be the only woman in the room.
So, if you get to be self-confident enough
that you can use that opportunity,
then you should be using it for good.
And clearly, you have.
And I want to come back to your crossover post-military
and into the corporate world and where that synergy lies,
because I'm sure there is an incredible crossover
and clearly the roles that you're doing now,
provide that.
But we've seen this sort of shift
in what we think is a change in leadership, Simone,
in the spaces, started a business in leadership.
We work in education and sport and arts and social venture.
And we see leaders now are much more self-reflective,
much more collaborative, self-aware.
They are really conscious of the impact they have on others
and away a bit from command and control.
Is that possible in military leadership,
given the life and death situation,
or is it all about command and control?
I think that's the perception.
I think that's the perception from outside of the military.
And in fact, sometimes I think people's views
are based on those bad Hollywood B-grade movies.
And it's, look, there are times in which it is about command and control,
but most of the time it's not.
So it is setting that environment
for people to actually understand what we're doing.
So, you know, set the purpose.
If you align everyone to the purpose
and they understand their role in it
and you've empowered them to do things differently,
because much like when the whistle blows on the ground,
you can have whatever wonderful plan you had at the beginning
and it changes.
In the military, it's exactly the same as that.
So you've got to have enabled people to do what's required
and then to be able to pivot,
depending on what the circumstances are.
So that's why I talk around the fact that they invest a lot of time
teaching people about teamwork and leadership.
And I think one of the things I saw probably change
in the 2000s,
there was a big push on changing people
from being selfish to selfless.
So in the military, it's a values-based leadership system.
And so you need to make sure that people
who are coming into your organisation
are aligned with your values.
I think over time, there was a widening gap
between what the military's value system was
and what people were coming from society.
So how they've been socialised at home,
at school, with their friends,
all of those sort of things.
So you then invest more time in making sure
that they understand this is what's required.
So you live up to our values,
you don't live down to the rules.
And I think if you focus on a rules-based environment,
which sort of hits that command and control view,
you won't be successful in the long run.
That's a fascinating insight and conversation, Simone.
The values at the core,
and as you said, I mean,
society's always evolving and changing.
And I think every generation feels as though
that's happened more rapidly than the one before.
It may or may not be the case.
But I mean, even organisations,
as regimented as the military,
have to adapt to the generations that are coming through.
Otherwise, you can't be successful.
So for you, the key is then understanding
the demographics of people, young people coming in,
and then say, hey, these are the values you need to align.
Is that, and that's the core of success for you in some ways?
Oh, absolutely.
And in fact, if you,
if you just went down to the recruiting station,
it'd be different.
It's a lot different than it was when I went,
you know, way back in the dark ages,
you know, before we had electricity and everything in 1983,
because people have changed.
And, you know, that sort of ticks on that expectation.
People, what are people's expectations?
How resilient are they?
What do you need to do to provide them that opportunity
to be their best self?
And, you know, much like sport, it's about collective success.
It's not about individual success.
So making sure that they know where they fit in there.
And I think we probably spend a lot more time
sitting down with people in a more nurturing environment
than probably we had in the 80s.
Yeah, which is in keeping, we think,
with what's happening in other areas of sport,
a much more nurturing environment in sport
than the dark ages when I started playing as well.
So I wasn't necessarily going to go there,
but my mind is going,
it feels like the Army's had a bad PR run in recent times.
And there's been some high profile cases.
And I'm sure you won't want to comment on individuals
for obvious reasons.
But when you have Victoria Cross winners
and coming back post these, you know,
extended theatres of war,
and now we've got vision and video
and more so than ever in the past
and overlaying, I suppose, a complex environment
and what we think society's values are
onto those environments.
Is that a challenge for senior leadership
in military as well to say those environments are complex
and what we need to do?
Yeah, I think it's a challenge.
I think it's a challenge.
What does good leadership look like?
And do we cross the line sometimes
and get that wrong in battle as well?
Well, look, we're all in, we all make mistakes.
And I think the sooner you step up and accept
and acknowledge your mistake, the better it is.
And we've seen that in many different organisations.
You know, that sort of bad news only gets worse,
particularly if you hide it in the back cupboard.
What you see playing out in large organisations
like the military is accountability.
And it's public.
It's public accountability.
And we absolutely should be demanding organisations
to step up to the plate when things have gone wrong.
So over the times we've had, you know,
things like the defence abuse response,
there's been any number of poor behaviour, misconduct.
You can put as many rules and policies in place that you like,
but unfortunately people will still do the wrong thing.
A simple analogy would be I'd probably, you know,
bet my coffee here.
Luke, that you've probably put your speedometer
on more than 100 deliberately knowing that,
oh, maybe I can do 102 or 103.
I'll get there a little bit faster.
Did you see that email that just came through?
You've got a sixth sense.
But that's you knowingly stepping over the rules
because you think that rule's okay.
But if something really went wrong,
you have to own the fact that that went wrong.
Yeah.
So from a strategic leadership position,
sure, everyone looks at the reputational risks
and all of the different risks that come into that.
And, you know, it does surprise me that many of people
that I know around the country who haven't had a military background
have a different view than I do.
If something happens on a battlefield and it's clearly murder,
that they think that's acceptable and, you know,
that's certainly not the way to do it.
But I think that's the viewpoint or the lens
that I look at those things from.
Coming back to values again and, you know,
we're sitting here at AFL House.
I want to talk to you about being an AFL Commissioner
and the same thing.
Young people make mistakes.
Older people make mistakes.
And what you're saying is the accountability part of it,
getting that next part right is an opportunity for great leadership.
Is that what you're saying?
And no matter what it is, whether in a military sense
or an AFL player making a mistake.
Absolutely.
So, you know, fess up.
Talk the truth to power.
Have the personal freedom.
The fortitude and the confidence to own it.
I mean, let's face it, we're all crap at some things
and that's part of how you learn.
It's part of how you become more resilient.
Wouldn't it be wonderful, like, you know,
if we could just unzip our skulls, pour in everybody else's lessons,
zip it back up and we'd all, you know, work together marvellously.
But that's not reality.
So I think that's why it's important to just own it if you've got it wrong.
And it's hard.
Sometimes it's really hard.
Yeah.
We want the advantages and the opportunities without the mistakes sometimes
because that is the painful part.
So sitting across from someone whose life has been in leadership,
what does great leadership look and sound like to you?
Look, I think a good leader is someone who can influence people to do things
for the better of others or for the organisation,
regardless of what those circumstances are.
So, you know, if you set the direction,
then a good leader will set the course.
What does good look like?
This is how we're going to get there.
Acknowledging that that's not going to be what everybody wants.
I think it was Colin Powell who said, you know,
sometimes during leadership decisions you piss people off.
And that's true because, you know,
a good leader can make those hard decisions,
adjust when the circumstances change,
has the agility to bring people along with them.
And then, you know,
set the expectations.
So this is what I want from you, Luke.
These are the, let's work together on the priorities.
If you don't have those sort of expectations outlined,
well, what will happen?
You'll end up with problems in dissent
because my expectation of what we're here to do
could be quite different to yours.
So in the absence of that sort of expectations,
I think you can, you know,
there's a bit of a balance probably
between the empowerment and art of delegation.
Yeah.
And giving people a clear sense of where they're going.
And then the final bit for a leader
is to provide the environment for everyone
to have a good crack at it,
have a fair go and meet the requirements.
Well, it's fascinating to me talking military leadership
because there's thousands of you.
You go back to the Roman army
and this has been fine-tuned, you know,
and thought about probably the oldest form of leadership
in some ways and then refined all the way.
And I think that's something that we've got to go through
to the way we train leaders in the military now,
which again, I want to talk to you about.
I just wanted to pivot a little bit
and ask you the question.
35 years you work in the army serving your country
and effectively your role, Simone,
is to do what the government of the time wishes
and that is without question.
Can I ask you this question?
If you look back, us in the West,
invading places like Afghanistan and Iraq,
does that on reflection to you
feel like it was a positive outcome?
Was that successful?
Was that a good thing to do?
Well, I'll just pull you up on the invading part
because in many cases when Australians go to war
or Australians go to other places
and it's not just war, you know,
we do a lot of humanitarian assistance.
It's because the country there has invited us to do it
or we've gone with the United Nations.
So, you know, the very first time I deployed from Australia
was to go to Cambodia in the early 90s
and that was to help set up the opportunity
for Cambodians to have an election.
So there's, you know, the reason and how you get there,
absolutely, you know, it's different.
That was on the back of the Pol Pot regime
where millions of Cambodians were murdered
in one of the most horrific human atrocities.
So, yeah, we all, yeah, get that context.
Is Iraq and Afghanistan slightly different, I mean, in your mind?
Is that...?
Yeah, well, the reasons for going there were different
and, you know, it's...
It's awful to see how other countries,
what they've gone through and what their people have gone through
and, you know, you'll find a lot of military people have joined
because they want to help other people.
Yeah.
So you arrive.
And it's also, you know, it goes back to that Hollywood version
of being in the military.
People think it's, you know, about taking lives.
It's actually not about that.
There's a small proportion of highly professional, you know,
like the infantry elements and the, I suppose,
you know, the vernacular would be the war components,
but there's a really large part of the military
that's actually not there for that purpose.
So it would be wonderful if we could all play together
in the sandpit nicely, but unfortunately that's not always the case
and there's a review right now on what do we want our military
to look like going into the future, what are its roles and purposes
and there's lots and lots of different things that you can do.
You just need to...
Much like a footy team, make sure which one you're more focused on
at the time and certainly around the world right now,
there's lots of things even in our region where, you know,
we're providing assistance after tsunamis and cyclones
and all sorts of things.
Simone, you've been the key leader, as I mentioned,
in the introduction, you know, to Australian personnel
in combat zones in Afghanistan and, you know,
you awarded the Bronze Star for your work in supporting
what happened in Iraq.
What sort of leader are you?
What's it like in that environment?
How do you lead in the danger areas that you've been in?
Well, I'll tell you what, one of the people that I had the honour
and pleasure to work with was General Petraeus in Iraq.
So he was the commanding general and I was his deputy
and one of the things that I learnt and I took away from working
with him was that point I was talking about before on the truth to power
and reinforcing what your priorities are and why you're there
because the higher...
The higher up you go, in many organisations,
people don't deliberately filter the truth or their views.
There are some people who have their own set of genders
and through their lens can only see a part of the bigger picture.
So I think they might be providing the right advice.
And so the further up you get, you're getting all different advice.
If it's not accurate and you're making decisions
that affect people's lives, that is critical to make sure
that you're getting out to find out what's going on.
So General Petraeus would regularly go out into the battlefield
and talk to people and try and get those briefings
so that he'd make the best decision on the information that he was provided.
That, to me, is really good leadership in an organisation
which was scores of thousands of people from over 40 different countries.
So if you can imagine, each country's got a slightly different reason
for being there.
They've got different rules around how their people can work
inside that one organisation.
So being able to bring all of those things together,
that, to me, is really true leadership and he was very good at it.
I think it helped also that he had a – I'm sure he must have had
a photographic memory because he never missed a trick or a detail.
It's fascinating.
My mind, as you're talking, was going – Brian McNamee,
I had the pleasure of sitting down in this context,
who was the legendary CEO.
He was the CEO of CSL, which grew from a really small government agency
here into one of Australia's great success stories,
40,000, 50,000 people internationally.
And he spoke about really having a clear diary
and he just walked the floor of that organisation
and randomly want to talk to people no matter what level they were.
And it's probably a bit of truth-seeking as well to find out
at the coalface what was going on in leadership.
You've transitioned from an incredible success story in leadership.
You worked for Boston Consulting.
You're sitting here at the AFL as an AFL commissioner.
Have you been able to – what's the synergy for you in military leadership
and your work that you're doing in other areas?
If I was to just leverage off that point you were talking about
with walking the floor, I totally agree with that
because it is your opportunity to see what the issues are.
So when I first joined the commission, that was one of the things
that I'd like to do pre-COVID was to go and visit the clubs,
find out what the club issues are, look at their training
and administration.
And I think that's a really good thing.
The administration systems, how can you sit on the board
if you don't understand everything that comes up within the AFL industry?
And I would describe it as a complex ecosystem.
There's lots of different things that go into AFL.
So that's important.
Going to games like I did on the weekend, standing on the sidelines,
talking to people, that's how you get a real feel
for what's happening in the organisation.
That's not to say that you'll understand everything.
It's impossible to understand every single aspect
and that goes back to that important element of delegating
and empowering people to make decisions
because it's what happens when you're not there that matters, isn't it?
I mean, you're talking about leadership.
So if you've provided the opportunity for people to make the right calls,
then you'll be successful.
And there's different models even inside the AFL
on the way that clubs do it.
And part of what we've been talking around really is culture
and the culture of those organisations.
There's a hell of a lot of similarities between an army unit
and an AFL football club.
In specific detail.
I mean, I think sometimes the emotion of the game
that I grew up loving and playing and we see that all the time
and I've marvelled at the volunteer aspect we get in our industry.
People like you come and donate your time.
With all the experience and you look at boards of AFL clubs,
some of the most respected people on the leash,
but then AFL has this emotional attachment to it and win-loss
and then suddenly, you know,
we perhaps lose our decision-making capability.
You might have seen that, Simone.
You're an Essendon supporter.
You grew up in Ballarat.
So they've had some challenges in recent time.
And is that unique to sport, do you think,
that the emotions sometimes override good decision-making?
No, look, it's a sine wave, isn't it?
There's ups and downs.
And many organisations sort of blow up for a period of time
and then come back and, you know,
that then goes to the culture and the identity of the organisation.
I think there's a real passion for sport in Australia
and some people nearly even define their week
by how well they've gone.
Probably not quite as bad as New Zealand.
You know, if the All Blacks are winning, the economy's in good shape
and if it's down the other side, it's down the toilet.
Yeah.
I think it's great that people can really relate to their football
and it's that community aspect that is so important.
I saw that after the bushfires in particular.
So, you know, we had lots of people donating money
that the AFL then has used around the clubs that, you know,
have been affected by the bushfires, none more so than down at Kangaroo Island.
And that club sort of right in the middle of the island
totally destroyed that.
It was the hub for that community, for netball and footy
and those are the things that I think help people come along
and want to volunteer and be involved, be part of the club,
be part of something that's bigger than themselves
and you've got to learn to accept the wins and the losses.
Loss is always hard but that's part of life, isn't it?
It's a bit like that resilience aspect we were talking about before.
That's what we love about going back to your community.
You know, I love, you know, four kids.
You're all involved in sport and footy
and you get to see the community aspect.
When it's done really well and the leadership's great around junior sport
and I know that part of the world, Kangaroo Island, to have that devastated,
that is the pulse and, you know, often that's the happy place for people,
you know, with the challenges that I've got in life.
And so, you know, again, it's the importance, isn't it,
of having that great community leadership and seeing that pass down
and, you know, even as complex an organisation as the AFL,
it does filter all the way back down to a small club on Kangaroo Island, doesn't it?
The senior leadership of the community.
You set the tone, really, don't you, for community sport right around the country?
Yeah, and you'll see that we've recently invested a lot more money
and we've now carved out a percentage so that we can continue to ensure
that everyone gets an opportunity to play or be involved.
Without community football, there is no talent pathway.
I really like our programs like Auskick.
You know, my godson's six years old and, you know,
we're trying to convince him that Aussie rules is,
you know, the way to go, but happy for him to play any and every sport.
But if I look at the different programs that are available,
it's a terrific system, but it relies a lot on volunteers.
So the AFL's doing a lot of things also to try and make it easier
for people to volunteer and be involved in those clubs.
And if I look back at, you know, even when I've played a bit of football myself
and I went to the Trailblazers,
I went to the Trailblazers event the other day for women
just before the Essendon-Hawthorne game,
to see the women there who set up a league here in Victoria in 1979.
I mean, it wasn't even cool to say as a woman that you played footy.
They're people volunteering their time and effort
to provide an opportunity for someone else to come along and have a go.
And that's fantastic.
And you've been a great champion along with the commission
of really blazing the path for AFLW
and we're into sports.
Season seven and backing up seasons, you know,
it has really, I think, led the way for Australian sport
and the traction and the horsepower of the AFL industry
is just brilliant to see it behind the women's game.
It must make you feel really proud of that contribution
to see how well it's evolved.
Yeah, look, I think the opportunity that I've had to help there
is based quite a bit on what's happened in my time in the military.
So, you know, good policy for women's good policy for all.
And we started,
you know, adopting that in the army in the 90s, you know,
and we were one of the first organisations to turn around
and say it didn't matter what your sexuality was.
You know, that was big news back in the mid-90s.
So to come into the AFL and to help establish not only the league
but opportunities for women more broadly,
and I think there's lots of different threads that have come out
from having the women's league, we've now got, you know,
things like the coach.
We've now got the coach accelerator program.
We now have three female coaches amongst 18 teams.
Those are the sort of programs that I think we need to continue to invest in
so that women have the opportunity to do any role in the AFL.
And that's a bit like what we had in the military when we turned around
and said women can do any operational role.
That was the turning point.
And I think AFLW has really helped to provide a more inclusive organisation.
And one that will respect the fact that women can be coach of the men's team.
Women can be CEO of AFL.
There's all sorts of things.
But over time, you need to put in things like gender action plans,
have a strategy like we put out with the 2030 vision.
So I've really enjoyed being given the opportunity to help steer that ship a bit
and get more women out there involved right from the grassroots level.
And, you know, things like...
The Mainsley Football Club, I'm not sure if you saw that recently.
That's one of the clubs from where I am in Canberra have just basically turned around
and said they're going to pay the same amount for all their players regardless of their gender.
That's sort of where we're heading towards.
I want to get to some dimensions of leadership.
But reading about you in preparations for this,
they tell me that your sense of humour in leadership is a big part of you.
You don't often think of that in the military.
But why is humour so important for you in your leadership?
I think, well, you've got to be careful because what I think might be funny,
you might be offended by.
And that's probably part of the way that I was brought up.
And I think it's a good leveller if people can feel more comfortable in their environment.
Part of it sort of goes to allowing people to say what they think.
You know, I grew up with red hair and, you know,
I think redheads sometimes get a bit misaligned, Luke.
You know, it's a bit hard.
Being a redhead, so you're either sort of, you know,
the Simone Wilkie thesis on that is you're either, you know,
an extrovert or an introvert.
Well, I'm way over left on the extrovert part.
And you know what?
Part of humour is storytelling.
And good leaders can tell stories.
People remember the stuff at the end.
You don't want to sit there and give a huge soliloquy and at the end people going,
well, what were the key points?
You know, sort of turn up, be bold, be good, be gone.
You know, those sort of things.
And I think humour helps in many cases.
Well, I like it when we sat down and I said, you know,
Simone, I asked you some questions.
I don't think there'll be any challenges with it.
And you said to me, I think I can get you from across the table.
I think that was humour.
I'm not sure.
It was, it certainly put me back in my place pretty quickly.
We, and I say we, passionate about leadership, Simone,
in all environments and shapes and size,
we're seeing there are some key patterns.
We think our dimensions of great leadership.
I want to ask you about them.
So please expand.
Starting with self-leadership, that term to us,
we think you can't be a great leader without a sense of self-leadership.
Does that resonate with you?
Absolutely.
I think there's four key things you need to know as a leader.
And the first one is yourself.
Who you are, how you make decisions,
how you deal with pressure and criticism and all those sort of things
so that you can try to be better.
You know, they always say that,
you could say criticism or feedback's a gift.
Well, it is if you learn how to take it properly.
And, you know, some people are not too good at that.
And if you identify that yourself, then you can continue to improve.
So it's a continuous improvement loop.
Yeah.
You need to know your people.
And that's so linked to knowing yourself.
I think the more people understand, I'm a bit fascinated by psychology.
I didn't, I've only done a couple of psychology units,
um, during my time in education,
but much of the army is all about people.
And so the more you understand, um, how they react and why they react
and that cultural aspects and the values bit and behaviours
that we were talking about before,
the more successful you'll be as a leader.
Um, the third thing you need to know is your job, right?
You can't be a professional if you don't know all aspects of your job.
And the fourth bit's, um, you know, it's a bit sun suey.
You were talking about, um, you know, military history before.
You need to know your enemy.
So in an AFL, um, view, that's what team are we going to play?
Where's their best players?
You know, do we need to put like a Crowley tag on this person?
How are we going to deal with this?
How are we going to adapt and whatever?
So the more you know the other people, you know, and of course,
if I say that at home, it's not, the enemy isn't your parents,
but you might think that, you know, as you're growing up,
um, you know, you're going to have to, you know,
you're going to have to, you know, you're going to have to,
you know, you're going to have to, you know, you're going to have to,
the more you understand, um, how they do their business,
the better leader you will be.
It's a brilliant, uh, answer and it leads to a lot more thinking.
And I, and that's why I love the, the crossover and, you know,
sometimes in football, we used to think it's, uh,
almost a little bit, um, naive to, to, to, you know,
think about being in a war zone.
But I think in terms of knowing your people,
it's been a much more sophisticated environment AFL.
You're getting 40 or 50 people from incredibly diverse backgrounds,
and remote indigenous communities, and private schools,
and all sorts of different, um, situations.
I think that has come a long way now in coaching the individual
and the care for the individual as a whole person.
And is that something that you've seen evolve in,
in the other leadership spaces you're in as well?
Absolutely.
Because that's how you make that team.
Yeah.
That's how you get all of those different people
merging together for the same purpose.
Um, and, you know, if I go back to the army,
when I was running recruit training,
and when I was running officer training,
all those people came from every different part of Australia,
just like a football team does.
So if you know that they have all those different experiences and backgrounds,
you have to provide an opportunity for each and every one of them to shine.
And you know that they're all different.
I think one of the areas, you know,
Australian as a nation sort of, um, moving to,
is accepting and celebrating difference.
You know, it sort of goes to the tenets of inclusion,
but we've, we are much better at that, in my view,
than we used to be, where we'd put people in categories
and we'd just leave them in those categories,
rather than helping them to shine and, and, um, become part of that team.
A friend of mine, Scott Gaten, who did his PhD in high performance teams.
And when he, um, the essence of what he came down to,
there were about four or five values that high performance teams have.
And that's things like, um, courage, uh, integrity, persistence,
good judgment, and being a team worker.
Now, that was a review that he did, well, not a review,
that was his PhD, I should say.
It takes a long time to do a doctorate.
Um, they were the values that he saw in special forces and, and officer training.
Do they sort of sound familiar to you in a footy team?
Absolutely. Yeah.
And they sound familiar, Simone, in high performing environments everywhere to me.
I mean, those traits are really common.
Yeah. I mean, those traits are really common.
And with different applications, and I, I love what you said before,
because I generally believe this, not just inclusion for ticking a box,
but celebrating people for their differences.
Because it feels to me that smart organisations actually understand
that's where the genius is.
If we all look the same and sound the same and went to the same school,
you don't get the creative thinking, you don't get the acceleration, do you?
And the best organisations now are, are so much smarter at understanding
that's where the competitive advantage actually lays, isn't it, in lots of ways?
Oh, absolutely. And of course, it'd be boring if we're all the same.
Um, so, you know, provide that opportunity for people to be different.
And if I was to bring it back to our discussion before on AFLW, that was one of the principal
tenets that we did, um, when we were running the, so I chaired the advisory group, and-
Around bringing the competition forward, or, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, about establishing-
Yeah.
The competition, you know, because let's face it, we had to set it up in a pretty short
period of time.
There were lots of different factors to put in there.
And one of them was, well, let's celebrate that it's different.
Yeah.
Um, and women are, for a start, physiologically different to men.
Um, if it was that easy, remember Flo Jo?
You know, she was on the juice, and she still couldn't beat Carl Lewis, the fastest man
on earth.
So, let's acknowledge that there are, uh, physiological differences.
So, things like, um, the size of the ball is smaller.
Um.
Um, the quarters are shorter.
We have six in a team.
Part of that was for congestion.
Um, there were people who didn't want it to be different.
You know, because their view of women's football and its value is rooted in, um, what the men's
game looks like.
It has to be the same as men.
And it actually doesn't.
And let's make sure that we're setting it up for success.
Setting it up to be the best, um, of football.
And, um, you know, I think that, um, I think that there's a lot of, um, there's a lot of,
think that was one of the really good fundamental things that we did at the beginning and you can
see it through each year on on whatever themes coming out and that's helped people to um i think
grow to love aflw yeah brilliant and you set it up for success and for those of us coming on the
journey and having sisters and daughters now and you look back and think that the possibility that
pathway wasn't there is just ridiculous and you know but it does take leadership to set it up
right and um you know my mind's still you know casting to 20 years from now and think you know
when eight-year-old girls have a pathway that is is clearly underway you can imagine that we're
going to see something quite uh amazing as time goes you already are season seven of aflw has been
brilliant in a short time we see leaders uh simone very conscious about how they positively
impact others in their environment on a daily basis does that uh dimensional leadership ring
true to you yeah i mean part of that goes to respect
and um the trust environment that you've set up ultimately for organizations to be successful i
think it is all about trust and relationships um and sometimes it's also the networks that you
involve and even in the internal politics of how decisions are made and who makes them so
setting that um i suppose it comes back to the point i was making before on
environment that enables people to succeed
you've heard you talk a lot about in leadership in this conversation around
you know setting the path and having the uh the the vision really clear and if you don't how can
you expect people to come on board with you as you said sometimes quoting colin powell they're
not going to always be happy but creating and sharing your vision is a really key
trait we're seeing consistently how have you gone about doing that in in the environments you're in
um well that that is critical because the vision's
the end of the vision is the end of the vision and i think that's a really important thing to
sort of let me put another way you can have a vision but if you don't provide the resources
for that vision or you've actually produced as an illusion so a vision is a great thing to have
but you have to make sure that you've enabled people to get there and it has to be an achievable
vision that's why i like strategies so you know you set that vision and then you put the key
tenets or the pillars that you need to have for it then you actually need to go away and produce a
vision for how you're going to get there and sometimes that's where people don't quite get it
right so making sure that you've got the right structures that you've got the right resources
that you've got the right people in those roles and then being able to adapt them i always think
one of the hardest things you can do as a leader is actually to turn around to someone say you're
no longer part of our team and i'd call it i call it swimmers and non-swimmers
you get into the pool and there's people who can naturally swim and there's people who haven't
been taught to swim and then you can teach some of those people to swim and then there's people
who's still going to be floundering around in the bottom of the pool what would you do if those
people look well there's not a role for you is there eventually if you're not up to it so get
them out of the pool because it's not good for them and it's not good for everybody else but to
actually sit down with somebody and say we know you really want to be there and this is probably
one of the hardest decisions i ever made in the army was a young lady who was in recruit training
she so wanted to be there she'd always wanted to be a soldier if everyone was as committed as she was
would have been fantastic but she just couldn't do it and all the other girls were helping her
and eventually i had to say look i'm sorry but we're discharging you yeah you know that was
really difficult because that was a person who so wanted to be there
then you'll have some other people in your team who are just naturally gifted and
lazy you know and how do you then motivate those people um to give their best so that that sort of
comes back to those elements of you know how do you empower people knowing them how's the best way
to get them to be a good team member and and then the courage and leadership as you said some i'm
andrew bassett uh one of the co-founders of seek his brother paul's on the afl commission with you
seeks one of the most successful uh businesses in recruitment and so they have sophistication
around it but he went to that category and said that's specifically the hardest you've got someone
who's a good person who you really love in the organization but you work out they just aren't
up to the he said really that's that's really tough but you're not doing the right thing by
them or the organization if you don't identify that and share it and he said you know the
sometimes easier one is the person who is lazy and not going to do it because you can pretty clearly
make that uh make that call it's interesting to hear your you know personal experience with that
curiosity is a term we hear a lot simone with the leaders that we're working with and through
curiosity they are on that constant learning and improvement journey does that ring true with you
as well yeah well i mean if you're not curious and things will pass you by um or you'll miss
indicators so i think it is really an important thing part of that curiosity bits also your
analytical skills and your critical thinking skills
so you know can you identify patterns can you identify the opportunities going forward
can you identify who's not actually pulling um they're part of the bargain anymore and
you know in line with that that part you're talking about how do you respectfully
help them to work out there's a better way or respectfully help them find another opportunity
if you're not curious you're going to miss a lot of those things you can't sort of
chuck all the ingredients in throw it in the oven sit back and forget think you're going to
get a wonderful cake i mean i can't cook i'm looking forward to the days that uh technology
produces robots and i can just just put curtis stone's recipes in there and bingo beautiful meal
as you said not everyone can do everything so there's always um growth for all of us uh
communication with clarity i i suspect coming from your background you're really sophisticated
in how you communicate i mean i think of you and your role in iraq working with general petraeus
you've got countries from all over the world you've got countries from all over the world
with slightly different objectives i mean how have you gone about communicating with with clarity
um i think it's absolutely imperative requirement to be clear if i remember um would have been when
i was a brigadier and i was running training um in the army and i had five people um direct
reports to me and so i gave out simone's vision of what we're going to do and you know a bit of
an idea of when i wanted it done by and on one side of the world i was a brigadier and i was a
of the room i had got a boss great no problems and on the other side i had a fellow saying to me
no no i need more detail i want to know what you want when you want it by etc so you know like
really detailed approach and so i learned i learned from that which is some people
you really need to just provide an overview of what's what you want and other people you have
to clearly communicate to them exactly what it is that you're doing and i think that's a really
you want still providing the opportunity for them to put their own color and movement
on it their own shade of whatever they want it to look like um but if you haven't communicated
it properly in that gap people will make stuff up they'll do msu msu makes
it was uh um fair enough i mean john worstfold in this same conversation is that the same thing
you come out of a team meeting and you say hey you know we're
really going to strengthen our defense and and this is a real key tenant of the game plan that
i want to implement and he said you walk out and then you've got the defenders uh again this is
the best and and some of the forwards are going right you know he doesn't care about attacking
and and so you realize out of 42 people in a room how you you know nuance that conversation around
you know this is what we think's best for everyone and how we're going to perform together but
there's a skill to it isn't there because you can lose people unintentionally just by you know not
getting it right
yeah and that comes back to we see and hear things differently depending on how we've been
socialized and how we've been brought up or the environments in which we've lived in in the
military we spend a lot of time um teaching people what we call the rules of engagement
and so you will give orders and it's very clear on some so there's some things that there's no
room for interpretation on and then there are other aspects that totally are yeah i had the
great pleasure of
you know being uh gallipoli on the centenary of ansec the dawn service one of the most uh extraordinary
days i've ever been to see the sun come up over that peninsula famous peninsula of australian
history and you sit in the trenches and you look and you know 10 meters on the other part where
the turkish soldiers were literally you know you could long jump it felt like a cross and and you
know to have the whistle blown and you're going to run into that you know with a machine gun across
them and that that is is there room in do you look back on military history and that and think
you know what what choice did people have back then was that something that's evolved over time he
looked at that and just thought that was just tragic to see that up close i mean how much more
sophisticated is it now is there choice in those situations um so i think you're probably talking
about the neck were you at gallipoli you know and which you can't imagine until you're actually
standing there looking down at um or it's one of the most emotional things you've ever seen
15 16 year olds who are sitting in there literally
running into and then there was beauty in it too because you read the history and you think you
know eventually they blow a whistle and and both sides come out and you know exchange gifts clear
up the bodies and there was a you know even with the enemy there was a sense of respect and
camaraderie at that that incredible time as well so yeah it was a it was an experience you can't
forget but i i couldn't help but think i'm not sure if you blew the whistle i was going to go
i don't know whether you know that's a that's a reflection on me but it's
at some point you almost feel like someone had to say that's crazy yeah have you ever watched
blackadder yes so you know in the last series where they blow the whistle and they go over the
top and everything before that was you know sort of dark humor around yeah um being there and if
you go back to our history in those periods you know it was still queen and country so a lot of
people volunteered without truly understanding what it meant but there was this sense of we're
doing it for the right reasons yeah if you actually go to the other end of the neck and
you try and walk up that gully um it's it's even more horrific because the vegetation and and
everything that's there so and you've got this sort of tunnel vision towards the top i think one
of the um really interesting parts of of that campaign is at a turk and you probably saw what
he wrote after you know after that terrible period um of for his nation and he wrote
to the australian mothers didn't he and said your your your sons that are here and i'll get i'll
butcher this and get it wrong but we care for them like our own sons effectively or words to that
affair i mean you're not you know the hair stands on the back of your neck doesn't it to think that
that was and he you know really wanted to bring you know together understood the tragedy of it
all didn't he and understood the leadership going forward it's an amazing presence and sense of
history that he had wasn't it yeah absolutely yeah and he went on to lead his own country
and i think it's terrific that lots of australians want to actually go to gallipoli um if you get the
opportunity absolutely go there if you don't go to places like the australian war memorial in canberra
because it's not about glorifying war it's actually about those stories and
um you know getting back into helping other nations and helping people get through tragedy
and crisis and no but i can assure you this like um military people don't want to go to war
that that's the
worst case scenario you train for it but you'd much rather the politicians and the big decision
makers don't put people in harm's way and and that you can negotiate without having to go to war
the last dimension i want to ask you about was collaboration and maybe segwaying from attiturk
into as you just said you know the last resort is the opposite of collaboration isn't it how
important in leadership do you think collaboration is i think there's a whole policy words that are
really important like you know collaboration
celebration cooperation compromise even you know there's a whole swag of those words that sit in
there about how you meld people together and if you're not prepared to cooperate um then how are
you going to get to an outcome that everyone's or as many people as possible are happy if you're
not going to always end up with a solution that everybody's happy with but you know that's why
we talk about win-win some people are only focused on
win-loss win at all at all costs but the long-run implications of that you will get festering
problems so try and cooperate and collaborate together so that you get the best outcome
so final two questions uh simone it's been uh incredible privilege to sit down and and uh spend
this time with you and and so much uh to learn i and i have been along the way um but asking these
two questions of all the leaders have had the pleasure of sitting down with who's been the
greatest leader in the world and who's been the greatest leader in the world and who's been the
greatest leader in your life i haven't actually thought about that before and i wish i'd done my
reconnaissance so i knew what you what your questions were um probably marty studdart so he
was uh the commanding officer that i went to cambodia with and he was so good at aligning
everybody to the purpose and reason that we were there for in difficult circumstances an environment
in which we didn't really know that we were there for and so i'm going to ask you a question
that we were going into um and with different people coming into the organization on
on regular occurrences um and just a really decent good human being and that came to you
as just someone that had that effect i mean you've been around leadership all your life i suppose but
when you're someone in real time does it like that it really stands out for it
yeah absolutely it does um and making the hard calls um when people did the wrong thing and then
um getting people to appreciate where those boundaries are of what's acceptable and what's
not acceptable so that people um can then in their own minds do the right thing much like we're
talking about before you know what's happening when you're not around if you're a good leader
people are still doing the right things a brilliant answer um in the sense of collaboration we we're
fascinated by that if you could collaborate with anyone in the world on on anything and there's a
range of different interests that that you've got um and i think that's a really good answer
we mentioned some of them you work with boston console and you work here at the uh the afl on the
commission and um you know the beauford group and a range of different interests is there anyone that
you looked at so if i could collaborate with someone is there someone that springs to mind
no not really um i think working with lots of different people is the spice of life
so it comes back to the fact that i'm an extrovert and i like working with lots of individuals
lots of different people um so i haven't really sat down and thought maybe it's you
well that would be a great pleasure and a great privilege and i love the answer because you know
there's so much diversity in what you do and continue to do and uh you know blazed a path that
very few would have thought possible back in 1983 when you signed on it's fascinating to hear that
you know four months in you're nearly out and we wouldn't have uh you know had the incredible story
that uh has unfolded and uh you know again um it's been a great pleasure pleasure and a great
privilege thanks for your time today my pleasure empowering leaders was
by me luke darcy produced by matt dwyer with audio production by darcy thompson
start your leadership journey i encourage you to go to a leader collective.com
take our empowering leaders indicator tool and understand the impact you have
on your environment join us at a leader to learn lead and collaborate listener