This week's guest is Major General Simone Wilkie.
In sitting down with her, you immediately get a sense of her presence,
her leadership and her strength of character.
Having spent 35 years in the Army,
she was responsible for 1,500 soldiers in the combat zone she worked in.
She is truly a trailblazing female leader.
I get to talk to her about leading in combat,
how she was awarded the Bronze Star for her work in Iraq,
the interesting and surprising synergy and crossover she talks about
between her leadership in Army and corporate life.
And you'll hear a lot about her passion for accountability,
stepping up and acknowledging that the Army itself makes mistakes
and taking accountability in life in general.
It's always a great privilege for me to learn from incredible leaders
like Major General Simone Wilkie.
It's the basis for the work that we do in our leadership business, Alita.
And if you're interested in learning, leading and collaborating,
check out our signature Alita Connect,
you can head to alitacollective.com.
Major General Simone Wilkie AM spent 35 years serving her country,
breaking new ground for female leadership within the ranks of the Australian Army,
including becoming the first female commanding officer
of the Royal Military College, Duntroon,
and the first female commandant at the Army Recruiting Training Centre at Kapuka.
Her post-military leadership portfolio is extensive.
Professor of Defence Technology at Deakin University,
Director of the Australian American Leadership,
Dialogue, AFL Sports Ready, the Beaufort Group,
and she still serves as a Commissioner on the Australian Football League.
Major General Simone Wilkie, it's a great pleasure to spend some time with you today.
Thank you.
Nice to see you, Luke.
Can I start back in 1983?
You joined the Australian Army, and at that stage,
it was the Royal Women Officer Cadet School.
Men and women didn't train together at that same stage.
And looking back 35 years later,
you become the most senior role in the Australian,
Australian Army.
Could you have even dreamt at the start that you'd end up there?
Oh, absolutely not.
I actually joined the Army on a bit of a whim.
Sometimes people ask me, why did you join?
And it was actually more to do with one of my friends who wanted to join,
and we went down to the recruiting unit,
and she didn't like it because it was too physical.
And I was at school trying to work out what I wanted to do,
and I was too young to join at the time.
So I went off and did, started a phys ed degree.
So for a start, I thought I was going to be a teacher,
and then I joined the Army a year later,
and to be honest, I was pretty hopeless as a cadet.
I was often in trouble, and after about four months,
I decided that this is not what I want to do,
and I'd gone back to my university, and they said,
oh, you can come back second semester,
and I thought, giddy up, here we go, this will be terrific.
And I didn't bother to tell my parents about that,
and so the Army rang them up and said, oh, you know,
Simone wants to leave, and my father,
my father said, and, you know, sorry, they said to him,
look, we can send her back to Ballarat, or she can stay here,
to which my father said, put that application in the round file,
she'll like it eventually, which is short for,
well, we don't want her back.
So, you know, it wasn't a particularly auspicious start,
and I didn't particularly like it for the first year or so,
and then before I knew it, the decades were disappearing,
and I was finishing up as 35 years later.
Yeah, so.
So, it was a pretty interesting journey.
The resilience to get through that, you know, it would have been,
you know, in the Army, it's a pretty brutal environment,
and the training, and you hear a lot about how tough that was.
Was that part of it at the start?
You thought, this is too much, not for me?
I think it was more around the discipline aspects,
and because I hadn't really thought through why I wanted to join the Army,
so that was part of the naivety element.
But then I realised, you know, it's a bunch of the things
that I really like.
You talked about the sports industry, so you're a part of a team,
you're learning about yourself, you get to, you know, in those respects,
you get to live in different places and get to know people
and get to lead teams.
So, eventually I saw the light, and my father was quite right.
I was actually better off to be in the Army at the time than being a teacher,
even though I sort of ended up doing a lot of education and training.
Well, it's an extraordinary leadership story when you think
of the many glass ceilings that you broke through,
and that male-dominated environment of the Army.
When you look back now, what are the unique leadership skills, Simone,
that have allowed you to achieve what you have?
Yeah, that's a good question, because I think leadership's
about influencing people and setting the environment
for people to succeed.
Many of those things are the same.
Actually, they're very similar in the AFL and the Army.
You know, set the direction, set the expectations,
and set the environment for people to learn.
I think the military is a bit like a couple of other industries.
Anywhere where you're taking lives or saving lives,
it's all about trust and respect and relationships.
So, I think those things are certainly drilled into you
as part of your leadership and development training.
And the military certainly invests a lot in people and individuals,
making sure you understand where you are as part of that team
and how you can lead.
So, as a woman...
I was reading an article on the weekend where...
I can't remember the name of the lady, but she was basically saying
she really enjoyed the opportunity to be the only woman in the room.
So, if you get to be self-confident enough that you can use that opportunity,
then you should be using it for good.
And clearly, you have.
And I want to come back to your crossover post-military
and into the corporate world and where that synergy lies,
because I'm sure there is an incredible crossover
and clearly the roles that you're doing.
Now, provide that.
But we've seen this sort of shift in what we think is a change in leadership, Simone,
in the spaces, started a business in leadership.
We work in education and sport and arts and social venture.
And we see leaders now are much more self-reflective,
much more collaborative, self-aware.
They are really conscious of the impact they have on others
and away a bit from command and control.
Is that possible in military leadership, given the life and death situation,
or is it all about command and control?
I think that's the perception.
It's the perception from outside of the military.
And in fact, sometimes I think people's views are based on those bad Hollywood B-grade movies.
And it's, look, there are times in which it is about command and control,
but most of the time it's not.
So it is setting that environment for people to actually understand what we're doing.
So, you know, set the purpose.
If you align everyone to the purpose and they understand their role in it
and you've empowered them to do things differently,
because much like when the whistle blows on the ground,
you can have whatever wonderful plan you had at the beginning and it changes.
In the military, it's exactly the same as that.
So you've got to have enabled people to do what's required
and then to be able to pivot depending on what the circumstances are.
So that's why I talk around the fact that they invest a lot of time
teaching people about teamwork and leadership.
And I think one of the things I saw probably change,
in the 2000s, there was a big push on changing people from being selfish to selfless.
So in the military, it's a values-based leadership system.
And so you need to make sure that people who are coming into your organisation
are aligned with your values.
I think over time there was a widening gap between what the military's value system was
and what people were coming from society.
So how they've been socialised.
Socialised at home, at school, with their friends, all of those sort of things.
So you then invest more time in making sure that they understand this is what's required.
So you live up to our values.
You don't live down to the rules.
And I think if you focus on a rules-based environment,
which sort of hits that command and control view,
you won't be successful in the long run.
That's a fascinating insight and conversation, Simone, you know, the values.
And I think that also is at the core.
And, as you said, I mean society's always evolving and changing.
And I think every generation feels as though that's happened more rapidly than the one
before.
It may or may not be the case.
But I mean even organisations, as regimented as the military, have to adapt to the generations
that are coming through.
Otherwise you can't be successful.
So for you the key is then understanding the demographics of people, young people coming
in and then saying hey, these are the values you need to align with.
Is that – and that's the core of success for you in some ways?
Oh, absolutely.
in fact, if you went down to the recruiting station, it'd be different. It's a lot different
than it was when I went, you know, way back in the dark ages, you know, before we had electricity
and everything in 1983, because people have changed and, you know, that sort of ticks on
that expectation. People, what are people's expectations? How resilient are they? What do
you need to do to provide them that opportunity to be their best self? And, you know, much like
sport, it's about collective success. It's not about individual success. So making sure that
they know where they fit in there. And I think we probably spend a lot more time sitting down
with people in a more nurturing environment than probably we had in the 80s. Yeah, which is in
keeping with what's happening in other areas of sport, a much more nurturing environment of sport
than the dark ages when I started playing as well. So I wasn't necessarily going to go,
but my mind is going, it feels like the army's had a bad PR run in recent times. There's been
some high profile cases, and I'm sure you won't want to comment on individuals for obvious reasons,
but when you've Victoria Cross winners and coming back post these, you know, extended theatres of
war, and now we've got vision and video and more so than ever in the past and overlaying, I suppose,
a complex environment and what we think society's values are onto those environments. Is that a
challenge for senior?