How do you handle expectation and what can you do to use that expectation as a means to achieve
great success? G'day, it's Luke Darcy. The idea of self-improvement and leadership both on and
off the field has been a lifelong passion of mine. With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader
collective and have had the privilege of working with thousands of leaders in education, sport,
industry and the arts that have helped shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership
where everyone has a voice. In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders. In 2013,
Marcus Bontempelli was the number four pick in the AFL draft to a struggling Western Bulldog side.
At just 18 years of age, the Bont was hailed as a future star of the game and a pivotal figure for
the club. Three years later, with all the weight and expectation, Marcus Bontempelli and the Bulldog
stunned the AFL world by winning the 2016 premiership. So what did Marcus do along the way
to exceed those high expectations and what are the tangible actions he's now taking as the captain of
the Western Bulldogs to lead the club to further success? Bont, great to catch up with you. Thanks
for your time. Thanks, Darce. Good to be with you and talking. I hope you can fact check me at any
stage, mate. I think there's so much to talk about with you, but I wanted to start an old shared
teammate of ours, Bob.
Murphy described you when you arrived at the Witten Oval, and you may have heard this before as an
18-year-old, as football's equivalent of Jesus arriving in the West. Now, were you aware that
you were making such a big impact at such a young age? No, I wasn't. Bob always has a good way with
words, doesn't he? But that seemed to heap too much pressure on a young bloke at the beginning
of his career. But he obviously sensed or had been around long enough to know he'd seen something
different probably in me.
Yeah, it was a great time to be probably joining the football club where they're on the up. I was
quite lucky and fortunate to come into, I guess, a club with a rich history, really strong sort of
leaders that really probably gave me the freedom and the lack of expectation from the word go to
just explore my football and the curiosity side of things when it comes to trying to establish
yourself as a footballer, but find that confidence at the level.
Yeah, it does go pretty quickly to think that I've just finished my eighth season,
but I've been pretty fortunate to be where I am now and have some of the accomplishments that I have.
You seem to be a really natural leader as captain of the Bulldogs. What were you like as a kid,
Bob? Did you always see yourself in a leadership way?
Somewhat, I think. I always strive to probably be in leadership positions, but I reckon that
sort of, not the hunger or the want to be a leader probably changed as I got a little bit
older. I probably ended up in leadership positions just more as a result of my sort of actions and
behaviours and appetite to want to get the best out of myself as opposed to focusing on being a
good leader. It sort of shifted for me probably when I joined maybe the football club or just
before. I wasn't probably as focused on leadership, more focused on sort of how I was acting and
behaving and ultimately just sort of trying to be myself. So I had a few little leadership
positions as a teenager growing up. I was a little bit more of a, you know, a little bit more of a
So I've always liked being in that position, but it wasn't something I necessarily, you know,
craved from the word go or then even, you know, once I joined the football club.
Common thread, Bob, when I, you know, researched about you and having had some exposure over the
years that you've always been mature beyond your years. Can you explain that? Where does that come
from?
It's really probably hard to pin down where it started, maybe having, you know, three sisters
and them sort of wanting me to be a leader.
Either grow up or, you know, be a certain way. I just, yeah, I just, it's sort of the way I've
always been. Obviously, you know, your parents and your family have such a big and strong influence
on you as a kid growing up. It's really probably just the way that I was. I sometimes think people
maybe because I'm a bit, you know, more, you know, cruisy and low key by probably nature and
personality. People take that for mature. I don't carry on like probably some others or have the
same sort of exuberance energy, but it's probably the way I've always been.
It's probably just always the way that I've been is just happy to go wherever, do whatever and
just, you know, jump in line almost. Yeah.
Might pick up that thread because I know family is such an enormous part of who you are and,
you know, quite clearly with the three sisters, Alana, Olivia, Sienna and your mum, Geraldine,
your dad, Carlo, they had a huge influence clearly over you. But you particularly, I hear you
reference the girls' influence on your life. You've been an ambassador for a charity called
The Line, which is a national violence prevention campaign that aims to support young people to
understand what respectful relationships are. And I think that's a really important thing.
So can you talk about that influence of the girls in your life and why that's so important to you?
Yeah. I mean, we were so close as, you know, most families are, but particularly ours and the way
obviously I grew up and I was raised through them and obviously by mum and dad. I just think,
you know, you see, you know, older sisters, particularly what they do, how they act and
how they behave and obviously having a strong connection and influence, particularly in my
family to women. I probably, as I grew up, I grew up with a lot of women and I grew up with a lot of
women and I grew up and matured, felt more and more inclined and more and more, I guess,
empowered to try and support a greater message of, you know, obviously, as you mentioned,
The Line and the violence and just responsible relationships towards women in general. So
they're always there for me, always supportive. Obviously, you know, women have this sort of
caring sort of maternal nature to look after you and in being the only boy, they definitely
fostered that mentality or emphasis with me. And it definitely has, I guess,
rubbed off on me in terms of probably how I try and see things, how I try to treat people.
And yeah, their influence on me has been pretty significant to definitely who I am today.
So what's it been like, you know, for them watching, you know, you're the second youngest
in the family, but to see your success over the last eight years, I mentioned off the top and,
you know, to become, you know, an out and out superstar of the game and on your way to doing
incredible things you've already achieved so much already. Has it been a change in
the dynamic to have, you know, you with such a public profile now?
Not really, which I think's the really good thing. And really important thing about family is that
you're always family regardless of what you're doing or what you've achieved. And
in many respects, that's, you know, never that I, you know, ever felt like I was getting too
carried away with, you know, some of the things I'd achieved from an early age, but they were
always there to quickly bring me back down if I ever was carrying on or getting a bit cheeky,
which, you know, that's the...
The awesome thing about, you know, professional sport, which does take a toll on you mentally,
obviously, and physically, that always knowing you've got that, you know, safe space, those safe
people in that environment to be yourself in. And, you know, as I progressed throughout my career,
they've always treated me the same and it's always stayed the same in my family. And then
that environment, I'm still there, you know, younger or older brother, and they still won't
let me get away with anything as it was when I was a kid, I was bossed around most of the time,
never got to choose.
What we're watching on the TV and that probably in a way led me to just jumping outside and
kicking the footy. So I do have them to thank for, you know, not giving me an inch when it came to,
you know, who was in charge. And yeah, that probably sent me outside, which they were,
you know, great with as well. They were all, you know, active and sporty as kids and as children
too. And definitely helped me probably, you know, foster my love for the football game. Yeah.
Yeah. I couldn't think of a better ambassador for what, you know, respectful relationships
sound like. And it's a great credit to you. I know,
you support many great causes along those lines. So I hear people say that you've got this great
ability to connect with, you know, teammates and people outside of the footy club, regardless of
what personality type they are. They could be fanatical trainers and you're an extreme professional.
They could be the guys that, you know, get in a bit of trouble and don't mind, you know,
pushing the boundaries. To me, that is the art of great leadership. Is that something that's
again, come naturally to you or have you put some time into being able to connect with all
different types? It definitely has. I think,
you know, from a, from a young age, I always remember, you know, mum sort of describing that
way that, you know, I'd be able to sort of make friends with anyone. And it's probably like that
in the, definitely in the locker room when it comes to football, you've obviously got
a number of different lads from, you know, completely different ages, grown up with
different backgrounds. And it's just the one thing that's probably always come naturally to me. Like
I enjoy being part of a team that's clearly made up of, you know, different personalities and
different people.
And it is the one thing that, that definitely, you know, lends itself to, you know, good leadership
is, is that ability to connect. And it's, it's nice that that's probably one of the things that,
that has, you know, come naturally to me to, to, to be able to, you know, connect with young and
old people. And it's probably the thing that I look at, you know, all my friends and in my career
and then, you know, note that from, you know, a young age at 18, I was, you know, probably pretty
good friends with Bob Murphy as much as I was, you know, Jack McCrane and these blokes who are
the exact same age.
And it definitely, I think, helps when you're trying to, you know, bring people together to, to jump
into a, to a journey and, you know, inspire them and try and entice them to get the best out of
themselves.
Part of the evolution of being a captain is that sometimes your role is to hold behaviours to
account when people, you know, inevitably have challenges as it goes along. How's that been for
you having to maybe, you know, hold your teammates to account at times?
Yeah, it's been something that I've, I've grown in. I think something like that probably should,
should take some time.
Naturally, you know, when you, when you come into a football club and, you know, you progress,
you know, relatively quickly like I was, was able to. I think those, those sort of outside calls of,
of leadership, people are quick to put that label on you. When you're probably, whenever you become
good at something, they like to think that there's another, another level for you to go. And then,
and as you do, I think, you know, as I did, I looked to the people who were, you know,
the most influential players in our team as, as the most sort of significant,
leaders and all for, for different reasons. But once you do become in, I guess, that leadership
position and people look to, you have to develop that ability to have, I guess, you know,
stern conversations with others as they start to, you know, potentially either make mistakes or,
or start to, you know, venture off onto a path that doesn't quite suit the direction of our
football club. And it's something that I've, I've, I've definitely gotten better at. I wouldn't say
it's a, you know, probably not a huge strength. I don't think it necessarily is something you want
to do too often. You want the, the power of the, the group and the message that you're constantly
giving to continue to bring people back in line. But it's something, you know, it's, it's part of
leadership, but it's something I've, yeah, gotten better at in the short term. Yeah.
I want to ask you about the coach that you've played under now for, for many years, Luke Beveridge,
and you've achieved incredible success together, the 2016 premiership and, and beyond and everything
that you've done. He's a unique leader. We talk a lot on this podcast, Bon, about sort of face a
modern leader.
And to me, that sort of sums him up, self-reflective. He's emotionally intelligent. He's full of care
for those around him, but he's also incredible on strategy. How would you describe your relationship
with him?
Yeah, we've got a really, really close one, a really, really tight one that's been built
probably over time, over, you know, basis of sort of trust, you know, and, and, and the respect that
we have for each other. And obviously there's a lot of, a lot of love there in terms of what you
go through, you know, we probably bond over the, both being in sort of, you know, leadership
positions and being, I guess, figureheads of the, the football club and, and being able to deal with
the, the challenges that you have to face sort of week in, week out. And those questions that you,
you ask yourself. And, and I remember, you know, Martin Flanagan, who spent a lot of time with
probably both of us at different points off the back of the, the 2016 flag and the, and the book
that he wrote. And he described Bevo as someone who he thought had asked himself like the big
questions in life. And I think that's, that's a good way to, to sum him up. He's really, you know,
he's a really loyal,
person. He knows, he knows what he's about and he's asked himself probably those big life
questions, which allows him to be, you know, the person that he is and allows him to, to feel
comfortable, you know, in his own skin, which I think is the part that, you know, I and a lot of
people respect about him is he's sort of unashamedly himself, which I really admire from him. And it's
something that I continue to admire about him. And you're right, he's a left field, left field
thinker. It's, it's one of the things that allowed him to connect with our group, you know, really
well is because like we spoke about before, we've got a lot of lads who are, you know, different
personalities, different backgrounds and need to be, need to be motivated in different ways. And
him coming to the football club in, in 2015, you know, gave us the freedom to, to be ourselves and
then play a certain way, which gives you the confidence to, to roll out on match day and just
do your thing. So yeah, we've, yeah, obviously, you know, got closer and closer over the years
and, and he's a mentor of mine. Yeah, for sure. The language to me, I, I, I find fascinating.
And I love it, you know, even the word love, there's a lot of love there is the word that you
used before. And that wouldn't have been something in the era that I was involved in. It was, you
know, and, and probably for, for, for what the times were, it was very much hierarchical and
you wouldn't really ever get that close to a senior coach. And you probably weren't really
asked about what you thought about it. It seems to be a much more collaborative care base, but
it's pretty feedback driven environment too, isn't it? So how do you manage that? Because it seems,
you know, unique relationships that you've got, but at times, I suppose the hard questions have
to be asked as well. There is this, I think there's an understanding there within elite
sport at the minute that you can't have it all, all one way. It can't all be, you know, can't
all be rosy. We've still got to work in a, in a workplace and industry that's requires, you know,
critical feed feedback. And, and sometimes that can be the best thing, thing for you. And there's
a lot of trust within, I think the group and the, and the relationship that, you know, your best
interests are at heart.
There's a, there's a team process, there's a team goal that's in place. And I think Bevo's
thing over the journey has been to try and empower our players as much as, as possible. At the end
of the day, you know, they provide the, provide the, you know, supporting structure and framework
of, of the football club and are there to, to guide us. But you need the, the playing group
to be the ones that drive the standards and drive the program. And, and it's about, you know,
ownership. It's about, like you said, the collective being able to sort of send the right
message and,
and ultimately continue to sort of lean on that trust. And we probably found ourselves
off the back of the 2016 flag, losing a bit of that within the group, probably
external to that is we didn't quite follow up from that year as well as we would have liked.
And that took us a few years to probably understand and mature through. But it seems like we're in a
position now where, you know, we've, we understand sort of what's required and understand that it's
our journey to sort of, you know, try and bring everyone else on.
I want to go back to something you just said earlier before
around,
asking yourself the big life questions, Martin Flanagan describing Luke Beveridge like that.
What do you mean by that? What, what are those questions in your mind?
Yeah, I think it's, it's ultimately what you want to represent, what you stand for and not
probably going back on that because it seems, seems easy because it's unpopular, you know,
popular opinion is to think a certain way or do things a certain way. That's the thing,
once again, I've, I've loved and admired about Bevo is his courage to just be himself and say
things. And that's what, what you want from people is to feel comfortable to, to say and be who they
are regardless probably of, of, you know, if it's unpopular or not. And I think that's the thing
about Bevo, he's as loyal as, he's in your corner right until, until the end. And he's happy to walk
a, you know, a path lonely at times if he believes in it. And that's probably the thing that I think
Martin was reflecting on. He might not have been, he might've been referencing something else,
but that's just definitely how I interpreted what he was saying.
Yeah. It's a, it's a great insight. I was thinking of a conversation I had with
Trent Robinson who's a Sydney Roosters triple premiership coach in the NRL. And
he reminded me a lot of Bevo. I don't know him, but his language was the same. And he spoke about
coaching these guys to be brutal and win, but there was this softness and care and love at
the same time, which as I said, sounds a lot like your reflections on the environment you've created
in the last eight years. I wanted to talk to you about a program we've called Alita Connect that I
heard of. And again, credit to you. You and I had a conversation going back 12 months and talked
about this collaborative learning group and you wanted some diversity in terms of the way you
think, which again is, is unique. I really admire the way that you go about trying to learn and you
created a group with Pat Cummings, who's now just been appointed the captain of the Australian
cricket team. And Andy Lee is extraordinary. I've had the great pleasure of interviewing on this
podcast and Rob Sitch as well. Can you tell me about what that's meant to you in the last 12 months?
Yeah. Well, timing is, is everything.
So it just happened to be that we found each other at a similar time where you're exploring
something and I was curious to try and understand more about leadership, about difference, about
trying to continue to bring people together and empower them. And I obviously managed to become
part of this amazing group of, I guess, a bunch of people in all different walks of life. And other
than Patty being, I guess, another professional.
The rest of them are elite in their environments and in their industries. And it was just, it's been
such a great, great experience to just hear from them. And that's, that's, I still see myself in,
you know, very much the infancy of, I guess, my, my leadership sort of journey, you know,
title or no title. I think I've always just been curious to understand what I don't know. That old
saying, if you don't know what you don't know is, is something that I sort of continue to follow
sort of day to day about, you know, just trying to spend time with people who are, who are different,
and have had different experiences to, to try and learn a thing or two for myself. So it's been
great to hear from, like I said, a bunch of people of different ages at different sort of timelines
of their, their careers and then, you know, in their leadership experiences to, to glean some
things from them and hopefully give some back. Yeah. The idea of the program is initially sort
of eight, one hour, you know, Zooms, given the fact that the world had shut down and to sort of
connect, facilitated by my great friend, Matt, who, Matt Waterwitz, who's,
you know, been doing this for, for a significant period of time without giving away private
conversations, because they are, and I certainly don't want to encroach on that. Has there been
sort of specific things that you've added to what you do out of those conversations?
Definitely, definitely has. The emphasis was to try and come away with, you know, this, this,
I guess not product, but, but try and put together some, you know, hacks, I guess,
when it comes to leadership, that's what it was, how it was sort of deemed and termed is,
is, you know, we'd begin with a, you know, a question about leadership,
or a challenge, or, you know, a circumstance, and try and help each other with some, you know,
some hacks that you could use, you know, essentially leadership hacks or life hacks to,
to help yourself, you know, process that the challenges that come with leadership.
And a lot of them had to do, and the other ones that I probably most took from it was, was, you
know, your, your time management, particularly being able to, you know, obviously, you know,
with the long-term view of being able to maintain, you know, the balance of, of, you know, I was very,
I'm very, you know, football,
football focused and, and performance focused. So I put a lot of time and energy into how I can
best prepare myself and, and perform, you know, come game day, because I've always felt like
that's my best attribute from a leadership perspective is how I'm able to perform and
do what I do sort of day in, day out, but definitely week in, week out. And that's
probably how I've, I've come to be in the position that I am. So I probably at the beginning of my
probably leadership journey, when I talk about, you know, the captaincy stuff got the balance
a bit wrong. I,
sort of felt like I needed to probably give more to the team, start to change a few things and
play, play a certain way, probably in the vein of, of what, you know, some of the, the great
leaders, you know, football leaders I've seen before me and the things that they, they've done
probably more on field and tried to probably be someone who gave more time to others and probably
took a bit less out of my own sort of performance and preparation focus. And just trying to get
that balance back in, into, into the correct sort of shape was important for me.
And the other things are that you can't sort of be everything to everyone. It's something I've
struggled with initially as a footballer is trying to sort of please, please everyone and then be
someone, you know, definitely people can rely on, but as long as it doesn't come at the expense of
your own sort of energy and, and the boys are really good at sort of helping me sort of work
through, you know, different ways and different things you can do to, to sort of prevent yourself
from sort of cooking yourself too much so that you can still get out there come the weekend and be,
you know, the, the energetic, influential player that you want to be.
Yeah.
Great insight into, as you said, is, you know, all high profile people in that group and, and,
and you especially living in Melbourne, this crazy football town that's obsessed with
AFL, particularly someone that's achieved what, what you've achieved. Have you found you've been
able to just get better balance away from footy, but still keep your performance preparation at the,
at the level you want it to be?
Yeah, without a doubt. And I sort of, I feel like that process is an important one to,
to go through as a leader, um, working out, you know, what,
what can work, what, what might not, um, and sort of, you know, what you can get the most bang for
buck out of. Um, and you know, the, the boys were really good at, you know, the, the, the space is a
very private space where you feel like you've got, you know, five, five lads who are in a similar
position facing very similar challenges. And you can be quite open and honest about that. Um, and
some of your potential insecurities or the things that you're not coping with as well. Um, and
without a doubt, there was someone within that group who'd been through a similar process or a
similar challenge and can shed some light on how they managed to navigate their way through it.
Um, and it's that, you know, leadership and probably sport, you know, life in general,
it's not necessarily a linear process that just continues to trek upwards. You do find yourself
dipping and, and, and eventually ending up hopefully where you want to be, but it does
have a little, you know, up and down in it every now and again. And, and just trying to navigate
your way through that was certainly a lot easier with, with being able to reflect on some of those
challenges with these blokes. Yeah. We love that. I had self-reflective learning and that
collaborative learning you're talking about. It was to have, uh, you know, Pat Cummings through
that period of time, break new ground, really very rare for a fast bowler to become the captain of
the Australian cricket team. So that would have been fascinating to see that unfold for, for him.
And clearly he's, uh, he's got incredible leadership qualities as well. Yeah. Well,
having only seen, you know, what Pat was about from, you know, externally, like everyone else
up until probably 12 months ago, always had a, you know, a huge amount of respect how he,
how he performed, how he went about his business.
Um, presents really, really well. Um, and then getting an insight for, you know,
you know, more of a insightful, you know, view on, on, on who he is, who he is and how he,
and I felt myself probably, it's probably was easier in a way because we were talking the
same language at times when it comes to sport, um, professional, professional sport, um, and,
and the same sort of thing, trying to find that the same balance, you know, in, in still performing
the best way you possibly can, but then also trying to continue to, you know, navigate and,
and provide others the same level of, you know, empowerment to, to, to find their best and,
and be at their best. So we were able to sort of thrash a few things out that we'd sort of had
similar experiences with. Um, but it's, it's makes complete, you know, sense to me. And it
seems like a really good fit, you know, for, for him to be, you know, the skipper of the cricket
team now. Outside of footy, you've completed a bachelor of business, I understand. And you've
got a range of different interests. We've spoken about property interests before, but now an author.
A kid's author. Congratulations. Little bomb and the, and the big secret. Tell me about
where that came from. Um, just through a question, the publisher, um, had, uh, you know, basically
rang up and asked whether it would be something, you know, I'd be interested in, in, in doing with
them. And, um, uh, like I always do, I do tend to take a little bit of time to, to process and,
and make sure, um, the fit's right. And I've probably got the right story. I don't really
like to do things just for the sake of it. It's one of the thing that, that, um,
probably Andy Lee, um, you know, managed one of the hacks was like, if you don't feel like it's a
hell yes, then, then maybe it's not for you. Like you should feel anything you're going to say and
do, you want to feel like you're sort of all in with it. Um, and I really liked that from, from
Andy. Um, and so that was the book. I initially was like, yep, I think it's, I think it's a good
one for me, but do take some time to process. And then it was ultimately then about the story for
me. If the story is something that, that really meant a lot to me, then I was definitely in. Um,
this, my, my story in life is about family. So it felt like the right, um, the right fit was to
sort of run through how, I guess, a little bit of a snapshot of how my family was like growing up.
And then obviously my nan, my Nana Nancy is a, is a key, you know, character in the book. And we
were really close with, with Nana, um, from a, from a very young age. And, and she, you know,
just fostered one of those really nice, warm, um, comforting environments as a kid growing up.
Um, and I just thought she passed away a few years ago. It'd be great to, um, put together something
you know, a physical reminder or memory of, of what she was like for us as a family. And,
and it really just went from there. Yeah. Congratulations. It's, uh, you know,
I'm sure and inspire many of that generation with, uh, your values and everything you stand for.
It just comes through and everything, everything you say, but we've been identifying these range
of different, uh, dimensions of what we think, uh, modern leaders like yourself, uh, identify
with. And so I'm going to ask you a handful of questions and love you to expand as much as,
as you like, or as little as you like. But the first dimension we're seeing
is that I'm going to ask you a handful of questions and love you to expand as much as, as you like,
your idea of self-leadership. Um, when I asked you about self-leadership, what does that mean to
you? Um, it's a self-leadership. It's the way you probably, um, try to, I guess, identify how you
want to act and act and behave and what you're probably doing to, um, you know, create, create
relationships, create, um, pathways probably for yourself and then, and then for others.
Um, to, you know, following I've always like self-leadership is probably, you know, what I
consider probably actions and actions and behaviors. And, and, um, Bevo, you know, puts up this quote
quite often for us is, you know, the whole group, not just our leaders, we've moved away from a more
formal leadership group. Um, but, but, you know, leadership's an act, it's sort of less a title,
but more of a string of actions and behaviors. And it's something that, that I really identify
with, um, as a leader is that I feel like I'm a leader. And I feel like I'm a leader. And I feel
like I'm a leader because of those things, not because someone else sees me as, you know, having
the, you know, leadership qualities. It's really what people see in you, what you're able to do
consistently. Um, so, you know, self-leadership is probably how you, you know, how you hold,
handle yourself. And I think leadership's the, you know, the outcome.
I've seen a lot of, um, you just clear values that you stand for when they come out and everything
you say, is that something formally that you, you've written down and you, this is who I am,
or is it just, you, you reflect, as you said, take your time and know what works for you,
what doesn't? Yeah, I'll probably, you know, in the past have, you know, through, um, probably
early parts of, of, you know, my career in football, um, that you do, um, probably go
through that process of, of, you know, starting with a big sheet of values, then probably
circling what the key ones are for you. And, and I definitely know what they are, but I wouldn't
have needed a big list to choose from. I sort of, um, I feel like my family values, um, you know,
obviously hard work, humility, um, and then,
and outside of that, I feel like your application just sets, sets the rest of light to, to whatever
you're doing. So, um, I think, you know, once again, we're such a, we're a product of our sort
of environment and the people that we spend most time around. So I'm just, I guess, a reflection
of, of my family and the people that I've grown up sort of around and then managed to sort of
attach myself to in the, in my younger years. When we're seeing leaders, um, you know,
like yourself really conscious of how that positively impact others in their environment.
And before we started this conversation, I was talking to you, you spent your off season and
you've, uh, uh, carted along, that may be not the right term to use, but, uh, Jamara
Ugelhagen was, you know, a teammate of yours, number one draft pick and wanted to try and
follow you effectively in the off season to learn your professional behaviors. It's a,
it's a great commitment in your break time to, to do that. I mean, it's a great example of
how you positively impact others. There are other thoughts about how you do that?
Um, yeah, definitely. I think, um, as you, as you get older,
um, and through your career, um, and feel like you get a better feel and a better, um,
a better consistency with, with, you know, or confidence in your performance and your training
and feel like, um, you can continue to add sort of add layers and add little things,
but you start to realize, you know, what, um, how you want your, probably your influence or
things to not last, but leave, I guess, a legacy in a way. And, and your best way to do that is,
is through others and through, you know, those definitely younger than you,
that, um, are about to go on a similar pathway and similar journey to you. And, um, once again,
I was sort of reflecting on, you know, my own experiences with, you know, Bob Murphy,
Matthew Boyd, Dale Morris, um, you know, Easton Wood, who's just recently retired and their impact
on me from a very young age and how, how influential it can be if you're just willing to sort of take
the time to, to spend that with, with young people. So Jamar is an example of, of obviously a young
player, um, who comes in with, you know, a lot of, you know, a lot of, you know, a lot of, you know,
who comes in with, you know, a heap of attention, a heap of focus, which I had to a certain degree,
but definitely not at the same, same level. And we're even living in a, in a pretty different
sort of world nowadays to what we were sort of eight years ago when it comes to, you know,
phones and social media and the, how much it probably follows you more than it did even when
I came in. Um, so that, that was, you know, really Jamar is sort of doing and his appetite
and desire to, uh, you know, probably start this pre-season off maybe a bit better than, you know,
than he did the last one and basically set himself up to, to have a, you know, an improved
season. And, and, um, I was really just happened to be around at the time and he was keen to stay
in and, um, you know, stay on and stay away with me and just start training together. So, um, it's,
it's really good maturity for him from one year to the next to be able to go, um, you know, I want
to, I want to make more of this season. Um, and he's applied himself, um, really well. So excited
to see what, what sort of happens there for him. But ultimately I just love the idea,
of, of that being able to help others through their challenges and, and try to, you know, be a,
you know, a bit of a, an all-star in a way for him to, to try and follow and reflect with.
Yeah. It takes great leadership to, to give that commitment in your, in your downtime
as well. We talk about creating and sharing a vision and, and footy clubs generally have a
pretty clear vision about what they want to achieve. How have you gone about that influencing
and sharing and creating a vision within the group you work with?
Yeah, that's probably been, you know, the one thing, um, that I've had to sort of develop and
get more confidence in, um, because, uh, from my own perspective, I always found it quite easily
to, you know, be motivated to, to set goals and then, and then try to, you know, achieve them and
put all the things in, in place. Um, but it's sort of, it becomes a different, different challenge
when you're trying to inspire, once again, like we spoke before, a group of, you know, in our case,
40, 44 odd, you know, different, you know, ages, demographics, different personalities to try and
find, you know, something that connects with them. So, um, I guess I spend a fair bit of time,
you know, listening and, and, and watching and, and reading things that I feel like could be
quite useful and then different, you know, motivational pieces. And, um, it's always
about feel for us at the, at the Bulldogs. It's something, you know, just probably with Bevo,
with Bob Murphy, um, and with probably a number of our players that, um, it's got a feel right
for us. It's a process I go through with Lisa Stevens, who's, you know, a friend of mine,
sports psychologist, and she's been, been at the football club for, you know, a year or two,
I reckon longer than I have. Um, and we've both got a pretty good sense of, of what the group,
you know, feels connected to. Um, it's not just words on a wall that it has to, you know,
has to land right with our group and has to feel right. So it's, it's a process more than anything.
It's not just, oh, that's a great quote that can drive us. It's more, um, do we feel like this is
the right story for us? And can we, can we breathe life into it? Um, cause ultimately if the group
doesn't connect with it, it's virtually useless. Um, so that's, that's a process I like going
through, but it is quite difficult, but something that I know Bevo does incredibly well, but I could
imagine wouldn't be easy as he, you know, researches in the off season, what our themes and
what our, um, what our visions are going to be for the year, sort of year on year. It's something I,
once again, other things I really admire about him. I love hearing, uh, the language, you know,
Lisa Stevens is, I know it's had a huge impact, uh, to say a great friend and also the club
psychologist. It's such a,
different era that, you know, in the past it was not really even available or accepted. In fact,
people probably, uh, felt ashamed if they, you know, if something was going on, your marriage
is going to break down. It's clearly a different culture that you've created. Now I've heard you
use the word curiosity several times when we've been chatting already today and we see great
leaders really have curiosity and they approach their learning and development through the idea
of curiosity. Can, can you expand on that? Yeah, it's, um, I think it's something that
nowadays is a pretty common trait in, you know, especially the people that are best,
the best in what they do, um, sort of ever curious about what else is out there. And,
um, you know, Bevo was another one who sort of led the way with the, back in sort of 15,
16, the why not sort of ask that curious mindset of, of us as a, as a team exploring,
you know, something better than we were and, and, and that, um, we shouldn't count ourselves out.
Um, and another, you know, another major influence in my football and my career has been, been Joel
Corey who started the football club at the exact same time as I did, obviously Geelong sort of
champion and, and triple, you know, premiership player, um, but a really, really quiet sort of
reserved personality. And, and, um, I was probably a bit the same when I first sort of started out.
So he managed to really connect on, on that level, but he was someone that continued to sort
of ask, ask me questions rather than, I guess, tell me the things that he probably knew, you
know, the answers to and how I could get there. The idea of asking the questions is because you
need to experience it.
You need to experience the process, process yourself. And that's something I probably have
just, you know, continued to do, um, ever since sort of my, you know, early, early days at the
football club was continue to ask questions about, you know, certain things, even from a club
perspective or club direction perspective, continue to maintain that curious mindset and understand
why I guess the, the things are happening the way that they are. And it's definitely something that
I continue to do with my football and, and, and skill development is continue to be curious about,
you know, what else there is.
Out there that I can try and master or how I can, um, you know, make things more difficult or more
challenging.
And as a captain of an AFL club, you're in the communication business a lot more than, uh,
perhaps you would have been a few years ago that the times and the, uh, demands for you to,
to represent the club and be the face of the club. We, we, we identify, um, leaders talking
about their communicating with, with clarity regularly. Is that something you've put some
time into how you communicate?
Yeah, for sure. I think it's an important thought whenever you're, you know, addressing the group,
um, you know,
even I guess addressing, addressing the public, it's something that maybe he's come sort of
naturally when it comes to sort of communication and hopefully, hopefully being clear. Um, but
ultimately wanting to, to be really confident about the message that you're sending. And, um,
I, once again, I've got a process that I go through when I speak to probably, you know,
when it comes to, you know, big, um, big meetings or big, you know, I've got a big emphasis on a
message that I want to send is, is going through a process of, of discussing it with a few people
to make sure I'm, you know, clear. And that involves my teammates, it involves, you know,
Bevo, Lisa, um, and that allows me to have that confidence, I reckon, to be sort of, you know,
clear with my communication. And, and, um, once again, you're dealing with, you know, 18 year
olds to, to 30 sort of five year olds. So you need to, you know, be able to provide, um, you know,
communication that's clear for, for obviously all ages and that you really don't want people sort of
walking away a bit unsure about, about what you're saying or the message you're trying to send. So,
um, definitely something that I,
continue to work on, but feel like, um, yeah, it's, it's something I've naturally sort of had a
bit of, um, ability to do. Bon, in, uh, the work we're doing with, uh, the leadership space,
our tagline is this world of collaboration and we're seeing great leaders want to collaborate
to, to do all the things you're talking about. Um, how important has collaboration been for you?
Huge, really, really big. I think, um, it's the one thing that definitely,
you know, you know, I can't speak for before my time at the football club, but from the
sort of 14 year, my first season, then going forward is the, um, you know, like you probably
spoke to, there probably was still some, some hierarchy, all those, um, pretty clear, um,
lines of, of hierarchy when I joined the club. And it's something that, that, you know, Bevo was
able to do pretty quickly is sort of flatten everything out, um, and have everyone feel like
they're valued, like their, their opinion and their, their thoughts, um, were, were willing
to be recognized, um, and basically to create once again, that empowerment of, of, of everyone
and helping everyone understand that you need everyone on a journey like this. Um, so it's
something that I continue, I continue to do. We, you know, create spaces for, you know, the, the
team and our different age groups to, to get together and bring up, you know, concerns or
positives, um, and bring those things to the table. And, um, you know, the, the football club
environment of, you know, standing out in front of you, your mates, um,
or, you know, people you sort of look up to, or those that you're scared of is quite a daunting,
daunting process. So we really try to break that down and try and we, I guess we circle up now
rather than sitting in a, in a theater. So it's just little things that create an environment
for people to feel more comfortable and more willing to, to open up and, and, and, you know,
potentially take a leap of faith and say something that, um, they've been thinking about or chewing
on. So, um, you need everyone to feel like they're a part of it. That's certainly the message. Yeah.
To me, there's great, uh, learnings for, you know, people listening to that in, in small
business or whatever discipline in education or whatever passionate idea that you are really
properly listening and wanting people regardless of whether it's your first year or your 12th or
15th year. And, you know, you can clearly see that environment that you've led, uh, is something that
works incredibly well. It's such a healthy and, um, positive environment. It's incredibly
impressive. I've been asking these two questions, Bond, of, uh, all the, um, inspirational leaders.
I've really, uh, been fortunate to, to speak to people like yourself and, um, two final questions
for you. Who's been the greatest leader in your life? Um, oh, it's, it's hard to go past my, my dad.
I think family's always, um, you know, the, the people that you, you know, spend the most time
with, but you get, um, probably the, the greatest understanding of my dad was, um, you know,
a concreter from a very young age from a, you know, an Italian family. So that seems to be,
um, where a lot of the Italians obviously ended up in, in the concreting business, but, um,
he was someone, you know, just from a, you know, you know, uh, watching
worked incredibly hard, you know, provided obviously, um, for our family, um, you know,
clearly with mum as well, but, you know, concreting is a really, you know, hard business. People who,
who work in that, in that industry and probably the building industry in general, they work,
you know, obviously long hours and it's very physical work. Um, but he definitely, when it
came to, you know, my football and when I was probably 15 or 16, felt like I was, um, you know,
falling further and further away maybe from the football dream, which I'd sort of prayed and hoped
for since a very young age.
But, um, sometimes you just need that person sort of in your life who can give you the confidence,
um, and lift your, lift your spirits and lift you up. And he did that for me, you know, pretty much
around that age. And, um, it's, it's just, he's someone I can, you know, rely on someone in your
life that, you know, always be there regardless. And her mum and dad are both the same in that
vein, but, um, his work ethic and, and his, um, you know, his appetite to, you know, always,
you know, remember your family values is, is really strong. And that definitely has run,
run, run, run, run, run, run, run, run, run, run, run, run, run, run, run, run, run, run, run, run, run, run, run,
true with me for sure. And he, you know, was such a big influence for me from such a young age that,
um, yeah, he continues to do that sort of regardless. Yeah.
Well, I haven't heard you talk about that for a lot of, you know, if, if there's kids listening
that, that 15 years of age is a tough thing in sport for, you know, you get the early developers
who, who jump out and have a massive size and strength advantage and, you know, kids lose
their confidence at that age. Did that happen to you a little bit where you're a bit of a later
developer?
Yeah. And I wasn't sure how, you know, far back you wanted to go, um, sort of with this,
with this chap, but definitely.
Definitely as a, you know, 14, 15 year old, um, late developer born later in the year.
Um, probably, yeah, lacked a bit of confidence at that age when, when players, you know,
start either get bigger, grow faster. Um, and once again, your mates around you are
all progressing, but you seem to be, you know, stuck in mud almost. Um, and yeah, dad was
probably the one that probably saw me slowly like questioning or doubting. And I imagine
as a, as a father, you, you, you see that and try to do everything you can to, to continue
to try and, um.
Um, you know, push your, push your son along. Um, and, you know, I'd spent, you know, it's
funny, I spend, you know, school holidays, I'd, I'd work with him, you know, and, and
sort of developed. And, and that's probably where I got a sense for how hard he worked.
Like I think, you know, that two week school holiday period you got, I'd spend, you know,
with him being his lackey, just going to get different things for him, like not doing a
whole lot, but just sort of watching. Um, and actually being able to do that probably
gave me a greater appreciation for, for how hard he worked. And then the things that he
did, you know, just, just, just, just, just, just, just, just, just, just, just, just, just,
just to provide for, for our family. So I really probably even just now think about
that and think what a, what a great opportunity it was to, to do that. And it also probably
gave me a, you know, a look at, oh, I think if I can make this football thing work, I'd
probably prefer to do that maybe. Um, then be, you know, pouring concrete. Um, so it's,
you know, and maybe he thought about that. Maybe he didn't. Maybe, you know, he thought
it's a good insight into, you know, what I do and potentially what you can maybe go and
do if you work hard enough for it. So inadvertently he's probably had an impact like that,
without even probably thinking it, or maybe he was smarter than I give him credit for
and did. Um, but definitely as a 15 year old, I sensed I was, you know, falling behind and,
and had a bit of a growth spurt probably when I was, you know, 16, 17. Um, and I remember
him, you know, we went down to one of the training sessions, um, at the Northern Knights,
um, more or less just to show, try and show me that, you know, it's sort of a bit in your
head that, you know, these kids are good, but you're definitely, you know, capable enough
to be sort of out there, out there training. Um, and like I said, I think that's, I think
that he'd be, he would be out the back with me, you know, didn't grow up playing much
sport or play, you know, football, um, like I did. And he'd be doing his best just to
try and, I guess, support his son in, in what he sort of hopes and dreams were. So, um,
yeah, I definitely felt myself, I guess, coming back to the initial question, falling a bit
behind. He was there for, from a confidence perspective to try and sort of continue to
lift my spirits. And, and sure enough, I managed to, to grow, develop a bit more confidence
and then really come on late sort of in my, I guess, my dream.
Um, which was sort of all started with his, you know, initial push.
What a gift that is to have someone like that in your life. And, uh, and still to this day,
the final question is back to the, uh, the word of collaboration. If you're asking this
question, if you could collaborate with anyone that could be in any part of your life, uh,
Bono, I know you've got passions outside of your love of football, but if there was any
collaboration, any person who would spring to mind?
Oh, straight away, I think sort of Roger Federer, um, which, um, you know, maybe that's just
from a, um,
you know, he's an incredible, you know, obviously, you know, tennis player, but I've always admired
the way that he sort of handles himself, um, clearly off, off the court and the things
that he does, how he speaks. Um, there's a real, um, genuine sort of nature to, to him.
Um, and I think a lot of people are in the very similar vein of, of how they sort of
see him. And, um, he's a, you know, authentic person. And I love that probably about him
as he can, you know, um, yeah, represent, um, you know, he's a, he's a, he's a, he's
a, you know, such a, you know, really nice and caring and, you know, nurturing sort of
personality, um, and be such a, you know, obviously a, a successful sort of tennis player
and athlete. So, um, he'd be one that I think if you could just sort of sit down and have
a coffee with, it'd be really interesting.
I feel like, uh, you're cut from a very similar cloth to that man. I'm not surprised by, uh,
that answer and, uh, you know, the same values that come out in this conversation. Uh, I'm
not sure I've had the chance to say this to you before, but, uh, as someone who's lucky
enough to play at the club that you're the captain of, uh, what you've done and the way
you've inspired, um, so many people has really changed the game for people who love the red,
white, and blue. And, uh, you know, I think, um, you know, the successes that you guys
have achieved, but probably the way you've gone about it has made, uh, I think all of
our passion for the club we played for even greater. So I, I feel like we need to say
thank you. We love watching you from afar and, uh, love talking to you anytime we get
the chance and appreciate you taking the time today.
Thanks, Darcy. My pleasure, mate.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me, Luke Darcy, produced by Matt Doyle.
With audio production by Darcy Thompson. Start your leadership journey. I encourage
you to go to a leader collective.com. Take our empowering leaders indicator tool and
understand the impact you have on your environment. Join us at a leader to learn, lead, and collaborate.