A Listener Production.
G'day, it's Luke Darcy.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership both on and off the field
has been a lifelong passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective
and have had the privilege of working with thousands of leaders
in education, sport, industry and the arts
that have helped shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership
where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
Marcus Godinho's impact on those less fortunate and in need
is a great Australian story.
FairShare, founded in 2007, is a charity that works with businesses
to cook surplus food into free, nutritious meals.
FairShare operates Australia's largest charity kitchens
where every week, 1,000 volunteers cook more than 50,000 meals.
They collect food that business can no longer use,
vegetables that no longer look perfect but are perfectly edible,
meat approaching its use-by date,
pastry off-cultivation,
cuts from commercial bakeries,
high-fibre bread not sold on the day it was baked
are some of the examples.
Each of FairShare's ready-to-eat meals contain at least half
an adult's recommended daily intake of protein and vegetables
to improve the diet and health of people who have fallen on hard times.
Marcus' outstanding contribution is seen and recognised
as one of Pro Bono Australia's 2022 Impact Award winners,
City of Yarra Local Hero Award
and one of the 100 most influential people in the City of Melbourne.
He's a Harvard University,
University Alumni in the Not-for-Profit Management,
Innovation and Performance sectors,
as well as holding an MBA and a Commerce degree.
Marcus, congratulations on an incredible amount of work that you've done.
I feel like a lot of us feel really bad about food waste.
Not many people turn that into 50,000 nutritious meals a week
that were destined for landfill.
Can you tell us about how your story started with FairShare?
Oh, Luke, thanks so much.
It's great to be with you.
Look, it's funny how these journeys start,
but, I mean,
my roots are probably different to many others who are involved with FairShare
and it started from an environmental perspective
and having been involved with environmental issues for some time,
you know, water issues, climate change,
I could see that things were going to emerge on the food front
when you think about all the resources that go into producing food.
And I guess being of Mediterranean extraction and loving food
and cooking it and entertaining,
when I heard about a group of people getting together
and using surplus food
to, you know, not just spend time together in a kitchen,
but to cook it for people going hungry in Melbourne.
Oh, okay.
Are there people going hungry?
So I offered to help out on a Saturday morning.
I went down and loved it, really enjoyed it.
So I said I'd come down next Saturday.
And it was one of those early revelations for me.
The woman said, no, you can come back once a month.
We've got many people wanting to volunteer with us.
But look, it was just such a small-scale operation.
But I just loved that concept of taking food
that was otherwise going to go to landfill
and doing something with it.
And I'm not the only one to have had that thought.
There are some great organisations out there rescuing food.
Yeah, and I think, you know, listening to your story
and researching your story,
the nutritious healthy element to what you've done.
And 15 years later, I think you said to me,
there are 2,000 meals a year that were being produced back then,
up to 3 million meals a year.
You can correct me on the numbers there.
But, yeah, it's incredible growth.
It's an incredible impact you're having.
And you really wanted to focus on making sure
that it wasn't just surplus food that was going,
regardless of the quality.
You wanted to focus on the quality
of what you were preparing for people as well.
Yeah, look, it's Australia.
It's not North Korea.
It's not Horn of Africa.
We've got different, I guess, diet-related health issues here.
And what we find is that most people who are struggling
for...
or food, with food insecurity,
are struggling to access healthy food,
are struggling to cook meals themselves.
So it's not just a matter of feeding hungry tummies.
It's a matter of actually trying to get nutritious food
into their diets to improve their health.
And I was speaking to a nutritionist, Karen Inge,
who has a history with the Hawthorne Football Club.
She's done a lot of work in nutrition in football.
And she said to me, she used a term
that I'd never heard before, but I immediately
knew what she meant, malnubicity.
And it resonated because from having gone out
to a lot of local charities over the years
where our meals are being served, you'd
see people turning up, receiving food, who were just
a bit overweight.
And you think, gee.
And what she's describing is that there's malnubicity,
there's type 2 diabetes.
And it's a great play on words.
But that's where we really want to go,
is that it's not just about calories.
It's not just about any food.
It's about getting nutrition into the diets
that people are doing it tough.
Yeah, it's a fascinating term, that for mine, isn't it?
And in some ways, we do ape American culture a lot,
don't we, in the over-processed food that's become
part of Australians' diet.
And you're seeing, I hadn't heard that term before,
but it is.
It's accurate, isn't it?
It makes sense, doesn't it?
People that are overweight and unhealthy,
but really having poor diets.
I read this feedback from one of your customers,
I suppose, if that's the right term,
or one of the people in need.
And I wanted to read it back to you,
because I'm assuming this is what you do it for.
It's such nice food.
I get my veggies, some beautiful roast usually,
and they serve it hot.
Lots of places just have white bread and sausage,
which is OK now and then.
But I need to keep healthy.
It was lamb last week.
I haven't had lamb in ages.
It was so good.
It was so special.
So much thanks to the chef and those volunteers.
They make such a difference.
It really gives me something to look forward to.
That sounds life-changing to me.
Is that what you do it for?
Oh, look, we don't get as much feedback from the front line,
from people who receive it.
And you can understand, given the stress that they're under,
that we're not going to.
But, jeez, when you get it, it makes you feel good.
And then to share it.
I make sure I do with the volunteers,
the hundreds of volunteers.
We've got a lot of volunteers that we've got coming down regularly
with the businesses that donate food because, I mean,
that's what it's about.
Yes, it's about stopping food from being wasted,
and that was our genesis, and that's how we do it.
But it's about the difference you can make to someone's life.
And, yeah, malnutrition, obesity, it's a cool term,
that malnubicity.
But, yeah, I think in Australia, society,
for too long,
has relied on this coming together,
which is what you want of sectors, government, business,
the third sector relying on businesses have surplus food.
They give it to charities,
and charities give it to people who are doing it tough.
And it's kilos of food.
They're equated to meals, in averted commas,
but it's just kilos of food.
And some of it can be pretty wacky.
But, really, I think we need to shift.
And I can see this starting,
starting from,
from there just being just kilos of food,
any food being passed on that,
as one woman from the front line said to me,
can just exacerbate the diet-related health issues.
We need to move to food that is actually going to improve the quality of life,
the diet, the health of people who've fallen on hard times.
We need to start with a demand, not start with a supply.
And so we've really switched our thinking at FairShare from being pushed to being
poor, from being supply to being demand.
How can we actually address some of the issues that are being tackled by those at the front line,
those local charities who are helping those people who are doing it tough?
You're just kind enough to give me a tour of the facility here in Abbotsford in Melbourne.
And you can see the volunteers hard at work and,
you know, beautiful chicken casseroles and meals that you look at and go,
get me involved in some of that.
We are here talking leadership.
It's the passion that I've got around what leadership looks like in different spaces.
For you to mobilise a thousand volunteers a week,
you've got to deal with partners, huge partners like Woolworths and the logistics
and the organisation of that.
Can you tell us something that takes a lot of skill?
How have you gone about it?
Look, there are different ways of going about things.
The way that I've gone about FairShare is by providing an opportunity for people
to participate in something.
And I've seen with some charities, they raise a bit of money,
they pump it into PR, they pump it into fundraising.
And their brand builds.
And that's a formula for success.
And a lot of those charities do great work.
We've taken a different path and it's provide individuals a chance to regularly volunteer.
It's provide businesses with a chance to donate their food.
It's have corporates, have their groups of staff come down and participate.
Service clubs, rotaries, lines, have them come down and volunteer with us.
Yeah.
And you never know who's in the kitchen.
And I always say to the chefs, be careful what you say,
because you never know who's listening and what they pick up on.
And there are some wonderful stories of people who've got involved under the radar at FairShare.
And just, it's not serendipity, it's deliberate.
We've tried to get people involved with FairShare.
And we've known that by doing so, there'd be some people who could be pretty influential come
through without necessarily heralding who they are.
But then, having had a good experience or having spent time with us, have then gone
away and helped us.
There's countless stories of people like that.
And it just makes my heart sing, spending time with individuals and with organisations
and the feedback that I get from those who participate about what it means to them.
And I think these days, that's one of the most rewarding things.
Yes, we're stopping food from being wasted.
We're helping people who are doing it tough.
But there's this unintended byproduct, which is volunteering, and it's an input, but it's
also an output.
Yeah.
And you can tangibly feel it just walking through your organisation a few moments ago.
You can see this sense of community and this sense of participation that clearly you've
created.
There are a lot of charities, Marcus, and a lot of great ventures with great intentions
and great causes.
But very few have the huge social impact.
And I think that's the real impact that FairShare and you are having, and you have it educated
in this space.
What's the key for people that do want to make an impact and have got a good idea in
this space?
How do you make the biggest impact?
How would you describe that?
Well, I hear quite often people going out and saying, look, I want to do something on
this.
I'm setting up a charity or I'm setting up a foundation.
And I think people can solve and rush to that.
What's critical is you actually do your homework first.
And I've had that many conversations with people saying, look, I've had a great day.
I've had a great day.
I've had a great time in the corporate sector.
I want to move into the community sector.
What was your path?
What's your recommendation?
And I always start with, you need to actually identify what are you passionate about?
What keeps you up at night?
What puts fire in your belly?
And so finding what that is, is it climate change?
Is it human trafficking?
Is it kids cancer?
Look, there are so many important issues.
There are so many great organizations working on these issues.
So to find that.
To then do your research.
And to, well, who's working on it?
And different organizations do different types of things, play different roles on issues.
Some are doing advocacy, some are doing practical action.
Are you more the activist type of person?
Are you the person who just wants to plant trees rather than be tying themselves to a
tree?
So there are different ways that you can get involved, finding your passion, working out
which organizations.
Finding, volunteering with organizations to help find yourself.
And then finding yourself working for an organization and then, look, yeah, you don't know where
these journeys.
Well, that's an interesting point that I'd like to pick up on, because I look at you
and I'm an incredibly intelligent guy, incredibly articulate, incredibly well-educated.
You could turn your attention, I feel like, to anything in the commercial sector and probably
make lots and lots of money if you so choose.
Yeah.
So how do you balance that out with wanting to support your family plus contribute to
so many others like you do?
I was fortunate because I started off in the corporate sector and I had a good decade there
and I was pretty frugal and saved and bought a house.
So I got off to a good start and I think that held me in good stead.
And probably not as easy to do these days with cost of living pressures and real estate.
And that's where I've seen some people who've had it.
I've seen people who've had tremendous impact, who have both juggled a career and careers
that have been well remunerated and also doing things on the side.
I mean, a close friend and colleague very quietly spent 12 years chairing a disability
accommodation organization that has had incredible impact, did very well in business, but at
the same time was doing tremendous community work.
So often these things happen at different stages of your life and not everybody's going
to be an activist from straight out of school or straight out of university.
But I think it's a matter of people finding their balance between career and community
service.
And look, if you've got young kids, you don't have as much time and you might back off and
I find myself doing that now.
But then you might be able to step up when your kids are a bit older, when you've got
a bit more time, maybe career wise.
So yeah.
I don't think it's the same for everybody through their life.
Yeah.
Look, I think most people have that idea of wanting to contribute, wanting to do that
effectively, balancing that, as you said, with the day-to-day needs of raising your
family.
Where is that point?
And I've spoken to a lot of people in the charitable space.
That's a hard...
Even so, what do you pay yourself when you run a charity?
How do you start there?
I mean, what's the balance?
How do you incentivize people like you to do it?
Is that a path that you've had to tread?
Yeah.
Look, I get pretty personal with this.
There've been a few arm wrestles.
I remember once my president said, look, we're grateful for the work you've done.
We want to give you a pay rise.
And I said, look, I'm comfortable with what I'm being remunerated.
What did your wife say, though?
I can tell what my parents said.
But I said, look, at the end of conversation, I do the pays at fair share, so I'm not going
to give myself an increase.
Oh, look, I think it's about being honest.
I think it's about benchmarking what's reasonable in the community sector and paying at that
level.
But conversely, the labor market in the community sector is competitive, as elsewhere.
And there's an argument going that if you actually pay a little bit more and get somebody
a little bit better, then you actually can have more impact.
So I think the notion of just looking at, and I've had this conversation with people
before, just looking at the payroll or the pay rates of charities, how much they're paying
people, it's the wrong way to look at it.
You really need to be looking at, well, what impact is that charity?
People say, well, what percentage do you spend on administration?
Wrong conversation to be having.
What impact is the organization having?
Yeah.
I think there are charities out there that do what they do really well, and they've got
a good reputation.
They tell a good story.
They raise money to sustain what they do.
But decade after decade, what impact are they actually having?
So it was one of those things in that Harvard course you referenced that they really drummed
on about.
You've got to look at the impact of your work.
It's not just doing it well.
What difference is it making?
Marcus, I interviewed Dan Flynn, the founder of Thank You World.
Thank you.
He's the founder of Thank You Water on this podcast, who I found a really interesting
and inspirational story, and a significant change maker in what he's done in that space.
But he spoke about the not-for-profit sector held to a bar much higher than the commercial
sector.
If you wanted to innovate here at Fair Share and spend some money that may be investment
for the long term, there can often be a critical eye on, as you said, what was the cost of
that?
And perhaps we don't get that innovation in that sector at times because there isn't that
wiggle room given.
Is that something you subscribe to?
Or do you think you can work that out okay?
I don't know whether I necessarily agree with that.
I think there's a lot of ... Look, people who fund the community sector vary quite a
bit.
You've got government.
You've got corporate.
You've got philanthropic.
Philanthropy can take risks and back good ideas and exercise their judgment around people.
Government has to be more cautious.
Using taxpayers' funding, corporate, they've got their reputation that's worth so much.
So look, I think it varies depending on where the funding's coming from, who you're talking
about.
I don't think it's as simple as that.
There's ... I think within the ... I think within the ... I think within the ... I think
within the ... I think within the ... I think within the ... I think within the ... I think
within a lot of giving it's, well, what's the cause?
Is the cause important to me?
Do I have confidence in the organisation and how it's going about its model to addressing
that cause?
Then who's working on it and do I like that person?
Do I trust that person?
I think if you've got that alignment between a funder, your cause is important to them.
They have confidence in the organisation and they respect the person, then I think you
do have some latitude.
And what we're seeing happening more and more, and we need to see more of this in Australia in giving, is that philanthropy is pivoting to not just one year funding of projects, of something that's tangible, but actually saying that organisation does good work that has impact on an issue that's important to us.
So we're just going to back it to do what it judges as being important. So it's what we refer to as backing the OPEX of the organisation, because a lot of people want to fund the brick in the building. They want to fund the oven or the cool room or the van. But what we don't want is stranded assets.
We don't want an oven that looks great and costs $50,000, but we can't afford to pay the chef or the electricity or the maintenance for that oven to turn out meals. So that's where we're having that conversation.
That conversation is taking place within philanthropy. We're certainly fuelling it. We want it to take place because we want organisations to just back us to do what we do. Because I've had the conversation with quite a few politicians, oh, we'll support you with your capital expenditure, but not on your operating costs, which is not surprising, but it's not particularly helpful.
It's a great answer, because it makes sense, doesn't it? This is what our expertise is in. We're competing, if you like, with anyone.
Your expertise.
Your skills around creating nutritious meals for those in need is world-class. Just trust the process with accountability that we're going to be doing. My mind's also going, Jeff Harris, the founder of Flight Centre, who's an incredible person in the philanthropy world, he was talking about social ventures being underutilised in Australia and not really understood, and that other parts of the world were way ahead of encouraging.
Can you first of all describe the difference between not-for-profit and social venture, and are you a subscriber?
Are you a subscriber to the social venture world?
Oh, look, absolutely. I agree with Jeff. There's a place for both, though. Jeff's been a fantastic backer of Street. A woman called Bec Scott set that up. Her creative thinking and entrepreneurial flair is inspiring. I always feel so inadequate when I'm speaking with her.
And not everything works. Not everything's going to work commercially or in social enterprises. But what she's doing, what Jeff's backing her to do, what he's talking about is…
A way of running something that, through doing what it does, has social benefits. So, for instance, a cafe that's taking at-risk kids and training them in some basic hospitality skills, the cafe is breaking even or making a little bit of money, but there's a social benefit from doing what it does because of the way it does it.
Now, that's a relatively new model compared to a charity.
Like FairShare, which exists and runs in as efficient way as possible to provide a service to the community to have impact. So, I think there's a role for both. And this is one of the things that I've struggled with over the years because people have said to me, oh, FairShare needs to have a social enterprise.
And my response has always been, yeah, a friend of mine says he always wants to buy a business. And I said, well, what do you know about? And what's your idea?
And, you know, if you're going into business, it's not quite this straightforward. It's the same for a charity. Okay, you think we should do a social enterprise, but what? I don't have an idea, for one. But I'm open to it. I'd love to. And it's not to say that at FairShare, we wouldn't do one. I think you've got to start with the idea. But certainly, both charities and social enterprises can both do fantastic work and have impact.
You're affected.
Like everyone else here in the city of Melbourne, the core base of your business, it was the longest lockdown in the world. From a charity point of view, you've got 200 volunteers a day. How did you approach that?
Panic. I think a 72-hour funk. Look, I remember this so vividly. The FairShare model's based on participation. So, get as many people in, shoulder to shoulder, through the kitchen a day.
It's the anti-COVID environment. The advice from government was to have as few people on site over the course of a week as possible. And so, I flipped just, it's the opposite to how we roll.
And so, yeah, it was 72 hours. And I vividly recall on the Thursday, coming out of this funk and saying, no, you need to find a way of changing the way we operate.
Because what FairShare does...
It's going to be needed more than ever. But we're going to have to do it differently. And I've had this wonderful partnership with a woman called Kelly, who's been with us for 12 years, like myself, started as a volunteer and could do anything.
And so, I rang her up on the Friday and said, look, we need to remodel. We want to operate, we've got to operate with a very small number of highly productive paid hospitality workers and suspend volunteering. And so, she facetiously said, oh my God, that'd be so much easier.
Yeah.
But you've just been complaining about having written off all of this income because we're not going to be able to do fundraisers. And you've been talking about we can't operate with volunteers for all the obvious reasons. But yeah, okay, I'll go away and model it for you. And it was just one of those moments that was, I say good fortune more than good luck. But the very next day, mid-Saturday, I got a phone call from the state government. And it was a senior bureaucrat. And he said, hi, mate.
Hi, Marcus. My name's Jim. We've met a few times through a mutual friend. I've been thinking, you do important work for Victoria and we don't ordinarily fund you. We're going to need you more than ever. And I've been thinking, you can't do what you do with volunteers. And I've been thinking, there's all of these hospitality workers that are losing their jobs. So, I want to get in 24 hours a proposal from you to suspend volunteering and put on laid off hospitality workers so that you can not just suspend volunteering.
You can't sustain what you do, but you can scale. Sorry, mate, what's your name? How do we know each other?
How good a call is that, Marcus?
How good a call. So, I straight away hung up and rang Kelly and said, right, you know what we talked about yesterday?
It's on.
It's on. It's on. And within Monday week after that phone call, we had suspended all of our volunteering. And that wasn't an easy thing to do.
And we had more than 70 highly productive paid kitchen workers in the kitchen. And in between those two days, I remember that was the Saturday phone call.
The Sunday phone call, I was at home playing Dungeons and Dragons with my sons around the kitchen table and the phone rang and it was pretty boisterous.
But I took it because, you know, everything was happening so quickly back then. And it was, Marcus, Marcus.
It's Marcus. It's Brad Banducci from Woolworths here. And I had the CEO of Woolworths on the phone committing to support.
And then the following day, I had Bruce Matheson from the ALH group.
So, what we were able to do very quickly was suspend volunteering, the usual model, rely less on surplus food.
And that's where Brad committed to buying $100,000 a week of meat and vegetables for us.
And we had...
Bruce Matheson at the ALH group putting in around 70 full-time staff of his that couldn't go to work, that he was paying, you know, their usual place of work was shut.
And he had them in at fair share in our Brisbane kitchen, in our Melbourne kitchen.
And so, that's why we scaled to cook about 140,000 meals a week and a great range of meals.
And I remember one of the chefs stopped me and he said, I can't believe the quality of food that's going out of this place and going out to local charities.
How good's this?
It was terrific.
It's an amazing story.
Incredible in that short amount of time.
And it's probably a lifetime of work because not many people get to see Woolies calling on their private phone.
That takes time, you know.
I think that was it.
I say good fortune and there was a reaction there.
But there was a relationship there with somebody who remembered me talking about fair share, which I'm always doing.
There was Brad Banducci and we've worked with Woolworths for 14 years.
And they're...
They've got a relationship with the ALH group, obviously.
And so, yeah.
And there's a reputation there.
There are relationships there.
There are partnerships with corporates.
So, it was a lot of things coming together.
It wasn't just serendipity.
A lot of trust, isn't it?
And I love the bureaucrat story.
And we're often critical of bureaucracy and we should celebrate.
That's great thinking and great initiative with all that was going on in Melbourne.
Yeah, a lot of us were critical.
It's easy to be critical, but you've got to come up with a solution as well.
So, what a brilliant story.
We need to find that person, Marcus, and celebrate them better for their initiative.
We've been looking at a range of leaders and I love your leadership story.
It's brilliant.
And that's a great example of it right in the making in the most challenging time to turn that into the success it is.
And we're seeing these sort of common traits appear across different leadership and wanting to pick up the cues and learn for them.
We think most people who are leading the way you are with the self-reflection and care have a sense of self-care.
Yeah.
They have a sense of self-leadership.
What does that mean to you?
Oh, look, it really starts with understanding yourself.
Look, there are a lot of very intelligent, much more intelligent people than me out there.
But I remember hearing many years ago, to be successful leading an organization, it's not just about your IQ.
It's also about your EQ.
And that's understanding yourself and being able to manage yourself and understanding others and being able to relate.
So I think that self-awareness is critical.
It's about really working with your strengths, playing to those, and not bashing yourself up because of your weaknesses, working on them where you need to, but also bringing people around you who complement who you are.
And I think that for me at FairShare, one of the things I'm really proud of is having recruited people.
I mean, not just staff, but it's the board that we have of volunteer directors.
It's businesses, being able to bring them and have them stick with us.
But look, aren't we our own harshest critics?
And I bash myself up all the time.
But yeah, and I probably need to spend more time reflecting on who I am.
I think one of the things for me in this whole journey has been, I mean, I started in the not-for-profit.
I started in the not-for-profit space with an environmental advocacy group.
And I was passionate and committed and gave so much of myself.
It was before kids.
But the thing that I found really hard was the combative nature of it.
It wasn't like at FairShare where it's a no-brainer and people just say, that just makes sense.
Advocacy's hard.
I mean, I remember a few mates ringing me up and saying, geez, I've just seen Terry McCrown's article about you.
He's...
Mentioned you 12 times and ripped shreds through you.
I mean, that I could handle because, you know, as Roz Kelly was saying to you in the past, it's not about you.
It's about the role you're playing.
But it's the divisive nature sometimes of advocacy and the conflict that I found really hard.
And so after six years of doing that, I just had that awareness that that wasn't me.
But...
What had you done to get Terry's attention 12 times?
I've got to ask that question.
Oh, look, we were pretty annoyed about some moves that were afoot to try and give extra coal.
Look, it's very complicated.
But extra coal to the Hazelwood Power Station, which was the most greenhouse...
Unfriendly.
...intensive power station in Australia by some measures.
What year are we talking here?
Oh, God, this is going back 2000.
2003, 2002, 2003.
You're ahead of your time.
Well, look, so we didn't want them to get extra coal.
I mean, I just couldn't see, though, in some respects that pushing the life of this power station out from 2028 to 2033,
I mean, surely we couldn't still be digging coal out of the ground then.
Surely this power station couldn't still be running.
But, you know, that's what was proposed.
Anyway, Terry obviously sees things from a different perspective.
Yeah, perspective, so pulled me to shreds.
But, look, there's a funny thing about that story because in my first year of going from volunteer to full-time at Fair Share,
I got a phone call from the Lord Mayor's Charitable Foundation.
And they said, we've got a business that wants to make a donation to something similar to what you're doing,
and we want to put you forward.
And I said, oh, jeez, thank you.
That's, wow.
Yeah, it's $10,000, and that is a lot of money.
Back then, it was a lot of money for us.
And I said, oh, can I ask what the business is?
And they said, yeah, it's International Power.
They run the Hazelwood Power Station.
Of all the businesses it could have been, I took a deep breath and I thought about it.
I thought, no, we have to say yes to that funding because we're not an advocacy group.
We're not working on climate change at Fair Share.
Gee, do I say something about, yeah.
Look, can you just say that if you're putting us forward that I,
I'm not going to work with the charity?
I mean, as I said, we were a chef and a driver and me back then.
It was tiny.
But just mention that.
Oh, why is that?
They'll know.
Just mention it.
Anyway, we got the $10,000 a week later.
And of course, you ring up the head of corporate affairs at International Power and say,
thank you, because that's what you do.
And he answered the phone and laughed.
He laughed so hard.
He said, when the Lord Mayor's Charitable Foundation recommended you but mentioned your name,
everybody in the office said, we can't give any funding to them.
You know what he was trying to shut down this power station.
We weren't.
But Jim Coots was his name.
And he said, no, because that was Marcus's role.
And he always did it really respectfully and professionally.
Yeah, he disagreed.
He would rather the Hazelwood Power Station have not been admitting what it did.
But he did it very respectfully.
And he's doing something now, which sounds fantastic.
So we are supporting them.
I love it.
And we've got a 14-year now history with that organisation.
Yes.
And that's, you know, it seems like a happier time, Marcus, where you could disagree but have respect,
you know, as opposed to what feels now, I don't agree with you, I want you cancelled.
I want you out and I'll try and run you out of town.
And I love hearing those stories because it feels like they need to come back.
You know, if you were disrespectful and a whole range of other things that had done things underhanded,
you probably didn't deserve the $10,000.
But it sounds like.
Your reputation was strong enough, even on the other side.
And I saw your leadership firsthand a moment ago.
You know, you walked through the kitchens as volunteers from everywhere and you introduced us.
That's Prue.
That's, you know, the warehouse guys.
Clearly you're hands-on enough to know who everyone is, which, again, is one of the great traits we see all the time.
Yeah.
I mean, just going back to that power company, it's ironic now that that company is now French-owned.
The French-based head office said we're pulling out of coal.
Despite how profitable that power station was for them.
And they're very heavily, it's a company called Engie, very heavily in renewable energy generation.
And it's a very different company.
But because of that ability to be able to work with them over these 14 years,
we find ourselves in an incredible partnership with the company.
So in some respects, you could have easily cancelled them, as you said, early on.
But just by working with them, we've done some incredible things.
We've done some incredible things together.
Yeah.
Thanks for sharing it.
It's a great story.
We talk about leaders.
And this question almost seems redundant with you.
How do you positively impact others in your environment?
That's what you do every second of your working life.
But clearly that's a huge part of you.
I mean, how have you gone about that for people listening in what you do day-to-day, positively impacting others?
Well, look, the obvious thing to talk about is improving the diets and the health of people who are doing it tough.
But it's the way we've done it.
And it's by spending time with people who've come forward and heard about us and want to participate and having a conversation with them.
And they're doing it in their own private capacity.
They're doing it through their family.
They're doing it through the business that they work for.
And exploring how you can work together around a common interest.
And so that's where I think why FairShare is so strong.
There's not a vulnerability to, for example, losing funding from one source.
Because there are so many people and organizations that have bought in.
And there's a real stickiness as well.
And quite often in philanthropy, just in that side of things, in Australia, there's a come and go.
And they'll support you for three years and then they'll go.
But there's something about...
There's something about how we've gone about things that have meant they've joined us and they've stuck.
Not necessarily forever, but for much longer than they would have with other organizations.
Why is that?
Is that because their people come and volunteer?
Is it because of your relationships?
Both of those things.
It's...
I once heard one of the most important things you can teach your children is how to say thank you.
And I think that in part comes from feeling generous.
Genuine gratitude.
So when somebody has actually supported us, geez, I'm grateful.
Because it empowers us.
And then it's how you say thank you, how you communicate your gratitude so that you're not just unprofessionally,
but people can hear it in your voice, whether it's an email or a letter or you're having that conversation.
It's about them trying to find a way to actually get them in here.
And like you've seen it today, to get them come in, have a tour through it,
to come in and even jump on the tools for an hour,
to find a way of the CEO of that business that supported us for years to come down with her two teenage daughters
to spend a night on the tools together because she's busy, but she wants to spend time with her kids.
And here's a way of ticking a work box, ticking a community box and doing something with her kids.
So it's one of the great things about Fair Share is that...
You can actually participate.
So I think people have stuck with us because they can be a part of it.
And yeah, I love it when groups come down.
The Laidlaws that were very much behind Collingwood and Hard Yakka.
Great family.
Fantastic family.
And so they have a family foundation that supported us.
They really backed our kitchen garden program.
And if I look at the next generation, John and Betty's children,
Mark's down here in the warehouse every Tuesday in his shorts and his work boots,
helping Ray down there move things around.
Michelle's been in here for years helping in the kitchen once a week.
And then I've got Melissa helping with some of our fundraising.
So the family's really engaged and I just loved it.
And I think if I could say a thing about the family,
when we had two generations,
so the second and the third generation in the kitchen a couple of weeks ago,
on the tools for a night.
So it was a way for that family to come together,
spend time in Fair Share, a charity they support,
and then go out to dinner afterwards.
So, geez, if you've got that connection, it certainly helps.
You don't take it for granted and you work hard to keep it.
I think that helps.
Amazing family story, isn't it?
It's a really successful family.
that find the time to get on the tools, not just give money and feel good about it. I love that
story. We see leaders very conscious, the leaders that we're speaking to around how they create and
share their vision. You sent me some information before I caught up with you today about mission
clarity and the not-for-profit space. It feels like you've got a real sense of what the mission
is and sticking to it. Can you share that with us? Yeah. Look, it's interesting as this
food relief sector has evolved and matured over the last couple of decades.
There are some great organizations and some fantastic people doing good work. But I think what
for me, we needed to find was our niche in that. And for us, it wasn't too difficult. It was around
the cooking bit. And so therefore, if I look at food,
and Oz Harvest and Second Bite and Fair Share, all of us work with businesses that have surplus
food. All of us give food to frontline charities, but only one of us cooks on a scale. And so more
and more, we're having conversations with those other organizations at a strategic level, at an
operational level around Fair Share honing its operations to just that cooking bit. So it means
that Ingham's Chicken can approach Second Bite.
And so we've got probably two to three pallets of chicken breast and Maryland with a day or two
left on it, a week that we can donate to you, but it can't be frozen and it must be cooked
before it's given to a charity. And Second Bite, obviously knowing the value of that chicken,
it's tasty, it's nutritious, wants to do something with it. But the only way they can comply with that
requirement of Ingham's is by passing it through Fair Share. So they said, yes,
they brought Ingham's down here. Ingham's had their
checklist, their notebook, and they looked at our procedures and our facilities and our staff
and said, right, you can have this chicken as long as it passes through Fair Share.
So this is where that mission is really narrowing to the cooking bit. So let Second Bite work with
Ingham's, steward that relationship, collect, bring the chicken to us, we'll cook it. But before that
van of theirs backs out, load it up with three pallets of Fair Share meals and take it out to
the local charity.
When you're taking out the fruit and veg, you're giving them as well. So they've got chicken
casserole, chicken curry, and a whole lot of chicken-based dishes as well. We're not cooking
it in a couple of minutes, but what we cooked the day before. And so that's where we've got
our biggest facility up in Brisbane. And it's there because there's so much surplus food in
Queensland that Foodbank gets offered it. The only solution to them is for it to be cooked.
And to Foodbank's credit, they looked at it and said, well, cooking isn't our,
that's not our expertise. We're warehouses, we're logistics. But gee, that group down at
Fair Share could come and set up up here and we could bookend them. We'll bring the food to them,
they can cook it, and we'll distribute the meals they cook. And so we've got Australia's biggest
charity kitchen up in Brisbane, and we've been working with Foodbank in that way for five years,
and it just makes sense. And it was funny going to a few philanthropists and they said,
yeah, we've supported Foodbank before. We've given grants to Second Bite, we've backed,
Oz Harvest, and we thought we'd done food relief. But what's so unique about this is that you've
teamed up here and you're working with respective strengths of charities, not competing because we
see so much competition, but actually collaborating around your respective strengths.
So it's a great story. I'll come back to that collaboration in a moment because I love that
you're doing it. As you said, there's so much overlap in the charitable space and therefore
lots of wastage, which is the opposite of what you do, your reverse wastage. Curiosity is a term
that we...
Attribute a lot to leaders. They're very curious about how they can self-improve and
they approach their learning and development through it. Does that resonate with you,
the idea of curiosity?
Yeah, I'm not particularly curious though.
And I've heard that a lot as well, you know, from people that just
quite know themselves well enough to know that that's just not their thing.
It's not. I wish I was. I'm not. But gee, I know somebody who is, and I've worked with her for so
well for so many years.
So that's part of what you said about surrounding yourself with people who compliment you.
Yeah. And so her happy spot is at home after dinner with a glass of red wine on the internet,
looking at, I wonder how they do that over there. Oh, gee, I've heard about this model
and coming to work with, I've got this idea or I've seen this being done. And
that's why I value you so much, Kelly, because you've got that curious mind that I don't.
You need it in an organisation, but not everybody needs to be that way. And we've got Kelly.
And it's brilliant, isn't it? That idea of complementary skills and shared values makes
enormous amount of sense. Communicating with clarity is a common dimension of leadership.
And clearly to have those long-term partnerships that you have and saying thank you and being
grateful to those relationships, clearly you've got a really strong communication
bent to how you lead. How would you describe it?
Very simple. As a bachelor living brand, one of,
the most wonderful relationships in my life is a friend, Michael Magazzanich, who was in the media
for many years. And for years, he drilled me in keeping things very simple and rewriting
things I'd written. And it culminated for me in a board meeting one day where Philip Brass,
just a great Australian, who has been a wonderful, yeah, a bit of a guiding light for me over the
years in a quiet way. He was on our board for 12 years. And he once commented in a board meeting,
Marcus, your writing is very simple. I didn't know how to take that. I thought,
is that a criticism or a compliment? But I reflect on Michael's coaching of me to write
in very simple English and talk in very basic ways. Because in the case of FairShare,
it's not particularly complicated. And when I'm writing a grant application or a report to a
funder or something, it's keeping it simple. I think that makes it accessible.
Let what you're doing speak for itself rather than trying to dress it up into something it
might not be or to make it sound really smart. So I've seen a few consultants' reports where
some big firms have done some work for us pro bono. And I look at the language and thought,
jeez, I could never write this. But I'm not trying to either. So I think, I mean, for us in this
space, it's what's the need? What is the organisation doing about it? What's different about it?
And
I think with communication in the not-for-profit space as well,
you've got to inject a bit of yourself into it. So what's your story? Why are you doing this?
And talking about your journey a bit, I believe that's important. Not everybody agrees with me
on that one. And I think also then impact as well. So those things, I think, are critical.
And I think we do that pretty well. We're not out there
in the public limelight enough, but I think that when people see us
and whether it's in what we post on our social media channels
and our newsletters, it's communicated pretty clearly and plainly
and it's accessible.
Scott Pope, the barefoot investor who spoke,
he sold more books than anyone in Australia, Scotty Pope,
and people say to him, it's such simple writing, it's so easy,
anyone could do it.
And there's genius.
Yeah, if anyone could, you'd sell however many million books paid
for your soul now, but the simplicity in the language
and the genius in making something, finance that bamboozles a lot of us
as simple as he did, it sounds like you've got a very similar understanding
of how to communicate.
I want to come back because it seems to be a big challenge
in the not-for-profit and the charity space is that too many people
doing the same thing or trying to do the same thing
with limited resources.
You're incredibly open about that.
You mentioned OzHarvest and Foodbank and SecondBite.
To find that collaboration, how important are those collaborations to you?
Because we see that leaders are really now understanding
that that's where a lot of strength lies.
Look, absolutely, we can have so much more impact
and we can use finite resources available to us so much more efficiently
if we are collaborating.
Look, it's not all kumbaya.
There's still some pretty dysfunctional collaboration happening
in our sector.
It does my head in.
It really annoys me.
But I think with collaboration, you work with those people
and organisations where you have common values and a common mission
and a genuine appetite for collaboration.
It's not everywhere.
And I've found over the years that at times with organisations,
the leadership has been very competitive of other organisations.
And then you get a change of leadership and all of a sudden it flips.
And for me, it's flipped both ways.
It's gone from being highly collaborative to being just the door shut
to being really competitive and then opening up in wonderful collaborations.
So, so much it depends on the leadership of other organisations
as to whether you can collaborate with them or not.
And I think that in our space, it's going to be really interesting
to see where we're at in five or ten years' time because you, yeah,
yeah, there's a lot of collaboration.
Who knows where that collaboration goes?
Yeah, you can bring a lot of things together to make things more efficient.
But at the same time, you know, mergers aren't the answer to everything.
We have the title of this is Empowering Leadership
and yours is an incredible story of leadership.
In that spirit, who has been the greatest leader in your life?
Oh, goodness.
There have been a few.
I think one of the people who,
I've found most inspiring over the years is the person who's succeeding me
in the CEO role at Fairshare.
I think we talked about self-awareness before and, yeah, from, I mean,
I know I'm a mobiliser.
I love engaging people externally and bringing them into Fairshare
and having them be part of what we do.
I've been lucky to have people join and stay.
And we've got a really strong team operationally.
And as our long-term president, David Harris, says,
you're lucky because you can just hamble blindly over your shoulder
and know that Kelly or any one of a number of people will catch that and run with it.
You don't need to look over your shoulder.
But, look, Fairshare's now around 70 staff,
the equivalent of about 45 full-time,
and internal leadership's as important as external leadership.
And it's...
It's not a space that I play naturally in.
And I looked at it and thought, gee,
I could train myself to do that differently, to do it better.
I could spend time on it.
And then somebody became available.
And I'm speaking about Paul Conroy, who's taken over from me.
And I thought, gee,
the team will be so much stronger if he played at CEO than if I did.
And you'd look at this in your footy career
and somebody would come along and over a few years you'd think,
yeah,
that'd be a good thing.
And if I play better in that position
than the person we've played there for five years,
the team will be stronger, so we're changing it.
And that's how I've looked at this.
Lucky enough to have Paul come in.
And from day one, even though he said, I'll come in as COO,
he acted like he was CEO, which is exactly what I wanted.
And it's what the organisation needed.
And internally, the staff responded so positively to it.
And I just watch him with awe.
He's exactly what the organisation needs.
He's exactly what the organisation needed to be, FairShare 2.0.
And it was a funny one because a number of people have said to me,
but FairShare was stronger than it ever had been.
It was doing more important work and doing it so well.
And you've changed it.
And there's a risk there.
And I think one of the things for us is you don't want to throw the baby out
with the bathwater.
There was a real magic there.
I don't know why, but it was something.
But you don't want to lose that.
But to see,
to see how Paul's now leading the organisation, it's wow.
And I've never worked with somebody who I've had as much respect.
Not easy, but I just see the organisation even stronger for that.
And that takes incredible self-awareness and self-reflection.
Most people in the past, to give up that title, to give up the hierarchy,
I know you shrug and you think, you know, that isn't important to you,
which again is reflective of the type of leadership we're loving sharing
and those stories we're loving.
If I can find someone to do that role better, you know, that makes sense,
but you still have to be, you know,
in touch with your ego and a range of other things to make that happen.
We've got a wonderful guy who's just about to step onto our board.
And he's, I'm not going to say who it is, but really impressive guy.
And he said to me, Marcus, I've watched over the years, many founders,
and I didn't start Fair Share, got involved very early on, but didn't start it.
He said many founders haven't got the self-awareness,
when an organisation that's successful and gets to a point,
to know that it needs something else.
And even if they do have the self-awareness,
they can't necessarily step away from that role.
And to me, leadership is not about a title.
So I see myself in the leadership role at Fair Share.
That's not to undermine Paul's role as CEO,
but we've got a wonderful partnership.
We bring different things to the organisation.
And,
and I think that just makes Fair Share stronger.
And I know that I can have even more impact now without being CEO.
And that might sound a bit odd,
but I think we're going to have so much more impact through him in that role.
And so it's, it's about this, how you,
how you play the team to have the most impact.
Yeah.
It makes sense.
Easier said than done for a lot of,
I'm thinking of Andrew Bassett,
the founder of Seek, who I interviewed on this podcast.
And, you know, incredibly humble, incredibly successful Seek.
He's a $10 billion.
A company by market cap.
And the thing he wanted to speak about most that he felt was the best thing he'd ever done
was replace himself as CEO in the,
in the past 18 months.
And,
and he spoke the same language as you,
that humility.
It's Ian Narev,
who's the former CEO of the Commonwealth Bank.
He can do things that I couldn't do.
He,
he does it better than I could ever do,
which for people who've had great success,
it takes great humility to,
to understand that.
We love the idea of collaboration in current leadership.
And the sense that,
that is where a lot of sweet spots lie.
If you,
if you could collaborate with anyone on anything,
I'm assuming fair share is where we're going to go with this.
Has there been a partner?
I mean,
you,
you casually connect with incredible leaders all around the country.
Has there been one collaboration that you thought of?
I could,
could get that going.
That would make a difference.
Yeah.
Look,
the pandemic's been a real opportunity for us to rethink how we,
I'm going to say staff the kitchen.
So,
before,
before the pandemic,
we had one and a half thousand regular volunteers.
We had the same number on the waiting list.
It was easy.
One person retired and a friend of theirs had heard about it and they stepped in and it was just,
you know,
it was easy.
Volunteering is not returning to charities in the numbers that they were pre-pandemic,
which is harder for the charitable sector.
And that's an opportunity for us because it means that we can look at how we can diversify our volunteering.
So,
and,
and Paul's really leading this and I so agree with it.
So can we have more ethnic diversity in the kitchen,
volunteering on our kitchen gardens,
driving our vans?
Can we have younger people?
So people maybe not staying with us for 15 years as volunteers,
maybe for three years while they're at university.
Can we have people who are recipients of our meals coming in and helping as well?
And long,
I haven't answered your question,
but I think that last bit is where I'm interested in going.
And my mother was an academic up at Melbourne university and did a lot of work with in Arnhem Land.
And a few years ago she said,
we've got a group of indigenous kids coming down to Melbourne for a week.
And could they come down and spend half a day in the fair share kitchen?
And I pushed her on and said,
well,
look,
the,
the staff and volunteers would love that,
but why?
And they want to go to the MCG and they were going there.
She said,
because they've got tough lives.
Yeah,
there's no hiding that,
but there are others in Australia that are doing it tough as well.
And I want them to say that,
and I want them to be part of something that's helping others who are doing it tough.
I think there'd be a really,
it'd be a really interesting experience for them.
Anyway,
we did it.
The staff loved it.
The volunteers thought it was great.
The kids left and I was speaking to mum a few days later and I said,
how did that,
how did that go?
And she said,
bar none,
the best experience they had in Melbourne was volunteering at fair share.
Wow.
I said,
I don't believe that it would have been going to the MCG,
but she said,
no,
it was,
it was exactly what I wanted.
And so I've reflected on that and to be able to take some people who yeah,
are doing it tough.
And who have received or are receiving our meals and getting them in,
I think would be very empowering because if you think about it,
it's pretty challenging having to ask for and receiving a meal when you're doing it tough.
There's a real,
there's a power imbalance.
There's a dignity thing there,
a dignity challenge for us as a giver.
And if you can then give people the opportunity to then be part of helping others,
it's not a pain,
back thing.
It's just,
I think that's a very empowering thing.
And a beautiful moment for me one day in a fair share was a school group walking into the kitchen.
They'd been inducted,
they'd washed their hands,
they're putting on their aprons and a young secondary school girl just pulled me aside and said,
thanks for doing what you do and for the opportunity to come in today.
Um,
our family received some fair share meals when we were doing a tough a few years ago.
So it's really special for me now coming in and being able to help somebody else.
Amazing.
An incredible note to,
uh,
to finish on,
Marcus,
um,
congratulations,
uh,
on the wonderful work that you do and the contribution you make.
It's inspiring.
And,
um,
I love the opportunity to sort of walk through today and,
uh,
see it firsthand and understand the impact that you're having every single day.
It's a great leadership story and I appreciate you sharing with me.
Well,
you talk about walking,
Luke,
um,
we've got our chefs walking about 10 kilometers a day in the kitchen.
So what we do is we mobilize,
um,
our supporter base to walk for fair share and fundraise for fair share every October.
Um,
so they set themselves goals over two weeks.
we,
uh,
we're going to walk a hundred kilometers or 150 kilometers and get them to get their friends behind fair share.
So my challenge is to you,
will you walk a hundred kilometers in,
uh,
October for fair share over a couple of weeks and rally your community?
Sign me up,
Marcus.
And in any way I can,
uh,
contribute,
I'd love to,
uh,
to be part of,
it's pretty close to home,
uh,
for me and,
very small thing to walk for,
uh,
for a great cause like yours.
So sign me up,
hold me to account on that.
One,
that's a pretty big effort for the chefs every day.
That's,
that's the scale of your kitchens,
isn't it?
I've got to taste a lot of food.
So the calorie,
calorie intake's probably a bit high.
Thanks again,
mate.
Great to see you.
Absolute pleasure.
Empowering leaders was presented by me,
Luke Darcy,
produced by Matt Dwyer with audio production by Darcy Thompson.
Start your leadership journey.
I encourage you to go to a leader collective.com.
Take our empowering leaders indicator tool and understand the impact you have on your environment.
Join us at a leader to learn,
lead,
and collaborate.
Listener.