I remember when I was moving into position to catch a wave, I was so scared and nervous that
I had to literally rewire the process of what I was thinking about because I was triggering
thoughts of what if you fall off and all this kind of stuff. And I was literally trying to
change that process in that moment while I was moving towards it. And it was so intense. I've
never felt so scared before in my life, but I remember my heart pounding that hard that my
eyeballs were pulsing with my heartbeat. And I still to this day, I can't describe ever feeling
so fearful. This week's guest is legendary Australian big wave surfer Mark Visser. You're
going to hear Mark's insights into overcoming fear are fascinating to me and how when you
understand the techniques as he explains, your life can improve dramatically. Mark also explains
the advice he gives his mindset coach to people like 11-time world surfing champion Kelly Slater
and also the detail and preparation.
To ride a 40-foot wave off the coast of Hawaii in total darkness in the middle of the night
is an extraordinary story in itself. Mark Visser inspires the work we do at Alita. Check out our
Alita Connect program. We curate groups of five to six leaders from unique and diverse backgrounds
like legendary big wave surfer Mark Visser. We'd love you to get involved. Book a discovery call
today. Head to alitacollective.com. Thanks to Jason Nicholas and his team from Temper Bedding.
It is NASA approved, the world's best in bedding, great leaders,
understand the importance of a good night's sleep. Sleep on a mattress like Temper and it
will change your life. Mark Visser is a legendary Australian big wave surfer, author and mindset
coach. Mark made history by surfing one of the world's biggest waves that jaws break Maui in
the Hawaiian Islands in total darkness. A true world first achievement known globally as Night
Rider. Mark's chase to ride the biggest waves in the world have seen him dive out of aeroplanes
with jet skis and remote waters around the globe. For the past 30 years, he's been a
mindset coach to some of the world's most successful individuals and organizations. Working as a personal
coach for world champion Kelly Slater, Australian SAS, the US Navy SEALs, Olympic athletes, sporting
teams and business professionals. He has a huge passion for helping individuals connect to their
ultimate self. Mark, great pleasure to catch up with you. Great to be here. How does a young boy
who grew up in country Victoria, hundreds of kilometers away from the water, go on to be
one of the world's most revered big wave surfers? Probably the fear of
just being so terrified in a space that I wanted to do whatever I could to get out of it.
That's probably the best summary because when I was younger, I had an experience where I literally
nearly drowned and that just changed the scope of my life going forward. You know, we were in the
country and then we moved to the Sunshine Coast in Queensland, which is a tropical environment.
And I basically spent my life trying to overcome that fear of that water experience that rattled
me as a kid. But then I kind of made it almost a point to
prove to myself, I've gotten over this, I've gotten over this. And I didn't realize that that
consumed me in such a way that it turned into a career and a never-ending passion. And then
just overcoming fear itself became its own sense of a passion.
Mark, a bit more detail on that. It was a feed trough effectively full of water, is that correct?
Yeah, sheep's trough.
Sheep's trough. And how old were you and how close did you come to not being with us?
Yeah, the details on that, it's probably, I wouldn't remember it because I was three. So I was three years old.
I was eating.
I was eating a peach, dropped it into the sheep's trough and apparently just dove in head first for
it. And my mother told me that I was holding onto the peach underwater. And then basically they
weren't there, but my older brother saved my life. He pulled me out by my hair and he would have been
young. He would have only been maybe eight or seven years old himself. So for him to have done
that, he literally saved my life. I could have easily drowned in that situation. But mum said to
me, I wouldn't have a bar. I wouldn't have a bar. I wouldn't have a bar. I wouldn't have a bar.
For about a year or so after that. So it really must have rattled me to the core. And I don't
remember the experience, but it's really odd to say this. I remember the feeling. So I would go to
the ocean years later and have this elevated heart rate, not knowing why, or this fear of just
feeling like I'm not in control here and not knowing where does that come from or why. And I didn't
actually know it until years after that my mother told me about that. And then I went, oh, it was
like a feeling that came over me. It was like, oh, that all makes sense. So, you know, as a young
person, sometimes you might remember actual, the memory of a, of an image of something, but you
remember the feeling and that feeling was ingrained in me like no other. And that's, that's really
the being at the forefront of my mind, trying to push through that, that barrier, the majority of
my life. So much research we now mark into childhood trauma and the fact that we are dealing
with that scar tissue for our lives. And often it's unconscious. I mean, you're a great example
of actually unconsciousness. I mean, you're a great example of actually unconsciousness. I mean,
consciously experiencing that because you were too young, now consciously knowing about it and
that driving your whole life outcomes. It's a fascinating study. Family moved to the Sunshine
Coast. I suppose every kid you're going to school with has got a surfboard or the water dictates
life on the Sunshine Coast. So did you feel, hey, I've got this fear. I don't even know where it
comes from, but I've got to deal with it. Is that what drove you? Yeah. And full outcast, you know,
like feeling like every, like you said, you nailed it. Every single person had a bodyboard, surfboard,
confident, and the water was a fun place. Whereas I'm like, oh, I like the water too. But then as
soon as there was waves, I was like, I'm out of my depth and, and really felt like a, an outcast in
like, I don't know this world and I don't understand this space, but I'll try and play along. And then
every time, you know, you're exposed to situations, I remember just feeling like, oh, I'm so out of my
league here. And I almost sort of said to myself, oh, I'm never going to be someone that is going
to play in that space. Cause I, my parents enrolled me in a junior lifeguard program,
obviously called Nippers. The first exercise was something like you had to swim out to a can
and that was just so full on. So I remember thinking to myself, ah, I'll just focus on
the beach sprints. I'll just focus on the things that I knew I could do well. I felt like majority
of probably around about 14 or so, I felt like I had this connection to the ocean where
the ocean was almost felt like a person that I knew, which is really odd to say that,
like it was someone that was saying like, you're welcome in this space, come in this space. Yet I
was the most awkward person to feel that way. Like if anyone else had said that, who grew up surfing
or grew up doing things, you'd go, of course it's in your blood or whatever. Whereas it's not, you
know, but I felt that, that, that feeling of just feeling like this thing is calling me or I feel
safe here, but at the same time, I'm looking over every shoulder and not feeling like I'm safe.
So you might be better placed than anyone on understanding overcoming fear from nearly
drowning, terrified of water to putting yourself in the most extreme situations in the ocean that
anyone in the world is doing. What's the secret to overcoming fear? The secret I think is accepting
that you don't actually ever do. And I mean that in all sincerity, because the things that I have
done, like the levels I have pushed myself to as an individual to essentially overcome fear,
like surfing, surfing, surfing, surfing, surfing, surfing, surfing, surfing, surfing, surfing, surfing,
surfing jaws at night and things like that. I was essentially trying to, and I didn't know it at the
time, but I was trying to prove to that inner child that I'd gotten over this fear. And when
you do those things, you'd think you would be free. You'd think you'd, you'd finally have let
that go. And there were moments of that feeling, but then every time I'd try and ride a bigger
wave or take on a new task, I still felt those feelings of fear. And then I still heard those
little voices of doubt. But then as I broke down the process, I've understood that I'm not
understanding how I push through the barrier or limitations of fear. I found myself starting to
feel somewhat free and then feeling like a sense of, okay, there's a lot of possibilities here.
And then from that space, then I realized you don't ever really get over fear. You just accept
that it's part of the process and that you will break through to the other side at some point.
And that other side of it is where we can live at our highest level. And that's what I got excited
about. Because when I understood that, I was like, I'm going to do this. I'm going to do this. I'm going
Like, I can share this with other people.
It's not just about riding big waves.
It's about understanding and acknowledging that every single person has that fear or
that little voice of doubt stopping us from doing things that we can do and that we have
to just understand that it is a process that we will break through, but it's also enjoyable
because when you break through it, you're living life on the highest frequency or vibration
and that's when it's like, this is amazing, you know, and that's the part that I love
the most.
There's an old saying, Mark, that was going through my head as you were talking there,
on the other side of fear and challenge is everything you've ever wanted in life and
it sounds to me that that's your life story, to push through this ultimate fear and now
you're someone that can mentor, you can ride big waves, you can teach people that other
parts of your life, you're always going to have that self-doubt and that fear, but to
face it, walk through it, never goes away is what you're saying, you're always going
to have to deal with it, but.
Yeah, and I think it's healthy.
There's been one time.
There's been one time that I didn't feel fear and I was at a place in South Africa
and we surfed this wave, it was a really big wave and that day was like 70 foot and we
went to another spot and it was about 50 foot and a friend of mine was doing an interview
for his sponsor and one of the other guys said to me, hey, do you want to just catch
a wave at this spot while your mate's doing this interview?
And I was like, yeah, yeah, I'll just, for sure, you know, give me one wave or something,
just something to do.
And I had two life jackets on because I was wearing his because he was doing his interview
and I was like, yeah, I'll just, for sure, give me one wave or something, just something
I thought, I'll just clip his on and that, which is over the top, right?
We didn't have inflation vests then, or that wasn't a thing.
It's just a normal standard jet ski life jacket.
And this guy towed me into this wave and it's about 50 foot and I went down it and I looked
down the line and I realized I was way too deep and I wasn't going to make it.
And because I'd been surfing something that seems so much bigger, I went, I'll just go
anyway.
And I didn't have that feeling of fear and I went it and ate shit so bad and got so hammered
and got so ragdolled.
And it was probably one of the worst wipeouts ever.
And I remember thinking to myself, if I ever don't feel fear again, that's not a good thing.
So I almost use it as a sense of heightened awareness.
And I just, the thing is, what I've learned is I don't want to be consumed by it.
Yes, it will be present, but I don't need to live in that state.
Like, you know, there's an elevated emotion and I'll call that fear.
I'll call it stress, whatever you want, but acknowledge it, work with it, but don't let
it consume you.
And that's, that's the little difference.
That's this change for me.
I love that you've put yourself into the most extreme situations, as you said, to prove
to that inner child that you could deal with that.
I mean, I've been to Jaws break, sat on the beach, by the way, Evan.
The idea of even being on a board out there is terrifying to me.
To do it at nighttime is beyond belief.
To catch a 40 foot wave, and I love how you talk about 50 foot, 40 foot, that's eight
story buildings, nine, 10, 12 story buildings of water that are simply terrifying.
You did that at nighttime.
How was the heart rate on that night?
I was so scared and the buildup to that, like I was so scared that my body was so
overwhelmed with fear that I could barely function.
Like I could barely stand up in a position without just feeling so like over overwhelmed.
And I literally had to use my own medicine, so to speak, like the things that I'd learned.
I remember when I was moving into position to catch a wave, I was so scared and nervous.
That I had to literally rewire the process of what I was thinking about because I was
triggering thoughts of what if you fall off and all this kind of stuff.
And I was literally trying to change that process in that moment while I was moving
towards it.
And it was so intense.
I've never felt so scared before in my life, but I remember my heart pounding that hard
that my eyeballs were pulsing with my heartbeat.
And I, and I still, to this day, I can't describe ever feeling so fearful, but, but at the same
time, there was, it felt like I'd said to myself, there's no other choice.
I look back on that experience and think maybe I didn't need to go that far and that hard
for sure.
And if I was advising someone else, I'd probably be don't, you don't need to do that.
But what I was really searching for and I didn't understand it was self-acceptance,
you know, and self-worth because that wasn't strong enough to identify some other things
that were going on.
And I reckon when I look back on it, I'm like, there were some key indicators that were very
obvious to me now that I'm like, right, there's a, there's a.
There's a person there that's so hell bent on proving a point that they probably don't
need to go to this extent to do it.
Another phrase in my mind, if you risk nothing, you risk everything as well too in life, don't
you?
And it's, it's like the idea of wrapping yourself in the corner and staying away from any danger
has some appeal to it, but that's not a life anyone wants to live effectively.
I mean, you're going to the other extreme and you've got some other big ideas.
I've seen vision of you pushing jet skis out the back of planes with parachutes attached
to them.
You skydiving out after them in the ocean.
What's that project all about?
Well, that one's a project called Operation Deep Blue.
And that was basically the biggest wave ever ridden to date is 86 feet at a place called
Nazare in Portugal.
And year after year, that place would always get the big, the big wave of water.
I don't know if you've seen it, but there's a little lighthouse.
I've seen it.
It's famous.
It's a beautiful image, isn't it?
The lighthouse off the coast of Spain.
Have you surfed that way?
I've surfed Portugal.
Yeah, I've surfed it.
Yeah.
So there's a little red lighthouse and it wraps off Portugal.
Huge mountains.
Kind of cliff thing.
And over and over, that wave has sort of dominated the big wave space.
86 foot's the record, isn't it?
The record.
And every time it'd be said, oh, this one's 100.
This one's 100.
But it always falls short.
And it made me think, there's got to be another place.
There's got to be another way.
And then so on my journey working with other individuals and helping other individuals,
I worked for some military groups.
And then I got introduced to a head admiral and basically said, can you tell me where
you tell boats never to go?
There's got to be somewhere.
There's got to be some areas somewhere that you're like, that's a spot that we don't want
to look at or there's been shipwrecks or something.
And anyway, long story short, I got access to some information and I found a few spots
that had potential sightings or readings of a 30 meter, 100 foot wave.
And then I had to wait years, like literally two years, for each one of those to light
up and then fly a reconnaissance plane or something or go out to sea in a boat to see
if they were actually real.
And a lot of them had cracks.
Crazy hazards, like rocks, like in front of them.
So when it broke, if you rode it, you'd get cheese grated, you know, or it'd just be a
suicide mission.
And some of them might have just not been real.
It could have been what's called a rogue wave.
So that was the thought was, is it actually real?
My thoughts were they might be in the surfing terms, it's called a fat burger, right?
It's the term of a fat burger is a wave.
It's so big and it just claps at the top and it doesn't really stand up top to bottom.
And it could just be this rogue kind of fat-ish wave, which isn't that appealing.
It's not appealing to ride.
And then there was one that stood out that actually looked like a top to bottom huge
wave.
And I waited and waited for the window to go to that.
And then I missed days that would have been pumping in other areas.
And, you know, and people would, friends at the time were like, well, why aren't you going
to that swell?
Or what are you doing?
And I was just so like interested in exploring and seeing what was real.
And I believe I've found one that does stack up.
The only problem is it's so far.
From land that when I first sort of thought how I'd get there would be to send a ship
out and it would be a four day trip because it's literally like, you know, 4,000 nautical
miles from land or a point of land.
But then someone was sort of saying, well, the forecast changed and, you know, you're
two days into that, you could keep turning around.
So the likelihood of you being able to time it would be pretty hard.
Almost, you know, you could be sailing around for years trying to, trying to get this.
So maybe you could fly a plane in, you know, like a strike mission and then parachute
everything into that location.
So then for me, like I've spent my life trying to overcome the fear of water and then I'm
just now figuring out how to skydive because I'm like, all right, that's, that's the way
to do it.
And then I'm just shitting myself all over again.
But I learned a lot, you know, so I'm going through the process and I must've been 20
skydives in just going, I hate this sport.
I don't feel safe.
I nearly crashed into like hangers and stuff coming down, landing.
And I was just over and over just going, I'm going back through it all again, the same
childhood.
Years, but I'm older and smarter and I'm learning what's happening and I'm seeing my
own flaws and then how to deal with it.
So that was really an absolute blessing because it was like, I'd, I got to go through it
again, but I was re-equipped with new tools.
And then that started the quest for learning, you know, like I went and worked with a lady
called Kate Reardon, different like healers in Ubud and Bali, all sorts of different people
from, you know, ladies that had spent, one lady spent 14 years studying one section of
the brain.
And I was really determined to figure out why is my body and mind doing certain things
and why am I feeling certain ways and how do I flip that around in an instant or is
it possible?
I just kept, because I was able to use myself as a real example.
And a lot of the time when I'd worked with say a psychologist or mindset coaches, they,
some of them would draw their conclusions from textbooks or from books or knowledge.
Whereas some of the really good ones had real life experiences.
Or lived out family experiences where they'd learned their craft.
And to me, that was more fascinating because I was like, that's a different level of learning
when your life or someone else's life is on the line that changes the way you make decisions
and textbooks won't give you that.
So that's what really drove that passion to want to go down there.
And that has made you the go-to person for the likes of 11 time surfing world champion
Kelly Slater and Simon Goodwin's a legendary AFL premiership player.
Yeah.
And had a remarkable time as coach of the Melbourne football club, broken records there.
And you've been in his corner.
What sort of advice are you giving to people at that level who know success, they know
themselves, what are you teaching them?
Well, first of all, I'd say I wouldn't be their go-to guy because there's so many people
they could go to, but definitely connected with them and was able to offer them some
advice.
And really, I guess for Kelly, it's like a sounding board, like the guy's an 11 time
world champion.
Already achieved so much, but there's another space that I paid a bit more attention to,
which is outside of the sport of surfing.
And I was able to offer a different insight, which I didn't think.
And I was definitely thinking to myself, how am I going to help a guy that's already so
accomplished?
But that's sort of what it was.
It was a different insight to a world that they hadn't seen.
And particularly with Simon Goodwin, Goody is now someone's great friend of mine.
Same with Kelly.
But when I first...
When I first started with him, the perspective that I had was so different from the one that
he knew.
And I thought, he's going to think I'm so far out there in what I'm thinking that he
might just go, this guy's batshit crazy.
And it might be too hard to relay the information.
But what I really work on and how I really help people is becoming the best version of
themselves, but stripping that back, pulling back layers of fear, which is also linked
really closely to ego.
And neither of these people had that.
But teaching them, because ego comes in two parts, not standing up when you should, and
then also blurting out when you shouldn't.
But both those two people were probably on the opposite side of that scale.
But understanding that and understanding the patterns of that and being able to share with
them a totally different insight was probably really refreshing.
And particularly for Goody, because in a world of footy, and you'd know this better than
anyone, you're surrounded by people that all understand the same things.
And when I come in, it's like, I'm not talking.
I'm not talking about anything that he knows, which is probably refreshing.
And I'm not giving him information based on previous football or those kind of experiences.
So it was really, he was able to kind of let his guard down for me to really help him.
But it was great because the Goody that I know today is a completely different guy to
the one that I met five, six years ago, because he works so hard.
And I threw things at him again and again and again.
And he, to his credit, he was the one that put in the work.
He was the one that said, okay, I'm going to, I'm going to try and work and change that.
And again, and he, he grew so much in such a short space.
And by the time they won the first flag in, I think it was 56 years or something, it might
be wrong, but about that kind of period, he was a different character.
You know, I'd talk to him to things that it would be embarrassing to say at first, you
know, talking about energy stuff, that's the space that I'd play in, you know, and it would
sound too like woo woo.
We're out there.
And, uh, he would then talk back to me in that way because he understood it.
And it was kind of funny because early days, you know, that, that, that the person I met
is different, is a different person now.
And even to see him cop criticism for things that he has nothing to do with, but how well
he's handled it and how, um, centered he's stayed through it.
And then, you know, being such a great role model to so many players.
And now he's really such a strong shining light in that space.
It's really,
really rewarding, you know, uh, but he's the one that deserves the credit for it because
he had to put in the work.
Yeah.
He's got great composure.
Goody, hasn't he?
He's been, you're watching him under enormous pressure.
He handles himself incredibly well and deserves the success.
It's been great.
So you said something fascinating about ego.
I just want to pick up on it.
It's resonating with me.
Two sides of ego.
You describe you either don't stand up when you should for your ego or you blurt things
out when you shouldn't.
Yeah.
What do you mean?
What do you mean by that?
It's well, in a sense, like there's, there's.
The fear of failure, right?
So there'll be the person where their ego gets in the way and says, no, no, you shouldn't,
you shouldn't be up there.
You shouldn't be leading from the front.
You just stay back here.
That is a form of ego too.
That is crushing you from the, the, the skills that you have.
You're suppressing something that you could.
So your ego won't let you be the person you are because you've framed yourself in a way
that you put a lid on yourself effectively.
Correct.
And then the other side of it is you'll project something because you're also fear.
Yeah.
The fear of not being something, not being enough.
So you'll see the egotistical person say, oh, I'm this, this, and this.
They're saying it because they're afraid that maybe I'm not.
Yeah.
And if I say this, that maybe everyone will believe me.
So both come back to the same person, the same, you know, but you've got to understand
that there's two parts of it.
And when you see that, you're like, ah, that's really interesting because then you can really
help someone.
But they, with everything and all the different people I've worked with over the years, awareness
heals.
So you have to be aware of it to even start healing yourself.
We always talk about that as a club, a self-awareness club, but you can't actually open your account
without self-awareness.
So I want to ask you this question.
You've had great success in so many areas of your life.
What does success mean to you?
Short answer, to be happy.
Because if you're happy, you're not hanging on to things or, oh, if only it was this,
or if only it was that.
If you can, at the end of the day, go big smile on your face and go, you know, it's
a good day, or I'm looking forward to doing this, that's got to be the trait of happiness.
And I think Fijians do it better.
You know, you don't have to spend long in Fiji to realize the secret to life is happiness
because they live that life all the time in a way.
And we all have these financial goals or all these other goals.
Yes, you can have them all too, but you've got to be able to enjoy the process.
So I think the secret to that would be able to be ultra present in every moment to, you
know, to like, if I look back at some of the things that I've done and go, oh, geez, that
was an amazing achievement.
What do I wish I could have done better?
The answer is always.
Being able to enjoy the process a bit more, you know, instead of being fearful of, is
that enough?
How will that be perceived?
Or, you know, the young version of myself, you know, if you could go back and talk to
him, the advice would be, mate, just enjoy every day of this and enjoy your failures
because from that is what you're going to learn to be that better version of you too.
And it's hard pill to swallow.
Yeah, Matt, we say the term a lot, success leaves clues.
And I love talking in these forums because, you know, your story is amazing.
And to me, of what you've been able to come and at the coalface of understanding fear is
such a fascinating term for me.
But we see these patterns around what different leaders look like.
And I want to ask you a handful of questions now.
And it probably comes back to what you said.
We talk about self-leadership.
That's hard to lead someone else without a sense of your own self-leadership.
What do you think about that?
100% spot on.
You know, you cannot like stand up and be a person that's, you know, projecting this
or that without having that inner self-worth and self-love.
And that's exactly right.
And that's what I could see.
That I lacked myself or, and I see it in a lot of leaders, you know, you've, and that's
what I specialize in helping people is getting that person to be the best version of them
first, because then you can integrate that into a team environment.
And without that, how do you expect others to believe you or follow you if you don't
believe in yourself?
Yeah, I love that you keep saying that, inspiring people to be the best version of themselves.
Comparison is the thief of joy, isn't it?
If we're comparing ourselves to someone else, it's a economy that is never going to work.
People like you are constantly onto being positive.
You've in the impact of others around them and they're really focused on that positive
impact on others in their environment.
How have you gone about that?
Look, I probably have to be honest and say there's times that I'll crack the shits too,
but that's the beauty of that too.
You know, just accepting being who you are, but I think it's just constantly looking for
that opportunity to say to yourself, is there an opportunity to grow here or are we capped
out?
Like these projects that I've worked on and the ones that I'm working on still, I won't
be afraid of.
It not going ahead as long as I've given it all that I've got.
But that's an interesting phrase right there, giving it all that you've got.
Because if you can walk off and go, okay, there's nothing else that can be done.
That is a question that lasted four years in the process of wanting to ride the world's
biggest wave at night because it failed so many times over and over.
And I used to climb up onto my roof because I trained at night at 12 o'clock because we're
riding out in the night to test this stuff out.
And I'd climb up on the roof because no one would hear me.
And I'd ponder like,
you know, what went wrong there?
What went wrong there?
And a lot of time I thought, I'm a nutcase.
I've gone too far with what I'm doing.
And I wasn't prepared to climb off the roof until I'd sort of decided, all right, is there
nothing else that can be done?
Like, is this project a complete flop?
But I always, when I asked that question, I always went, I haven't tried this.
And the depth of that question, man, that can span out a lifetime.
So you'd be prepared to answer it if you're going to ask it, I'll say.
You've had some big vision.
You've had some big visions to do some crazy things.
How have you gone about, you know, creating and sharing those visions with others to bring
them to life?
Transparency, I think.
Like to, to have visions and I never see them as crazy.
I see them as calculated and the process of, you know, minimizing fear in every single
element to make sure it can be done safely.
But to have someone else share that vision, you have to be really transparent.
You have to be so open because a lot of people would say, well, what does your wife think?
You know, how does, surely she's going to be freaking out by this side of things.
And I'm like, I don't know.
She doesn't.
And then if you ask why, it's because she knows what's going on.
She sees the level of training that we do.
She sees the information that's happening in the background.
She knows how, how hard we're working.
So when someone says, I bet you that's scary to her, she straight away knows they're minimized
fear and stress in those areas.
So that is not a high risk factor.
It's, it's 4%, 5%, you know, we've broken it down.
So when everyone in the team understands that process and we're all along for that journey
and we've, we all know that.
We all understand what we're doing and how we're doing it.
It's such a strong, united force.
It's hard to break.
And when you see a sporting team or a business group have that same level of understanding
together, that's a lethal force.
And you don't want to mess with someone like that because they will, they will take you
down every time.
I love you went straight to transparency, isn't it?
If you're completely 100% transparent with everyone and they understand that you're not
crazy, you value your life as much as everyone else.
Then I can understand that you've been able to break that down.
As you said.
So curiosity is a word that we see a lot.
And through curiosity, we see people like you are constantly learning and developing
themselves.
Does that resonate with you?
Yeah.
And I think you have to be, and that's also letting go of the, the ego.
Like at no point do I ever consider myself in a space where, you know, I've, I've learned
enough.
It's like, you've, you've always got to keep learning and whether that's being a better
father, um, friend, whatever that is.
And in, you know, we're always learning.
And you, I think the moment that you stop is probably when.
Um, when your time's up, because when you, if I think, if you think, you know, everything,
that's probably when you're going to get a pretty quick reality check.
You're a much sought after keynote speaker.
You've just come today from a presentation in front of 800.
Yeah.
I'd love to say I always dress like this, but.
I love how sharp you are, mate.
The surfer with the, uh, with the business attire.
Well, well done, mate.
You're making me feel, uh, decidedly underdressed, but, uh, how about you communicating with
clarity?
How's your strategy been on, on that communication style?
Yeah.
I think it's.
It's just being okay to be me, you know, sharing it in a way where I'm extremely vulnerable
about who I am, what I've done, my failures and, um, the process of how it was done.
And there's a real genuineness to share that with other people to help them connect to
the, the fact that they could do that too.
And that's, that's the point of it.
Being a keynote speaker is, is helping, uh, every single person in the audience be able
to understand that they can structure their life in a way to be the best version of themselves
and same with business groups and different organizations.
It's always, it's gotta be about, um, a story that is not necessarily, uh, about what it
seems like to start with.
You know, it's not about riding big waves.
That's the opening theme.
And that's what some of the visuals are an example of, but it comes back to the individual
that they can sit there and go, you know what?
I could probably step up what I'm doing a bit, you know, and there was a clear process
and path of how that was done.
Maybe I could do that too.
And that's, that's always what I want to achieve.
How important has collaboration been for you, Mark, in your life?
Um, I think.
You're absolutely screwed without it.
You know, I tried to do this project, the Knight Rider one in particular on my own for
three and a half years.
And it wasn't until I worked with a team that it quickly accelerated and it was done in
six months.
So I straight away knew as an individual, you can only do so much on your own and it
comes down to every single person being valued.
You know, no matter what role you play, every single person within the team is so crucial
because if you're missing those cogs, um, you know, straight.
You start to, you start to try and compensate for someone else, you know, and then you start
to overwork or you, you put yourself in a situation where you're not functioning at
a smooth level.
So it's so crucial to make sure that you have the right people in the right place.
And, uh, and without that, I just see it as being nothing really without the right people
around you and whether that be friends, mentors, whatever that is, even if you are an individual,
but you have to have the right people around you.
Who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Tough question.
So many, so many inspirational people, um, early days.
So as a surfer, my manager is, uh, Pat Rafters, brother, Steve, who's Pat's manager.
And I was introduced to Pat at a young age.
And I remember asking Pat kind of like a young kid wanting to get a cheat sheet to life.
Okay.
How do I do this really well?
How do I get to where I want to get to?
And he took, he took me out for brekkie and he sort of said, you know, hard work, hard
work and more hard work.
And I was like, that is the shittest answer.
You know, young 20.
I could ever get.
And I'm like, so what about this?
And he, he kind of just looked at me like, you don't get it kid.
The reality is you've got to put in the effort.
And he's so right because when I was doing the things that I wanted to do, it wasn't
until I realized that I went into serious depth about how something would be done, that
the answers came and the process, you know, came together.
So, um, Pat's definitely been a big mentor in that space and his brother, Steve has been
to such level headed, uh, individuals, um, that have really helped me.
In that space.
And even the people that I work with, I, it's, it's almost like a two way street.
You know, I get to work with some amazingly talented humans and often, although I'm sharing
a different, uh, insight to what they're doing, I'm also very inspired by what they
do too.
Uh, so yeah, I'd probably be here name dropping and saying things all day long, which I don't
really need to do in a sense of the fact that the people around me that I'm involved with
and, uh, have been around, have been so inspiring to me in so many different ways.
Yeah, it's great that you've got that, uh, list to call on, isn't it?
In your life and you're, you're, you're blessed aren't you to be able to, and you're passing
that onto so many in your own authentic way, which is a brilliant story to hear.
We're, we're obsessed with collaboration, feel like the world descended into silos a
lot and we love the idea of connecting people and collaborating in the, in the work we do
in our leader space.
Has there been one person in these projects that you're undertaking or any part of your
life in so many different dimensions to you thought, God, I'd love to collaborate with
that person.
Is there a name that springs?
At this point, I'd probably have to say I've almost got the blinkers on.
Like I'm so entrenched in what I'm doing in the team that I'm involved with, but I, you
know, when I get a chance to look at other things, you know, I look at some of the formula
one teams and think, wow, look at the way they do things.
And some of the NFL teams, the process of how they do stuff.
I just think, geez, that's impressive.
And there are different groups that I'm super impressed by, and there'll be so much to learn
from, but I kind of think to myself, um, either it'd have to be the right time, you know,
and, uh,
and at the moment, cause we're so gung ho and finishing, um, the project that I'm doing
now, I've probably limited my ability to, to sort of span out in that space.
But yeah, I think it's something I've probably just got to be open to.
Yeah.
Well, Mark, I know I've learned an enormous amount from our chat today.
I think all of us have that level of fear and your ability to break it down in a way
to say it's always going to be there, but you can practically take steps through it.
And the part of that is actually joyful at the other end about how to find your way through.
It's a great life lesson.
I'm glad it's not me out in the middle of the ocean.
Having to do what you do, mate, that would be a level that, uh, is just extraordinary.
Congratulations on all you're doing and all the work that you continue to do.
Thanks for joining me today.
Oh, thanks very much for having us.
Thanks for listening to another episode of the empowering leaders podcast.
Huge.
Thanks as always to our great friends at temper, and we encourage you to check out our leader
connect program.
New episodes are out every Wednesday morning at 6 00 AM.