My conversation today is with Mark Bunn.
Mark's expertise and passion is in creating a shift in our thinking about health, happiness,
high performance, and higher consciousness.
In this conversation today, we discuss how ancient wisdom can help us with modern health,
the way that Mother Nature can assist us in leading a happier, healthier way of life,
and how when we focus on our intuition and gut wisdom, it often leads to a better and
happier life.
Mark Bunn is an inspirational modern leader in my mind, and his use of ancient techniques
to help people with a better life is a really remarkable story.
His passion for what he does is one of the fundamentals for the work that we do in our
leadership business, Alita.
If you're interested in leading, learning, and collaborating, you can find out all about
it at alitacollective.com.
There are some fantastic resources there, and I would encourage you to check out our
signature Alita Connect program to get started and to understand how people like Mark Bunn
are leading in your life.
Mark Bunn is a highly respected and educated voice in the world of health, happiness, high
performance, and higher consciousness.
Former professional AFL footballer with the Fitzroy and Hawthorne football clubs, Mark
completed an honours degree in exercise physiology, studies deeply entrenched in Western health,
before moving on to become one of the world's most sought-after experts in Ayurvedic medicine,
a tradition with thousands of years of history in the East.
Mark's book, Ancient Wisdom for Modern Health,
is a three-time Nobel Prize winner.
and a brilliant guide for anyone wanting to live a simpler, healthier, and happier
life.
Marty, it's always good to see you, mate.
That's likewise.
Now, you're uniquely placed in my mind as an expert with roots in the East and the West,
and this is a pretty big question off the top, but given you've written books about
it and you write extensively on this topic, but in your mind, if you could sum it up,
what are the keys, if you could break it down in any way you want, to living a healthy and
happy, successful life?
The one-word answer would be simplicity.
My travels, Southeast Asia, I'm sure many of the listeners, you go to these, I'm putting
air marks up here, inverted commas, third world countries, you know, a bit sort of backward
or simple, but they live a very healthy, happy life, predominantly, and it's just basically
a connection to nature, would be the second piece of it, that really nature has certain
laws.
There's a wisdom to life, an intelligence that runs our universe.
And we humans are a part of that intelligence, and there's certain laws that Mother Nature
uses to guide us as to how to live that healthy, happy life.
I don't know why I've got avatar in my mind, because that's a sort of low-rented answer
I can give you back, but I did go and see the recent version of it, which has got links
into that, but there's so many connections that I have with you, and I want to talk to
you about a health retreat.
In Bali, I have a health retreat, and I'll ask you about that, but that's what I enjoy.
You walk out of the door there, you walk into the village, the smiles and the laughter and
the happiness for that generation, that group of people are so connected to everything that
you just spoke about, and we get back in the West and get crazy and take on so many things
and develop this stressful life.
I mean, I still find, even with knowledge and understanding and a desire, I still find
it hard to make healthy choices all the time.
What's the key to doing that in your mind?
Well, we should differentiate between simple and easy, because I'm nodding my head, I'm
exactly the same.
I can't do all the stuff we're going to talk about in the next half an hour, hour, myself.
It's a challenge.
And so the wisdom, this is the important, the understanding and the wisdom of what we
need to be a healthy individual is very simple.
It's been around for thousands and thousands and thousands of years, Ayurvedic medicine,
traditional Chinese medicine, indigenous cultures.
They've known it for thousands of years.
Yeah.
They've known it forever.
Our Western culture, and particularly the way we've structured our working lives, makes
it difficult to implement some of these simple wisdoms.
So again, coming back to that sort of philosophy we're going with simplicity is just start
small.
You know, don't try and turn your life upside down from the end of this recording.
You know, just take one or two simple principles and implement them slowly over time until
they become a habit.
And then take on the next one.
So just what resonates and we have this, this, we'll get to it probably throughout the session,
but this, this gut wisdom, you know, which we don't often pay attention to in the West,
you know, it's all about the what's on the app or what the experts telling me, but our
bodies according to Ayurveda are infinitely intelligent and they're telling us in every
moment exactly what we need to eat to nourish ourselves, what relationships nourish us,
what work nourishes us, but we just don't listen to it.
So just pick that little, that little insight that's sort of welling up inside us.
And this is the thing I need to focus on, do that well, and then move on to the other
stuff later on.
And that is fascinating to me that you went there around the intuition.
So many of the different people I've spoken to on this podcast reference that all the
time when they really have made great life decisions.
It's based on that inner knowing.
And when they've likewise had decisions they'd regret, it was something telling him it didn't
quite feel right, but they overrode it because.
I think I can make this where I certainly relate to that and, and, you know, going back
into that, that sense of when it feels right intuitively, you think you're generally going
to make a good decision.
Is that, is that how you'd frame it?
Absolutely.
Yeah.
Well, one of the things I've really loved about this whole research into the Eastern
cultures is, is this reframing of life in the, in the West or the modern world, I should
say probably more than the West is we often see life as hard, you know, it's difficult.
It's a challenge.
We've got to work hard.
You need sort of willpower.
Whereas in the East, they see it more as a flow.
We had this analogy of, of nature's intelligence and the analogy I use is, is like a surfer.
You've got a wave on the ocean, a surfer who understands that there's a certain time to
catch that wave, enjoys it.
It's absolutely exhilarating time of their life.
They're having a ball.
Nature's doing all the work and the surf is just enjoying the ride.
Now, Darce, I don't know about you, but when I go surfing, I'm usually paddling out when
the.
The waves crashing down on top of my head, you know, so I get the timing wrong.
I don't understand the laws of nature about surfing.
So for me, it's bloody hard work.
It's a mouthful of water and I'm never, never doing this stupid sport again.
So life is exactly the same.
The ancient rishis, they're called in the Ayurvedic tradition, they're the sages.
Rishi means a seer who can actually see or cognize those laws of nature that structure
life.
Tell us if we can turn our life around, we move our surfboard around a few degrees or
180 and we actually start going with the currents.
That flow, that intelligence, that life is very easy.
It just, it's just the way it's meant to be.
And so this is a, this, I think is the real sort of turnaround or thing we want to keep
in our awareness.
And Ayurveda itself means science of life.
You correct me here.
Anytime, you know, 6,000 plus years of history, longest, oldest living known health system
in the world.
And I want to.
Can I just jump in?
Yeah, sorry.
It absolutely means that.
You know, people leave Ayurveda at that they see it as this 6,000 year old, you know, books
that sit up on the, in the library shelf and it's called defined as the science of life.
But really what Ayurveda is, is knowledge of those fundamental laws of nature that govern
life.
So if you wanted a manuscript, a guidebook, like a constitutional Bible of how to live
Ayurveda.
Yeah.
Has all those fundamental laws.
So practically buddy, you know, people hear that and say, okay, that, that still sounds
a bit esoteric.
And how do I practically make that work?
And I can, I've got intuition.
My intuition feels like a donut.
Yep.
Is that a good choice, Mark?
And that will be complex.
So can you break that down more simply because the, you know, the West makes life so complicated
around coffee's good, coffee's bad.
We're going to have a paleo diet one week.
Yeah.
And a keto diet the next and vegetarian versus meat.
I mean, you know, I have experienced a fair bit of Ayurveda over a long period of time.
All of it intuitively makes perfect sense, but for someone listening to start, what does
it look like?
Yeah.
Beautiful question.
I've actually just come from doing a talk in a town to a group of graduates at an accounting
firm.
So all in their early twenties, just about to start their career.
And I was brought in to sort of give them tools on how they could sort of manage the,
not get burned out and resilience.
And so one of the key planks we discussed was connection to nature.
And so we use this term nature a lot.
So how do we practically do it?
Well, when you get up in the morning, going outside and just one morning, get up really
early and just greeting the early morning sun and do you feel better?
You know, is that sort of just that feeling of, Hey, this getting this natural light through
my eyes, does my mood lift or does it get depressed in the middle of the day?
You know, do I feel hungry?
In Ayurveda, the theory is that in the middle of the day, the sun is at its strongest and
also our inner sun, the Agni, the digestive fire is at our strongest.
So get a feel for if I haven't eaten a huge breakfast, do I feel hungry in the middle
of the day?
At the end of the day, you know, do I finish work and go out and walk down near the beach
if I live near the beach or a lake?
And does that connection to nature, does it make me feel calmer, more relaxed?
And everyone reports, yes.
You know what?
I spend time in nature.
I just, I feel better.
And so the science is now coming up of before it did, it's just that was the intuitive sort
of feeling we get.
At the end of the day, if I eat a really big meal at eight o'clock at night, you know,
I eat the steak and three veg and you would like some dessert with that, Das, I'd love
to, you know, it'd be rude not to have some dessert and we fill our belly up, do we feel
good when we go to sleep and do we wake up refreshed and perky early in the morning?
Or when we have a sort of lighter meal at night, do we sleep better and wake up fresher?
So these are the sort of starting things, this idea of that nature is out there, that
we see nature, we see the sunrise, we see sort of darkness descending at night.
Just this first step is to understand we're actually connected to that.
That cycle of the sun through the day mirrors 100% one to one, the cycles of our inner physiology.
And so these types of things are good ways to sort of get our teeth into connecting to
these rhythms.
And I can't help but jump into that point as well, because it has got in my mind, incredibly
pear-shaped here in the West for want of a better term, where we now fear the sun and
you drive past the primary school and we understand why, we live in a, you know, in a country
that has got, you know, extreme heat at times, but you know, middle of winter, kids are wearing
the full brim hats, that beautiful winter sun that makes you feel good and you want
to enjoy it.
We've been told, you know, there's no time that sunsets.
Yeah.
That's, that's good for you to, to, to be in the sun and.
It's like a lot of things in, in our modern life, we go a little bit to the extremes.
And so traditionally Ayurveda, many ancient cultures, the sun was esteemed as the most
health giving, life giving, energy promoting thing on the planet.
In fact, even biochemically, physiologically, we can't live without the sun.
The sun's the most important thing to human life.
And all of that, you know, anything I've ever heard in this space from, from, you know,
the ancient wisdom of, of Ayurveda or other cultures intuitively makes perfect sense.
Yeah.
And everyone can relate to that.
Getting up on holiday in the morning, seeing the sunrise, being out in nature, the, the,
the energy and the happiness, it just flows from that state and trying to recreate it,
you know, is, is something that, you know, I'm really passionate about and it's, it's
what you do day to day.
You know, I mentioned earlier Sukhavati Bali and Ayurveda health retreat, very fortunate
enough to be there.
Yeah.
To be a founder and partner of 11 years ago, and I would describe being attached to that
money as completely transformative for my and my family's health.
And I think if I look to the sort of Western system here in Australia, we're allegedly
got the best health system in the world here in Australia, but there's more obesity, depression,
you know, you think of all of the cancers and autoimmune diseases and, you know, we're
drowning in heart disease and anxiety and other challenges in what is supposed to be
world's best practice.
But I look at Ayurveda and I always just think of preventative health, looking after yourself
consistently well, to, to live a healthier and happier life.
Is that a simplistic way to think about it?
And people that come to our retreat have that experience of what it looks like to do something
regularly to look after your health before it gets too bad.
Is that, is that a fair, fair call?
Yeah, absolutely.
Ayurveda is definitely prevention focused.
It does have treatment modalities, but I think you touched on it, just, just going to Bali
is like a treatment in itself.
I was there last year and literally two people from Australia in the first 24 hours I was
there, both one had moved there from Sydney and the other one, I think from Melbourne.
And both of them said exactly almost word for word, it's so much easier to be healthy
in Bali because just that, that surrounding stress is not, you know, you're on your motorbike
and you're just going to park it wherever you are, right outside the restaurant.
And you know, you're not scared you're going to get a fine or the people are friendly.
It's just, there's this relaxed lifestyle that surrounds even the treatment.
So the question underlying it is how do we take those principles back to our lives in
Australia as a, as more at prevention focused.
And again, I think it's starting really, really simply just to appreciate that community and
how we value the older people in our communities.
Yeah.
And the two things in my research, and this is not just Bali, it's cultures all around
the world.
The two distinguishing features of them are that they live in communities.
So how can we focus maybe more on our relationships and our friendships and that extended family
rather than just going to the gym and getting the six pack and drinking the green smoothies
or blanching our almonds or whatever it is.
And then, and this is a difficult one, but it's more a societal thing, how we bring more
value and veneration and esteem to the older people in our communities.
So that mind body connection as we age gets strengthened rather than the opposite, which
we often have.
So roundabout question to yours or answer to yours, but yeah, in terms of the Sukhavati
and those, those treatments, I think it's just the icing on the cake to really sort
of.
Yeah.
I might ask you a bit more detail on that, but going back to the connection and community
piece, I'm reading a book I'm really enjoying at the moment.
Yeah.
It's called Lost Connections.
He's just released another book that's international bestseller everywhere, which I'm looking forward
to getting onto next on Focus and the algorithms and social media and AI and what that's doing
to us.
But one of the surveys he references, one of the studies is that decades and decades
ago in the US, people would, on average, if you asked them if they had how many people
in their life that would trusted confidence, they could ring and would support them.
Most people had at least three people in that light where they could share anything with,
would get that support.
But the overwhelming answer now for people in the US is zero.
Yeah.
So you have to say that again.
The majority of people have not got one person that they feel like can support them or they
could support themselves.
Like we have completely lost our way with, you know, even when I grew up, you knew all
your neighbors.
They often became your extended family and family friends.
And now we live with along more people, but no one speaks to their neighbors anymore.
We've lost that connection, haven't you?
Would you agree with that?
Totally.
Yes.
Yeah.
And I love his research.
I love the story about the cow, the depressed guy and the cow, you remember that one, in
Cambodia.
But yes.
And I often quote the study that I'm sure you've mentioned on the podcast previously,
but the Harvard University study, the longest study ever done on wellbeing, now up to 80
years, four different directors went back to the 1930s, I think, where they had two
groups of young men from one from a low socioeconomic group.
Boston, Tennessee.
The other one from a high socioeconomic going into Harvard studies, and they tracked them
for 80 years.
And basically the single finding was that the most important thing for our lifelong
wellbeing wasn't blood pressure or cholesterol or how much sleep we got, but the quality
of our relationships and the number of social connection, particularly those that we could
depend on when times got tough.
And so exactly backing up what you've just said.
And you've done a lot of work into the Blue Zone communities.
And people listening to this podcast would have heard me talk about that before, the
Okinawans in Japan and Sardinia in Italy and several other communities around the world
that routinely live to 100 and work healthily and happily to that age.
And that is the older you get, the more revered you are in the communities.
In fact, the locals, you don't want to touch people that are older, just feel a bit of
that wisdom.
Yeah.
We put people in nursing homes and don't visit them, don't we?
Absolutely.
Tragic.
Absolutely heartbreaking and tragic in every way.
Yeah.
Both for the outlaws with the wisdom, the wisdom holders, but also such a loss for everyone
else in our community.
I remember when I studied in my Ayurved course, I had a teacher who had such wisdom.
One of our practical assignments was to go into a nursing home or to interview someone
over the age of 75 years of age.
It was one of the best things I can remember doing.
Yeah.
It was so good for me, wisdom that I otherwise wouldn't have got, and so good for the people
we were interviewing because it gave them a purpose, they got to share their wisdom.
So there's just such a loss for people in their 20s and 30s and 40s that don't get that
wisdom because their grandma or grandma's not on TikTok or seem to be up with the latest
tech or such a shame.
It's tragic, isn't it?
When you break it down, go back briefly again to ... I love that you said this, that the
community, the connection.
The connection, the getting back to nature, that's the essence of good health and good
life.
I've found the treatments to be pretty profound, too, and when you get into that space for
prevention health, they are magic, I would describe them as, and life-changing.
Can you give a bit of a ... People come to a place like Sukhavati Bali, which clearly
I've got a passion for, and they do a treatment called Panchakarma, for example.
Why is that so profound in the way it works?
It's so profound.
Why?
Because the health remedies we rely on during a year when we're in our busy lives and there's
pollution out the door and there's stress only get to a certain level.
One example is toxins.
Toxins come into our body, sometimes in the food we eat, the environment, and they get
lodged into the adipose tissue, the fat tissue.
We can go and do a two or three day intermittent fast, or we can do a detox for a week, and
that's it.
And that won't really dislodge those deeply rooted toxins.
Panchakarma, which is for those who haven't experienced it, you imagine those beautiful
brochures with people lying on their backs, getting oil dripped over them, and massages
with one or two people, and it's blissful.
But what it does, if you do it properly, which you obviously do at Sukhavati, is a pre and
a post treatment.
So like everything in the West, Panchakarma has become a bit ... You know?
Yeah.
Flavor of the month, and people race over to India or America, and they sort of get
off the plane, and they go and do their seven or 10 days, and they jump straight back on
the plane, and by the time they get back, they don't feel any better.
In Sukhavati, they understand the traditional wisdom that there is a pre-treatment.
So there's certain diet you go into to loosen up those deeply held impurities, and then
you have the treatments that help dislodge them, get into the elimination track, and
then the post treatment is really important.
Yeah.
And rejuvenate the body.
So the analogy we learned in our training was when you're drinking herbal teas or you're
having a certain diet, it's like you pacify the imbalances in the body.
In Ayurveda, they're called doshas, D-O-S-H-A-S, and it's like you're sort of patting them
down.
If it's a tree, you're sort of spraying the water on the leaves, and you're sort of giving
a bit of fertilizer.
In Panchakarma, you're completely ripping the roots of the tree.
You're putting the tree out of the ground and replanting it.
So you're almost just cleaning the slate clean, and then you're able to reinvigorate and rejuvenate
the body from scratch.
So it's like you come out and you've experienced it.
I've experienced it.
People experience it all the time.
I feel like a new person.
You go to a health retreat for a weekend, which are great.
I'm not minimizing those impacts.
They're fantastic.
But this is like, I feel better.
I've got more energy.
This is like, I feel like my old self again.
You know?
And that's the way I describe it, buddy.
When I come back from there and have some time, I feel like ... I describe it like a
grease and oil change.
I feel like I've put the body in for a service, but for the next six months, I'm dialed back
in.
I make better choices after that.
I eat better again, and I just feel really back to the version that you want to be.
I did want to share a bit of a personal story, because I know he'd be happy if he was here,
to do it, around my dad, who got a multiple myeloma blood cancer.
I think it was close to his 72nd birthday, and the prognosis, talking to his oncologist,
going back after we'd lost dad eventually, it wasn't great at all.
In fact, probably in the handful of months.
And I wanted to take dad up to Sukhavati, because one, I just thought it'd be beautiful
for him.
He had been there before, but I'm one of four, and the four siblings, we decided that
we would all go and do that with him.
He had some treatment here, he had some chemo and some radiotherapy, but then as soon as
that was the case, he would get on a plane and go there for a couple of weeks.
And then in the end, he did a nine or 10-week stay, and he would come back, and his doctors
back here in Melbourne just were going, I don't know what you're doing.
Mm-hmm.
Markers are off the charts, and it was just incredible to see what happened.
And what I genuinely feel, and I know I spoke to dad before he eventually passed, he felt
like he'd got six brilliant bonus years, and they were brilliant years because he genuinely
knew that they were in overtime, for want of a better word.
So you're right, and that's taking it, when you've taken someone there incredibly sick,
to still be able to get that sort of benefit at that stage of life was a pretty good thing.
Mm-hmm.
Pretty special thing to watch, actually.
Yeah.
Well, to jump in, I've got a very similar story, and I think you're going to bring it
up yourself, but my wife, I was married 14 or 15 years ago, Sydney girl, and it touched
on one of the topics we just sort of touched on earlier, and we're thinking sort of around
this idea of, we know the theory of health a lot, these simple wisdoms, but very challenging
to put in, and she was in an environment which was very, very stressful for her, really
toxic, had been in it for seven years when we sort of got together, and when I was going
out with her, I did the same thing.
We called it the sweep it under the carpet routine, you know, it was a bit of a challenging
situation, too hard to sort of change, so we rationalized that stress was a part of
life, and stress was a part of the job, nothing will happen to us, and sweep it under the
carpet, and about three months after we got married, she went to the doctor, routine check,
came back with diagnosis.
She had breast cancer, but it wasn't early stages, sort of right through her body, you
know, most organs, so it was a pretty uphill battle right from there, but I still remember
at Sydney airport, we moved out, we were sort of living in a sort of part of the house of
her parents, because if I was still working, they looked after her, they were absolutely
amazing, and so we brought up this idea of going to India to do some panchakarma for
her, and the parents were very old school, you know, they were like, meet me at the hospital,
and veg at nine o'clock at night to get your strength up, so all the sort of Ayurvedic
stuff I was trying to sort of suggest wasn't going down too well, so Kara found that really
tough, because she was sort of caught between the east and the west, and the parents, and
the, so that wasn't great, but we finally got them around to letting me take her to
India, they came to the airport, and I remember the mother asking her, as we were going through
the terminal, the departure terminal, would you like a wheelchair to make it easier to,
you know, get through?
Karen declined, but that's how bad she was, basically, going to India, and then she's
got to get on a flight to, you know, India, and then India's crazy.
When she came back, the parents basically said, if you want to go, take her back again,
we'll pay for it, anything you want to do, because she was just so much better, and again,
like, gave her five, six much better quality of years before she finally passed.
So, I mean, for someone who's spent, you know, from professional assets...
That's led into the world of health and wellbeing, you get married three months after you're
married, your wife diagnosed, as you said, with incredibly challenging upfront battle
with cancer, I mean, I can't even understand how tough that must have been, and your desire
to try and help and heal, I mean, how challenging was that at that, and then I want to ask you
also about stress, you mentioned stress there, you know, stress's role in creating illness
at the same time.
Yeah, well, I'll start with the second question.
Second question first, and that's really the lesson that came out for me, everything
I think is a lesson in life, before Karen got sick, I had most of the same knowledge
of Ayurveda, and I thought, you know, I know about health, it's all good in theory, and
then I think life tests you, you know, here's smack you on the head, and how much do you
really know, and so, but hers was, I would say, 99% stress-based.
Absolutely.
She meditated, she sipped hot water, she did most of the Ayurvedic things, you know, bed
early, pretty quiet life like me, just a massive, it's like that analogy of you put the frog
in the warm water, or cold water, heat it up gradually over time, the frog will stay
in the water, even when the water's absolutely boiling, and we do it with life, you know,
the stress just starts, it's a little, and a little, 10 years later, you look back, and
you're just swimming in it, and that was the case with Karen.
The first question, the answer is really, and I say it now, blessing and a curse all
wrapped up in one.
The day she got diagnosed was certainly the worst day of our lives, and the subsequent
seven or eight year battle, but in other ways, it was absolutely the best day of our lives,
and the best thing that ever happened to both of us.
She got an excuse, basically, to get out of that toxic situation, she got much better
perspective on her life, which I did too, you know, and as we're talking about the
these simpler cultures, that maybe, you know, work, and money, and flying around the world,
doing talks wasn't the most important thing in life, and just having a good relationship,
and simply, so we learnt so much.
She began to paint, her parents were both really good painters, she'd almost never held
a paintbrush, she began painting, and you would not believe the paintings, unbelievable.
And so yeah, so many good things came out of it, and probably the word I always struggle
whether I use it or not is regret, because I think everything has its purpose, and she's
in a better place now, and I certainly have beliefs on afterlife, and you know, physical
death, and all that sort of thing, so, but yeah, I regret back at that time, not having
the courage or the bravery to say, hey, we've got to change this now, let's do something
about this situation, not just let's sweep it under the carpet, because it's a difficult
decision.
So I think that.
That sort of permeates for all of us, that we tend to put things off, and put things
off, particularly as men, you know, sort of the lesson for me now is, let's do them when
they come up, and focus on the sort of simple, truly nourishing things.
So it's intuition again, I'm seeing something here that's clearly life-shortening, and stressful,
and that sort of health, there's always an alternative to avoid that, no matter how hard
it seems.
And we find that hard, don't we, to shift jobs, or relationship, whatever it is, or
partnerships we're in, because we find the challenge of moving really, you know, we all
do, it's hard, but, you know, again, you're going back to what you said at the start of
this interview, which was, your intuition doesn't let you down, you know, too often.
You did a beautiful thing, I was reading last night, you've shared the journal of your,
you know, your wife, Karen, and her thoughts, and I went through, I couldn't stop reading
it, actually, I just, it was a really generous thing to do, and I, you know, you prefaced
it by saying that she'd planned to do it herself.
Yeah.
A bit of your humour in there along the way, Bunny, which I enjoyed as well, but, and
then just some of her favourite quotes as well, it was a really moving thing to read.
The first quote you had, spread love everywhere you go, let no one ever come to you without
leaving happy, it's a Mother Teresa quote, but pretty profound wisdom she was getting
through that time, wasn't it?
When you sit back and read, you know, how open she was on all that, I encourage you
to go and look up Mark Bunn's website.
Yeah.
And check that out.
It was, it was brilliant.
Yeah.
And I think it, and you might've found the same thing with your dad.
I think when people are at that point where they sort of are closer to that, we call it
dropping the body, you know, that sort of death, that means they're also closer to the,
whatever we call it, you know, that high consciousness, the transcendent sort of level of life where
as we started with the conversation, those, those impulses, those seeds of intelligent
wisdom.
They're, they're most lively, you know, that's why we, you know, I meditate every day, you
know, when we transcend, we go beyond the busyness of the arguments and the work and,
and we get to that sort of peaceful, quiet place within us where those seeds of, of wisdom
are.
And so death is an, is another transition that gets us in touch with that.
So yeah, the closer she got the, the, um, the more she was able to sort of just naturally
bring those sort of things out, which was really, really nice.
I'll ask you about transcendental meditation in a moment.
But I was smirking on my own.
My mind was going to my dad and, uh, and this is classic him, he was an old school
public and, uh, money, great person.
I couldn't have had a better relationship and credit to him, you know, we, we, we've
asked him to, you know, go and take on this whole new system of health.
And my sisters, we went to every appointment with him and we were, uh, you know, my beautiful
sisters and my older brother were really just, we wanted him around.
And so we're going to do anything to come and be sitting down with the head doctor up
there.
Dr. Arju.
I think you know.
I was talking, uh, Dr. Arju about alcohol and you know what they're like, the Ayurvedic
doctors.
They're brilliant.
Alcohol is fine.
Mr. David, it's a good, it's a good thing.
And dad's, you know, how much, how much?
And, uh, and he's, oh, no, no problems.
You know, maybe 60 mils every three months.
And dad's got 60 mils.
Why spill 60 mils a night?
What do you mean?
That's a, so the perspective was, you know, and dad genuinely then just shifted everything
and changed and got those five better years.
I, I'll come back with, you learnt to meditate as well.
You know, you, you dialed into everything and, um, and it had a massive impact.
You've been a passionate, uh, meditator in that space for a long years.
You teach Transcendental Meditation.
People listening have heard me bang on about it a lot.
Why should you do it?
Why, why does it work so well?
Uh, well, I, I started a long time ago, so I was 19 and I, I noticed, Darcy, you haven't
brought up my, uh, very, um, dignified and, uh, glamorous AFL career.
So.
That's probably the fact that.
How many did you play, buddy?
No, I'm, I'm, I'm taking the piss because I'm, I'm glad you didn't because it's very
inglorious and, um.
How many games did you play?
The less, the less said about it, the better, mate.
Um, I got, I got to 50, but that was about it.
Just got over the wall.
Well, you're in the top, not many people get to 50 games, buddy, so.
But, um, no, I learnt, I was 19, so I just, I just played my third game of AFL footy and,
uh, my brother-in-law was a Victorian wicket keeper, Michael DiMartino.
And my darling sister had both learnt.
And they said, cause I was no good at footy, they said, oh, this might be good for you.
Needed all the help I could get.
So I went along and, uh, yeah, best thing I've ever done.
So I, I sort of talk about, it's like a holiday for my brain and body twice a day, regardless
of what's going on.
Just allows me to get beyond the stress and the agitation and just sort of get to that
sort of quiet space.
So, um, yeah, it's just been, it's, it's just a.
Foundation for me, it becomes a habit, you know, I've since gone on and researched sort
of a, you know, like you, a lot of the top performing business people around the world.
My research suggests that the single most common trait habit or daily ritual of the
world's highest level performers, male, female, other gender, parent, athlete, artist, you
name it, is that they close their eyes and either do some form of mindfulness or they
do transcendental meditation twice a day.
And.
And it's just the analogy of our life.
You know, I have a friend in the U S we were, I speak over there and she has a, a saying
that we, we bow down to the altar of activity in the west.
You know, everything's about activity.
Whereas in the east and what TM does is it brings out the fundamental wisdom that success
is not based on our activity alone, but on the ancient natural formula.
Of rest and activity.
The more dynamic you want the activity to be, the deeper you need the rest, the higher
the skyscraper you want to build, the deeper you got to dig down first, the further you
want the arrow to go forward, the further you got to pull it back.
And so TM or transcending is like drawing the arrow back.
We get that dissolution of stress.
We get that clarity.
We get that.
We get it clear.
We get it.
We get that.
We get that clarity.
The moment we come out and we come out and we get the same quality of success that we
had, and we get the same mechanism of success that we had to, to, to for the past couple
of years in the past, we had the same objectives that we had, but now we have to come out, we
have a, a new lens of success, but now we've got a new objective that we need to push the
pendulum to a higher place, a new course.
That is a beautiful description of it.
I've never been able to get the words out quite like that, but I agree with everything
you said and, you know, I know you so many people around the world, the people will know,
but didn't know that that was part of what they do.
And again, I was thinking of Jerry Seinfeld, for whatever reason, who's a lifelong transcendental meditator and, you know, he's got his way of describing it.
But he talks about just putting almost like you've got the iPhone charger and you just turbocharge that energy and that clarity twice a day.
Holiday for a brain, you called it.
Yeah.
I think there might be a Hugh Jackman analogy, the holiday for the brain.
He's been, again, another 40-odd year practitioner and, yeah, so many of those sort of creative, high activity, high success people have done it.
I'm going to ask you some specific thing about leadership and your unique leadership story in this space.
But a lot of what you do in your leadership is helping people achieve what you describe as higher states of consciousness.
Now, a lot of people, what does that even mean?
Why is that something that we would want to attain, a higher state of consciousness?
Can you start there?
We need a bit of woo-woo music in the background.
Yeah, you're going to get a bit deep on us here, aren't you?
Yeah, a bit esoteric.
So, yeah, let's break it down.
And basically, we think of brain science.
Neuroscience is the Western correlate these days.
We know about the importance of the brain.
If we can make the brain work better, more integrated, so we know there's different lobes, different parts of the brain, that if they go offline and they don't communicate with each other,
performance decreases.
If we can make the brain, if we like, more expanded so that it can comprehend a more broader range of things, we're going to be better as a business leader.
You know, so many different parts of our business and our life that we need to keep on top of.
If we have a more broader comprehension, we can keep all those parts in place and know what to attend to at a certain time.
At the same time,
what we also want as a leader is precision focus.
So when it is time to make a decision or to be clear on something, we need that sort of laser-like focus.
What transcendence does in these transcendence-based meditation techniques is they develop both simultaneously so that we have the prefrontal cortex, the front of our brain.
They often call it the CEO of our brain, incidentally, which is the focus and the task orientation.
But also what they call the default mode network, which is like this network of neurons that sort of those million-dollar ideas come from.
You know, when you're having a shower or you're having a sleep on the hammock and this idea comes, oh, shit, let's do this.
This is a brilliant idea, which we don't get when we're always sort of busy and thinking.
And so if we can develop those insights over time and we can reduce the stress from the physiology,
the more we can take stress.
The more we can take stress out of the body, the more those insights will naturally come.
And so really, higher states of consciousness are really just the body and the mind becoming more integrated.
So we meditate, we get rid of a bit of stress.
The body and the mind function more integrated, more coherently, we could say.
And then so that what the Eastern masters, the great yogis you hear about doing all these crazy things of, you know,
sitting out in the.
Ice and warming up their body or never getting stressed because they're in a state of enlightenment or self-realization is really nothing other than more consistent removal of stress without incurring more stress on top of it, which we do in the West.
Maharshi Mahesh Yogi, who's the founder of TM, has this great analogy.
And it's basically that if you have a piece of white cloth and you want to make it blue, you've got to dip it into the blue dye.
And then you don't leave it in there.
You take it out, expose it to the sun.
It fades, but there's a little bit of faint blue color.
You put it back in the dye, take it out, expose it to the sun.
And it's that alternation of in the dye out that over time makes the blue color permanent.
Same with our physiology.
We transcend.
We remove some stress.
We expose it to some activity.
Hopefully not too stressful.
We transcend.
Over time, as stress is removed from the body, the body's natural state, the body's natural state is a non-stress, completely coherent state where mind and body are functioning perfectly integrated fashion.
That is enlightenment.
When that becomes a 24-7 reality, that's enlightenment.
It's not esoteric.
Maharshi said it's the most practical thing we can do as people.
It's like as a business leader.
That's our first priority.
Why wouldn't you want perfect mind-body integration and have a higher state of consciousness than a lower one?
It's fascinating when you say it like that because to even understand what consciousness means would be a good question in the West.
Again, go back to the East, it's very much understood, isn't it?
And you revere the great masters, as you described, and your great teacher, Maharishi.
And his legacy.
It's lost a lot on the activity and the craziness, Bunny, of what we do.
And I'm certainly guilty of no doubt about it.
In different leadership settings, I've loved talking to, you know, your story's brilliant.
I've loved following it for a few decades now.
We feel like there's some common traits to leadership that are identifiable in the work we're doing in a business.
I'm just keen to talk to you about, Bunny, and call it a leader, where we're bringing together collaborative groups of leaders.
From different backgrounds.
And, you know, I love what you said about every business leader wants to have that harmony and synergy so your brain works and builds a bigger dimension.
We think you can achieve a bit of that through collaboration as well and bringing different minds together.
So we think the common trait first and foremost with anyone who is achieving in this space is a sense of self-leadership.
When I talk about that to you, what does that mean?
The self to me is the deepest part of ourselves.
So that sort of intangible non-self.
The non-physical part.
I think the part we all want to get in touch with and have more connection with, but we often don't know how to do it.
So we touched on intuition at the start of the podcast, and I think that's a nice tie-in.
So self-leadership is that trust of following the rudder or the guide of those intuitive impulses.
Which I think every business leader, as you said at the start, over their history will say the ones that they've followed have turned into the best business ideas, the best relationship builders, the sort of best things in their family life.
And the ones that they've sort of denied or gone with the data or the logical sort of outcomes haven't turned out so well.
So I think self-leadership is really about trust, trusting that sort of inner voice, that gut wisdom to sort of lead us on the right path.
Great description.
Bunny, I love, you know, again, I'm really focused back in on that intuition.
Again, my mind, I'm listening and I'm thinking at the same time.
I need today a lot.
Nicole Gibson was on this podcast.
Amazing young entrepreneur and leader and youngest ever person on a government commission.
She was on the Mental Health Commission.
Brilliant story.
And she's actually developing some tech around teaching people.
We've got these iPhones in our hand all day.
Yeah.
And, you know, they measure a lot of...
She'll do a book.
She'll do a much better job than me.
But, you know, to actually think about making decisions from that place and can we measure that in all the decision making is a healthier, happier life in that, isn't it?
If we take the time to stop and really...
We've even lost that art, haven't we, of actually just going inward to think about it first and foremost.
So if you haven't heard her podcast, have a listen to Nicole Gibson.
She's brilliant.
We think leaders are really conscious of how they positively impact others in their environment.
You speak around the world, around Australia.
One of the most sought after speakers in this society.
Space and clearly your life is about positive impact.
But how have you thought about that on a daily basis?
It's ever evolving for me.
One of the things I've really found I've loved, and even since Karen had her journey and passed away, that life certainly isn't perfect.
You know, that bubble of sort of, you know, there's this ancient wisdom that has this theory on life and it all sounded fantastic.
But, you know, like you, I'm bumbling away and trying to live life.
Not get too stressed and, you know, all that sort of stuff.
So I find it changes and evolves.
And I think it's that...
I think one of the best things we've heard over the last five years, and I'm sure you've interviewed many guests who've touched that whole idea of embracing our imperfections and our, you know, being vulnerable.
And that's been a big one for me.
Shame was a massive thing for me as a young sort of boy and adult and sort of putting on the mask of bravado and fear.
Failure in footy and not rewards of success, all that stuff.
So for me, it's really been coming back to just self-kindness is probably the best term for it.
That, hey, life is tough in many cases.
Yes, there's these great wisdoms of life and cultures that have sort of been a lighthouse for how we live individually and collectively.
But it's not easy unless you're in those cultures 24-7 to do it.
So let's sort of be kind, kind to myself, kind to those around us.
And just try and embrace that.
Embrace those wisdoms gradually over time so that collectively and as a society we can embrace them.
Because I think that's the real game changer when we do it, do it en masse.
You mentioned shame there.
What do you mean by that?
Yeah.
What was that so hard for you to overcome and where did that come from?
Well, I've only really found out probably the last five or 10 years.
I remember sitting at a kitchen table in Perth.
I was traveling over there.
And I was staying with a friend and telling, I can't remember what the original story was.
But she says, you have to read a book by John Bradshaw.
It's Healing the Shame that Binds Us.
One of the best books I've ever read.
He was a sort of a religious American sort of pastor and alcoholic father and just massive shame issues.
And he went through just how shame manifests, you know, particularly as children.
And shame.
Shame.
This idea that shame loves secrecy.
That if you keep things in, shame just gets stronger and stronger and stronger.
And shame hates being spoken about.
And so I was a classic.
If you ask my parents, when I was a teenager, it was the classic family joke.
You know, I'd come back.
I'd play football.
And for some miraculous thing, I'd have a good game.
If I hadn't been to watch, they'd say, how'd you go?
And I'd say, good.
One word answers on everything.
Not bad.
Good.
I was just a shut up shop.
And even throughout my 20s and 30s, you know, I was always very reticent to sort of spruik myself or, you know, that whole sort of get smashed by the universe.
But I realized that I was just doing myself a lot of disservice.
And the great work of, you know, the Resilience Project and Ben Crow and these sort of people that are now showing us that the way we connect with others is through our imperfections and our invulnerabilities.
And so I really looked back at my history and saw that shame was really the driving emotion of most of my life.
You know, I was very conscious football and sport because I was good at it was my way of having a facade that I was successful.
And so I was driven to, as I said, so I didn't fail.
And so I didn't lose face.
If I had a bad game, I'd feel really embarrassed about it.
If I played well, it was all right for the next week.
And then it went into speaking, you know.
It was very much about the performance of speaking, which then shut off a little bit of that connection with the audience and really being there to sort of serve and get the message across.
So, yeah, probably particularly the last decade has been very much a journey of sort of realizing that that's been driving a lot of my life.
And now, so I open up a lot more.
I speak a lot more to friends and joined a men's group, which has been unbelievably powerful.
Just being able to share stuff.
That I wouldn't otherwise share.
And I find I'm now much more sort of, you know, a bit freer, a bit more playful.
My, you know, talks, I don't get so anxious about them.
I don't plan them as much.
This podcast, you know, no thought to bring you up and say, what are we going to talk about this?
And, you know, plan all this.
We just go with the flow a lot more.
And so life's just a lot more enjoyable.
And what Ben Crow and the researchers, Bren Brown, all these people show that when we sort of put shame under the spotlight.
And we're just open about it, then it sort of loses its power and life becomes a bit more joyful.
So that's my journey and still a long way to go.
Yeah, it's probably a pretty common one, isn't it?
Very common.
For all of our generation, isn't it?
We really weren't taught any other way.
And there wasn't conversations on any of it.
It wasn't open to anyone, was it?
And it is great credit, isn't it, to Ben Crow and to Bren Brown, the international champion of this space, isn't it?
It is.
But I love, you know, you listen to her in recent times as well.
She talks about authentic vulnerabilities too, like anything in the needle can switch kind of too to inappropriate vulnerability.
And, you know, you've got to then reteach back to say we can overshare, you know.
Time and place.
There's a time and place.
But we came out of the generation, funny, where the door wasn't open at all for any of it.
And that caused huge issues for, you know, a whole generation.
Yeah.
Men and women.
But the men were privileged.
Probably even at the point you're in, in some ways, about not having anywhere to go on that space.
We often see people who are really clear on creating and sharing a vision.
And I've got to go back to your book.
It is absolutely brilliant.
You're a brilliant writer.
You know, Ancient Wisdom for Modern Health.
It is a three-time bestseller, as I said.
You've got a great way of explaining things.
And you can hear that in the way you're talking today.
How have you gone about creating and sharing your vision?
Back to the first word I mentioned on the podcast.
Simplicity is my...
I guess my skill set, something we haven't discussed today,
which is really another fundamental of Ayurvedic wisdom, is Dharma.
Dharma is that activity, that vocation, that helps us to evolve maximally.
So people talk about today, you know, passion in life, your higher purpose.
So in Ayurveda, it's like that, but it's actually a deeper.
It's like almost...
It's our duty in life that we're born for a specific reason to fulfill.
We do that.
Life flows, the analogy of surfing the wave.
And we're the greatest service to those around us.
So Dharma is a real key plank to that.
And my Dharma, I'm pretty confident, is to help take what can be complex or esoteric
or woo-woo type things and hopefully simplify them down that they're more practical for
people.
And I think it's really important to help people that are just out there and struggling
with the four or five kids and the crazy boss and the, you know, road rage and all that
sort of thing.
So yeah, it's really about simplicity.
I really believe that it's just about cutting out the waste.
And the waste, I mean, just the complication and trying to do too many things too well.
You know, health's sort of my speciality and I see it every day in health.
You know, people out there trying to have the perfect diet.
And they spend half their day, you know, I said, blanching their freaking almonds and
grinding their linseeds and which means then they don't have time for the good relationships
or, you know, they've got a fantastic relationship.
They're just not nourishing or they've got a healer relationship or exercise.
So we can't do everything.
But what are the real fundamentals?
And we need to keep life simple to sort of focus on those sort of key things we touched
on earlier in the episode.
No doubt.
In my mind, that is your gift, listening to you.
And reading your work.
It's, you know, the thing of Scotty Pate, the Barefoot Investor, I spoke to on this
podcast and there's a million books have been written on finance and Pate, he was talking
about sort of almost the backhanded compliment.
Oh, geez, it's so basic the way you write.
And he goes, yes, that's what I do.
You know, that's the art of it.
And there's a lot of skill behind that.
You know, he's sold plenty of books on making.
Well, I wrote the book, funnily enough.
Um, because I think as authors, we do try and make out where we're smart and put sort
of Sanskrit words or words that, but one of my principles of writing the book was if there's
a word that 95% of the population might not understand or a bit confused, I wouldn't use
it.
And so probably the most common feedback I had of the book was easy to read.
People just found it easy to read.
So, yeah.
And done with purpose on exactly that.
And, um, curiosity is a word that we hear a lot around the leaders that we're working
with at Alita and, and through curiosity, that's how we finding people are approaching
their learning and development.
Does that resonate with you?
Love curiosity and, and something I haven't been good at.
And so why I love the question, because it's probably a new, a new term and a new field
for me, but yeah, I think I was really shut off to, to new knowledge and new inspiration
and, and teachers.
Uh, for much of my life.
And again, probably the last five, 10 years, I've really understood that, Hey, I don't,
I don't know everything long way from it.
And, uh, being curious of people that have sort of gone down paths that I haven't and
have wisdoms that I'm not sure about.
So I love being curious, particularly of older people, those with the wisdom, but also people
just doing stuff that, uh, I haven't done like a Tim Ferris podcast.
I love his stuff because it's so broad.
And fascinating.
So very curious about, uh, life these days.
Yeah.
He's brilliant.
Tim Ferris.
Absolutely.
Isn't he?
And, and yeah, I love the beauty of this medium.
Isn't it now?
Is it in real time?
Might've taken someone 20 years to get around to writing a book where we're getting to sort
of learn really quickly, aren't we, from people doing great things and they're sharing more
than they probably ever have done before.
Communicating with clarity, um, again, is a common thing that we see leaders are really
conscious of and a real strength, I think of yours.
How have you gone about it?
Silence.
Probably not the answer you're expecting, but I was trying to bring a few of these threads
in of what we've discussed and I remember one of the, and it's still to this day, one
of the best quotes I've ever heard was by Claude Debussy and he said, silence is the
space between the notes or music.
So music is the space between the notes and that's life.
And, and that could be the same answer to.
A number of questions you asked me.
You could ask me another 10 and it could be the same answer because life is just so busy
and we think, we think that's the activity.
It's again, this rest and activity.
All the answers, how I find them, I think everyone finds them is in the gaps.
When we take a break from the activity, when we get that night off from the kids or we
have the two day break from work or, you know.
We switched the TV off or we're off the phone or off the technology.
That's when we get in touch with that intuition.
That's where that rest comes and that's where we get the answers, the solutions to whatever
we're dealing with in life.
So for me, I'd say just getting silent, going out in the nature, turning the technology
off, just being with myself.
We use that term self, self-leadership, I think that's where it all starts.
It's a consistent message that you've given us today.
How important is collaboration been for you?
I'm pausing because again, historically I haven't valued it and I've paid the price.
Just speaking to someone yesterday, I rang him up.
He's up in Mulaney in Queensland.
I'm starting a new brand called Dharmic Living.
And I was explaining to him that previously in my incarnations of business and speaking,
I've always tended to want to do it.
I've always wanted to do it.
I've always wanted to do everything myself and I had the expert's hat on and I want
to do it this way.
I don't want people to ... And that I'd realized my mistake of that, that very narrow, not
so enjoyable, that working as a team and from 40 days you would have known when you leave
a football environment or any sporting environment, you realize very quickly that you had a self-contained
everyday team, collaborative mix.
Which is beautiful.
And then you go into this, oh, all of a sudden I'm by myself and I've got to either create
new ones or I'm going to flail along.
And I flailed for ... I was successful, people would say I was successful, but that joy of
doing things wasn't as high as it could have been.
So yeah, collaboration, again, more recently is really coming to my forefront of my mind
and how I can do things with others so that it's one, more effective because people have
skillsets.
People have skillsets that I don't.
And it's just more fun and enjoyable, which I think's the way to live and healthier.
Brilliant answer.
Who has been the greatest leader in your life?
Oh, it's hard to go past my father.
My father was not a business person per se, very staid, staid probably not the right word,
conservative.
Shunned the limelight.
No fanfare, but just in terms of what I'm now learning are the true principles of life
that a leader should impart, sort of kindness and volunteering for community and just such
an amazing parent, right back from taxiing me everywhere and my siblings.
So yeah, my father, I think in a different way would be a great leader.
Paul Roos comes up also for me.
He was my captain at Fitzroy and since had a bit to do with him because he's also in
the wellbeing space and the men's health space.
But he, to me, from seeing as a coach, what he brought to the AFL was almost that first
leader to change the perspective of a coach as this hierarchical do as I say, old school
fear mentality to everything we've discussed.
I think he was a great, great leader, which I sort of had the benefit of experiencing sort
of firsthand as a player, but really I think blossoming as he went into coaching and obviously
now in business.
I heard Roosie talk a lot about while he was playing, he was an unbelievable player, as
you know, and at time, all Australian, one of the great players the games have assumed,
but he wrote down this list of stuff.
This is crazy.
Yeah.
If I ever get the chance, we're going to stop doing this and I've heard him say that he
used to just pull that open drawer out when he was coaching and just go, just check, make
sure I haven't drifted into some of that, but he definitely changed the nature of the
way leaders in sport operate.
It's a great legacy.
Yeah.
It's great.
I didn't realize that he crossed over with Roosie as a player at Fitzroy.
We're a bit obsessed with collaboration.
A leader is all about inspiring connections, but in a world of collaboration is what we
talk about and we're fascinated and I often give it a plug because people listening, we
love the idea of bringing people together in these bespoke leadership groups, whatever
your background, whatever it is and have to be Paul Roos or Mark Bunn or whoever it is,
we think there's something brilliant in inspiring those connections.
And the collaboration that comes out of them, we're seeing some brilliant stories and I've
asked this question of everyone, if you could collaborate with anyone in the world or whatever
passion on anything, but is there anyone that springs to mind?
Bob Roth probably springs to mind, which I have had the pleasure of collaborating with
or working with a little.
Bob Roth is the head of the David Lynch Foundation in America.
I know you've had the pleasure of meeting him a few years back in New York.
But Bob is a Transcendental Meditation teacher, spent a lot of time with Maharshi and that
whole knowledge, but is arguably the most practical person I know.
One of his mottos is no woo woo.
But as a leader, I think he's just an amazing embodiment of this.
We spoke about this idea of broad comprehension, this expansion, we could call it a cosmic
mindset.
Yeah.
Anything's possible.
One of his other mottos is the answer's yes.
As long as it's a good, I'm saying yes, and then we'll work out how to do it.
But just really personal, down to earth, focused, he's there to serve, but just this amazing
balance of this sort of cosmic mindset that everything's collaboration, everyone's connected,
anything's possible.
But when it's time to focus, he's right there, he's right with you, and just so inspiring,
so inspiring.
Yeah.
I remember that night very clearly, and we were invited to this function, and Bec and
I were in New York and hadn't met him before, and he got that presence around him.
He came out, found the table, took the time to shake your hand, and then he just ... But
we're sitting there, just the scale of the impact that he's having.
A lot of people know David Lynch.
Yeah.
David Lynch, and again, he's a lifelong meditator that, I believe, he might have put $50 million
in to start the foundation.
He's donated huge amounts, and I didn't quite understand how revered David Lynch is in Hollywood.
He's sort of the producer that everyone wants to be, because he's made money doing stuff
that isn't mainstream and can do what he likes, basically, David Lynch.
But even just sitting there that night, I'm trying to think who was the ... The speaker
list was just ... I think it started with Ariana Huffington, Michael J. Fox presented.
Jerry Seinfeld might have done ...
Seinfeld was there, yeah.
It was just ... Not the name-dropping part of it, but then it was the kids in schools
that they taught, and the post-traumatic stress with veterans, and just how sophisticated.
It sounds like clearly a friend of yours, but brought through his genius that he's been
able to have massive impact and pass on that knowledge in a really powerful way.
He's the one.
Yeah, I think so.
He's the one that comes to mind.
So, yeah.
But collaboration, as you say, is very key to his processes.
Yeah, absolutely.
Buddy, it's been a great pleasure catching up with you again, and hearing the work that
you do, and the simplicity in the way which you deliver it.
It's a crossover passion of mine, clearly, but thanks for sharing today in such a profound
way.
I believe there's more books coming.
Can we get a scoop on that, or we'll put you under the pump here with that last question?
Yeah, well, they are coming.
As I usually say to my family, the motivation is to live a long life, because then you might
still be alive when they come out, but hopefully one or two are coming out in the next year
or two.
But don't hold your breath is always my motto.
They will be full of wisdom.
Thanks so much for joining.
Good to see you.
Thanks, Darcy.
Lovely to be with you, mate.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me, Luke Darcy, produced by Ed Gooden, with sound design
by Matt Currie.
To start your leadership journey, I encourage you to go to www.empoweringleaders.com.au.
Thanks, Darcy.
Bye-bye.
Welcome to www.elitacollective.com.
Take our Empowering Leaders Indicator Tool and understand the impact you have on your
environment.
Join us at Elida to learn, lead, and collaborate.