Matthew Nix is the current coach of the Adelaide Crows in the Australian Football League.
Before he became a coach, Nixie was an outstanding player for the Sydney Swans
and part of their famous Bloods culture.
Nixie was built from the ground up in the AFL,
with legends of the Sydney Swans making him earn his stripes as a young, brash 18-year-old.
I had a bit of swagger about me.
I was young, I was so nervous walking into that footy club
and my way of dealing with that was to sort of push the chest out a bit
and swagger my way in like I'm a big deal.
They tell me the story to this day that when I went down that day training,
there was a couple of guys that had a bit of a smirk and a bit of a laugh
and said, well, this was probably needed.
That Bloods culture has stuck with Nixie right the way through
and using that to mould his own style in his current role as coach of the Crows.
It was a very simple thing that we prided ourselves on and that was putting the team first.
We had a culture that was basically just prioritise others and put your teammates first.
The team's always number one and then from that individuals will shine.
We see many leaders like Matthew Nix, constant, never-ending self-improvers,
always looking for ways to get better.
And for Nixie, the pillar of leadership he is working on the most is his communication.
It was probably one of the things I thought was my weapon.
Since being in the hot chair, I've found it's one of my work-ons.
It's one that I've got to improve on.
People like Matthew Nix, who we are incredibly privileged to have as part of our Alita community.
You can be part of it yourself.
Go to alitacollective.com, book a discovery call today.
We curate groups of five to six leaders.
Around the globe.
You don't have to be the coach of the Adelaide Crows like Matthew Nix to be involved.
We'd love you to book a discovery call today.
A big thanks as always to Jason Nicholas and his team from Temper Bedding.
A mattress like no other.
NASA approved.
A third of your life is spent in bed.
You may as well make it at Temper.
Matthew Nix was an elite junior soccer player as a kid.
However, after watching the Adelaide Crows play in his home state of South Australia in the early 1990s,
he decided to switch codes to the Australian Rules football game.
It was a decision that would see him.
He went on to have a decade-long, 175-game professional career with the Sydney Swans
and ultimately leading back to where it all started as the now senior coach of the Adelaide Football Club
for the past five seasons.
Nixie, great to catch up with you.
Thanks, Darce.
Am I on the money with that?
Can you tell us about that night where you're sitting at the footy, soccer was your game,
and you thought, you know what, I'm going to change codes.
Is that true?
It's 100% true other than one word, which was elite soccer player.
I was solid.
I was solid as a soccer player.
I played it right through to 60.
16, 17 years of age, but definitely not elite.
Definitely not elite.
What drew you to the round ball game?
Probably friends.
You know, as you do, you start out at school and you build, I guess,
connections with other friends and so on, and then you follow.
And I followed a lot of my friends into soccer.
My older brother played soccer.
It wasn't necessarily as invested in sport as what I was, but yeah,
I just ended up with the round ball rather than the over one.
And can you literally remember sitting there?
It would have been footy park in those days.
Yeah.
You know, the Crows are the biggest game in town and huge amount of passion,
as you know, better than anyone else.
And do you remember thinking, Hey, I'm going to have a crack at this?
Yeah.
I got to do this.
It was almost one of those.
I remember standing with dad.
You can't stand there anymore.
The grandstand's gone of where I was exactly standing.
But if you were to drop down 20 meters, we now run out through
that area for training every day.
So every now and then I'll reminisce on the moment that where I was standing
there, the grass is still the same oval.
And so I'm able to look back and say, well, this was the spot almost.
Where I made a decision to change sports and had no idea that I'd end
up getting an opportunity.
I did classic sliding doors moment in life.
Isn't it to go from there at what age?
Well, I would have been, that would have been 16 when I was at the footy at that
stage, and then went with a few mates to West Adelaide, which is one of the
SNFL local clubs, um, played under 17s at West Adelaide and then 19s reserves.
And talk about being in the right spot at the right time.
We won the reserves premiership into 1994.
I was in the right spot at the right time.
Recruiters were there watching.
Amazing to then go on and have, you know, as I said, a 10 year career at the Sydney
Swans from that later start in life.
I mean, you clearly took to the game pretty quickly.
I had some very good coaches.
It wasn't super fast.
I arrived in Sydney after being drafted in that first week, I took on Dean McRae,
who was one of the strongest guys in the side and I came off second best.
I broke my tib fib.
So I spent the first 12 months watching, which in, when you look back on it, talk
about sliding doors.
It was a blessing in disguise because I wasn't ready for footy.
You know, there was a lot still to learn about the game.
And so that 12 months of being able to watch build up my body in the gym was, was a blessing
for me.
Pretty serious injury.
And you break both those bones in your, in your leg, but you look at that as a blessing.
You gave you a chance to really understand and learn rather than trying to slug it out
without being prepared.
Yeah, it taught me a couple of things.
One, I had to drink more milk, uh, cause it was the second broken leg I'd had.
I broke my leg playing soccer a couple of years earlier.
The other one.
So it taught me that, but it also gave me that, that chance to sit back and watch.
I was, it was interesting because when you go back, Paul Kelly, Tony Lockhart, you know,
these are the sort of names that, that I, I came to the Swans and joined as a teammate.
Now I had a bit of swagger about me.
Um, you know, I was young, I was so nervous walking into that footy club and my way of
dealing with that was to sort of push the chest out a bit and swagger my way in.
Like I'm a big deal.
They, they tell me the story to this day that when, when I went down that day at training,
there was a couple of guys that had a bit of a smirk and a bit of a laugh and said, well,
that if this was probably needed.
So talk about blessings, you know, that gave me a chance to watch, become a little more
humble and understand how good you've got to be to play at the level.
And then they shared that with me a number of years later, Paul Kelly, of all people
were the nicest man in the whole world, you know, taught me a really big lesson.
That's a bit of feedback, isn't it?
At a young age, isn't it?
Coming into an environment, you said at all time, legends of the game, the greatest ever
goal kicker and Brownlow medal winner and Paul Kelly, but you just felt like you were,
your nervousness was portrayed the wrong way.
You felt like you probably needed a little bit of that lesson.
Yeah.
And it's, well, and it's taught me a lot too, because I now see it every 12 months.
We get a new batch of young guys coming into the club through the draft, you know, 17,
18, 19 years old.
And occasionally one will come in with a similar persona, a similar sort of walk and strut
and the chest out.
And my experience enables me to sit down with them and have a great conversation and share
with, you know, some of the stuff I went through.
And I think it's been out of help.
I think it's been out of help in a big way.
I'm told that is one of your great strengths.
You're a great connector of people and you light up a room no matter who it is.
I mean, it's a different generation.
As an 18 year old, you were probably going to get a bit of a clip and someone was going
to come after you.
That generation now at 18 are a very different mindset.
Do you have to change the way you approach that given the evolving nature of this young
generation?
No, I know we talk about the generation being different and some will say they're a lot
more entitled.
I don't find that.
I think we're all the same.
I think people are just able to express themselves a little more.
Eventually, our guys realise if they do come in and the strut's there and there's that
almost that front or a mask, you've got to take it off if you're going to build the
connections you need to build and you're going to become a successful team.
So you're able to work through it.
But I think we allow that though now.
I think we open up and we want to hear, we want to see that expression from our players.
We don't want them to come in and hide and say, hey, you respect the sixth year player
for this reason.
It's like, no, respect them because they're a human being.
And then that sixth year player needs to respect the young kid coming in as well.
It's going to fast track our development.
But yeah, we do get some good characters coming in nowadays though.
In the early 90s, Nixie, when you walk into an AFL environment, the coaching landscape's
pretty brutal.
I remember one of your old teammates, Paul Roos, a legend of the game who went on to
coach and win premierships successfully saying that he wrote down a list as a player of the
things he thought were crazy.
About the way the game was coached.
And he put it in the top drawer.
And as a coach, you take that out and read it and go, I'm never going to be like that.
Have you had a similar thought from your experience?
Not exactly the same as Roosie, but I had heard that story and I was lucky enough to
be coached by Roosie and he's a huge influence on who I am as a coach.
Along with others, you know, Roosie had a style, amazing communicator and his ability
to connect our group or bring out the belief in players.
You know, I saw him transform.
Adam Goodes, you know, from a good footballer into one of the greatest I've seen play.
And I was lucky enough to play alongside him.
At his best, Adam Goodes was outstanding.
I have a similar or something similar to that.
I have a contract with really close friends and or mentors that we drew up.
And it's just a pretend rollout fake contract that we've got.
If I ever change my values or I change my behaviour, then I've got a certain amount of people in
special areas that are able to just.
Maybe call me up or sit me down face to face and just let me know and roll the contract
out and say, hang on, we agreed on, you wouldn't change who you were and what you valued.
And I've had to do that once or twice over the five years since taking the head coaching
role.
The head coaching role comes with some challenges, but I've been able to stick to what I value,
but I have had some help with that.
So you've had a couple of moments where, you know, these great mentors and friends in your
inner circle have tapped you on the shoulder and said, I reckon you're just slightly getting
away from, from.
Can you give us a bit of detail on that or maybe not the tap on the shoulder?
It's probably me sourcing out, um, you know, trying to find some information and it there's,
you know, there's been recent ones where I've called them up and I've said, listen, I've
got a, I've got a decision to make, and I just want to get your thoughts around this.
And, and after, you know, five minutes of me speaking and not a lot coming from the
other way, we then sat in silence for the next minute and then back down the phone.
I said, are you there?
Did you, sorry, still there?
And the line, the message back down the phone was, you don't have a decision to make my
friend.
Unless of course you've changed what it is you value.
And that was enough for me.
That was, thank you.
I'll, I'll chat to you soon.
Good on you for seeking that out.
I think there's a lot of things you can't control as a senior coach in sport or a senior
leader in lots of ways, but having an impact on the culture and those values, it sounds
like you've got a really clear idea of what that is.
Can you describe the culture you're trying to build at the Adelaide Crows?
What does that look like?
Yeah, well, it's, I mean, it's a blend of a lot of cultures I've seen, but there's one
standout culture that I spent my whole football career.
Which was the Sydney Swans.
And we, it was a very simple thing that we prided ourselves on, and that was putting
the team first.
And there's a lot of different terminologies around it.
You know, a lot of people spoke about the Bloods culture and so on and so forth.
I'm not sure we ever used that terminology.
I think that was someone made that up in the media, but we had a culture that was basically
just prioritise others and put your teammates first.
The team's always number one.
And then from that individuals will shine when it's their moment.
And so I've really driven that.
That's what we're going after at the Adelaide Footy Club.
I spent time with Port Adelaide as well.
You know, eight years working there as an assistant.
And, you know, even as an assistant these days, it's really important that you're able
to bring your own values.
And I guess if you're true to those, then others will follow.
So I spent time there and a year with the Giants as well, where I was lucky enough to
be alongside some, you know, some super players, as well as some super people off field.
You know, Leon Cameron was a massive influence on what I'm doing now.
And, you know, there's not many better than him.
It comes to understanding others and prioritising others.
So that's what we're trying to do at the Adelaide Footy Club at this point.
It's tough because we don't have any winning wallpaper at the moment or not a lot of winning
wallpaper, but we'll get there.
To go micro for a minute and the story that comes to mind, I think one of the most exciting
players in the competition, Josh Rochelli, in your team, you have a difficult decision.
He's made some choices.
And how do you get to those choices where you decide to leave him out for the last game?
But is it just being, that's another part that's been really clear.
This is what we should do.
This is what we stand for.
It's team first.
Can you give us some detail on how you arrive at decisions like that?
Yeah.
Well, you really nailed it.
You know, this is what we're about.
Unfortunately, it hasn't, you know, the behaviours haven't quite fit that at this point.
If you talk about why we did it, we did it or in the end, I say we, because we make decisions
as a group.
Ultimately, I'm the one who has to stamp that.
We did it because of the relationship that Josh and I now have, which is 10 times stronger
than it was pre the decision.
And that's where we've come to.
That's where I just knew there wasn't really a decision to make.
I knew long-term Josh and I were going to be better for it.
I know he's going to be a fantastic footballer and a leader of our footy club into the future.
It was important though, in this moment, that we made the decision we did.
What I don't want to do is have a leader, which Josh is going to be, going the wrong
direction.
And so it was a small adjustment we made.
And I look forward to him coming back next year and some people saying, oh, well, they
did make the right call there.
And that's what great leadership's about, isn't it?
Making those calls.
Even when they are uncomfortable, I look at your role and we just chatted briefly before
we went to air and the amount of pressure that professional coaches face here in Australia.
And I think here in Australia, maybe at the absolute extreme, but around the globe, you
lose two games, sack Matthew Nix.
You might've won four premierships in Alistair Clarkson, you lose three games and it's, hey,
we want you out of the space.
It's an incredible amount of stress to absorb continually.
How do you go about it?
How do you cope?
I don't read it for one or listen to it.
So how do you do that?
That's interesting to me.
You really just decide that's not helpful, but it always gets back, doesn't it?
Someone's going to share it with you.
Yeah.
Well, you just shared some with me then.
I'm sitting back now going, really?
Did they say that?
No, you can't hide from it, especially where we're based in South Australia, which is a
two-team town, as is Victoria, super passionate about Australian rules football.
But with the two teams, it does make sense.
It does make it tough.
I've just watched one of my mentors, a former coach I worked under in Ken Hinckley, lose
a prelim final.
What a fantastic effort to get there, to battle to where they did through injury.
And yet I'm looking at Ken under pressure at the moment, externally, which is just madness.
There's one team that's going to succeed this year, if you think success is winning a
premiership only, to then judge a coach around that and make decisions off the back of a
game that goes one kick on the siren.
Either way, it's madness, but it's what passion brings.
It's why we love the sport.
It's why it's the most watched sport in our country.
It's why there's so much commercial dollars coming in behind it, because people are entertained
by it and we're all driven by it.
So my job, though, is to try not to listen to too much of the noise and just continue
to back in what it is we're doing, as we were talking about before, the values of what we're
building.
Because if we go into the detail of where we're at as a football club at the moment,
we're not going to be able to do that.
We're not going to be able to do that.
To think we're going to win the premiership and to be a bit blase about it, like, if we
don't do it, we fail, then we're kidding ourselves.
We have a very young group of players that are still learning and developing.
We're having some huge success in a lot of areas, and it's not necessarily being seen
at the moment on the scoreboard.
But we know it's going to put us in a good space for that sustained success.
And I think this is a really important conversation.
What does success actually mean in life and in sport?
And I've said this a few times.
It was one of the saddest quotes, and Nathan Buckley, I've discussed this with him, where
he said he didn't enjoy one moment of his whole career because he was told, until you
win a premiership, you can't celebrate it.
And that's one of the all-time greats.
Tony Lockett, who you mentioned earlier, didn't win a premiership.
Does that mean his career wasn't successful?
I think that language is something that is interesting to me.
It doesn't clearly make sense.
Clearly, if you won premierships, that's the ultimate.
Everyone's trying to achieve it.
But there are degrees of success, aren't there?
Yeah.
There are.
But you're building for that ultimate success.
But I think what you'll find when you do get it.
Now, we won a premiership in 2005.
I didn't play on the day.
I played all year and missed out on the day through injury and probably wasn't quite up
to the form at that point.
I would have been selected anyway.
But after winning that premiership, the moment was there for a fleeting moment.
And then it was, what now?
The journey to get there was what?
It was the most rewarding.
That's what I look back on and I say.
The relationships we built over 11 years, that was the rewarding part.
And that's, I think, when you come back and you have a reunion as a premiership side,
you don't come back necessarily for that one day.
You come back for the 10 years prior to that that you built together and that camaraderie
that you've got.
It's hard because I understand, you know, for Bucks, a lot of that was the noise from
outside.
But the ability to take that pressure away from yourself, too, as an individual, and
rather than think about,
well, that's the only way I succeed, then you might actually find another level in your
footy as well.
Nick, it's been great to have you as part of a space we call Leader Connect.
We bring groups of people together to collaborate.
And your group's got University of Michigan, Manchester City, the Utah Jazz, Green Bay
Packers, and we love the idea of this collaborative learning.
Can you tell us a bit about that experience for you?
Well, I've probably sold it better than everyone because it's just the best experience I've
had as a coach since finishing up footy.
Especially since being in the, I guess, the head coaching chair, which can be lonely
at times.
I've got an amazing group of staff within our footy department and some really key staff
in that that are mentors of mine, even.
But it's something to have someone from outside the organization that you can just jump on
a phone call, on a Zoom call, sit and chat and share hurdles, share some of your successes,
ask questions, see what experiences they've gone through.
And as you mentioned, I mean, you read out the group I've got.
When I was told, this is the group you're going to sit with, I was kind of nervous getting
on that call.
But they're just fantastic people.
And I love for someone like you is curious enough and open enough to even want to expand
that and go into a second group as well, I believe, which is something we're seeing happen
quite regularly.
Yeah.
Well, as much as I can.
As many people as I can listen to, learn from, share ideas, get support from, welcome into
our environment as well.
Yeah.
I was lucky enough.
We had one of the members of my first group come over and join us and spend a week with
us just watching how we operate.
She probably thought that that was us doing her a favor.
It was actually me wanting to get some feedback from her on what she saw.
And, you know, she's had some fantastic success over in Michigan.
As many people as you can bounce ideas off and share thoughts with, no one knows everything.
We're all still learning and we always will be.
Even the best coaches in the world are still, in fact, there's probably some of them involved
in the Leader Connect.
I'm sure.
And they're the most curious we find, the ones that are having the most success and
constantly learning and constantly doing exactly what you're doing.
It's a familiar pattern, which is fascinating.
We see these patterns.
I love asking these questions and you'll know a fair bit about them.
But the idea that you can't really lead without understanding your own sense of leadership
and how do you fill up your cup?
You've got a busy schedule.
You've got lots going on.
Three young kids, high pressure job.
What do you do so that you can be at your best?
It's one that obviously everyone asks you.
My CEO, he comes and sits with me and says, what do you do, Nixie?
Because I used to play golf and then we had kids and five hours doesn't work walking around
a park.
Hard to justify.
You can't walk in the door afterwards and be real with yourself.
It is funny because what actually fills my cup is what I do for a job.
And my wife, my partner, she knows that.
Courtney's massive on that.
She goes, I know you don't go to work.
And we'll often.
You know, she has to look after three kids and I don't spend as much time at home as
what I would like to and what she would like me to.
But she knows that what I do is my passion.
And so I've got 45 kids that I work with every day and I get to go in and be amongst them.
And, you know, I spent 11 years being one of those kids and loved it.
And so whatever I can do now to share with them, to help them develop faster, to make
them better and ultimately we'll get the ultimate success in a premiership.
And that's where I get my rest from.
I don't come home from work fatigued.
It's unusual, I know.
I work massive hours, but then someone says to me, how do you do that?
I said, well, I'm not working really, am I?
And so it's really just balancing that with family is the hardest part.
Making sure that if I don't need to be in the club, that I am at home to support what
we're doing with the kids.
So that's a unique way to think about, isn't it?
When you're absolutely loving what you do.
If that's filling you up, why can't that be the balance that you get?
Have you got one piece of leadership advice that you pass on the most?
Yeah.
I mean, the biggest one is one of my values, which we, I mean, it's our overriding value
at the club, which is prioritise others.
My theory on life, and it's not just on sporting organisations, I did get a little bit of time
out of footy afterwards, about five or six years working in stockbroking, which is probably
about as close to footy as you get.
You know, you ride the waves week to week or day to day as the market changes, but the
biggest thing.
The biggest thing I found is if you put others first, you just, it's amazing how quickly
the reward comes back to you.
It actually makes you feel better.
I found a children's book when I, when I first took over at the Adelaide Footy Club, I was
sitting in bed reading a children's book to one of my kids and the book was, Have You
Filled a Bucket Today?
And I was sitting there, I was flicking through the pages and I was thinking, this is exactly
my philosophy around life and around, especially football, like when these young guys come
in.
And if I could use this book to explain it.
I had to go to Adelaide and I was going to work with Tex Walker, so I knew it had to
be a reasonably, reasonably.
A lot of pictures.
It's got a lot of pictures.
We didn't want it to be a year that we had to read this book.
It had to be like a couple of nights where you took it home.
So I ended up using that book with our playing group and that book then went through our
entire staff.
And so up through our admin and we now use that book when we initiate someone and welcome
them to our footy club.
We provide them with a copy of Have You Filled a Bucket?
And it's basically about doing the right thing by others.
It's amazing.
How that makes you also feel better.
And then this is, it's just basically fluent from there where we just look after each other.
And I've got no doubt that's why we had success at Sydney.
I've got no doubt that that still sits in.
I know the culture up there.
I've still got some guys I've played with that are involved and they take real pride
in the way they look after each other.
I say that is the highest form of living when you actually get to the level where that is
what you do naturally without expecting anything in return is maybe the catch.
And so I'm not, I'm not surprised that that's.
Right at the top of the tree for you.
I'm sure you've got a really clear vision for success at the Adelaide Crows and what
that means.
Is there specific things that you implement to bring people along the way to help support
that vision and make it their vision as well?
Yeah, we talk a lot about, about high performance.
So we talk about and we discuss, look, what is, what is it?
Especially at the moment with where we currently sit.
Members of the group can get a little bit flattened down on themselves when you're not,
you know, we haven't played finals football now for five years.
And that's.
Basically the five years that I've been at the footy club.
If you look at it purely from that and you look at, for example, this year, 15th, you
can get pretty down on, we're not having success, but we know that's not the case.
So what we go back to is we factor on what is high performance.
Now, high performance for me is getting the best out of yourself that you possibly can.
And then when working in a team, getting the best out of the people that are within that
team.
And we feel at the moment that we're doing, you know, we are working and having a lot
of success in that area.
And we know that.
Given time.
And that's what we're, I guess we're yearning for at the moment.
It's just that time.
We know if we keep going the way we are, we're going to have, you know, success.
It's going to be seen externally.
It's going to come with wins.
It's going to come with finals football.
And then hopefully, as we've discussed throughout this, it's going to come with that, that day
where we can look at each other and smile on a podium and go, it's not about really
today.
It's about the 10 years we've spent prior to this, or I better say that differently.
The five years we've spent prior to this.
When we do it next year.
Nice correction there, Nick.
It won't be that long.
Curiosity is something we talk about a lot.
And we love this idea of sort of having your head in the sky, but your feet on the ground
where you understand you've got to do the basics and the fundamentals, but you want
to be implementing and forging new ground.
How do you strike that balance?
Yeah.
And it's a really tough one.
It's backing in what you believe in, but also understanding that our game changes all the
time.
So if we're talking from a football point of view, we're constantly struggling.
We're searching for what's next.
It happens across all sports.
I was lucky enough to spend some time with Rick Charlesworth back in the day, early, early
coaching days.
And Rick, I mean, he'd had so much experience to that point that he was thinking in completely
different spaces to what I was as a young coach.
And it kind of confused me at the time, but looking back on it, I could see where he was.
He was finding what's next.
He'd spent some time during that period, I reckon with Fremantle and with Ross Lyon and
working on what the game of AFL was and where it was going to head.
And so I've taken a fair bit out of that.
We're now, without overdoing our opposition or game trends, we are heavily involved in
how do we change the game?
What can we do next that's going to advance us and get us ahead of our opponents?
We talk about communication a lot.
Maybe the thing that people focus on the most in terms of how they go about their leadership.
Do you have a mantra when it comes to how you communicate?
Yeah, I do.
I mean, it was probably one of the things I thought was my weapon.
And I had a lot of people talk about that before becoming a head coach.
Oh, you know, Nick, he's such a good communicator.
And so I started to believe the garbage.
Since being in the hot chair, I've found it's one of my work-ons.
It's one that I've got to improve on.
I'm extremely honest, sometimes to my detriment.
And it's a ruthless industry that we work in, but I've got a theory that I don't want
to be chasing my tail.
And something that I've been, you know, where it's been a small lie or something that's
not quite the truth, I'm going to tell it as it is.
And that way, we're not ever sort of dodging bullets.
We're not looking back and saying, oh, actually, no, sorry, we got that wrong.
You know, that might be a small fault.
I think my staff appreciate that, the fact that I'm really open about what we're doing.
Occasionally, I get a raised eyebrow, but it's like, well, I'm just telling you what
it is.
So it's probably one of my mantras is like, let's be open and honest.
Let's have a conversation.
I would definitely over-communicate rather than under.
And you know, as a great collaborator, is there an example of where collaboration's
been a real win for you in any area of your life?
Well, there's been both.
There's been examples where it hasn't.
Where it's, you know, every now and then you have someone come and just say, Nick,
you just make the call for us.
Go and make the coach's call.
We've got to get this done.
And I'm really open and want to share what it is.
I want to hear your view.
I want to hear what your view is.
So we've worked through that side of things.
But I've got no doubt, the more you collaborate with people, the more,
they feel empowered, the more they feel involved and the better level of work
that you get back from them or the better level of enthusiasm or input they're
going to give.
And you have to learn to strike that balance to occasionally go,
I'm making a captain's call here.
I've heard all the voices, but this is the path we're going down.
Is that the balance you're still looking for?
Yeah.
I think we've found that over the last few years.
But I think early, you know, especially early sitting in a head coaching seat
to actually understand at some point into a three-hour match committee meeting
around one selection.
Spot that's going to play the sub on that weekend.
I think everyone's looking for you to just make a call, Nixie.
You know, we'd have the odd one of those, but I think we've improved on that.
Time to go home on that one.
Yeah.
Who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Yeah, it's a good one.
Cause I've had some, I've had some crackers.
I mean, my mum, my mum was a high level tennis player, but played it down.
And it's not until you get older and that you look back on some of the things
she would tell me coming through playing sport that I went, yeah, mum,
you know, I thought that was just my mum, but I look back and she was quite successful.
So she was a huge influence and a leader of where I ended up getting to.
And so I was dad.
I don't want, I don't want to be disrespectful.
Dad played, you know, reasonable high level footy as well.
But, but mum was a teacher.
So she understood what it meant.
Didn't push it on me, but, but had some words of wisdom, you know, across the years.
I started at the Swans.
Ron Barassi was the coach in the first 12 months.
So you don't get many bigger.
As you know, as I mentioned, I broke my leg.
So I didn't spend a lot of time there playing footy, but,
but just watching Ron and how he operated, he,
he was a coach who taught me about attention to detail.
You know, I had Paul Roos who, I probably played my worst football under Paul Roos,
but it had nothing to do with him as a coach.
It just happened to be the time of my career where I wasn't at my best,
but I watched him bring the best out of some individuals, which I was just in awe of.
And that was through just,
you know,
ultimate communication.
And then I've worked alongside some amazing coaches along the journey.
You know, Kenny Hinkley at the moment, who's under some pressure, but he just,
you know, he taught me so much.
Leon Cameron, who I mentioned earlier.
That's just within footy.
Outside of footy, as I mentioned, I got out of footy for a short period of time.
So I had some amazing mentors in the wine industry, in the finance industry,
who sort of put me down a different path and taught me what some of that was about.
It's interesting though, because I did find that,
when you talk to corporate industry, they're not quite at the level of sport.
If something happens within a, within a sporting organisation, where there's an understanding that everyone,
if we all work together, we're going to be stronger.
Whereas I found the corporate industry, maybe it was just stockbroking.
We're all a little bit, uh, individual.
It's a bit hard.
I found it really hard finishing up and then same thing, getting into some of those spaces.
But you're so feedback driven, you're so team orientated.
You're almost programmed that way that it's confronting for other people, isn't it?
They're not used to it.
They're not used to just the feedbacks instantaneous in the world you're operating in now, isn't it?
And that there's a delay, you know, if it ever gets there, perhaps in other spaces.
Yeah, that's a real, it's a standout that you notice.
And even, even, even within a footy club, you know, you have a football department, uh, and an administration and an administration area.
Even the connection there is a, is a tough one at times because we are, and some would say we're a bit more ruthless in, I guess, in the football side of things than, than what you can be in a corporate.
Well, but if you ask us that that's not ruthless, it's actually just being open and honest, but just being honest, because if we're not, then, you know, sometimes you, sometimes you can be a young lady walks in with his chest puffed out, like thinking you're all it and a bit, you don't actually realize until someone's honest with you.
And it goes back to my first day at Sydney, you know, we don't know that until we're told.
So we're a bit obsessed with this idea of what collaboration can do.
And we're seeing great things happen when you bring people with values like yours together, who've got great intentions.
Is there,
a person you've thought, wow, you know, I'd love to connect and collaborate with that person on clearly what you're doing now or any other aspect of your life?
Is there a name that springs to mind?
Yeah.
There's a big one.
He's a big name.
Pep Guardiola.
If, if he's, if he's listening, um, no, I've always had a passion for soccer.
As you know, I started there.
Um, some of our game plans still based around similar to what, you know, some of the best soccer teams in the world play.
And it, and it's simple.
It's, um, our guys are all in with it.
But Pep Guardiola.
One I've, I've looked at, I've watched obviously some of the documentaries, I'm in a position at the moment where I have a reasonable connection there.
And so it may happen at some stage.
I'd really, I'd love to sit down over dinner and just, you know, spend a half an hour, an hour, just listening, just listening to how he operates.
What, what are his values?
Cause you don't see, it doesn't quite come out in the documentaries, but there's no doubt he has something that it just works.
Um, and he works with some of the, you know, the biggest names in the world.
Um, and he works with some of the biggest names in the world where it must be tough to get them to collaborate or, or, you know, to come together to play the way they do, especially every club he goes to has success.
Well, when that happens next year, and I reckon it's a live chance, we need to chat again.
I'd love to hear, uh, uh, what that interaction would be like.
And, you know, you've been a, uh, a great champion in everything you've done.
Your, your reputation and everyone who comes across you has got enormous respect.
And five years into, uh, a journey at Lake Crows, I wouldn't be backing against, uh, that success coming, uh, really quickly.
Thanks for joining.
Me today, mate.
It's great to catch up.
No, thanks to us.
Enjoyed it.
Thanks for listening to another episode of the Empowering Leaders Podcast.
Huge thanks as always to our great friends at Temper.
And we encourage you to check out our Leader Connect program.
New episodes are out every Wednesday morning at 6am.