A Listener Production.
G'day, it's Luke Darcy here.
Welcome to the Empowering Leaders Podcast.
It's the product of one of my oldest friendships.
Matt Wadowicz and I started playing junior footy together
when we were 14 years old.
He was the junior superstar of our team,
but when he shattered his ankle in our last game together,
it was me who went on to play AFL football for a living
while Matt became an incredible school teacher.
Matt's relentlessly authentic nature
was behind his refusal to allow a group of 25 kids
to be managed out of his school.
He went to the principal and told him
that these kids were the reason why he became a teacher.
The story of how all these kids went from being out of the school
to successfully completing Year 12,
and many then on to further education,
captivated me.
As a father of four school-aged children,
the idea that our kids would have a voice
in their own learning environment
and that their teachers would collaborate,
share ideas and work together
on the best outcomes,
for everyone,
was a lightbulb moment for me.
A leader,
spelled A-L-E-D-A,
a misspelling of an old Scots word
meaning to guide,
educate,
teach,
and draw out information,
was born out of this.
Together,
Matt and I have had the great privilege of working
with thousands of leaders in education,
sport,
industry,
and the arts.
And the only place to start, really,
is at the beginning,
and I'm sitting across from one of my oldest friends,
Matt Wadowicz,
who I met,
I think,
at the age of,
I'm thinking 12 or 13,
at the South Adelaide Football Club.
Is that your recollection?
I think so, mate.
I remember meeting you at a game against Sacred Heart
and South Adelaide were playing against them.
And I remember when you arrived,
you stole my position, mate,
in the first game.
So I wasn't too happy with this big skinny fella
from Ross Trevor coming to play for us.
Well, and that was my recollection, mate,
speaking about leadership and empowering leaders,
that you were the captain of all our junior sides.
You were the best player in all our junior,
and I was the ring-in that was father-son,
because my dad played at South Adelaide.
So I was a private school boy coming down South
with all the tough lads from down South.
And I did take a few people's positions,
and that didn't go down that well, mate.
But you stood up for me at a young age,
and I never forgot that,
because you were in my corner,
and it never lost me that you were the person
that came and extended that hand of friendship
when others weren't prepared to do it.
I do remember it, mate.
And yeah, I remember it fondly.
And so,
I'm really glad I did, really.
I mean, I just,
I can remember thinking to myself,
you know,
he's definitely got more aggression than me,
and you just, you know, you did.
You had a lot more aggression than me.
It's a work in progress still, mate.
But yeah, I was a bit surprised,
because I didn't realise growing up down South,
the rivalry between Ross Trevor and Sacred Heart.
And I was wondering,
why is this guy so fired up?
And I just had to try and settle you down.
But I just love playing footy with you.
And I remember, you know,
I just had this sense you're going to be a good player.
And you hadn't put it all together.
You were still growing at that stage.
But I remember really making sure when I had the ball,
I'd kick it to you as much as I could
and trying to support you as much as I could.
And then it was just awesome for me to,
you know, when my journey ended with footy,
to be able to watch you continuously get better and better
and watch from afar.
And no, it was brilliant, mate.
We loved having you on board.
And yeah, been great mates ever since.
Yeah, it was a fierce school rivalry
and a great friendship, mate,
being able to come down and play,
with you and we played all the way through.
We ended up, you know,
playing our first games in league football
in South Australia with South Adelaide,
I think a couple of weeks apart from memory.
And it culminated in 1992.
You were drafted to the Bombers.
I was drafted under the father-son to the Bulldogs,
which was probably the fulfillment of a lifelong dream.
But unfortunately for you, mate,
now last game of South Adelaide,
you shattered your ankle horrifically
to the point where the Bombers thought
that it was a two-year recovery and didn't take you over.
But how hard was that on you?
Because it changed your life.
Pretty much from then.
Yeah, it was at the time.
I remember it's funny now because you feel so long ago
that you feel like it's a different lifetime.
But I do remember at the time really affecting me.
I remember being, you know, very flat
because, you know, for probably the five years
leading up to it, you felt like, you know,
potentially this could be my career.
This could be my life.
And it was those days where SADFL players
and I'm sure Waffle players were the same
is that you would go over and train
with the team that drafted you.
Yeah.
I remember getting drafted the first year
and actually staying home, which is unheard of now.
But a lot of us did do that.
And including yourself, I think, Darce.
But a lot of us stayed home that first year.
And, you know, I always had in my mind that I'd go.
But the experience of training at an AFL club
over that pre-season, really just amazing.
And you just think, you know, this is going to happen.
This is going to be great.
So you almost get a taste of it and then it's taken away.
So I do remember dwelling on it for a few months.
But it's probably with me not so much in my nature
to continue to dwell on that.
I recognise that, you know, that door is closed for me.
Gave it a little bit of a go to come back,
but it didn't quite work out.
I remember you coming back from your first training session
at the Bombers.
We were desperate to make it in the AFL
and you'd done a weight session with the great Paul Salmon
and you were full of life and full of stories, as you said.
And you were, mate, I've said this very often,
a star player and athletically gifted.
Unfortunately, that recovery meant that that chapter was closed.
But I often tell this story.
You went to teachers.
You went to college, which is where our paths crossed again
and became a legendary teacher in South Australia.
And I remember, you know, we stayed in touch
and you're a great friend connecting all the way through
whenever you came to Melbourne.
But I'd occasionally hear the stories of a friend of a friend
or someone I knew ended up in Matt Waterwitz's class
and that it was a life-changing experience to be in your classroom.
And I know you're probably humble enough not to want to go too far into that,
but you clearly had a passion for being a teacher.
And you were clearly really good at it.
Yeah, it's funny.
I think when you reflect on it,
I reckon the original idea for getting into teaching
was the idea that I could do PE
and that I could have 12 weeks a year holiday.
So I think if I search really honestly in myself,
that was the reason.
But I remember in my last year,
and I still, you know, probably not dismissing the fact
that I really love working with kids.
But in my last year, I remember doing this presentation.
It was my final presentation at university
and it was about accountability.
And, you know,
you're going out in the world to become a teacher.
What's the most important things in terms of accountability?
And there's so many things you're accountable for.
You know, you're accountable for the students in your care.
You're accountable for the teachers around you,
the school values.
You're accountable to the Department of Education.
You're accountable.
And I remember this.
I remember thinking, I've nailed this presentation.
Like, this is great.
I'm going to get some great responses here.
I'll get a good score and away we go.
I finished.
And luckily for me,
or luckily for me in that,
my lecturer at the time was away.
And a philosophy major PhD doctor came in
and he was looking after our class that day.
And I'd finished my presentation sitting down,
feeling good about myself.
And he said, Matt, I've got a concern for you here.
And he said, I think if I was a teacher sitting in this room right now,
I'd be thinking, why the hell am I going to be a teacher?
Because you've just told me about all these terrible things
that I now need to worry about.
So think about the list now, Matt.
And you tell me,
what is the most important thing you're accountable for as a teacher?
And of course, there's a long silence and a big pause by me.
And I'm thinking through the list
and I'm thinking about all this stuff that I've just covered,
wondering what is it?
And of course, you know, you come straight back to it.
It is actually, you're accountable to the kids in your care.
And so that was big for me because I just thought, right,
if that's true, then I've got to get bloody good at this job.
So I can't really just think about the 12 weeks of your holidays
and kicking the footy with the kids out in the oval,
which is my original intention.
I've actually got to really take this seriously.
And that way you really enjoy it because it's part of your value.
So that's how I got into that.
There's around 25 kids, I understand,
were troubled and having challenges at school.
And schools traditionally manage kids out of school
who maybe aren't living up to the standard.
You're at a Cardone College on the McLaren Vale of South Australia
and some of those kids are probably going to get exited out of the school in year 10.
And you go to the principal and you say,
I became a teacher for these kids.
Give me these kids.
But there was a couple of conditions.
Can you pick up the story and tell us what happened?
Yeah.
Originally, I was a bit challenged by it because I just had this belief
that every classroom teacher should be integrating
and finding opportunities for those kids.
And I was sort of diametrically opposed to getting them out of class at the start.
But when I really realised that they were going to be turfed out,
I just came up with some alternatives.
And I got together with a great mate of mine,
who's now working with us, DAS, Damien Hill.
And we came up with this concept of masterclass,
which is this fully integrated rich task scenario
where the kids would be immersed in deep learning for each term of the year.
And the way that we tapped into the interest of the kids is,
day one, we brought them down to a beach.
They didn't know what was going on.
They just knew they were going to be immersed in this learning experience for the year.
And we took them down to the beach down at Somerton in South Australia.
And the way we launched it with them is we said approximately 40 years ago,
and I thought they had the exact date of the time.
And I said, there was a body here that was a dead body was found here on the beach.
And to this day, no one knows exactly what happened.
And it's a true story.
And now it's been in the media this year a lot, actually,
because I've tapped into some DNA stuff about this body.
But we gave the job to the students to help us solve the mystery of the Somerton Man.
The unknown, the unknown grave.
And yeah, we got them to, as part of this learning experience,
we got them to interview past detectives that worked on the case.
We got them to write letters to the editor.
We got them to do mathematical equations because there was a code that was linked to this story.
In this case, we got them to do presentations to their parents.
Yeah, the results were fantastic for these, for these boys.
Incredible story.
There's a theory that the Somerton Man potentially was a Russian spy who washed
up on Somerton Beach in South Australia.
He'd been almost surgically scrubbed, we understand.
And all the tags on his clothes removed.
And some of the markings were Russian tattoos.
And as you said, in recent times, the body's been exhumed.
There's such a fascination with it.
I believe you've got the old detective who was obsessed with the case back to speak to the kids.
So these kids have gone from being disengaged in their learning.
You've come up with a fairly random way to integrate it.
And all of a sudden, they're writing letters to the editor.
They're engaged in class.
And that group in year 10, from really maybe being out of the school, I understand every
one of them went on and finished year 12.
And a big portion of them actually then got to tertiary education after that.
Yeah, we had some great results.
And I guess the immediate impact we saw was attendance rates going up and behavior issues
was the big one going straight down.
And just the fact that some of the boys in particular were not attending.
And all of a sudden, they're writing me emails on the weekend saying, I've got another theory.
I've got another theory.
Mr. Man.
This is what I think's happened.
And even this is going back a number of years now, but as these stories have been unfolding
in the South Australian newspapers recently, I got an email from one of the old boys that
went through this program.
He said, Mr. Woodhouse, I thought we solved it.
What's the problem?
But it's great that we had that experience with the boys.
You being who you are, then said to the principal in the school, I'm handing these boys back
into the system next year, but I'm only doing it if you allow me to.
I'm only doing it if you allow me to help coach the teachers on how to engage these
boys properly.
And that is why you and I are sitting across from each other today.
It's where this whole story starts.
Can you talk about what you did and where that's gone?
The story of the summited man was great because it engaged people, but I knew it would only
last if teachers picked up and run with it.
And to their credit, the way they collaborated with us and took up this advantage to all
of a sudden for young Jimmy to want to write an essay about a topic that maybe wasn't part
of the syllabus.
But it's actually part of, you know, still doing the skills of essay writing, but now
it's about the summited man.
To their credit, they picked that up and they started really working and collaborating together.
And so I started to understand like the real power of me making a change was not just me.
It actually was all about the way that I'd construct the conditions where teachers were
working together.
And when I was asked to, you know, and work with my principal at the time, who was brilliant
at supporting me, to try and work out what's going to be the best way to coach teachers.
And how can I convince teachers that, you know, to ask what it's like that in education
that, you know, teachers are often in their classroom by themselves and they're given
that responsibility from such a young age and often the walls are shut, the doors are
shut.
So how do you create the conditions where you're breaking that down and trying to make
sure that they know you as a coach, you're in their corner and you're trying to best
support them because you know that they've got a really difficult job and it's incredibly
important.
And you ended up, I think people in education, I've been on this journey with you and I wish
they'd in touch.
I love the stories, you know, as a father of four myself and school age kids, you can
see the difference in their world when you have an engaged teacher and someone they connect
with, their life is just full of, you know, learning and excitement.
And when they're not so attached to a teacher, you could see what happens with, you know,
kids that were pretty otherwise happy.
So John Hattie is someone educators know a lot.
He's a professor of education.
He's currently at Melbourne University, but he was previously University of North Carolina
and also University of Auckland.
And he's known, Matt, for undertaking the largest ever meta-analysis into what effective
education looks like.
And, you know, without sort of stealing your thunder, I understand that he talks about
teachers first, second and third, the answer, good teachers.
So you can have a building that's been built for $50 million, the best new branch banking
library.
Excise is almost zero with that library, unless you fill up with great teachers.
And even greater than that, when you get teachers collaborating together, that's been shown
through his meta-analysis to work.
And he heard about you, heard about what you were doing, and, you know, maybe you can explain
what happened there.
Yeah, it was great to ask.
In Australia now, we have the AITSL standards, so the Australian Institute for Teaching and
School Leadership.
And teachers in Australia can now be judged, I guess, by criteria or standards in terms
of the way that...
They're impacting kids in the classroom, with the whole concept of we want to try and keep
great teachers in the classroom, and we want to try and increase their capacity and have
opportunities for them to develop.
And I went through the process.
When I was going to be a coach, I thought, well, I better know about these standards.
Managed to get myself certified as lead, which is the highest level.
And, you know, it was a funny story that I think is funny.
I had to present to a group of teachers who were going through certification.
I was one of the first that did it.
And I was talking about...
You know, I was a classic tall poppy, and some of my workmates were giving me a hard
time about certification.
And at that stage in South Australia, there was only about three or four teachers that
had been certified as lead.
And we had a consultant come out to the school saying, you know, we're thinking that the
next principal of this school will be certified as lead.
And everyone in the room knew that I was the only one in Catholic education in South Australia,
so they all looked at me and just started paying me out.
I was going to be the next principal.
And then all the payouts came through.
But when I was doing this story to the group of certified teachers, the CEO of AITS all
the time was in the room and liked my speech.
I didn't realise that later that day when she called me up on the phone to reflect on
that and how the process was for me and what I gleaned out of it, that John Hattie was
sitting in the car on speakerphone listening to my responses and taking note.
And I talked quite honestly about what I thought about the process and how it changed me as
a teacher, but also the bits I didn't like.
Yeah.
I appreciated that.
So they got me along to be on part of the teacher expert standing committee for Australia
for a couple of years.
So it was a real honour.
But you're right, Darce.
He was great at just cutting through stuff with the research saying it's all about the
teacher.
It's all about the way they collaborate.
It's not about the ego.
It's not about other things that we get distracted by.
And so that was really affirming to me that I was on the right track with the way I was
coaching.
So you built this model on the back of that, which initially called the Leadland Cycle.
It's been...
Rebranded to a leader, A-L-E-D-A, in recent times.
But effectively, we actually survey the kids in the classroom on their own learning environment.
And you think that, to me, would seem like an obvious thing, isn't it?
Let's listen to the people who we're trying to teach.
Not really done before, regularly.
And then getting these teachers to collaborate.
And I was just so inspired, mate, by getting a call from you.
You live in a beautiful part of the world, McLaren Vale, but you could be in the Barossa
and you'd be on the phone.
You'd be going, mate, I've just walked out of a year four classroom.
You're not going to believe what this is.
What are these teachers doing?
You can't...
This story, we need to capture it.
And I just kept thinking, God, imagine all the great teaching ideas and teaching practice
that's gone because no one shared it.
No one had collaborated.
We can all think of a great teacher that had an impact on our lives.
And great teachers change your lives.
We don't celebrate them enough, in my mind, in Australia.
What do we need to do that more?
I got through our process to go back to meet Peter Muddy Waters, who inspired me in year
four.
And amazing teacher, Tim Hart.
And in year 12, Ancient History, that had a huge impact.
So can you share with us stories where you've sat in classrooms and you've gone, God, we
need to share this.
We need to get teachers collaborating more.
Yeah, absolutely.
I mean, there's so many.
I'm really blessed.
I'm genuinely humbled by some of the teachers that are working in our schools.
And when you create the conditions where they're happy for you to sit in that classroom and
they're in your corner, you see some great things.
And one little example is when I first started this work, I remember going to a reception
class.
And it's actually in Old Norlunga in South Australia.
And I remember the teacher there taking the feedback from reception kids, you know, which
is staggering that they're even listening to the kids.
And I love that, that they're just not dismissing what the little ones are thinking.
Because, you know, they've got an opinion and they've got some thoughts.
And if you're smart about the questions you're asking them, you can actually get some real
insights into how they're going and how they're perceiving things.
But this teacher reflected, you know, with our feedback as well and just said, you know
what?
I think I'm being really much, 100%.
I'm teacher driven and I'd just love to hear some more of their voices sometimes.
And I think I can probably construct situations where they're actually engaged and really
having a greater level of involvement.
And so she she organized these little groups and pods of three or four kids and she she
worked out one person was going to be the leader and asking the questions and someone else
was going to make sure that someone was everyone was getting a turn.
And she just within a week had constructed this incredible learning experience and I was
just blown away.
Blown away by how amazing these kids were and how engaged they were.
And she was just sitting back just saying, like, this is a massive risk for me.
Like, you don't understand.
Like, I've never taken this much of a risk and I'm just so glad that it's working so
well.
And you almost get a tear in your eye when you see how pleased she is to be so, you know,
get someone in their corner and be reflective and just really change those, the outcomes
for those kids in the class.
And that's where, you know, the passion kicked in big time.
Is there anything more important?
And then us creating better environments for our kids and their education.
And I used to love, used to send me in the early days, a newsletter.
And so I have, this is principals taking us on and look at the front page of the newsletter.
And I used to complain sometimes most of the ones I would, we'd be telling us not to park.
And I felt like I was in trouble again, reading the newsletter from school sometimes, but
I'll paraphrase, but it was something like, I just want to write to the community and
tell you that we're surveying your kids on their learning environment.
Our teachers are undergoing a self-reflective practice on their own.
Learning journey, they're collecting that data.
They're working together to create better outcomes for the community and your kids.
I was like, that's what I want to hear.
I want to hear that everyone's on this learning journey.
And it just, it sounds simple what you've been able to do, but you've seen the transformation
in schools.
It's just, it's had a phenomenally positive effect on the places that you've been in.
Yeah, it is.
Uh, that's great.
Thanks, mate.
It's, it's brilliant to reflect on and, you know, I knew from the outset it needed to be simple.
Um, then there's gotta be, you know, if you understand something, well, you know, the
quote, you've, you've got to be able to simplify it and the concept of, you know, getting some
feedback, being curious, collaborating with others around you, being open that, you know,
no one's perfect.
You know, that's really part of this is to say no one's perfect.
It's a tough job, but, uh, we get so tied up in the next thing we have to do.
Sometimes we forget about how we're doing it.
And what are those strategies that we can harness from others that are going to make
our work more impactful?
And better for us.
And we can enjoy our jobs more, which I love those hacks that they shared within those
sessions that, uh, teachers can, can glean from each other.
Now the passion started in education, uh, Matty, but I've got to move to where it did
in our love of sport.
That's where we met, you know, 12 or 13 years of age at South Adelaide and, and clearly
onto AFL football in my journey.
But you've, uh, had that enormous passion for sport and, and the great part about the
coaches in 2020 and 2021.
And, and in recent times.
Is that they see themselves as educators more than ever.
They want to be better teachers.
They're open to feedback.
In fact, they're probably the most open group that you'd meet in the community.
And so we, uh, we started knocking on some doors in the world of sport and every second
week, I saw you in a different top, you're at the GWS giants one week, you're at Adelaide
Crows, the AFLW and the, uh, the Crows team.
You work with Luke Beveridge at the Bulldogs, Damien Hardwick at the Tigers, spent a lot
of time at Essendon who drafted you, which was fantastic to come full circle and work
with John Worsfold.
And.
His team and the handover to Ben, uh, Rutton now in the NRL, the Sydney Roosters and Trent
Robinson's incredibly successful team.
So it'd been remarkable to see how well that same cycle that you use in education, you
know, tailored a little bit to sport has been incredibly well-received.
Yeah, it was, it was fascinating, Darson.
Um, you know, I just had that hunch, you know, after doing it a number of times in schools
and getting such great feedback from, from an industry in an environment that is really
devoid traditionally of feedback.
Yeah.
education's improving a lot now. So I don't want to say that it's not, but if you compare it to
the world of elite sport, very devoid of feedback. So it was a challenge. And to get such good
responses, I was curious as to whether this would apply because I knew some of the great coaches I
had were great teachers and some of the great teachers I had were great coaches. And I was
wondering whether this would impact in the same way. And as you alluded to, what surprised me the
most is just how genuinely reflective and open the coaches in the AFL and in sport in general,
in regard to how can they best transmit information to players? How can they create
the conditions for learning? And how can they genuinely impact their performance? Because
they're given feedback from such a young age, as you know, and that really just sets them up for
this ability to be able to fast track any of the learning that I could bring to them, which was
great. Now, we're going to name drop here a little bit, mate,
because-
Because it has been quite an extraordinary story over the last six years. In recent times,
this process now from lead learn to a leader has passed its sixth birthday, but COVID hits,
hard to get into sporting organizations. But like a lot of people did, went to the online world and
you started the Australian Coach Symposium. I hope you can share some stories because the
Australian Coach Symposium had Don Pike, who's legendary West Coast Eagle and Adelaide Crows
coach, Justin Lang, the Australian.
Trent Robinson, who's a multiple premiership coach in the NRL. Matt King, who's a Melbourne
Storm legend and assistant coach as well to Trent Robinson. Ben Rutten is now at the Bombers. John
Wurstfold, Will Weaver has ended up at the Houston Rockets. So that group together through the COVID
period, right in the middle of their season in stressful times, decided that they wanted
you to facilitate a learning environment for them. Can you tell us how that experience has been?
Yeah, it's been amazing. And it came about through, you know, as a lot of these things do,
necessity because I was just driven to, you know, Essendon Football Club and the Sydney Roosters
had paid me some money, you know, to support the learning of their coaches. And so we had
organized an online learning environment for just their coaches individually with the Bombers.
But I knew that with Truck and Woosha, and then with Trent and also Kingy, that we weren't doing
them necessarily enough service there and we needed to extend their thinking. And so I started
to generate this idea of the collaboration. And then I got Pikey involved because he wasn't
coaching that year and he's good mates with Justin Langer. And we created, I'd come across
Will Weaver at the Sydney Kings. I'd been referred to him or he'd been referred to me, sorry, through
meeting at the Giants. And we put them together. And my concept was about, once again,
acknowledging that no one's perfect. Let's talk about what our strengths are and let's learn from
each other's strengths. And let's address what our greatest concerns are in terms of being a coach and
how can we support each other with that. And it's been an amazing, amazing group. So much so it was
meant to be an eight-week program and we've been going now, I think it's for about 18 months in
there. We still meet every fortnight and, you know, it's been an incredible example of that
collaborative learning. So these are highly successful people at the peak of their powers,
choosing to jump out, you know, with incredibly time poor, but, you know, the Australian cricket
coaches flying all around the world or even in COVID, they've got enormous amount of pressures
they are valuing, you know, jumping out even, you know, mid-test match. I want to get on and I want
to, you know, have this reflective practice with a group of my peers at the same level.
What are some of the things that you've seen firsthand? Because you've had this,
you've been flying the wall and facilitating and doing a great job in facilitating these
conversations. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, sometimes it can be as simple as little hacks in terms of,
you know, time management things that they share and little mantras that they use or
strategies they've got to make decisions.
Lots of those little hacks that they can all draw from, but sometimes it's even bigger than that.
You know, it could be that, and without the dropping the names, but you can imagine the
scenarios where a coach has just come online and after a really tough loss, you know, just
a soul destroying loss as a coach, you put everything into it. And then questioning quite
openly to the colleagues in our room, in our group, as you say, your peers and say, what do I do?
Like, this has been terrible. How do you guys relate?
I don't feel like my players have stepped up. I don't feel like they're delivering what they need
to deliver. And then, you know, someone else in the group will just, will say something. And this
is a real example of something that was said is, have you found a way to love every one of your
players? And just, there's this great pause and the other coaches are thinking like, you know,
what a great question, you know? And I reflect back as a teacher, having some of those kids
that you talked about, Dar, sometimes they're pretty tough to love, but you've got to find
that thing about them. And I think that's a great question. And I think that's a great question.
That makes them great and try and bring that out. And the feedback from the coach afterwards was
like, that is exactly what I needed to hear. Like, you know, you've made my day. Like I just,
that's exactly what I need to hear. I decompressed. I feel like I've got, you know, I feel like I can
go back tomorrow and I know my path's clear. I can now, you know, put that into action.
So there's some examples of the types of things that are discussed.
And I love it, mate. It's what inspires me and, you know, the passion and purpose that
I've got around this is that, you know, I played in an era where there was no collaboration. There
was no opportunity to do that. And in fairness to those coaches, they did the best they could
with their level of learning, but it was, you know, the one stick, which was, you know, probably
abuse and attack and see if you were strong enough to survive. And, you know, for some people that
worked, but for a lot of didn't. So to see, you know, the opportunity to be able to find ways and
learn from people who are in the arena at the moment, who are doing, you know, these things
high level. So the opportunity, that's what excites me to be out. And that flows, you know,
to me down to junior level, because a lot of, you know, you and I spent a lot of time at junior
sport and you just see people coaching like a video I saw from 1960 of John Kennedy screaming
at his head and said, probably not appropriate for 10 year olds. You know, we could probably
do that a little bit better and you can have a really amazingly powerful impact. The word got
out, Matty, and other coaches have been, you know, organically coming a leader's way. And you've got
now another group.
Paul Postacoglu is an incredible story. He's just signed as the first Australian to coach in the
Scottish league. The famous Celtic club having won a premiership in Japan. Neil Craig, legendary
Australian coach, former Crows and legendary in the world of exercise science. Eddie Jones is
coaching English rugby. Brian Gorgian, the current Australian basketball coach. And Luke Beveridge
is an old mate of mine, but incredible coach of the Bulldogs. So these other pods are popping up
of collaboration.
Yeah.
All of it. You're facilitating it. I know your eyes occasionally pop out. You go, you're
not going to believe what I'm hearing. It's been incredible, isn't it?
It has been amazing. I mean, it probably goes back to your previous point about in your
day, you know, there wouldn't have been that collaboration. I do, this is one I can definitely
share with you is that I got with the Australian Coach Symposium, the second group you're talking
about. There was a moment where we did reflect on the power of the collaborative learning
a couple of weeks ago. And Neil Craig did say, look, I really wish that I had this type
of forum when I was the coach of the Adelaide Crows. I've just, I've found it so affirming.
I've found it so challenging, but, you know, inspiring as well. And I thought, what a great
testimony to that. But, and I think, you know, if you, if you meant those names you've just
mentioned, Dars, what's, what's also been good is the, the challenges that they're facing
to be able to bounce their ideas and thoughts off a collaborative group of their peers has
just been outstanding. And my job is to really, uh, sometimes a lot get out of the way.
But make sure the questions are really, um, to the point where you're really delving into
the things that are going to matter most to them.
And based on reflection and a bit of data and them surveying their players. So they
take on the feedback. This is what you're doing well. And this is what, you know, the
areas to improve. And you always talk about being in the, in the corner of coaches. Um,
I had this great, uh, lunch a few months back. Marcus Pontempelli, uh, gave me a call. He
was a superstar, Australian rules, captain of the Bulldogs, the club that I was lucky
enough to play for.
You couldn't meet a more impressive young person in your life. And, you know, I think
he's close to 25, but just the way he's thinking. And again, he'd heard about this collaboration.
He was talking to me about it and he wanted to form a group of his own. And so he's ended
up with, uh, Pat Cummings, who I understand, I know you've been working with that. He's
almost the identical person in cricket, revered as just an incredible young leader. I know
you've been working with him and they, uh, you know, I know the guys won't mind, but
Andy Lee is one of the great success stories in entertainment.
You could meet a better person than Andy Lee, Hamish and Andy, and their success is
just extraordinary. Rob Sitch from Working Dog, who, again, you couldn't, you know, describe
the group that are more creative. And to think that group of people are getting together,
two young sporting leaders with a couple of leaders from the arts. Um, tell us a bit about
that one.
Yeah. And I mean, you can take a lot of credit for this too, Darce, in terms of, you know,
us reflecting over, over COVID time and saying, you know, we really probably need to challenge
ourselves a lot more in terms of getting, you know, a lot of people involved in the
sport.
Yeah.
We've done this great work within schools and we've done, well, we think it's great.
I think it's great.
We've done this work in sport, you know, but is there these opportunities and we'd done
in a working corporate, is there an opportunity for us to challenge, um, you know, I guess
what we'd done previously and have cross collaborative groups.
And if the, if the focus is on our own leadership of self or, you know, improving our own environments,
why can't it be someone from the arts and why can't it be someone from sport?
And so, you know, that's been a really good opportunity.
good process, hasn't it? It sure has. And again, I love what, I certainly at 25 years of age didn't
have the thought process of Marcus Bond and Pellier, I'm sure Pat Cummings, but it's sports
a chapter for all of us and there are other things to learn and the opportunity to be out, as you
said, create these learning collaborative pods. And that's where you and I see it, don't we,
this opportunity to connect, we're calling it. And the idea that organically now we're just sort
of pulling groups together, these learning environments based on you and your environment
in real term, it's not, you know, the guest speaker, we've all been and seen great guest
speakers and it's, you know, it's fantastic and we love it. This is really, we see incredible
opportunity to learn and grow. So we're interested in expanding that, aren't we, mate? Because you've
seen firsthand, the stories are just really powerful. Absolutely. It seems to be a really
great combination between having some rigor and depth and understanding of your own environment
and then being able to take some
really practical steps from the group, you know, as to how to address issues that we all face,
you know, issues about communication or issues about collaboration, issues about, you know,
having the vision of where to go. You know, there's a lot of great leaders out there that
have got brilliant hacks and a lot of people have listened to podcasts or read books and,
but if you've got the synthesis of people that are living it and breathing it at the time and
they can put it into practice and give you advice, but also on the flip side, if you can come armed
with some questions that are really going to be timely,
it's just such a powerful forum. Yeah. And that's, you know, why we're here.
The Empowering Leaders podcast is, you know, part of what we're hoping to bring together. And
we're seeing the 21st century guys firsthand who just get the idea that you need to give everyone
a voice. You can impact your invite, not just about you. It's not all about self all the time.
It's the shift from I, how about my self-improvement to how do I impact others? That's something that
we're really passionate about identifying, aren't we, mate?
Absolutely. It's such a key, isn't it? It's a crucial element. And if you think back to yourself
as when you had your first job, you know, any of the job you've had, if you had the type of leader
that really appreciated your thoughts and supported you along the way, communicated where they wanted
you to go with, provided you with feedback about what it was to get better, gave you opportunities
to impact and create the vision with them. I mean, it's an inspiring thing. And as you alluded to
with football coaches that coach the way that they were coached,
sometimes leaders lead the way they were led. And what we're finding is now the ones that are
really making a big difference in their environments and pushing forward, just they've got humility and
an understanding that they've got to bring people along for the journey. Sometimes it can be a bit
more time consuming because they like to be able to be decisive and there's always a time for that.
But great leaders recognize that collaboration is going to get you better results.
And we know firsthand that investing in this space, Matt, is an investment that does
pay off. I was looking at some stats, you know, in preparation for today, and there's a state of
the global workplace analysis done by Gallup back in 2018. And they came up with a number of 85%
of people generally not happy at work globally. And they had a number of $7 trillion annually
lost in productivity based on that. There was another survey of 400 large companies
called the cost of poor communication, talking about tens and tens of millions of dollars
just on the communication part alone. So,
to me, there's nothing sadder than being disengaged at work. It flows into your personal life. It
flows into your family. It flows into your general well-being and your happiness. People
take more sick days when they're disengaged at work. They cut corners because, you know,
they don't feel like they are connected to the place that they're in. It's a serious opportunity,
isn't it? Because we're, you know, seeing at the coalface. When you do reverse that,
you get buy-in, you get engagement. All these things come together in such an awesome way.
Yeah. Yeah, exactly right. And if I come back to my beginnings, you know,
the research into education leaves clues. And I know there's a lot of sporting analogies that
leaves clues too in terms of how to get the best out of people. But if the teacher has the greatest
impact in the environment of a classroom, it certainly makes sense to me that your leader
at your workplace has an incredibly impactful presence in your environment. So, if they change
their practice and their attitudes and their, you know, their, you know, their, you know, their, you
know, the way they work with the team, then it certainly can impact, you know, this idea that
you're talking about, which is people's willingness and love for their workplace. And as you know,
with this next era that we talk about, Darcy, there's going to be more and more push towards
working with a place that's, you know, relevant to you, they align to your values, and it's working
in the direction that you want to be going into. Now, the educator in you, mate, is always about
effectiveness and efficacy, and you won't do anything unless you measure it and can understand,
and part of what we're thinking in the Empowering Leaders podcast is to try and focus in, you've got
a lot of work now and a lot of history and a lot of data on the dimensions of what makes a great
leader. And you really put some work in the process of building an indicator tool. So, I encourage you
to have a look at doing that and start your own self-reflective journey on your impact on others
in the environment. But you've really put some thought and time and data into what makes a great
leader. So, I might try and delve into that with you. And hopefully, as the podcast progresses,
we can talk to you about that. So, thank you so much, Darcy.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
Kylie Watson-Wheeler from Disney is an extraordinary leader about these dimensions and all the people
that we've mentioned before. I'm looking forward to finding if there is some synergy around these
dimensions we've talked about. So, let me start because self-leadership is a big part of what you
talk about and one of the key dimensions. What does it mean to you? Yeah, it's fascinating,
isn't it? So, your ability to be able to impact any environment, really, you can only do that if
you're feeling good about yourself. You've got a lot of experience, you've got a lot of experience,
you've got to be able to know what you stand for, know where you're headed. You need to be
healthy. And so, if you think about some leaders out there that don't look after themselves and
get that right, it's really hard. And the other thing I should say too, you've got to live the
example. Leaders that you want to follow are ones that actually, they walk the talk. They've got
often very aspirational in terms of what could be done, but they've got their feet on the ground
and they're trying to get things done that live up to where they're headed. And so,
they're some of the most important things to get right. Your well-being,
your clarity of your direction, your values, they need to be going in the right direction.
A lot of leadership in the past, Matt, has been about the I and this is my personality profile
and this is who I am. And there's a lot of those tools out there to identify you as a certain
character type. And in my mind, I've always felt that's a little bit restrictive in that that's
almost a definitive part about you're that type of character and you're going to have these
limitations. Whereas, we're talking about a lot of people that are going to have these
limitations. We're talking now about, yes, self-reflection, as you said, is where you need
to start. But then, the dimension you really want to focus in, how are you impacting others?
Why is that important? Yeah, that's right. I mean, I reflected on a lot of, I've done a lot
of those tests and they do give you an insight into yourself and I'm not dismissing those. But
that to me is always a small part of the puzzle. I'm with you, Darce. I just believe it's more
about, it can't be just about me. It can't be just about my knowledge of self. It's actually
going to be about me. It's going to be about me. It's going to be about me. It's going to be about
me. It's going to be about me. It's going to be about me. It's going to be about me. It's going to be about
me. It's going to be about me. It's going to be about me. It's going to be about me. It's going to
be about me. It's going to be about me. It's going to be about me. It's going to be about me.
How can I genuinely, and you've said it previously, how can I genuinely positively impact
those around me? That is the outcome of improving. You lead self, you change the environment,
you can change the practices around your environment. And the outcome of that is the
impact. And to your question about what have I seen and what's fascinating for me here,
and actually comes back to your comment about junior football coaches or junior any coaches,
is we just do, we get mesmerized by the scoreboard. And what's
astounding to me is that a lot of those junior coaches may not recognize that
virtually no elite coach does that. They definitely are process oriented. And they're
really about the impact they're having on the individuals in their environment and the processes
they're trying to improve to create great outcomes. The scoreboard is a byproduct of that.
And the same applies to KPIs in workplaces. So if you're just measuring the KPIs and you're
not considering how you're leading yourself,
the outcomes you're trying to achieve in terms of betterment of people and developing your people,
you're measuring the wrong thing. If you measure those things about developing your people and
developing your environment, the scoreboard is a great indicator as to it's working.
But that's where the impact conversation comes out. And you take it back to your comments and
about John Hattie at the start, it's being so curious as an educator about what am I doing
in the classroom today and this week that's going to make a difference to these kids in my care?
It's being quite relentless in that.
Yeah, it's brilliant. So that's talking about the dimension of how you impact others and
you're passionate about how you go about creating and sharing it. What can you tell us about that?
As we talked about before, there's a general push now in society for people to
understand and be cognizant that they're going to spend a lot of time at work.
And you want to be working or working towards something that you believe in.
And that's not always going to be the case for everyone, but there's always going to be
opportunities for you to be able to do that. And that's going to be the case for everyone.
to align some of your values to the vision of the company. And if companies can recognize or
businesses can recognize where they're trying to make a difference, and then you can enable
your team to be part of contributing or co-contributing to that vision, I think it's a
really great opportunity. And the great organizations I've worked with are really quite
inclusive in terms of shaping that together. There's always someone that's got that inspiration
and you look for that and you need that. And everyone's got their role to play.
But the contribution or the co-contribution is really important.
So how do you approach learning and improvement? That's the other dimension
that you want to talk about as well, learning and improvement.
So learning is generally about being quite open. Carol Dweck speaks about growth mindset.
And it's definitely about having that aptitude to say, as a leader, I just definitely don't
have to have all the answers. I do really need to be clear on where we're going and whether
whatever you're bringing to me in terms of new learning is
going to support me going along that journey. But it's genuinely about, is this going to
be a possibility here and being open to that? And acknowledging that you as a leader do not
have to have all the answers. You need to embrace your allies. You need to use people around you
for support. You need to seek counsel. You need to understand that you can't do it alone.
And we want to set leaders up for success. And we're not going to do that unless we
understand those things. Communicating with clarity is a dimension that you're
really passionate about. And I think that's a really important thing. And I think that's a
absolutely. I mean, when we go in, I've learned this. This actually came from our research that
we've done. One of the areas that there's often a great discrepancy in any environment we've
worked in, whether it be schools, corporate, or in sport, is the clarity around this particular
statement. What's the criteria by which you're being judged? And the clarity around that is,
how well is that communicated? How well is it today? For example, how well am I
the criteria by which I'm being judged? It's an interesting question. And sometimes there's a
lot of guesswork that goes into it. And I think that the way that leaders can communicate the
expectations, but even if they're going to elevate their performance, what you want to do in the end
is you want to create the conditions where the people that you're leading are co-constructing
the criteria by which they're being judged. Because if I'm doing that, I've got an intent
knowledge of, or an in-depth knowledge of your expectations of me, but also,
how I'm going to contribute to the betterment of where I am, whether it be the classroom,
or whether it be the organization, or the team. How am I going to contribute to that? And what
am I being judged on? What should I be judged on? And often we're thinking immediately,
in any startup business, and that's what we've created ourselves. It's the bottom line and,
God, how do I get to a successful, sustained part of your business and have enough income?
The financial metrics are huge, but
as we know, if you don't work on, there's a stat that I read recently, if people don't feel like
they're being developed in their environment, they're 12 times more likely to leave. And we
know the cost of that, finding new people to work with is just enormous strain and burden. So
having an understanding about this, isn't it? Whether you're, as I said before, in a small
business of two people, or three people, or in a huge organization, there's an opportunity to learn
and have an impact on this straight away, isn't there? Absolutely. I'm thinking about
communication at the moment and thinking about, there are different communication styles too, but
one thing that's been a surprise to me is the absolute elite leaders, they are exceptional
listeners. And if you think about when you're at school and the different lessons you learn,
and there's so many things, we don't want to throw stones at school, but certainly when I was at
school, no one ever picked up on my listening skills. And the great leaders in terms of
communication, they're intent listeners. And I think that's one of the things that I've been
and they're really reflective listeners, and they just don't jump to conclusions too quickly.
And once again, it can be time consuming, but it's about having that disciplined approach.
I'm actually, now I've got to be really present. I've really got to listen. I've got to put
everything aside and just be with you, Luke, right now, be understanding what you're saying,
not just to respond, but actually think about how that can impact me and improve my life.
Underestimated skill, isn't that? The ability to listen as part of communication. And
we're talking about this world of collaboration,
the leader of the world of collaboration is the language where you, how important is it to you?
It is right up there as one of the most important things you can do. And there is a time cost,
but it pays itself back in spades. If you prioritize collaboration and you're strategic
about how you do it and you embrace great strategies to do it, the payoffs are extreme,
whether it be the scoreboard taking care of itself, whether it be the outcomes in the classroom,
or whether it be the outcomes on the field, it pays.
It pays dividends if you can collaborate well and not dismiss the ideas of others too readily.
There'll be people that will say, yeah, okay, but you've got to have a decision maker,
can't have too many chiefs. And that's a thinking that a lot of people perhaps listened to this was
a sounds great and it sounds fluffy. But your experience is saying that, and clearly at some
point you do need decision making and you collaborate to an extent. What's the fine
line in achieving that? Yeah, I think it actually does come back to
energy. If you're setting up the conditions for collaboration, you've got to only pose the
question if you're genuine about it. I think sometimes people collaborate on the little
things that actually don't make a difference and they think, oh, yep, I've ticked that box.
We're going to collaborate today on how to paint the studio. Brilliant. That's a great thing.
Try and think about things that are genuinely a chance for you to improve, processes you can
improve and genuinely ask the question, and then do it in a strategic way,
not that you're going to guide the answer, but that there is going to be a conclusion.
So you're already thinking about that opportunity to collaborate and you're going to think about
when is the decision going to be made and how am I going to get the thoughts in? But at the end of
the day, Darcy, you're right, there's still going to be a decision to be made. And mate, it's
interesting, those six dimensions are something I know you're really passionate about. It's your
hack, it's your data. You put a lot of time into what you think over this journey makes a great
leader and you've been doing it for a long time. And I think that's a great thing to do. And I think
witnessing great leadership up close and personal now for many, many years. And is there
something that you think, God, I'm seeing traits already. There's a pattern here around what great
leadership looks like. There is a pattern. There is a pattern. And a lot of the qualities we've
talked about today is certainly part of that. I mean, the other part that I guess we haven't
talked too much about is the curiosity and the creativity together. Just being really curious
about what you're doing. And I think that's a great thing to do. And I think that's a great
I can do as a leader to impact positively those people around me. And what can I learn from other
people? Rob Sitch sent us a great article the other day and we read through it as a group. And
it was basically written by an astronaut and it was about the lessons learned from being an
astronaut and how it applies to life on earth. Sometimes when we go into a new environment,
we want to stand out, but it's about sometimes we actually just really need to be a great teammate
first. And I think what I'm noticing,
about great leaders is that they were once great teammates and they used to pride themselves on
being a great teammate. And that actually becomes a really good hallmark of a really good leader.
Because if you're a great teammate, you like to embrace the thoughts of others. You like to be
clear about where you're going. You like to communicate well with people. And so this
chapter that he sent through was talking about when you're a zero, that's about being a great
teammate. When you're a plus one, you really want to stand out from the crowd. And the chapter,
goes on to explain that when they're filtering out the NASA astronauts from when they've got
through top of their class, what they do is they take them to a cocktail party and the prior
NASA astronauts are at the cocktail party and they separate them out. And then they have a
drink with them all to work out whether this person is a zero or a plus one. Is this someone
who's just going to be a great teammate? Or is this someone who is going to try and stand out
from the crowd and be a hero? What they want is a zero. They don't always want the plus one.
And so a lot of the great leaders I'm working with is a zero. They really want a compliment.
They really want to make the most of their environment for the people that they're
working with. They don't necessarily want to be the hero, the sage on the stage.
It's a brilliant story, Matt. And Matt, I feel as connected to this space as anything I've done
in my life. And I feel lucky that to play sport for a living was a great thing I wanted to do
from a young age, a bit like you. Playing sport, I wanted to work in the media. I had a pretty
clear vision around that. But I already had a lot of experience with the media. I had a lot of
feel like this chapter, when we sit together, talk about these stories, see the impact it has
on people, genuinely positive impact it has on people. And I've been in work environments and
seen work environments with disengaged people. And it makes me sad because I've never felt that
way. I've always been fortunate to, and I suppose maybe determined that I wouldn't tolerate not
being in a space that you weren't focused and passionate about. So Matt, the work you're doing,
it's inspiring, Matt. To reconnect our old friendship has been one of the great things
that's happened in recent times.
Not that we ever lost touch, but now, Matt, I think I spend more time on the phone than you,
than I do with Beck. And I think Sarah, your wife's going, it's a bromance. We love it. We
see that there's so much potential in it. And it is an opportunity, Matt, to talk about, I hope
people do have a look at Alita, have a look at, we want to expand those Alita Connect little learning
pods. We want to get into education. We're really passionate about. I know we're going to do some
work in the mental health space in schools because the cold face you're telling me,
really clearly that we need to get back into schools. And we've got some great plans in the
world of collaboration that we're undertaking, mate. So it's a great way to start. I couldn't
be more passionate about what we're doing. And it's based on your ideas, mate, and your execution
and the way you, to me, it doesn't matter if you're in a room with a prep teacher or Justin
Langer, you're yourself in every environment. People pick up on your authenticity, mate,
and everything you do. And it's been an awesome thing to be involved with you in.
Thanks, mate. It's my privilege. And you're definitely underselling yourself there in terms
of the impact you have on our work. And we've described you as our centred visionary of the
team. And you get us to think big picture. And I think, and it comes back to some of the self
leadership that you do yourself, mate, with the meditation and your link to purpose and doing
things that are purposeful for you. It just resonates with us. And it's why we connect so
well. And it's why it's a great partnership, mate. So thanks for having me along. And yeah,
thanks for all that.
Thanks for all of your work that you've done to get the podcast going as well.
Head to Aleda, A-L-E-D-A, and have a look at the Empowering Leaders Indicator. So final question,
question without notice, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Well, that's a brilliant question. The greatest leader. There's a big pause there. I mean,
I just, I'm genuinely, I just feel like, I just feel like no one's perfect. And I just feel like
I'm in the most privileged position ever, that I get to see these incredible,
incredible leaders. And if I could take parts of all of them, you could almost make up this
unbelievable leader. You know, there's some of the elements of some of these footy coaches that
are just incredible storytellers. There's elements of the school teachers that just got
incredible empathy and connection with their, with the kids that they're teaching. And then
some of these corporate leaders that have just got this vision of what's possible in terms of
having global impact that, I mean, if you could just combine those things together.
Um, but, but there's,
there's not one leader that just stands out as, as the, the standout that I've worked with
personally. Um, you know, from a historical perspective, I've just always loved, you know,
the idea of Gandhi and, and that, that the, the, the story of his life and the millions that he's
impacted and the way he went about it and the way he, you know, walk the talk. And so, you know,
he's one that just springs to mind to us, but there's, there's so many great ones. It's really
hard to, to choose. We didn't get you off the fence, mate. I think that's going to be a hard
question to answer for, uh, for our guests. We're, you know,
lucky to be connected, uh, as we said, from incredible educators to these amazing sporting
leaders and leaders from industry and the arts. That's what we're planning with the Empowering
Leaders podcast. We couldn't start anywhere apart from, uh, with you and your story,
Matty. As I said, it's a friendship that I value greatly, and we'll look forward to many more years
of, uh, hopefully inspiring people to, uh, to begin their learning and reflection and collaboration.
Thank you, mate.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me, Luke Darcy, produced by Matt Dwyer with audio
production by Darcy Thompson. To start your leadership journey, I encourage you to go to
elitacollective.com, take our Empowering Leaders indicator tool and understand the impact you have
on your environment. Join us at Elita to learn, lead, and collaborate.