Australian football icon Max Gorn is the guest this week on the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Max is the captain of the Melbourne Football Club in the AFL, a seven-time All-Australian.
He wears the number 11 in the Melbourne Football Club history, worn by one of their all-time
greats, Jimmy Steins, and the former president and a man who had the biggest impact on Max
during his career.
I knew Jim for two and a half years, but he has been my mentor for 16 years, which is
very weird to say it like that, because he wasn't my mentor in that two and a half years
of that.
And at the time, I was a young, naive kid, and I'm like, can the president stop texting
me?
16 years later, I've looked and everything I've done in terms of all my leadership is
the values that he's installed in me in two years that I didn't know at that time.
And it's unfortunate that a passing is almost what sort of put it in my head that this is,
oh my God, it's like my wow moment.
Everything I do in my leadership is a clone of Jim.
The Demons have had many issues in the last 12 months, and as their captain and leader,
it has been a real balancing act for Max Gorn to be the voice and the face of his club.
This is a lot.
I'm constantly defending the club, and then there'll be another fire in two weeks.
And the later stuff with track, it's worn me down.
And I don't like that, because I feel like I've always been able to handle it, but it's
starting to wear me down, because it's something I'm so proud of that I feel like I've had
a good handle of creating, like you said, the most successful era.
And I can just see it getting chewed, like constantly chipped at, chipped at, chipped
at, and I'm constantly trying to defend it.
Hear Max talk about how leadership has changed enormously in his time as captain and dealing
with the Gen Zs.
It's a completely different landscape to the one that he had known previously.
You almost do better as a team if you let them run the club and let the 20-year-olds
take you forward, because they'll just take you on a journey.
They've got no stresses or pressures or anxieties that Gen Y millennials have.
They're just loving life.
If you let them take you somewhere, you'd be amazed how far you can go.
It's people like Max Gorn who inspire the work we do at Alita, and we are really privileged
to have Max as part of our Alita Connect program.
Head to alitacollective.com.
We bring together groups of five or six people from around the globe to come together to
learn and to share and to collaborate.
You don't have to be an AFL legend like Max Gorn to be part of it, but we'd love you to
book a discovery call today.
Big thanks, as always, to Jason Nicholas and the team from Temper Bedding.
A mattress like no other.
NASA approved.
The best.
In bedding.
Check it out today.
Max Gorn is a seven-time All-Australian and Premiership Captain of the Melbourne Football
Club, regarded as one of the game's greatest ever ruckman, made even more remarkable for
me when he considered he had to overcome two ACL knee reconstructions before his career
had basically even started.
His captaincy in Melbourne's 57-year historic drought-breaking Premiership is legendary,
having been instrumental in the most successful period in the club's history in the modern
era.
Great to catch up with you, Max.
Thanks for taking the time.
Thanks to us.
Looking forward to this.
Mum and Dad grew up in New Zealand.
I did.
Three years of age, you're living in the South Island of New Zealand.
You played junior rugby union as a kid.
It's a pretty unlikely start for someone to go on and be an all-time great of Australian
football.
Were you close to choosing a different path?
Yeah, it's a unique upbringing.
Mum and Dad, not sure if you know too much about South Island, New Zealand, but they're
sort of like four hours north-west of Queenstown, and it's the most beautiful part of the world
and the best ski fields in the world, and I've never skied in my life.
I'm sitting there going,
and how have you not let me ski?
It's literally the best ski fields in the world, but I really enjoy that my parents are from
the middle of nowhere in New Zealand, and some of the questions that they were asking
when recruiters were rocking around at my house when I was 18, I'm sitting there going,
what are the facilities like?
And they're like, so when the ball goes through for a goal, what happens then?
Does it come back to the ... They really were raw, and now they've gone the complete other
way, and Dad's an expert and knows if I'm playing good or bad, but it's been a cool
little journey with that New Zealand heritage.
I played rugby until I was sort of 11, but then quickly learned in Victoria, playing
rugby, you're that kid that's probably going to get bullied throughout school, so I jumped
in and played with my mates and loved it.
I can tell you why you haven't skied.
209 centimetres, 110 kilos, that's not conducive, but maybe life after footy for you, but I've
got to go back to the ACLs, and I remember as a player hearing the news, this young Ruckman's
done his second knee, and I remember thinking, that's just going to be such a hard road back
from there.
Are you surprised that you've done that?
Your body has served you so well to go on and have the success that you've had?
I was naive around what a knee reco was.
In my eyes, I'm like, oh yeah, of course I'm going to get back.
The doctors told me it's a 12-minute injury, and that's all I ... Now looking back, I'm
like, phew, that's a fair scare there.
I went knee reco when I was 17 into seven knee arthroscopes into another knee reco.
It was a pretty catastrophic start, and you know when you're first walking to a football
club, all you want to do is earn respect.
You want to earn respect of your teammates, and I'm sitting there 18 months basically
just constantly getting knee surgery after knee surgery after knee surgery, and everyone
is like, okay, well this kid's not going to go anywhere.
The naivety sort of helped me through that, and also one thing that kept me going was
I love fitness.
In my head, when I'm sitting there on a spin bike and everyone else is doing the fun stuff
and out there training, I'm like, well, I would be doing this at 5 a.m. before my 9
to 5, paying to do it at a fitness first, and then having to work a full day.
Instead, I'm in the best facilities in Melbourne.
I'm getting paid to do the spin bike, and I'm doing it at 10 a.m. while watching football.
It's a pretty good job, even though I'd rather be out there.
That sort of kept me sane for that little bit, and I had some guys in there, like Mitch
Clark was long-term when I was long-term, and he was really struggling, highest paid
player at the club, struggling to get out there, and here's me.
I'm just happy as Larry that I'm getting to do a spin bike next to Mitch Clark.
That's a great perspective, Max, to get at a young age.
I must admit, I always try to have that perspective as well.
It's like your worst day in football is maybe someone's best day.
Instead of getting paid to get fit, you're surrounded by 42 players.
Even though you're not out there playing, a lot of people can't get that perspective.
For you as an 18-year-old, that was pretty unique to understand that.
Yeah, and I struggle more with it now because that Mitch Clark example, the pressures of
being a starting 18 player, older, family, there's a lot more pressure getting injured
when you're at a later age.
But when you're 18, yeah, I was literally happy to be there.
I'm where I want to be.
I've been wanting to be a footballer, and I get to just train in the best facilities
possible.
Little did I know they're not the best facilities.
They're quite far down the bottom, actually, the Melbourne facilities, but they were better
than the Sandy Dragon ones.
The stuff of your early career is pretty legendary, just how raw you were and smoking darts on
the way to training.
I mean, you look back and think, God, I hope.
I just didn't have any understanding, really, of how much it took to be a professional athlete.
Yeah, I mean, that story.
So it all sort of channels its way back to I would never change a thing that I've done.
I've learned and grown from everything.
And I smoked a dart on the way to training, which is phenomenal when you think about it.
And if you actually break it down, I was driving the Monash Freeway, and I'm injured.
And it was a 30-degree morning.
It was one of those ones that was going to be like a 45-degree day.
So it was a really hot morning.
I had all four windows down.
I had no top on and a backwards hat.
That's some detail.
Yeah.
And I'm driving in the far right lane of the Monash, and I pass Kyle Cheney, and Kyle
Cheney looks at me.
And so this is Kyle Cheney's point of view.
I don't see Kyle Cheney.
So he's seen me at my best, like all four windows down, not even noticing that someone's
seen me, just chewing back a dart.
But now, like fast forward 16 years, as captain, I just understand that not everyone is a private
school kid.
That's grown up with professionalism and has been wanting to be a footballer, like
a Jack Viney from day one.
There's some people that are going to come in like I did and not understand a thing about
what AFL clubs are about.
And it's put a lot more perspective in.
And ideally, I don't have the dart.
And ideally, Jake Bowie, when he comes in, doesn't smoke a dart, but creating a safe
place for him to feel a little more comfortable in that transition to be an adult and a professional
footballer.
Which may be the genius you're captain, Sam.
I want to talk about that in a moment.
I've got to go back.
You come to training, tops off, you're blissfully unaware that one of your teammates has seen
you driving down the fruit.
How did that play out from the feedback point of view in the club?
Yeah, I thought it wasn't a common thing.
It makes it sound like if I'm having a dart at 6.30, it was a common thing.
I think it was, I don't know why, I can't put my head around it, it was a one-off type.
It wasn't one-off.
I'd obviously had some darts, but, and I remember, so Kyle Cheney told Jack Grimes, best friends,
and Jack Grimes' leadership group, maybe even vice captain at that point.
And it filtered around.
The group didn't get to me until nine days.
So I've got some feedback around that as well.
The fact that it took them so long, it just festered within the group for nine days.
Everyone knew but me.
Anyway, I remember there was a nine-man leadership group back then.
That was quite popular to have as many in the leadership group as possible.
And there was a semi-circle and I was standing in the middle and Brad Miller started things
off and he goes, you're doing whatever it takes to be the best footballer you can be
for this football club.
Whatever it takes was our motto.
And I'm obviously unaware that I've been caught.
Yeah.
I think I am.
Obviously the knee is hurting me at the moment, but I really want to be out there, but I think
I'm working hard in the gym.
And then Brent Maloney, who's hard left, like I couldn't even really see him, goes, so you
weren't smoking?
I'm like, smoking?
No, I don't know what you're talking about.
And then I'm starting to get real hot in my chest.
I'm like, oh shit, what's happened here?
And then he goes, oh, Kyle Cheney reckons that he saw you on the way to train.
And I'm like, oh shit.
Yeah.
And then I went to water.
Famous Wayne Carey line.
Denied.
And then when caught, deny.
I went with that.
And I said, oh, mum and dad smoke.
My brothers smoke.
There's just smoking everywhere in my family.
It's hard to get away from.
None of them smoke.
I just ran them all under the bus.
And then, so I eventually, a young kid who didn't want to take accountability, I eventually
took accountability and we grew, but it was quite a unique moment.
I love talking to you about the late, great Jim Stines and the fact that he saw in you
something that maybe others didn't see when that was all going on and others in that era
might've been quick to pass on.
And for those who don't know, he was the pioneer of the Irish game, won a Brownlow medal as
an Irishman, lucky enough to have played against him a number of times and just the most wonderful
person you've ever met, Jim.
How important was it to have him as the president of Melbourne Football Club, see something
in you when that was a pretty rough start?
Yeah, looking, sort of looking back now, you realise with my work with Reach, that Jim
had a strength in adolescent youth that were, had a troubled, troubling.
To work out what they wanted to be and how they wanted to get there.
And that's what Reach basically does.
It just empowers young people to be the best versions of, of, of themselves.
So when Jim, I hadn't done much Reach work and I, to be fair, I didn't really know much
about Jim.
I'd, these playing days were before me, watching football and I just knew he was the president.
I don't know well Jim, I only know sick Jim.
He was sick the day I got there.
And sick Jim is an incredible person.
So I'm presuming well Jim would have been phenomenal.
Yeah.
I remember the first day, like we had pick one, pick two, pick 10, pick 18.
Tap Scott, Gisbert's, Trengrove, Scully.
Massive draft hall.
Functions galore.
And there's one, all our parents came in and the whole club's there.
And Jim just randomly said, I'm excited about this kid and made me stand up.
And I'm standing up and I'm like, what's going on here?
Like, there's a fair draft hall here.
And he just pinpointed me straight away, moved Matthew Warnock out of my number, out of number
37 to put me in 37.
And just constantly checked in.
And weekly, just constantly.
And if you remember what Jim was going for, he was president while cancer, family.
And he just kept checking in with me every week.
And now looking back, I'm like, oh yeah, I was a reach kid in his eyes.
I was a kid that didn't know how I was going to get there, but had the potential to get
there.
And he knew that a mentor would help that.
He's a man ahead of his time.
That foundation is so prevalent in today, youths that struggle with anxiety and a desire
to get to where they want.
And the fact that he saw that in me and I was blissfully unaware, that's what he was
doing there forever in debt.
And then for you to go on and be this cultural change maker at Melbourne Football Club,
premiership captain of the drought-breaking premiership, having Jim take it, there's
something, almost the hair stand on the back of your neck with that.
Jim wasn't alive to see that, unfortunately.
But do you feel his presence?
Do you feel, I can only imagine how much joy that would have given Jim and the Steins family.
Yeah, I don't think, I don't think he ever saw anything good for me.
Actually, I reckon, I feel like he passed away before I even pulled my finger out.
So I'm very lucky I get to wear number 11 now as well, which is also his number.
And I get a unique moment before I play every, every, every, every week where I get to just
look at the number.
And the first thing that comes up is, is, is Jim and more along the lines of how hard
his life was and how easy football is, how, how, how he was doing stuff to stay alive,
drinking his own urine, everything just to stay alive and be the best.
Dad and president he could be at that point and husband.
And I'm just going out there playing football.
Like I just put things into perspective for me, but yeah, it's such a unique storyline
that the fact that we're both rucks, um, he won a Brownlow, I'm going to win one tonight.
It's just, we're very, it's very similar.
The best leaders for me are authentically themselves.
I look at you and I just think you are a hundred percent authentically you.
Every time I listen to you, it just pours out of you.
Was that something you've consciously tried to be?
Or is it just you being?
The harder, I mean, very hard being yourself in AFL, let alone being someone you're not
in AFL, you found out pretty quickly if you're, if you're trying to hide and in particular
on the football field, if you're out there not being, if I'm out there not being Max
Gorn, trying to be Aaron Sandlands or Dean Cox, trying to be clones of them, there's
no way I'm going to get to where I got to.
So it was some learnings that I learned early on.
I remember about my six or seven year, year, it looked like I could be a leader.
I certainly, I was one.
I was one of those leaders that grew from, I had the playing group in terms of friends
and how could I make that next step rather than let's say the Jack Viney approach where
he had the standards and the, the values nailed.
And how does he approach to become, um, uh, a voice for all 45.
So I was the other way.
And I remember a lot of my feedback was just like, Dars, if I needed to sit you down and
give you some feedback, Gorn, you just don't always put a joke in.
Like you don't have to just hit me up.
Just, just say what you need to say.
Don't.
Start of a joke and finish of a joke.
And like, it was a lot around this class clown stuff.
And I battled with that for a while as this young leader.
And then it just sort of hit me.
I'm like, Dars, you'd feel uncomfortable if I did a meeting and I didn't start with a
joke because that is me.
You know me as that person.
So how awkward would it be if I came in and was serious, did not smile once.
And we had a minute chat and then we walked off.
Like, are you better off being the Max Gorn during that discussion?
Um, and it was once I sort of realized that, that,
um, this is me and if I get voted in to be a leader and
that's, that's why, because this is me and I, that's challenging.
I have a diary at home.
Um, you'd love to say it.
I write pretty much every conversation I've had good or bad points that I can do from.
It's a Jim science coming out of me.
I'm really interested in conversations and relationships.
And, um, so I think I'm an overthinker massively at nighttime, but when I'm
during the day, I'm just in the flow.
I'm, I'm, I'm me.
That's brilliant, Max.
And it.
It doesn't surprise me because you hear these stories, you know, in the
AFL world, you know, one of your teammates having a challenge, Clayton
Oliver publicly having some dramas.
And then you hear he moves into your house, you know, not long after, you
know, you and your wife have just had your second baby that to me is that.
Natural empathy that seems to come out of you is again, that just your style
and you're going to be you all the way along.
Yeah.
That didn't go down as well with Jess, um, surprisingly, uh, but now I'd like
if you, if there's an article about Clayton in the paper.
Jess is really patriotic.
She's like, what is that article?
Clayton's my boy.
She's like, she's gone full.
I'm his mom now.
Um, no, I just, there's no other option to me.
We had a, we had a really long chat one, one night, myself and Clayton.
And at the end I said, it needs to happen.
Done that you need to come into me.
And he said, yep.
So we made it happen.
It was about a month because it was off season.
I was going away at different points as well.
Still.
Um, he almost came with me to Fiji.
That was an interesting little, it was something that we both, um, felt like
we needed to happen where we're really close.
He's come out and had an unbelievable year as a person.
Um, and hopefully we'll continue to grow.
And Clayton was a really nice moment for me as a leader to see that, um, change
happen with the, with the hours and the commitment you put in.
Makes you the premiership captain of this legendary drought
breaking premiership, 57 years.
And then you oversee the most successful period really for, for five decades of
the football club, consistently top four.
And competing regularly, but it feels as though in that period, there has been
more spot fires and more dramas and more criticism of the Melbourne football club
than maybe ever, and you've been at the coalface of that all the time and had to
be the spokesperson under these pressure situations.
How challenging is that?
But
yeah, this is, um, I spoke about the diary, this one, this stuff gets written
down a lot when there's constant spot fires.
Is it something that I'm doing and I don't have a massive ego in leading, so I'm
happy for any sort of feedback and I'm happy to take the blame.
And so I, I, I constantly work through this and see what could I have done better?
Is this a direct reflection on, um, the group that, uh, that we've
created as a leadership group?
But yeah, there, there, there has been a lot and just by nature.
So I do a lot of media work, um, which we were talking about before, and I really
enjoy it and I don't find any stresses around it.
I don't feel like it makes me need to go play well on the weekend.
I just really enjoy, um, that side of the game.
By nature, I ended up being the person talking about it because I was on radio
Monday, Friday, every week.
Um, and clubs like a little bit of time.
They like a little bit of time to write a statement or to get in, get on the front
foot, but here's me addressing rumors Monday to Friday with Marty Sheargold, who
wasn't the best person to address rumors with, cause he, he went relatively hard.
Um, sort of did the heavy, the heavy lifting for me, but it put me in a
tough, tough situation a lot of times.
Um, I remember there was an Oz kick launch with Joel Smith.
I remember after I spoke, it was about 15, um, people that were going hard.
The journos after they spoke, I just walked to the other side of the sponsors banner.
I just sat down and I just, I couldn't move.
Like I'd almost had like an eight, like a panic attack, almost like I'm like, that
was a lot like, what have I got myself into?
This is a lot.
I'm constantly defending the club and then there'll be another fire in two weeks.
And the, and the latest stuff with track, it really war it's worn me down.
Um, and I don't, I don't like that cause I feel like I've always been able to
handle it.
But it's, it's starting to wear me down because it's something I'm so proud of
that I feel like I've had a good handle of creating, like you said, the most
successful era of, and I can just see it getting chewed, like constantly chipped
at, chipped at, chipped at, and I'm constantly trying to defend it.
Um, and I know what's happening in the four walls, but I just, you, you're
never going to trust that with nonstop spot fires.
So it's been a, it's been a delicate little time.
Well, people to understand, you know, as you said, you're, you're an
Oz kick ambassador, you're doing great things for your football club.
You're representing.
Your football club in a great way.
And then these stories break out, you know, of, uh, teammates who you love
and their friends, and they've had, uh, mistakes and Joel Smith had this, you
know, really challenging time and your great friend, Kristen Petra, you've got
hardened political journalists who for a living trip up professionals who speak
every day in front of press conferences.
You're at a bounce jumping castle center.
So that's not the environment.
You haven't got a team of advisors saying, guess what, Max, here's the
next question coming your way.
That is a pressure that I don't think.
People could quite possibly understand, but you've dealt with that.
And I think your resilience bands can be pretty thick.
Isn't it from there on a hundred percent and especially, you know, deep down what
you think, what the club thinks and what Joel thinks in that case, or with the
track stuff, you know, tracks point of view, you know, the clubs want to, and
you know, your point of view, but you've got to somehow combine them all to be
the most loving message for 70,000 members.
And it's, it can be quite challenging, but you trip yourself up if
you're not speaking complete truth.
So I just constantly just try and speak truth.
Sometimes I don't delve into truths that I don't really want to hear, but I don't, I
don't lie and that's where you can get caught up or I don't, I don't mislead the
truth.
I didn't, I can catch myself in that because sometimes I say a bit too much
and the club can go, come on, Max, we need you to pull back there or track
would be like, why'd you say that?
Or Clayton or Joel, anyone who I've spoken about this year.
Um, so, but I feel comfortable with everything that has been out there.
And that's your genius, Max.
That is your Dean.
I hope you never change.
You won't.
Uh, I'm sure you won't.
I'm sure don't need me to say that to you, but the truth always works to me.
Footy clubs always try and bend a little bit, maybe leave a few things out, but
I think you've been this incredible leader because of exactly that authentic
and, uh, and telling the truth.
We're this great privilege to cross over with you in this space.
We call a leader.
We bring together groups of five or six, and you've got so many diverse interests
outside of what you do in football.
Can you tell us about that experience in a letter connect?
I've really enjoyed it personally, because I've just, the year it's come into my
life is the year where I've had.
So many challenges and to have, uh, I've got a, quite a diverse group, some
hospitality geniuses, um, and then I've got, um, uh, the basketball players
association mastermind in Jacob Holmes.
So, um, it's been, it's been quite fun.
I'm I'm the athlete in the group.
So they love the footy dosage that I give them.
Um, but I also like, it's funny.
I don't know.
What's happened to the insurance me if it's not on Herald sun, but they know
what's happening in a Melbourne football club, so they, they almost start the
conversation.
For, for me, and then I'm able to, but the ideas I've bounced off, um, to be
able to know what I'm doing is the right thing or the wrong thing, or, um, to
work workshop, a couple of things to be able to be the best leader I can.
I've certainly really enjoyed it.
You've got a diverse interests.
I'm looking at the Lululemon ambassador.
I'm sitting in front of, and you've got a couple of restaurants and family's
got some hospitality history.
I think you might've started a lawn mowing business or something in the early
days, sorry, my apologies.
You'd be made tables for a living.
You'd be, has that been helpful for you to have all these other things?
And you're doing an amazing job when you front up in the meat.
Is that helped you along the way?
My wife always says this, but my parents, uh, the biggest impulse people known to
mankind, if they want something, they'll have it an hour later, or if they want to
go somewhere, they're on a plane, they're gone.
And I've got a bit of that.
I like to, if I think of something, I'm like, I'm all in on it.
And Jess is quite the opposite.
So we're actually a really good match because we can, we can get it out a tiny
bit, but I went to.
Cafe cause I wanted to do, um, cafes and I walked into a cafe and I loved the
table while I was sitting on and said, well, you know what, actually let's do
tables.
So I started doing tables and we did tables for two years and we closed the
doors because it was too busy, which is phenomenal.
We are, we outsourced and said, oh, do you want to do the tables?
And the, the, um, the regulation tables, regulation, tables, dining
tables, basically dining tables.
And you were that busy?
Well, that busy.
And we're working one day a week because of that was our day off.
And we outsourced and said, oh, we've got all these orders.
Maybe we just go get someone full time to do it.
And then we didn't really enjoy that.
It wasn't the passion piece that we thought we were.
And then our markup wasn't as good as well.
Cause we're outsourcing.
We're like, oh, let's just, let's just, let's just call it quits.
We had, I think we had about 20 orders to get done in a month at one point.
And the table takes one table, takes a whole day sort of set up.
And then you've got to, you've got to, it's got to glue together.
And then it's not ready.
And we on the tools on that day off on the tools and hard day off, um,
standing back, standing back tables.
Amazing.
Yeah, really love that.
But hospital was always my dream.
Um, my mom is my hero.
I love, I love, I love both my parents, but my mom's my hero.
I wanted to do everything my mom made to seem like was the best job in the world.
Dad, obviously he's in earth moving.
That's just, it wasn't something that I found passionate.
My other brothers do, but it wasn't something that I wanted.
I wanted hospital hospital.
So when the opportunity came up to start a bar, I initially, like I said, I wanted
cafes, but there's not an amazing amount of money in cafe, um, and the wine bar
sort of was the trend at that time, six years ago when I could, let's jump on it.
And I've really enjoyed it.
I've to be fair, I'm probably the fine answer, like, and I get my role.
I'm there once a week, once a fortnight, I'm on my laptop on zero, maybe twice a week.
Like I'm not doing a hell of a lot.
I'm looking, um, I get involved in any sort of hiring and firing and make sure I upskill
myself.
But the day I finished is the day I want to go full into one myself.
I want to be everything I can do.
Keep the same team.
They're a great team.
We've had, but I want to be a bit more hands-on and create and do what my mom made
to seem like was my dream.
Cause that's, I'm getting a bit of that dosage with the two restaurants I'm in, but
I'm also, I'm delegating to my two business partners and they're doing a lot of the
work.
Look forward to saying that, uh, that day come, hopefully get some, uh, some big
years ahead of you, which I'm sure you have.
We love the patterns of what leadership looks like in different spaces.
And yours is such an incredible story.
And this idea that it's hard to lead someone else without the sense of self
leadership.
What do you do?
And all that busy world.
You're, you're a father of two.
You've got enormous amounts of things to juggle and balance.
How do you fill your own cup up max so that you can be the leader you want to be?
I'm a, I'm up and down like everyone else.
My relationship with my phone is a dangerous one.
And I'd say most people my age would say that.
And I've created some really good self protocols around that.
I, um, in the back end of weeks, I, I turn my phone off.
Literally turn it off.
How do you communicate?
Can be bad.
I have hours where I turn it on.
Yeah.
You can find yourself.
Just.
Just spiraling.
But also the positive endorphins I get from not using my phone is phenomenal.
And I never thought I'd get that.
So obviously people say just to stay away from social, it's good to keep yourself away
from that.
Can I delve into that for a bit?
So what, what if you, if you're having a back end of the week, less phone time, how do you
structure it?
So I would be in the morning, it'd be on to what alarm, although who uses an alarm these
days, you normally naturally wake up to the three year old that's in your bed, but alarm
and whatnot, just to start the day.
And then that, it just goes off.
It goes off.
Either.
Uh, do not disturb.
I've created my own do not disturb, which is like, if it's a phone call that calls twice,
I'll pick up.
If not, I don't say it till.
So the wife can ring twice and you're like, okay, I've got to take this one.
Until the kids are asleep that night.
Full day without.
Full day.
That's normally like a Thursday, Friday for a Saturday game.
I would, I would sort of really ease up.
And would you jump on after bedtime and just check and say, Hey, there might be some business
I need to attend to.
Pretty much.
And then in the world of social media, I do have a brand there as well.
So you actually need to upload stuff every now and then.
And, um, like Lululemon don't want someone who doesn't use social media at all.
So I've got to do my part there.
Um, but that's something I've found really enjoyable.
And the person I am on Thursday, Friday compared to the person I am Monday, Tuesday is phenomenal.
The, the, the, the dad I am, the husband I am more importantly, I think more husband,
I reckon I'm always a good dad.
I'm a better husband and I give more time to, to Jess in that back half of the week.
And then, um, it just snowballed.
When you're a great person at home, the person you are in your workplace is even better making
sure I channel all the right energy.
Um, and I've also got some great wellness routines.
Um, I'm lucky enough.
It must be nice to have a sauna at home, but I do have a sauna at home and to spend an
hour in there and my phone does not work in the sauna.
So the wifi doesn't go in there.
So I actually can't use it.
So it's an hour of just thoughts, music, really relaxing, which I enjoy.
It's a brilliant piece of advice.
I love how you've been able to, and then equate that.
To being happier.
And then you, as you said, your performances are always at an incredibly high level.
This idea of impacting people.
We see a lot.
Is there been one piece of leadership advice that you, you take and pass on to others?
Yeah, there is.
And it's a little bit around what we just spoke about.
The best version of yourself is the best leader that they can be.
So not trying to be someone you're not always reflecting on what you could do better, but
then also making sure that you're your best self.
We do this.
We do this thing at the club that.
I've lived and died by now.
I've got a whiteboard at home.
So Jess hates this.
She wants to be all just on your phone.
Damn Cal, like everything goes in the same calendar, but I hate using my phone as I've
just said.
So I've got this whiteboard as big as this wall that has like a month up there and I'm
a visual person.
I love seeing it all there, but I set up my week to be the best version I can be.
So I know on Monday I need to go in the beach at some time, have a sauna.
I need to have uninterrupted time.
My kids, I need to read a book and I need to write in my diary.
And then what I need to do Tuesday all the way to Thursday, Friday, you've heard is no
phone.
Um, and that's set up my week.
And I do that every Sunday night.
I set my wake up and that allows me to be the best version of me.
And then bang, when I'm the best version of me come the time that's, let's say it's
midday till five.
I'm at the club on Monday.
I've delegated that time around it to be the best version.
I can be a 12 to five as a captain, which is a genius.
I'm the same.
I'm a, I'm a handwriting.
I don't have a note of that's typed up, but I'm a bit the same.
I like to see stuff and I like to hand write stuff down.
I'm a bit the same, but that idea you start on Sunday night and your week set up and you
know, you're setting yourself up for success.
That's a great thing to share.
The next dimension I want to talk to you about is, is vision.
And you've clearly got a vision for what success looks like.
And in a elite performance environment, has there been one type of visionary leader that's
really inspired you along the way?
I've got a pretty good one.
I work with in, in, in Goody, he challenges me, but more importantly, from the vision
point.
From the point of view, he always is talking about what is going to be the fallout from
this decision.
Like he's always looking ahead.
So him now, but in, in terms of early parts of my leadership, obviously the values I get
from my parents, you don't realize how much of a clone you are as your parents do.
You start to grow up a little bit and you go, why do I do that?
And then you look at your dad, you go, oh, that makes sense.
Like he's literally doing the exact same thing.
Um, so their values and then Jim, like honestly, the G I know I knew Jim for two years, two
and a half, two and a half years.
But he has been my mentor for 16 years, which is very weird to say it like that.
Cause I, he wasn't my mentor in that two and a half years of that.
And at the time I was a young naive kid and I'm like, can the president stop texting me?
But like 16 years later, I've looked in like everything I've done in terms of all my leadership
is the values that he's installed in me in two years that I didn't know at that time.
And it's unfortunate that a passing is almost what sort of put it in my head.
That this is, oh my God, like it's like my wow moment.
Like I wish I had that wow moment while he was there, but everything I do in my leadership
is a clone of Jim and a mixture of my parents.
I just love that legacy.
As I said, having the pleasure of knowing Jim for a long period and when he was well
and playing against him and to think impact you and then thousands of reach kids who've
probably got similar stories that are still being impacted by what he did for them is
quite incredible.
Curiosities are where we're here all the time in people that are successful like you or
I want to ask you, is there a rabbit hole you've gone down recently you can share with
us where your curiosity has been piqued and you just can't help but go after something?
Is that something that resonates with you?
Yeah.
Well, the impulsiveness of my decision-making sometime, but I'm certainly in a, I'm in a
space, I'm not sure if this is where you wanted to go, but I'm in a space right now where
I'm an older captain and I've been at the helm for a bit of an unsuccessful three years.
I mean, the way it depends how you look at it.
We've won a lot of games of football and been in top four, but we haven't been able
to get back to that, to that glory.
And then there has been spot fires of different little cultural stuff.
And I'm currently sitting there going, is it still right for me to be the guy who leads
the team?
I'll still lead in my own way, no matter what, but is it worth having someone new?
I've always been a believer and this counter acts counterintuitive to what I just said,
but I've always been a guy thinking I'll pass it on at a good time.
And this is not a good time to be fair for a new captain.
So I feel like I might continue on, but like I'd love to pass it on and a new captain can
come in and there's no pressure.
So that's probably what's in my head at the moment.
I'm trying to work out where I sit in my, in my, in my leadership space, where I sit
with a group.
I'd also like the idea of potentially just sitting there in my last couple of years in
the back row and not in the political press conferences and seeing if I can enjoy some
footy in the back end.
Brilliant.
You've got the succession planning in your mind and the way you're thinking about that.
I think the way people communicate might be the thing that we hear the most, that people
really have a strategy on that.
We've heard about, you know, your discipline with your phone, but have you got a mantra
in the way that you communicate in the role that you've got?
So the, the, the journal, so I've got sort of everything in terms of the last time I
spoke to someone, if I'm speaking to them again.
So I've got everything written down, like you said, we're, we're, we're both visual
people, so it's written down.
So I've got that to look at before and look at after.
It's a reflect, but I tell myself every time I go into, especially hard conversations,
obviously hard conversations, the easy, the positive conversations are fine, but you walk
in and just before I start, I'm like, be Max Gorn, which is, I mean, like I said, it's
harder than you think it is because it can be quite challenging with the different stresses
and anxieties in the world.
But as soon as I start talking, I'm like, be Max Gorn.
And then it's just, it flows.
The harder conversation isn't necessarily that hard.
I love, I love the way you sum that up again.
We're a bit obsessed with collaboration.
Max, and the idea that people working better out of their silos and coming together.
Have you got an example of a collaboration in any area of your life that's worked for
it?
Uh, I mean, that's, it's almost like leadership groups in a sense.
You can, you, you have strong ideas as, uh, as a captain, like this would be bored.
This is any sort of industry has these high level leadership meetings.
I really enjoy ours because we have so many different point of views.
I just love the idea that eight people chuck out an idea.
They're all different.
And then we eventually morph into what we think is the best idea.
Um, and I think that's a great part of leadership groups.
And if you look at myself and Jack Viney, we're completely polar opposite people, but
we've led the club together for five years, created a really strong bond together.
And we have different point of views, um, which I think is a really strong nature to
have.
And now we have track has a different point of view.
He's a leader.
Um, Jake Lever, if you ever meet him is extremely black and white.
So there's like four very different point of views in our leadership group, um, that
creates hopefully the best, the best possible.
Answer had the great pleasure of sitting across from, from, uh, Jack Viney recently.
And, and, and I love the way you sum that up is you don't all have to come from the
same point of view, but ultimately as a group, you've got to find that common ground.
How combative can that get at times?
We all live by these four values of our football club.
So as, as is trust, respect, unity, excellence, majority of industries, workplaces would have
the similar four words.
Um, they're ours.
So we, or you can have a hundred ideas that all fit under.
Those four values.
So that's the good part, but it's not fully rogue because they're there.
We're, we're still coming from, we want Melbourne football club to be the best thing possible.
So I'm not sure if in your line of work to ask, if you come across many gen Zeds, but
it's an interesting lot of people, Jen, Jen, Jen, Jen Zed, like the 18 year olds that are
coming in.
Now, if you look at Hawthorne and how Hawthorne are playing their football currently, Jen
Zeds, you're almost do better as a, as a team.
If you let them run the club.
And let the 20 year olds take you forward, because they'll just take you on a journey.
They got no stresses or pressures or anxieties that, that, that Jen, why millennials have.
They're just loving life.
Um, and if you, if you let them take you somewhere, you'd be amazed how far you can go.
And that takes skill, doesn't it?
Because, you know, I've got a couple of them in my house, Max, that's what I'm getting
unfortunately, but it's very hard to relate to something that you just didn't grow up
with, isn't it?
And that's the art of bringing, especially in footy clubs, you're into your thirties,
you're a father of two.
You've got a very different set of way.
You were sort of parented probably, and now you've got these 18 year olds who just have
got no rules effectively.
Yeah.
Is that, as you said, if you, if you don't let them be themselves, you're in real trouble.
Like I, uh, slightly going away here, but another mentor of mine is Russell Howcroft.
Um, he was a board member when I first got there and we've, I've had spaghetti bolognese
at his house every Sunday for about 10 years.
It was great.
He inspires me because he's been at the head of advertising.
He's now, he's now in the media game.
Yeah.
He's the head of advertising for 40 years and advertising is probably the one thing
that's changed the most in 40 years.
And he was able to adapt and adapt and adapt and no have, don't have an ego amongst his
views.
Constantly have people come in and say, Oh no, billboards isn't the thing anymore.
Now it's a tick tock, but still be able to adapt and lead his industry into that space.
I think that's inspiring.
And that's sort of, um, the fear of change is something that a majority of people have.
But it's your ability to, um, deal with the fear of change.
And I, I, I'm scared of change.
Like I'm, I honestly am scared of change, but once that change happens, you feel yourself
moving with the, with the group and Gen Z challenges you with that.
When I first walked into the football club, it's speak when spoken to.
And even then don't speak.
Now it's like, if you're 32, don't speak.
The 19 year olds are running the club.
It's, it's gone the complete other direction.
Um, and being able to adapt is, um, something like from Russ that I find is really, really
inspiring.
I'm going to give a little plug.
I did an episode with Russell, one of the most intriguing and positive people you've
ever been around.
The energy and what Russell Howcroft walks into a room and hadn't thought of his career
that way.
Isn't it adapting the way he does is, is genius.
Max, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Uh, well, good question.
In terms of football, Nathan Jones will forever be my skipper.
Like I, I call him skip.
Um, I'm sure you have someone you call skip.
Um, yeah, a lot of Melbourne boys in your era called David.
David needs skip.
Like he's, he's still, he's, he's still there skipper.
So Jones, you'll be forever my skipper.
I just think his way articulated these messages were really inspiring.
And also the relationship side to Nathan Jones, um, you work with him now he's, he's for someone
who's a Frankston Bogan, his ability to get a sentence out is phenomenal.
He's a, he's, he's a wordsmith.
We'd be sitting there for an hour going through a really strong values conversation and going
back and forward.
And then Nathan Jones would just say what he thinks an hour later.
And everyone's like.
That's correct.
Why don't you just speak at the start?
We wouldn't have been going for an hour.
Like you, he nails his points a lot.
And obviously the player he was.
So that's probably on the field.
Um, I would call him, um, away from football has always been my mom inspiring story came
over from New Zealand with $0, um, just had to get away from her family.
And then now she loves her family, but at the, at the time an 18 year old, um, Kiwi,
she needed to, um, just go see what, what the big land was about.
Um, and then went from hairdressing to.
All sorts to running their own successful cafe and then becoming a bit of a chain of
a cafe and starting a few.
I find that very inspiring.
And then the way she was able to put family first throughout that we've spoken about Jim.
So that would be the three in three different ways.
One is my leadership and one is my values.
And then one's my on-field sort of relationships.
When you look back, it's not surprising that you've got such a good handle on, uh, on the
way that you go about it.
It's when you bring those people together, what a, what a gift in life, really going
back to the final question, Max.
You're obsessed with.
This idea of what collaboration looks like.
And we feel like for the last 30, 40 years, it's been a lot about what I can get out of
life and what I can get out of my role, my work.
And now we're seeing this great opportunity to bring people together.
You've got so many interests.
Has there been one person you've got access to a lot of great people?
I'd love to collaborate with that person, whether it's your sporting life or your business
life or your family life.
Is there a name that springs to mind?
Yeah.
Well, I've got obviously different interests.
I've got a passion in sporting leadership.
If that's an industry.
Uh, I think it is.
There's a guy who works at our football club who's just finished up, but Jim, Jimmy Plunkett,
um, who initially worked with leading teams.
Um, and then he's been our, like, I forget the name.
They probably made it up, but it's like Pete manager of people, culture and growth at our
football club.
And I find that a really interesting space.
Um, and there's multiple people that excel in that.
Like a Ben Crow is famous for someone who excels in that space.
I feel like they'd be really cool conversations to have.
I'd love one day, um, to be able to.
Sit at like, imagine I pitched a team that goes to a world cups, like the wallabies,
the soccer roos, the hockey roos, anyone that goes to Olympics, just being able to go for
four or five weeks and be that leadership guy, um, that can help out culturally during
that.
I reckon that'd be a really cool experience.
So that's something that I'm inspiring to do.
Um, but certainly in hospital as well, there's, where do you, where do you start?
Like there's Julia Moose who dominates the cafe scene down here.
There's yourself.
Who's gotten successful pubs galore.
There's more Lucas group.
There's multiple people.
That you'd love to be able to have a chat with, um, to see where they're, to see where
they got to.
And
Max, I've been a massive admirer for a long period of time.
Um, Ruckman get a bag, bad rap, and you've changed the game.
I'm always, uh, on the lookout for someone who's, uh, I played a game at a level that,
uh, is at the top of the tree for the history of our game.
He's done it incredibly well.
I feel like there's much more left in the tank and the authentic way that you carry
yourself is, is inspiring.
Great to catch up with you and thanks for taking the time.
Thanks for having me.
Thanks for listening to another episode.
Of the empowering leaders podcast, huge.
Thanks as always to our great friends at temper.
And we encourage you to check out our leader connect program.
New episodes are out every Wednesday morning at 6 00 AM.