This week's guest on the Empowering Leaders podcast is the incredible Meggie Palmer, a
former foreign correspondent and senior journalist who experienced her own issues with the gender
pay gap and gender leadership issues and has created Pep Talker, an amazing community of
60,000 passionate professional women who are desperate to make a difference in this space.
She talks in this chat about finding out from a male colleague how much less she was earning
than all the men in the newsroom and how this has sparked her passion in this space,
how moving away from the anger and the bitterness and choosing to take action has been
a really powerful part of her story. She also encourages male allies to speak up and work
towards solving this issue together. She's got great tips on how to negotiate better,
how to get a pay rise. She talks about narrowing in on your own zone of genius, which is
a great bit of wisdom to share. She's a remarkable person. I hope you
enjoy watching.
I hope you enjoy the chat as much as I did sitting down with Meggie Palmer. Lots to learn
from her. It's people like Meggie who inspire the work that we do at Alita Collective. You
can check out our website, alitacollective.com. Talk about our signature program, Alita Connect,
where we bring together brilliant people like Meggie exactly around the lines of different
thinking, bring fantastic female leaders together with people from different industries. We'd
love to connect with you in that space as well. Book a discovery call, head to alitacollective.com
and we'd love to talk to you.
Talk to you about Alita Connect and our ongoing program. Huge thanks as always to our great
friend Jason Nicholas and his team from Temper. A mattress like no other. It is the world's
best in bedding. I've been sleeping on mattresses provided by Temper for more than 15 years.
It's a life-changing experience when you think about so much of your life is spent in bed
to invest in a Temper mattress. It's an investment that you will never regret.
Meggie Palmer is a Walkley Award-winning filmmaker, a former foreign correspondent,
who spent more than a decade working as a journalist for the BBC World, CNBC and Dateline,
amongst others. After her own personal experience of discrimination and inequality as a journalist,
Meggie has made it her life mission to close the gender pay and leadership gap.
Meggie's response to the challenge was to create Pep Talk Her, which has grown into
a thriving global business with a community of more than 60,000 passionate professional women.
Meggie's a sought-after international speaker and lectures at Columbia University on the
topic of gender equality and gender equality. Meggie's a sought-after international speaker and
topics of negotiation and confidence. Meg, it's great to catch up with you. I think we might
have crossed over at various stages in the media industry. Congratulations. It's incredible work
you're doing. Thanks so much for having me. Nice to know that we crossed paths back in our media
days. It's so exciting to have a chat with you today. I'm looking forward to it.
It's incredible work that you're doing in this space. Can we start by sharing
your personal experience with battling with the gender pay gap?
Yes. Possibly something that some of your listeners may be able to relate to.
Basically, at one point in my career, I found out actually quite by accident,
thanks to a male ally who slipped me some intel, that actually my pay and conditions,
my contract and the pay that I was getting was quite different to the guys in the newsroom who
I sat next to. I just thought it was a mistake. I was like, oh, well, we'll just fix it. That's
cool. No dramas, whatever. I had a convo. Let's just say it didn't go well, Luke. It wasn't well
received. Quote, unquote, they told me, this is no joke. They said, Meggie,
if you don't like it, why don't you quit or take us to court? I was kind of like, are you serious?
Because I was sort of raised like if you see something, say something. To me, things being
equal is very important. It goes to the core of what I think is fair in life. It's just part of
who I am from when I was a kid getting in trouble when actually my brother did the wrong thing. I
still remember viscerally being annoyed by that. That's kind of stayed with me my whole life.
Compelled that I had to do something because I knew they wanted me to just kind of like walk
away quietly. But I was like, well, I really back myself. I know I'm a great journo. I know I'll get
another job. What if I was pregnant or what if I was the primary breadwinner or what if I didn't
have savings? Like what if it happened to someone in that situation? They wouldn't be able to take
on that fight. And so anyway, long story short, yeah, I kind of stepped up and took on that
challenge, I guess. And then, you know, fast forward now, I'm based in New York,
and my business is all about closing that inequality gap in terms of pay and leadership as
well. Yeah, which is an amazing response, isn't it? And you think of the unfairness of that and
having experienced the industry and been around it at the same time, I'd hate to say that I'm not
surprised because passionate about what good leadership looks like me. And I think media
industry has been right at the bottom rung of general leadership in lots of areas.
Media is great at telling stories about what other people need to do well, but not so good
I've found at putting the mirror up to their own culture at times. But a lot of people
just move, most of us move on and say, okay, that's too big a fight to have. But you've decided
to turn it into an amazing project. Pep, talk her, tell us about how you've responded to it and
how that's worked for you. Well, you know, I think as leaders and, you know, even as members
of society, we always have a choice. You know, when stuff happens to us,
or when stuff happens to other people, there's always two choices. You can look the other way
and you can be like, oh, it's not my fight. It's not my battle. Or you can do something about it.
And, you know, I was really bitter. I was really angry. And really on reflection, it's in some
ways, it's a first world problem. Like I'm a middle-class white identifying woman. And the
first time really that I'd experienced inequality was, you know, in my mid career. And I think now
about all my friends of color, you know, my friends who identify as gay, like the discrimination
they've actually experienced.
So much earlier in their lives compared to what I went through, really, you know, mine was nothing.
And so I think actually putting into perspective is very important. And again, just reframing it,
I can get angry and stay bitter, or I can try and change it. And I think like, to me, that's a call
to action that all of us can take on when we see stuff that's wrong, when we see folks being racist,
when we see something happening in the workplace to someone else, that's not fair, that's not right.
We can turn away from it, or we can say something, whether we say something to that person and
support them afterwards, or whether we find a time and a place to actually call that leader out.
You know, it really depends on how comfortable you feel and how much power you feel like you
have internally. But I think we don't talk about that enough, you know, and I really want to talk
about that more. And so it was kind of an accident, really, like pep talker was, was just something
that I started to do after I had that, that situation, friends started asking me for advice
when they got sacked when they were on maternity leave, or, you know, you know, they had to take
days off for their kids who were sick.
And then all of a sudden, they got overlooked for promotion. So people would just ask me for
advice, because they knew what I'd been through. And then I had their friends, cousins, sister
calling me and then all these people and I was like, Oh, hang on. So this is like a bit of a
thing. I was pretty naive, honestly, to the fact that in the Western world, the gender pay gap is
somewhere between 15 and 20%, which is no joke. But it's even worse when you look at what that
means for retirement, right. And so in terms of superannuation and pension funds, there's a
massive gap there, you know, more than 40%.
And so the reason I care about this is because when women have money, we have choice, you know,
it gives us choice, it gives us options, and it gives us freedom. So that's why I'm really
passionate about it. Yeah. Yeah, congratulations. It's an amazing contribution you're making. I
love all great ideas come out of this desire to help, you know, and I think that's where the best
thing comes out of. Yeah.
is it not someone sitting around or how do I, you know, make more money? Effectively, it's you've
solved, starting to solve a problem. You've got a huge community behind you. Why is it do you think
women generally, as a rule, find it harder to ask for a pay rise than men do?
So it honestly comes back to how we're socialized, right? So if you think back to when you were
growing up, and I don't know, do you have siblings, Luke?
I'm one of four. Yeah, I've got two sisters and an older brother.
Okay.
Okay, cool. And so for you, and maybe for anyone listening today, like just reflect on when you
were growing up, right? So I'm one of three, I'm the oldest, got a younger brother and a younger
sister. And my parents were pretty good. They were pretty aware of, you know, trying to make us all
be treated equally and stuff like that. But even so, there were certain things that were a little
bit different, you know, in terms of how we were treated. Like when we had our grandparents coming
over, my sister and I really had to kind of help make the house look good and the table be nice
and, you know, entertain people as they came in and welcome them and make sure they had a drink.
Whereas my brother would kind of be breaking down and say, you know, I'm not going to do this. I'm
dancing on the front lawn and just kind of like doing his thing. And so from a young age, there's
like little tiny triggers that actually means that we're socialized to behave a little bit
differently. And typically what we see is that women are socialized from a young age to kind of
keep the peace, make everyone feel comfortable, not want to rock the boat. And so then you can
see how that kind of translates into the professional world where having a conversation
about money is not always something that we're comfortable doing because we're fearful that we
won't be liked or that we'll get fired or that our boss will frankly get pissed off that we dared
to ask the question, right? Whereas often we see little boys are kind of socialized from a younger
age to be open about talking about money, to talk about investing. They grow up, you know,
expecting that they should earn money and hopefully good money, you know, and the expectations are a
little different. And actually, Luke, there's a super interesting study. It's actually been done
in various ways in three different countries that shows that little girls get less pocket money
than little boys, right? And it's not because parents are bad people. It's just because there's
a perception that like, for example, collecting the firewood or helping in the garden is a tougher
task, for example, than perhaps preparing a meal or helping with the laundry. And so again, from
a really young age, there's these kind of really tiny, subtle clues that tell us that we're
different, right? And so that's kind of part of the reason that it parlays into the professional
world as well. And one of the other pieces of research that's super interesting is that women
are actually asking.
For more money. They are actually negotiating for their pay, but they're treated differently
and they don't get those pay increases at the same rate. And researchers hypothesize that that's
because of unconscious bias and discrimination.
And Meggie, I think for all of us males who've, you know, and I reflect a lot more these days of
going to a boys' school, a boys' boarding school, playing AFL football in a male environment. But I
always think of, you know, I've got an 18-year-old daughter and I think of my sisters and
it doesn't take a lot to be a male. And I think of my sisters and it doesn't take a lot to be a
male. And so I think it's important to get some perspective and some empathy and some passion
when you actually think how I would react if someone treated my 18-year-old daughter that way,
it would be a pretty short conversation, Meggie. And I think that's a really, for me, a really
profound world because you don't know what you don't know until someone like you articulates it
in that way. But hopefully we can play a role because we do genuinely care. We do genuinely
want equality in the same way, but perhaps it's just been not our lived experience. And that takes
some time.
Do you find you're getting men, you know, perhaps like me that are genuinely interested in care or
are you finding there's a bracket of men that are scared and don't want it to change?
Look, I mean, I think we're all a product of our upbringing, right? And we, all of us listening
today, regardless of how we identify gender-wise, we all have bias, right? Because of what we saw
growing up and we're a product of our parents who are a product of their parents. And so we only
know what we know from what is role-modeled to us, to your point, right? And so someone said to me
once, Luke, you know, it takes a long time to turn a big ship. And I think about that a lot when I
think about feminism and equality, and it kind of pisses me off that we're still having this
conversation. And yet I reflect on the fact that, you know, up until, I don't know, I think it was
only like 40 years ago, women needed their husband's signature to get a credit card in
Australia. So progress is happening. Obviously I wish I could click my fingers and it would change
tomorrow, but I'm also a realist. Like, you know, the UN is saying that it's going to take one
hundred to two hundred years to close the gap. And so again, I wish it was happening sooner,
but I think it's going to take generational change. And I think, you know, our generation,
the next generation, they do have very different views, which is a great thing. And so we're going
to see change happen at a faster and faster rate, which is awesome. But yeah, I just, I try and
reflect on the fact that all of us today are a product of the folks who've protested and advocated
for change on so many issues in the past. And so that kind of gives me hope going forward as well.
Me, I mentioned my sort of perspective and upbringing, but in this latter part of my
working life and in the leadership business that we run and being surrounded by so many more
brilliant females. And I wrote down in preparation for this, the traits that I saw, I sit on a board
of my old football club as well, which is full of unbelievable women. I just, it's like the women
are kinder, they're more efficient, seriously less ego, incredible attention to detail, conscientious,
more empathy.
I look at all the traits that naturally are feminine traits in lots of ways. And I'm not
sure if that's even the right language, but to me, it seems almost bizarre as I reflect to,
it's taken me so long and others to understand just how much better women are than men in so
many areas and how much more that should be rewarded and how much more efficient and better
it is. I mean, is that something that you think, you know, if you're talking about wanting to
negotiate a part, they're the traits that you should pay someone more on,
the things that I just said, it sort of makes sense at one level, doesn't it?
Yeah. I mean, we all bring different things to the table, you know, and when I think about this
issue of equality, you know, I get a lot of haters, Luke, online of people who are like,
oh, pep talker, that's BS, like it's fake news, blah, blah, blah. And the thing is like, it is,
to me, it's a moral and ethical issue, of course, to treat people fairly. But honestly,
even putting that to one side, if you're a capitalist, you should care about this,
right? If you own shares, if you have a superannuation account, you should be interested
and you should care that companies take this seriously. Because when companies take this
seriously, you know, you make more money, you're going to get higher dividends, you're going to get
a faster growth of your share portfolio, because studies have proven that when there are diverse
voices at the table, diversity across all facets. And so you actually don't want a company led
entirely by women either, by the way, we want all perspectives, because then problem solving is
better. You're able to sort of see those challenges coming around the corner a lot faster when you hear
those different diverse perspectives. So yeah, I mean, I just, I'm,
it's also important, I think, for folks like you to kind of share your experience. I love hearing
that. Certainly, anecdotally, we see that as well. But I think it's very important for allies to talk
about this openly, because I can say it. But then it's also easy for people to roll their eyes at me
and be like, well, you would say that you're a woman and you talk about this all the time. So I
think it's awesome for everyone listening to say, well, actually, what role can I play? Like, what
could I do this week? And here's a little challenge, like, truly, what can you do this week
to be an ally? And maybe that's just the way it works.
Sending an email to someone on the intern team to say, hey, if you ever have any questions,
reach out to me. Maybe that's just raising something with a leader to say, hey, how come
we haven't considered so-and-so for this promotion? Like, whatever it is, how can you use your power
and privilege to help create change? Because we can't just expect it always to come from the top
and from the execs. You know, I think it has to be push and pull. It has to come from the grassroots
too, so that we can sort of, you know, change the hearts and minds as well a little bit.
Yeah, remarkable. As you said,
and I can see the frustration that we're still having these conversations. It seems,
you know, obvious at so many levels. Can you just, how does Pep Talker work? You've created an app and
an incredible community behind you. What does someone do when they sign up to Pep Talker?
Yeah, so when I was thinking about it, as I said, I was having all these folks calling me
and asking me for advice on discrimination, on negotiating pay, on having the confidence to
apply for promotions. And I actually just couldn't keep up. I was a full-time journalist at the
time. I couldn't keep up with the calls. And I was doing a lot of stories actually as a reporter
then on tech and startups and how you could use technology and AI to kind of scale things. So
then I was like, well, could you scale coaching people on this stuff? And so I did an accelerator
and through that, I met a friend of mine, Alex, who's awesome, who's a product manager. And so
I had no idea what I was doing. I'm not a coder. I still can't code, but I know how to ask questions
and I know how to collaborate.
with people. And Alex really helped me on that journey. And so we mapped out what we wanted the
app to look like. He helped me find someone to build it. Actually, we were just like a couple
of weeks ago featured in the Google Play Store. Apple's done a big feature on us. They called me
and they were like, can you fly to San Francisco for a shoot for the Apple homepage? And I thought
it was, I thought I was being punked or pranked. And I hung up. I was like, lol. And I hung up.
And then they called me back and they were like, why did you hang up? So it's an app and it's kind
of like Luke.
It's kind of like a Fitbit, except instead of tracking your steps and your exercise,
it tracks your successes. It tracks your work wins. And I know that you know this as well
through the leadership work that you do, like our brains, unfortunately, are hardwired for
negativity, right? And so the app is kind of based on the premise of the nudge theory of
psychology of like, if we can make incremental tiny bit by bit change day by day, week by week,
in terms of how we view ourselves and our success at work, then if we can do that incrementally
every week, then we're going to be able to do a lot of things. And so I think it's kind of
like, well, we're going to be able to do that incrementally every week, a couple of months,
maybe for a year. That's actually really going to shift our perception of ourself and our value.
And then you can literally like use all the wins that you've tracked in the app.
You can print it out, you can PDF it, whatever. And you can like physically take that into your
conversation as notes, as reflection, as data points to say to your boss, listen, you know,
website clicks are up 22% year on year. The CFO sent me this note to say thank you for this
accounting practice that I changed. You know, I hired these three folks, which meant it's
saved the company $60,000 in recruiting costs. Whatever the KPI is that you've achieved,
you've then got it into one place. So firstly, you're going to feel more confident negotiating.
And also there's meat on the bone. You're making it easier for your boss and for the
leadership team to say yes, to say yes to your promotion or your pay increase request.
And is that what you described then in your mind, the art of negotiating well,
to come in with data and come in with a preparation to sort of sit down with a conversation and
genuinely,
pitch yourself worth, you know, what tone do you take with that? How would you describe the best
way to, you know, increase your own worth and negotiate better pay? Yeah, I mean, having data
and preparation is for sure one of the steps that we talk about a lot. So the app is kind of like,
it's free, by the way, we, you know, we make the app free. It's part of our impact work. We want
everyone to use it. It's on all of the app stores, people can download it. It's just called Pep Talk
Her. And really, that's one step in the process. It's definitely going to help you if you want to
get bananas off your chest. It's definitely going to help you if you want to get bananas off your
chest. And really, that's one step in the process. It's definitely going to help you if you want to
get bananas off your chest. And really, that's one step in the process. It's definitely going to
help you if you want to get bananas off your chest. And really, that's one step in the process. It's
results like we've seen some of our clients, like, you know, I had a text today from someone who's
just got a new job, and it's $45,000 more. Last year, one of our clients in Sydney, she's now
earning $108,000 more, because she went through one of our programs. And so she's putting in a
pool for her kids. So it's kind of like, it's, it's, it's a big deal, right? Like, it makes a
significant difference for folks' lives. Yeah. So when you think about negotiation, there's a bunch
of different steps. But the first foundational step is firstly, to understand your worth.
And the easiest way to do that is to track those successes yourself. And then the other thing you
can do is like, take a straw poll, like, text your best mate. Like, we can do that now, if you want,
everyone can grab out their cell phone, not if you're driving and listening. But otherwise,
you can get out your mobile, and just text your best mate, or text your BFF at work, or maybe one
of your old bosses who you're still in touch with, and just say, Hey, I'm listening to Luke's podcast.
And they've kind of asked us to do this random thing,
to text a friend. And I just want you to say, Hey, what would you say my best quality is?
And that's it. That's the text. What would you say is my best quality? And like, you know,
let's see what people write back. And make sure if you hear back, like tag Luke and I on social
media and let us know, because sometimes we're so in our own head. And we think, Oh, my gosh,
I put a spelling mistake in that email, or I stuffed up that client, or, you know, what,
maybe you've been made redundant lately, like, there's a lot of challenges that are going on
for people. But you forget that there's so many awesome things that you've done. There's so many
ways you've impacted folks around you. And so get that external feedback, never be afraid to ask
people who you love, trust and respect for their thoughts about you. Because you might be very
surprised about what they say. And it also Luke might help you kind of better identify your zone
of genius so that then you can kind of lean into that in the workplace, because then you'll be
happier, work will become a lot easier for you. So yeah, there's so many positive ramifications
of doing that. I love it. It's a great idea, Maggie, coming from the sporting world, you know,
the historical thing was to spend so much time on what you couldn't do. Oh, he's not a great kick,
or he can't reinforcing all of the negative as opposed to the great coaches, work out what you're
brilliant at. And then the research, as you said, you know, if you focus on those things and improve
that, the results automatically are much better than the reinforced negative. And so encourage
everyone to do it. It's a it's a powerful thing. And we're not great, particularly in Australia,
we're not great at celebrating what we're good at. We're very uncomfortable sitting,
in that space, you want to make someone uncomfortable in our part of the world,
and the Americans are a bit better at it. But tell them what you like about them, tell them
that exercise, and you watch people squirm. It's a fascinating part of our psyche. Hey,
it's incredible work that you're doing. I love that it was born out of your own
sense of injustice. And I can hear your values come through so strongly. And I'm fascinated by
this. We think that success leaves clues, Maggie, and that in leadership, there are some real
patterns that we've identified and love to talk about, starting with self-leadership,
as a term that we feel like to lead others, like you're doing, you have to have an understanding
of your own sense of self-leadership. What does that mean to you?
Well, like, candidly, Luke, like, for me, when I left journalism, when I had a side
hustle, I had another business that was a side hustle that I leant into when I left
journalism while I figured out how to make Pet Talk Her a business before we became a
big consultancy. And, you know, I honestly spent, I reckon, six to 12 months just figuring
out what I was good at, and also what I was bad at.
Because there's a lot of things that I'm bad at. And so I did a heap of coaching, like
a heap of self-reflection. I was just like, I actually just need to figure out, like,
not who am I? I kind of knew that. But like, what's going on here? Like, what should I
be doing? What do I actually just need to cut out? Because it's not my zone of genius.
And so I did a heap of coaching. I'm obsessed with Gallup Strength Finders. That's been
really instrumental for me to understand that I am different and unique, and that's okay.
Because I think, you know, one of my Gallup strengths, for anyone who's listening who
knows about Gallup Strength Finders, it basically says that we're all made up of, I think it's
like 30 or 35 different strengths, right? And they kind of plot you on this chart, and
this is your top, and this is your bottom, or whatever. And they focus on your top five.
And a lot of my friends, Luke, used to call me Cyclone Palmer in a very, like, a kind
way. But sometimes I used to, I knew they loved me, and I knew it was nice, but I was
kind of like, like a little bit offended. I was like, what does that even mean? Because
I didn't understand. I was just like, well, I didn't realize that actually I have Activator,
as one of my strengths, which means that I love to start projects, I have lots of ideas,
I'm very good at, like, getting things done quickly, and just being like, okay, we'll
do this, and then we'll book a trip to Jamaica, and then these people will come, and it's
just done. And people are like, what just happened? But I'm like, yeah, but don't you
do that? And I didn't realize that, no, not everyone does do that. And I realized that
some of the qualities that I loved in my friends was because I really, that was their strength,
and I didn't have that, and so I so admired it in them. So for me, like, I really think
that, like, really, and I'm really candid with my team as well. I'm like, listen, I'm
really good at this.
And I'm sadly really bad at that, but just, like, full disclosure, this is what you're
getting into working with me, you know?
Yeah, and we see that again, Miggy, is a great strength, that no one's got every skill in
the book, and that's why you bring people around. But the hard part for most people
is actually self-reflecting to understand that they do need help in that area, and then
getting great people around them to support in those areas. That's the genius that we
see in these conversations. So I'm not surprised that you identified that, and the
support.
Self-reflection part, too, isn't it, as you said, to understand those strengths and go
after them. We really see people who are having consistent success really conscious about
how they positively impact others in their environment, and your work is having a huge
impact. How have you gone about that impact on people on a daily basis?
I think, you know, I think when I was thinking about this podcast interview and that conversation,
I think one of the other things that I wanted to share with your listeners is that I think,
like, sometimes I drop the ball.
And I think sometimes I'm not a great leader, honestly. Like, I'm a bit embarrassed to say
that out loud, but I think it's important to share that, too, because I think so often
we listen to podcasts and we, you know, I do it anyway. I sort of deify these people.
I'm like, wow, that's amazing. And like, oh, my gosh, I'm not like that. And how did they get
that done? And I just want to kind of candidly share that I think I've sometimes let my team
down, for sure. Definitely when I was a journalist. And even now, I think there's so much that I could
do to improve every day. And actually, COVID was really interesting for me because
I was working from home. And so was my partner, Ryan. And he said to me one day,
because he could probably hear a lot of my chats or whatever. He's like, you know,
you're a micromanager, right? And I was like, what? No, I'm an amazing leader and I'm a fabulous
manager. What? Like, I just didn't want to hear it. I was like, oh, you're so annoying. Like,
what would you know? Like, don't eavesdrop. I just like really deflected it. And actually,
I had to think about it. I was like, oh. So what I've realized, Luke, is that I think I'm a great
manager, but I'm actually not a great manager. And I think the two things are quite different.
So I, you know, I like to think that I am very good at inspiring the vision and kind of getting
people excited about the capacity to change, about the capacity to influence their career trajectory
when we're working with, you know, Fortune 500 clients and ASX businesses, you know,
like Westpac and Salesforce and PwC. Like, I love the change that we create for them
at the mid to senior leadership roles. And I think I'm good at that. But in terms of
managing my specific team, I've actually just the last couple of weeks hired someone.
And really, she's going to take on 90% of that work for me, because I was just letting my team
down. And I was worried that I was going to start to lose some of my integral team members. And
yeah, so I just wanted to share that because I'm kind of embarrassed by some of the mistakes that
I've made along the way. But, you know, I like the concept that everything is figureoutable
and that actually no one else knows what they're doing either. And everyone else is also making
sure there's other people listening who've also made mistakes and, you know, maybe feel
embarrassed by that. But I just wanted to share that so that other people know that they're
certainly not alone in that. It's 100% true. And I appreciate you doing that,
Meggie, isn't it? Because often it's the highlights for you, isn't it? We sit down and say,
well, you've got this great community. And for all of us, you know, we're really passionate,
Meggie, about a leader as a business that started eight years ago, founded with my great friend,
Matt Wadowitz. And he's currently in New York today with you. He's been over at the Green Bay
Packers and he's doing all the work. And I think that's a really good thing. And I think that's a
incredible thing. And we sort of sit back sometimes and go, but really at the same time,
making it up completely and making huge mistakes as you go and trying to figure it out, trying to
get better. You know, sometimes you need to apologize to your team because you just didn't
know and you let them down. But I think to share that is really what we love because that is how
you get better. If you're self-reflective and curious to get better, I think that's just part
of how you get anywhere, isn't it? So, yeah.
I think you summed that up incredibly well. It's an amazing vision that you've got,
isn't it? Closing the gender and leadership, gender pay and leadership gap. It's a huge
vision. We see leaders are really conscious about how they create those visions and share them.
How have you gone about that?
I do. So, I try and do this thing where every year I take two days and I kind of rent an Airbnb in
the middle of nowhere on my own. And I just take like lots of massive notepads and texters and I
just kind of like go through this weird...
I basically like don't... I just like put ideas on the blackboard and on the whiteboard and I write
and I post it and I just kind of brainstorm all of these different things. And early on in my
business, I created this kind of like internal manifesto kind of thing that really set out how
what our vision is to close that pay gap. The fact that we want to impact 100,000 women by 2025.
The fact that we have a wishlist of our 10 top corporate clients that we want to be working
with over the next 12 months and just putting that out there. And then my team joined me
after about two days of me going a bit like all over the place. And then they kind of helped me
bring it into line and this is a terrible idea or we could do this or add this on instead.
So, I try and share that with them and then also making it very clear about
what are the values and the behaviors that I expect from each of them in terms of how they
live that bigger picture vision. So, there's certain language that we don't use in emails.
There's certain phrasing that we do use because we want to try and infuse
our vision and our practice into emailing back and forth. Even little things like that.
So, yeah. I mean, again, I probably could do a better job of doing that on a daily basis. But
one of the other things that I've been really focused on lately is, and this is a coach helped
me with this, is giving positive feedback to my team every week. Because I'm very good at when we
let people down or when we don't achieve the goals, we're very good at talking about that.
But we sometimes forget actually to live our values and stop and reflect about those wins.
So, now that's part of our team meeting. It's part of my to-do list every week that I actually
reflect and send a Slack message to everyone about something that I'm really grateful for them for,
something that they've contributed. Because again, I want to build that muscle for them,
that they're valued, that they're contributing, that they're helping support the 60,000 women
that we work with around the world. They're helping to shift the percentage of leadership
in senior roles for our corporate clients. So, I want to remind them of that. Because as you know,
Luke, one of the challenges of running a business is the impact work and the execution is one thing,
but having a team to work alongside you and to stay alongside you is really important. And one of
the things I'm most proud of is my assistant. I was telling you before we started recording,
she's on her second maternity leave from the business now, which is awesome for her and
terrible for my calendar. But she's been with me for so long now and I'm hoping that she's
going to stay with me for a lot longer. But it's hard to retain top talent. And yeah,
so we try and do what we can in little ways.
Someone said something profound to me the other day. You don't actually build a great business,
you hire and collaborate with great people and they build a great business. And never a truer
word has been spoken. And I also really resonate with Stacey Morlang, who's great to have been on
this podcast, works with us now. And she uses the term, catch them being good is the way she
coaches junior sport. And it's so true that free hits there all the time, isn't it? Just in an
email to respond and just give that extra little bit of positivity in your world. It's something
that's sitting there. It's an obvious thing to do, but it's so powerful when people do it. And
you know yourself, when someone takes the time to send you a little message, it's an incredibly
powerful thing to do. Curiosity is a word we talk about a lot in our space. And we see ladies are
really curious in every area. And through that, that's how they constantly want to get better.
Is curiosity something that resonates with you?
Yeah. I mean, I can only...
I can only imagine my parents when I was growing up. I was probably that kid that was like,
but why? But why? But why? It's probably why I became a journalist because I'm so interested
in people's stories and understanding. And I want to know the nuance and I want to get deeper. And I
really want to know the heart of people because I feel like if you can understand people and not
just the surface level, like beneath the iceberg, truly what are folks' stories.
And then you can kind of understand people. You can empathize with them when they're cruel or
when they do something wrong. You can understand why they're doing that because of...
their story and what they've been through. So I am very curious specifically about people.
That's what really motivates me every day. And it's funny. Sometimes even as a journalist,
I was asking hundreds of questions a day and now I still ask questions. But even with our students,
as the business has grown, I used to know all of my students like I would know their entire
backstory. And now I still know them relatively well, but it's harder to know as many people at
such a deep level. But recently, one of them...
shared something which piqued my curiosity to ask her more information. And I knew that when
she joined our program, she was in a bad place. She was living in a remote part of Australia
in a bad relationship and she wasn't earning a lot of money. And then fast forward maybe a month or
two months after the program, she landed a six-figure job, which blew her away. But more
importantly than that, Luke, she was able to leave that relationship. And as a result of that leave,
that geographic location, she was able to leave that relationship. And as a result of that leave,
which she was finding very isolating. And I was curious, I said to her, I was like,
what do you think it was that motivated you to be able to make that change? Was it just the money,
the extra salary? And she said to me, Luke, she was like, yeah, it was that, but it was also
understanding that I wasn't the only one going through that. And the community that she'd found
in the pep talker community, and that also gave her the courage, I suppose, to connect with other
women. Understanding that people aren't alone, I think is so important. And you and I both worked
in the middle of the world, and I think it's so important to be able to connect with other women
a lot of that means meeting a lot of people and getting comfortable doing that. And I think I
often forget that it's very hard for a lot of people to do that. And when we can create moments
for people to be curious with each other and to connect with each other at a deeper level,
that's really powerful. And you never know what the multiplier effect of that could be,
not just for their relationships and their connection, but potentially for their lives as
well. Yeah, another great point. And loneliness is a real thing. And again, I was reading a
study, I think the other day that, you know, historically, if you went back sort of 50 or 60
years, most people would be able to say there's three or four people that genuinely trusted
personal confidence that are there for them in their life. And that was just historically because
people did connect in that way. And it was more of a village. But, you know, the advent of social
media at one level, we've got more friends online. But in America, most people have got not one
person that they would say is the trusted, confident that they could go to personally in
that situation. It's what a shift that is and how sad it is and how lonely people are out there.
We're surrounded by more people, but lonelier than ever. And so again, I'm not surprised your
community is having that effect on lots of people in a profound way. Congratulations on
what you're doing that communicating with clarity. I'm sure as your spaces evolve that
you mentioned it earlier, that opportunity to communicate consistently,
how have you gone about it? You know, I mean, I think one of the advantages of having,
you know, sometimes you sort of think maybe it was imposter syndrome for me being a journalist
and then starting a business. And I don't know if you had this as well, transitioning from sport
and media into business. It's sometimes you think, oh, I need an MBA or I should have been in finance
to start a business. And actually, one of the great things is, is that business, whether you're
in finance, insurance, consulting like we are, or if you're a social media influencer, it's really
about people and relationships. That's at the core of what any business is.
So if anyone's listening and has a bit of a kernel of an idea, like I really encourage you to go for
it and reach out to folks around you who've done that, who can help support you and give you that
advice. So one of the benefits that I've found, you know, the curiosity piece is valuable in
business, Luke, because you get to understand your clients better and understand their needs
and their pain points and how you can help them with that. But also understanding how to leverage
media as well and being able to, when, you know, Apple rings you to feature you on their news story
and they're like, oh, I'm going to do this. And you're like, oh, I'm going to do this. And you're
like, oh, I'm going to do this. And you're like, oh, I'm going to do this. And you're like, oh,
despite accidentally hanging up on them because I thought it was a prank, actually not being scared
of those interviews, not, not feeling anxious about talking to another reporter. Like I think
that's been a real benefit. And then also working with people that are smarter than me, you know,
other people who are really good because sometimes you get so close to your own story and your own
business and you need other people to pull back and say, you know, you need to be communicating
this before you communicate that, because I thought that this was the business, but my cousin,
who's a creative has really helped me with his agency, Windsor born to kind of,
clarify actually what our message should be. So getting input from external people has been
really helpful as well, Luke. Yeah. Which leads into the next dimension,
how important has collaboration been for you, Miggy?
Oh my gosh. Like I, I get out of bed for collaboration. Like I'm so here for it. I love
it. I just think it's exciting. And I think as well, someone said to me, it was one of the
accelerators, I think, you know, sometimes people are like, I've got this business idea. I'm not
going to tell anyone. I'm just going to be in stealth. And like, and they actually said in
this accelerator,
they were like, actually, you should share your idea with everyone. Because even if someone else
has the vision of closing the gender pay gap and wants to start a company, firstly, that's awesome
because then there's two of us tackling the problem. And secondly, they're going to do it
differently from me. Some of the things they do will be better. Some of the things that will be
worse, but like, they're going to be different because they're different from me. They've got
different strengths. And so actually I want to celebrate those other people in this space.
There's so much pie to go around and also like, let's just cook a bigger pie and make more
opportunities for other people. That's the way I look at it. And I think, I try to have a real
abundance mindset about business. And I want to support my friends in particular, women-owned
businesses. We try and sort of live our values in terms of who we contract, what consultancies we
use, what gift companies we use. We try and focus on women-owned companies as well, just to try and
live those values in every way that we can. Yeah. Simon Sinek talks about worthy rivals
rather than competitors or, you know, people that you're not going to be able to compete with.
You want to defeat someone who's in your space. Doing it well is a gift because it automatically
makes you want to be better and improve. It is a great shift in mindset, isn't it? Because we've
all had that nervousness. Oh, someone's around the corner going to steal my idea. But you're
right. It's the idea of sharing it. And abundance is such a healthy way to go about it. Me, who's
been the greatest leader in your life? Oh, that's such a great question. I mean,
I think there's sort of like, there's definitely family members,
you know, my family, my siblings inspire me, obviously my parents, my grandparents,
even my grandparents who I lost really early, you know, who I hardly even remember, but just like
the lessons that stay with my mom, my aunts and uncles, you know, my mom lost her parents quite
young. And so, but those lessons and those values really are instilled in me and my cousins and all
of our gatherings. And then the same on my dad's side, like family is so important. And I'm so
grateful to have that connection with my cousins. But then I also reflect,
like, on a business sense, like early in my career, I had this great news director,
Kathy Schnitzling. I started my career at Channel 10 in Brisbane, and she was the news director
there. And she was like, awesome. She kind of modeled vulnerability and authenticity before
it was cool. Like she was very like hard on the table, like this is the situation,
highs and lows of her life. And now I reflect on that. I was like, she was kind of like
living what Bren Brown practices now, but she was doing it all those years ago.
And even when it comes to pay, she modeled for me, Luke, really early.
I was kind of there for a year or two and I was getting a bit bored and I was kind of like,
maybe I should get another job. I don't really know. And I didn't talk to her about it or anyone
about it. I just started like Googling, what should I do next? And then she called me into
her office and she was like, so you've been here a year, a year and a half. You should really ask
me for a pay raise. And I was like, what? And she was like, wink, wink. Like, so if you were to ask
for better money, possibly I could do something about that. And I was like, oh, so she was kind
of like leading the way. And I was like, oh, I'm going to do something about that. And I was like,
could I please have a pay raise? And she was like, yes, yes, you can. So she kind of coached
me, you know, from a really young age that it's okay to ask that there was money available.
And I actually wonder what would have happened to my salary if she hadn't taught me that early on,
because we know that, you know, if you don't negotiate your first salary, which by the way,
I did not, when I took the job while I was still at university, I just took what they offered,
which I think was like 28 grand or something. And I thought I was so rich. If you don't negotiate,
like I didn't, because of compounding interest and superannuation and all that kind of stuff,
you're going to retire with half a million dollars less than someone else who did negotiate
in their first job. And so again, I just try and pay that forward to anyone who will listen,
like, please tell your daughters, your cousins, your mentees, anyone who will listen, like,
please negotiate your first salary. They might say no, but if they say yes, it's going to make
a huge difference over the course of your career. Yeah. Great advice all around. Our space is about
a world of collaboration and the genius that comes out of sharing great stories like yours and
telling them in profound ways. If you could collaborate with anyone, Maggie,
on any of your areas of your life and you're full of passion, I can see the amazing passion
that comes out. Is there someone that you thought that's who I'd like to collaborate with?
I mean, there's so many people and actually this is an exercise my team and I are doing at the
moment. We're actually coming up with a hundred people, a hundred people who are further along
in terms of their impact.
Who we would love to collaborate with. So that's, we're literally in process of doing that right
now. I mean, there's, there's some pie in the sky people who we have on the list. Like when we think
about from a young age, women making a huge difference. Like if you look at like what
Greta Thunberg has achieved, like pretty remarkable. And then all the way through to,
you know, someone like Michelle Obama, who, when she was in the white house, really used that
opportunity to champion healthy food eating and, you know, trying to shift the, the habits and the
food habits of, of kids across the board. And I think that's, I think that's a really good
thing to do across America, because as we know, sadly, obesity is such a big challenge here.
And now she's doing great work again, in terms of vulnerably sharing her story and her
highs and lows of her relationship with president Obama. And I think by sharing those stories,
she's giving other people permission to know that things aren't rosy a hundred percent of the time.
So those are some of the people that I kind of admire in terms of the impact that they're making.
But again, Luke, I feel so grateful. Like we collaborate with different organizations,
like multiple times a week, we have a bunch of not-for-profits who we love to support as well.
So I, I feel like for me, the most important thing is to like, love the journey. Like the
destination is, is yes, there are goals. Yes, there are metrics we want to hit, but also like
loving jumping out of bed and like living the journey, the highs and lows every day. Like
that's, that's what I love to live and breathe. Another great piece of wisdom. I, you know,
friends that were at the other end of the journey and, and they say, oh, the best part was when we
were sort of scrapping and fighting and trying to find a way. And I go, I'll take sustained
success, you know, if you want to swap, but, but they're right. You know, I think, yeah, correct.
Yeah, correct. But I think you're right. Isn't it? It's the little wins and the joy along the way is,
is the best way to go about it. It's incredible story that you're creating and the impact that
you're having is such a profound thing. And congratulations to you for it, Maggie. I look
forward to, to following you with, with great interest. Thanks for taking the time today.
Oh, likewise. Such a pleasure to chat. Thanks so much, Luke.
Thanks for listening to another episode of the
Empowered Business Podcast.
Huge thanks as always to our great friends at Temper. And we encourage you to check out
our Leader Connect program. New episodes are out every Wednesday morning at 6am.