My conversation today is with AFL legend Michael Voss.
Vossier has described himself as a ruthless yet passionate leader on the field.
He's evolved his style of leadership over time.
He's now coaching a very different generation of young men
with different wants and needs from him as their leader.
In this conversation, we discuss how Michael Voss' communication
is one of his greatest tools as a leader,
how he's overcome the need to be liked, his growth mindset,
and how getting his group to buy in is one of the most important things
that he does as the head coach of the Carlton Football Club.
Michael Voss is a considerate leader, I would describe him as.
He's got great determination and a real inspiration in everything he does.
His passion for what he does is one of the fundamentals of the work we do
at our leadership business, Alita, and we're incredibly proud
to have Michael Voss as part of our signature program, Alita Connect.
If you're interested in leading, learning, and collaborating,
you can find out all about it at alitacollective.com.
There's some fantastic resources there.
I encourage you to check them out.
Check out that signature Alita Connect program and get started
and to understand how people like Michael Voss are leading in your world.
Michael Voss is a Hall of Fame triple premiership captain
of the Brisbane Lions, universally regarded as one of the all-time
greats for Australian rules football.
He was voted by his peers on four occasions as the AFL Captain of the Year,
a Brownlow Medalist, two-time AFL MVP, five-time All-Australian,
and received just about every other award the industry has to offer.
Voss is currently the senior coach of the Carlton Football Club,
having previously been...
and the head coach of the Brisbane Lions for 109 games from 2009 to 2013.
An inspirational leader, renowned for his courage and determination.
Voss, you're always great to see.
Thanks for joining me.
Sounds like a fair journey, it does.
So, well done there.
Sounds like a good CV, mate, is what it does.
And full of great success, mate, in everything that you've done.
And, you know, I look back and, you know, I think from the very first time I met you,
you've always had a sense of presence.
When you walk into a room, no matter what the company,
you can almost feel Michael Voss is in the room.
Have you always seen yourself as a leader from a young age?
No, I definitely didn't.
Even when I was at 21 and asked to do the job, you know,
at the Brisbane Lions at the time, it comes as quite a great shock to me.
And I remember that conversation sitting down with John Northey and, you know,
he said, mate, we'd like you to be, like to be co-captain with Alistair Lynch.
And it came at a great shock.
And I said, look, I don't want to, I don't want to sound like I'm not really keen,
but I just, this is, this is a real shock to me that I've been regarded like this.
So I had to go away and have a think about it without saying yes straight away.
But having some conversations, ironically,
probably the most influential conversation I had was with Chris Scott.
And he said, mate, we want you to be, we want you to be the captain.
So I think without that counsel, I might've said no.
So it's amazing with the sliding doors and then you become captain for a while with Lynchie
and then you take it on yourself and you sort of grow into the role, I think.
I guess the more comfortable you become in your role and more presence you have within the team,
you start to feel like that's when you start to have your influence.
Yeah, it's fascinating.
You know, Chris Scott, he'd become a great leader in his own right
and coaches said you longed to great success.
And, you know, young teammate of yours at the same age.
And, you know, Chris has got a great amount of presence about him.
Was that someone that you sought out around that age and thought,
do you think I should do it?
Is that one of the people you went to?
Well, we had a number of guys through that time where we were all roughly the same age
and we all come together and there was this peer group that was starting to establish
and some of the older ones were moving on and some of the younger ones were coming through
and fortunate enough to have guys like Nigel Lappin and Chris Scott at that time,
Justin Lippich as well.
So we started to become the next group coming through.
And so I guess Chris's advice more at the time was that this peer group
or that demographic of age is getting larger and larger
and we feel like we need one of presence within that group
and we'd love that for you to be you.
And so that was the conversation.
And, yeah, I guess without that conversation, I probably wouldn't have taken it on.
Yeah, interesting.
And we know the history of those that follow Australian rules football.
We know that Vossie went on to be a triple premiership captain, as I said in the intro.
And the names you mentioned are alongside him, Nigel Lappin,
and Chris Scott, Justin Lippich, also all-time greats of the game that we both shared.
Speaking of presence, mate, I have this image in preparation for today.
I can see it crystal clear playing against you in the early days.
I think I know what game you're going to be in.
Well, I don't know.
You might have a story back for me, but I can picture it.
And you mightn't think of this one, but I can remember being at a Boundaries throne.
You come smashing through the contest.
You win the footy.
You clean up one of our midfielders.
It ends up in a goal.
And, you know, we're probably getting belted at the time.
And I remember jockeying back to the centre bounce, and you were admonishing yourself.
You were sort of hitting yourself on the thigh.
That would have been the highlight of the game for most of us.
But I think, you know, you'd had a slight fumble.
I don't think anyone on the ground would have picked up that it was a two-touch grab,
even though you won it perfectly.
And I thought, geez, this guy's got perfectionism.
Is that how you play the game, with wanting to be perfect at it?
I think it was more the ruthless nature that I enjoyed more.
And that is something that I grew into as well.
I mean, one of the really big things that I had to overcome by being a leader
was actually the need to be liked.
And for a lot of my time, I actually wrestled with that concept quite a fair bit.
I actually cared with what a lot of people would say about me,
even how the opposition might even say things about me.
And it'd actually affect me if it come back the other way.
And I learned a couple of really valuable lessons through my time there.
And I just thought, oh, I'm never letting that happen to me ever again.
It really affected me.
And so I started.
I started to make it personal and started to make it more ruthless.
And I was going to earn respect a completely different way.
And that meant being quite combative, both physically and also mentally.
And there's been some games that you sort of think, oh, geez,
I really went a bit too far there.
You know, I was really in the moment there, wasn't I?
And you only hear some of those stories back now.
But I just enjoyed.
I guess I grew to like that part of the game.
I don't think it was naturally within me,
but somehow it sort of was drawn out of me and it sat comfortable with me.
I remember the ruthless edge as well.
I still remember seeing that up close and personal.
That is, again, I've never heard you say that,
that initially you did take it on and you had to train yourself that way.
Because it always felt like playing against the teams you were captain of.
Even when, you know, we could be down 10 goals at the end, it's over.
And you'd be, you guys would still be giving it to us with three minutes to go.
It's almost like we'll leave some scar tissue for you for next time.
Yeah.
Was that it?
Was that part of it?
And, you know, and is that still how you coach today?
Oh, absolutely.
You know, I think when you look at humility, you know, you can,
there's a hard edge in humility as well.
And fortunate enough to have some really humble moments early in my career
where I was taught some pretty big lessons in that regard.
And playing against West Coast Eagles teams and playing against John Wurstfold
and, you know, being bashed up and then going to Geelong.
And being bashed up there.
And so I think it's almost, I sort of write a passage
that you sort of learn these lessons as you go.
And you sort of learn what that ruthless looks like.
And, you know, so humility to me still has that hard edge.
It's not an arrogance.
It's just saying, well, you know, I'm going to play the same way.
I'm not going to stop what I'm doing.
And I'll play to the final siren.
And this is the way that I go about it.
And challenge others to raise the game.
But don't worry.
It comes back at you at some stage.
So.
So as you start to tail off and you get a bit older, Darcy,
and there's a fair bit that comes back your way.
So what goes around comes around.
But I guess I love that part of the game.
Do you ever regret one?
Do you ever think, you know what, I wish I could take that one back.
I overstepped the line.
No.
Well, actually, there is a game, Darcy, and you might know this
because we have had some great clashes with the dogs
over that little period of time.
Quite competitive with Libertore and Ramiro.
And I remember, you know, I got quite personal
in terms of just, you know, being at that ruthlessness
and I was just at it the whole day.
And we had some great exchanges as two teams
that didn't mind that little bit of banter
and certainly didn't mind that physicality
and probably boiled over at the end of the game.
And I remember him coming over and trying to shake my hand
and I just didn't shake the hand and sort of kept moving on.
And I went back late.
I actually went back and shook his hand.
I said, oh, mate, yeah, no, the game's over.
Because I was still as much as I'd like to play the game on the edge
when the siren sounded, it was over.
And then we carry on.
I think I remember Tony Libertore in that game
calling you the worst Brownlow medalist ever, I think.
He did it one stage.
It might have been another game.
And I remember thinking, jeez, that's not going to age well,
that comment, but as you said, that was the nature of the combat.
Whatever you thought could maybe unsettle someone,
it was fair game, wasn't it?
Yeah, yeah.
And look, I think that, and I talk about this often
when I go to corporate and like what you did at the opening,
you read out a CV and they're all the great moments.
They're all the great memories that you have.
But I think the things that sit with you
are all these little exchanges that happen
and little lessons you learn along the way
that teach you certain things and prioritise
and teach you what's important and what's not important.
And that's where I've had my biggest lessons.
It hasn't been in the greatest of moments.
It's been in these little exchanges of people
that have challenged you in lots of different ways
and then just try to reflect back on that
and what would you do differently next time
and then you grow off the back of that
and just been having that continual growth mindset
to be better and want to be better
and have some humility in that you don't know it all.
And I've had moments where I felt like I've known it all
and got it wrong and plenty of other times
where I felt like I've been open enough
to accept the fact that I've done it.
Yeah.
The feedback that's needed to come my way.
And that's where you evolve, I think, as a leader.
And that's where you're, as a leader,
I think you can certainly evolve your style over time for sure.
Yeah, I want to touch on that.
Speaking of growth mindset,
and we sort of laugh about that era and those stories
because they're sort of the war stories
that are told from our generation.
But it was a pretty brutal era
and you played under coaches like Robert Walls
and it was certainly a ruthless edge
to the way coaches were in our generation.
But tell me about,
your evolution now as a leader
because you're coaching a very different generation
of young men and very different needs.
How have you changed?
Yeah, well, I think if you just compare the,
I guess my first go at it at Brisbane compared to now,
I've sort of likened it like having a new hard drive.
You're sort of repackaging it with different experiences.
You're rewiring it with different beliefs and systems
and then you go on at it again.
And that's probably for the last,
seven years or report was that was part of that process
was going back, working on your craft
and trying to better yourself in the areas
and targeting some specific areas you think
that you need to get better at.
And I was really lucky as well
that I had some good leaders around me
that I could learn off.
And certainly the one things that really impressed me
with Ken spending some time with Ken Hinckley
as the head coach of Port Adelaide
and his ability to be able to let people do their jobs
and, you know, but keep them really,
really highly accountable at the same time.
He wasn't at the forefront in front of the players
all the time.
He let the coaches lead their areas.
But in behind the closed four doors,
he was pretty ruthless in his intensity
to make sure that we were across everything
and that we were covering it off.
And if we weren't, he was challenging us.
And I really liked that.
And then people as a result could flourish.
They could put their flavour on things.
They could bring their creativity.
They could own it even more.
And, you know,
you hope that you get more out of people because of that.
So that's been a really strong influence for me
in now having another go at it
and let people be able to do their jobs.
It's pretty important.
And also a little bit with the players as well
is trying to tap into that as well
so they can problem solve themselves
and they can provide solutions for themselves
and give them the skill sets that they need to be able to do
to be able to get the job done.
Yeah, the title of this is Empowering Leadership, Voss.
It sounds like that's what you're describing.
And we see that as a real trend now around modern leadership.
I know you can't be on top of everything.
In fact, people don't want you to micromanage everything
and you need to have that.
And it's hard, isn't it,
for people that have had great success, you know,
by working harder than anyone else to let go is challenging.
But without it, you know,
it seems it's hard for people only to really be their best, isn't it?
Is that a constant challenge for all of you?
Oh, absolutely.
Yeah, like coaches are control junkies.
There's no doubt about that.
And so trying to control every outcome is just impossible.
So the way we try to do that is we try to provide an environment
and a training environment where players get to explore more things.
They get to be able to, you know, mistakes are embraced,
imperfections are embraced, and you have to be able to, you know,
vulnerability is embraced because without vulnerability,
you can't have creativity.
You cannot innovate.
So and then you find out where the possibilities lie in between that,
and that can sometimes help shape the next place you go to.
Whereas if you stay really rigid and you don't provide those opportunities,
well, it becomes quite narrow in what you can actually achieve.
So we all have frameworks.
We all have philosophies.
But we want to sort of obviously make sure that we're still bringing people's
strengths to the table and getting the best out of them.
You mentioned, you know, your first time as a senior coach.
It's the club that you're famous for and arguably the greatest, you know,
player in the history of the Brisbane line.
You then take on the senior role as coach and you have success.
You know, in 109 games, and then they sack you.
We don't mention that in the intro on these things because you talk about,
I mean, tell us about that.
I had huge admiration for you, as you said,
going back to your craft and the humility to say,
I'm going to learn again second time around and be an assistant
under Ken Inglis-Puertolo.
But how hard was that at the start?
And how did you, you know, evolve as a person through that time?
Oh, that was hard, yeah.
When you get sacked, and anyone can probably speak to this,
but, you know, you invest so much time into something
and you're pouring all your knowledge and your family's impacted
because this job's not, it's a lifestyle.
You know, coaching's a lifestyle.
So your family's in on it.
You know, you pour so much into it.
So then when things don't go the way that you want it to, it's personal.
And then what you've got to, after all that,
you've got to sit back and then sort of get people to cast judgments on you
about what,
what worked and what didn't work.
And there's some truth in that.
And then there's some, there's some mistruth in that.
And so you've got to try and navigate out what's real and what's not real.
So once I got over the initial,
the initial hurt of it all and could sit with it,
my next little part was, okay, what was real and what wasn't.
But when I reflect back on it now and had some time after that,
I sort of thought, well, you know,
they've probably actually done me a favour here.
You know, it was tough getting back to this seat.
Um, it was a bit harder than I thought that was going to be.
But at the same time, you know, when I looked at it,
it just wasn't the right club with the right person at the right time and it
didn't work.
And, uh, and so they went their way and I went my way and, um,
they're doing well and hopefully I can do well at a, at another club.
Hard when it's the club you had that especially hard, isn't it?
That, that amount of impact.
But can you share,
is there anything you can share with us when you say what's real and what's
not real?
So you're trying to sift through and so, you know,
you know, you're not perfect first time around.
Yeah.
No one ever is.
But was there something tangible you say, geez, you know what?
I had to learn that skill and that's made me better now.
Is there anything that comes to mind?
Yeah.
Look, the main one was the,
the potential distractions you get involved in or could get involved in.
Um, and as such, it's interesting now coming in,
one of the first requirements, um,
going through the job was I want to have a relationship with the players and
the coaches.
Like I must be able to,
we've got to put a structure in and around it that,
that enables me to be able to spend time with players and be able to give
them clarity about what they need, um, to succeed.
Um, because I felt like that wasn't quite the case.
It wasn't the case at Brisbane.
So my relationships really suffered.
Um, they weren't as deep and weren't as rich as what they needed to be.
And I found myself drifting off in all these other, um,
other places and all these other people problems and, um,
trying to control lots of other things within our program.
And, um,
it just took me completely away from the playing group.
Um, so not deliberate, not intentional, but that's what happened.
And as a result of that, um,
your relationships suffer and, uh,
you don't get to spend as much time with them.
Um, and probably as a by-product of that,
I've never actually received that as a reason.
Um, but that would be my interpretation of it for sure.
So then coming back in and,
and sort of now with what we try to achieve, um,
with the current structure that I have there.
And I talked to Brad Lloyd,
our GM manager about this is that it has to support me.
I don't care what it looks like,
but it's got to support me to be able to do that.
Um,
so small wins I have is when the coaches are out planning training and I'm
sitting in with a player and I'm having a meeting with them and the coaches
are doing their thing and I'm doing my thing.
I just see those as little wins.
Yeah.
And building those relationships you see is,
you know,
really integral part of you being,
because my perception of you is that you're a great relationship person.
People love,
you know,
being in your company as a player and as a coach,
it was not as though that was,
that part was,
it was just allocating the time.
Yeah.
Time.
Um,
and just in the,
the,
the timely conversations as well,
you know,
you can just,
you can address things as you go.
You don't let them fester.
You don't let them pile on top of one another.
Um,
you know,
I've been very big on that as well as problems arise,
solve them,
have the conversation,
don't let them sit,
don't let them duplicate.
Um,
and you know,
that's,
that's been a,
it's a really big one.
And,
and we tend to shy away from those conversations a lot.
Um,
and I probably didn't have enough of those,
you know,
that I needed to have,
whether it was just,
it wasn't set up that way.
I didn't have the time that way,
or I didn't have the relationship for him to be able to embrace it.
But,
um,
yeah,
affording time to be able to have those conversations is time well spent.
And likewise with coaches,
the only reason why you can sort of get coaches to be able to go out and do
what they do is because they're clear.
Um,
we're all on the same page with how we're actually going to play or,
you know,
what our standards need to be.
so,
so lots and lots of conversations,
which is probably why you become exhausted at the end of the day.
It does.
I was staggered that,
you know,
it took you so long again to be sitting back into the position you are now,
head coach of a,
of an AFL club.
You know,
for me,
you know,
seeing you from the outside as this credible competitor,
lifelong learner,
finds a way,
no matter what the obstacle,
was that hard that the industry took a while to say,
Hey,
we value you again.
Yeah,
it was,
it was strange to ask,
because,
you know,
as a player,
um,
when you finish your career,
you're,
you're a person that of interest,
they,
they want you.
Um,
and then when I finished Brisbane,
I was,
I wasn't that person of interest anymore.
And the phone calls stopped coming.
Um,
there's lack of interest in yourself or,
um,
so that,
that was actually,
that was actually really sort of tough,
a little bit,
um,
and quite different.
so,
you know,
sort of fighting your way back in.
I spent some time,
in the media for a little while.
Um,
that was a great,
um,
time away from coaching.
Gave me a different perspective.
Um,
enabled me to be able to think and reflect a lot.
And then stepping back into the coaching,
the next part was just being,
using it as a,
just to be as clear as I possibly can on the philosophies that I really,
that I stand for and that I'd like our program to,
to be.
Um,
and then when you step in,
you have that clarity,
you can get it.
But there was plenty of times where it was close.
And I thought this is it.
And then it got taken off me.
And then when this last one came around,
it looked like it was nearly going to be taken off me again,
because Clarko was asked one more question about whether he was going to coach again.
I thought,
oh,
this would be right.
He'll say yes.
And I'll be in the same boat.
So,
I have to thank Clarko for saying no and giving me the opportunity to be able to step in.
But,
so no,
I didn't,
I've got to admit,
um,
certainly initially,
it was much harder than I thought it was going to be.
And then there was a point where I thought,
oh,
it's never going to happen again.
Really?
Yeah.
I mentioned the term lifelong learner,
Vossi,
and I,
I'm not surprised that,
you know,
I get to cross over with you again in,
in this chapter in a space that,
uh,
my old mate and great friend,
Matt Waterworth,
and I are really passionate about called Alita Connect.
And I remember sitting down talking to you and I love Stardew Island.
He said,
look,
I want diversity of thinking.
I've spent my whole life around other athletes and coaches.
And if we're going to set up an Alita Connect group where we bring different leaders together,
that was your,
that was your immediate thing.
You know,
I want some different thinkers around.
And I,
and I love,
um,
and I've had the great pleasure of,
uh,
taking a while to get to you,
but I've spoken to all the other guys in your group.
Dr.
Chris Brown,
who's just a beautiful human being and an amazing person.
Richard Oppie,
the global head of marketing at Budweiser,
an old friend doing extraordinary things.
He's got incredible wisdom,
rich Benjamin Northey,
the conductor,
legendary conductor and,
uh,
Melbourne orchestra,
but revered around the world.
And so bringing that artistic brilliance,
Trent Robinson,
who has got a bit of you about him.
I think he's got a big heart and,
you know,
three-time premiership coach in the NRL.
Can,
can you tell us about,
you know,
why that's been important for you,
why that's worked and about the group?
Well,
I think what we end up doing,
cause we live in our bubble.
Um,
you can,
you can sort of be confined in your thinking at times and,
you know,
link being able to explore anything like that is,
is about expanding your thinking.
It's about expanding your circle and,
and putting a different,
um,
I love people have a,
just a different angle on bringing conversations,
um,
to the table and the way that they think.
And,
and,
and you know,
I'm more than happy to be able to turn 360 or 180 on something.
If I've got a view and then having a conversation with another person,
they give me a completely different perspective on it.
And it just makes you really think deeper about yourself.
Um,
why you see the world as it is,
um,
and then see someone else's perspective on it.
Um,
I get great nourishment from that.
so the creativity part is actually really important to me and having
conversations with all those guys,
um,
has been extremely useful.
Um,
you know,
talking to,
to Rich about,
you know,
brand and,
hear him speak about his world and some of the stories that he's,
uh,
covered with has been quite exceptional.
Um,
you know,
and then just being able to listen to,
to everyone in their own stories and,
and what they're going through and some of the problems that they've faced or
challenges they've got ahead of them.
And for him to have those open conversations,
I just find it incredibly enriching.
Um,
and you learn so much.
and just,
they're completely transparent,
um,
which is,
I'm really loving.
Um,
I think sometimes when it's in your own world,
you can be a bit more protective potentially.
Um,
you know,
if it's another AFL coach or it's another assistant coach or it's AFL,
you can be a little bit protective,
but,
um,
it just feels such like an open conversation and open dialogue.
And so you get so much out of it.
And I think that trusted confidential environment,
and that is part of,
um,
a little can it non-competing industries for that exact reason.
I think you wouldn't be able to,
to share.
And they are private,
but conversations and,
and clearly you're not going to share them.
I have had people listen to this in the past and say,
you know,
I don't quite understand the mechanics of what it is.
Can you do a better job than me around,
around how it works in terms of how often you catch up and,
and how often,
how long the meetings go for and,
and how you make it work in your busy schedule?
Well,
I think it's about,
well,
you just got to set the time.
I mean,
that's just the,
what it comes down to,
um,
which is incredibly difficult.
And one of them's in New York.
Um,
so it's,
uh,
it's incredibly challenging,
but at the same time,
um,
you know,
we catch up initially once a month.
Um,
you know,
we have some slight structure to that,
um,
around what we want to,
what we want to table and what conversations,
uh,
are there.
So we,
we have conversations around those and then post that period of time after,
you know,
I guess the first 12 months,
if you want to call it that it's,
uh,
it's over to us and,
you know,
whether we want to continue that relationship and,
um,
and it's still,
still obviously facilitated.
Um,
and we catch up probably once every five weeks and,
uh,
we only have one just,
better,
a week ago.
Um,
and again,
really enriching conversation.
Um,
you know,
initially they're,
they're meant to be about 75 minutes long and we never stay on time.
It's always longer than that.
Uh,
just because,
you know,
the conversations,
um,
you know,
it's just good to see where everyone's at and,
and,
and what they're,
what problem are they bringing to the table?
Um,
so generally I'll bring a theme or a question and then we unpack that question or we unpack
that theme.
And,
um,
and it's really enjoyable.
We,
uh,
you know,
I believe,
um,
Chris Brown was,
you know,
the back of a combi van in,
in Iceland and dialing in in the middle of the night.
And so,
you know,
it's a great credit to the connection you guys have,
have created that people just,
uh,
you know,
busy people find a way to take that time to self reflect them.
I mean,
it's a bit intimidating when you've got,
you know,
people of your background and success and there's success everywhere there.
But a lot of people say,
am I someone that would benefit from that?
Would you recommend it to someone who,
whatever they're doing,
education,
or a small business?
Do you think it's applicable to,
to a wider audience?
Oh,
I think it's absolutely applicable because what,
what you effectively,
uh,
you're doing is you're bringing out of the club.
You're not,
you haven't got a classroom theory environment here.
It's all experiential.
And,
and so we,
um,
so all of it is about experiences that all of us have having and the common
problems that come up that as a leader,
you don't often get the chance to be able to put around the table and just,
you know,
problems,
solve all together.
And when you're a key,
when you're a leader and you need to make key decisions,
there's a lot of things going through your head and you're working out all the
pros and all the cons of every decision that you're going to make.
So,
and at times being able to just go,
Hey guys,
this is the thing that's occupying my mind at the moment.
Can you help me out?
Um,
you know,
this is where I'm thinking of going.
What do you suggest that I need to be able to think about,
you know,
what are the,
what are the things I need to go back with?
Um,
and that's put on the table and then we,
um,
and then we unpack it,
extremely useful.
Um,
because I reckon every time that we've had that type of conversation,
there's been something that someone's taken away that they hadn't considered
yet.
Yeah.
We're going to wrap to,
uh,
to be able to collaborate with you bossy and,
and your wisdom in that is,
uh,
is profound as well to,
to the Carlton fans,
this thing.
And I,
and they will be not in 95,
it's 28 years ago.
Last time Carlton had the ultimate success,
one of the proudest,
most successful sporting organizations in the world,
really.
But it's been a long time.
I mean,
is that the dream for Michael Voss to be at the helm of,
of the next time they win it?
Clearly,
um,
you know,
that'll be a special day.
I wouldn't,
if you could take that one.
Oh,
be an appetite.
There's an appetite for it to us.
There's no doubt.
Um,
and I do dream of that moment.
how can't you,
that's,
uh,
sometimes keeps you going every day,
um,
when you're lost in the weeds and you're trying to sift through the next problem.
Um,
you sometimes just nice to remind yourself of the reasons why you're doing it.
But,
um,
I look,
it's a massive club.
Um,
yeah,
there's no doubt.
Uh,
I guess there's no doubt a weight of frustration amongst the,
amongst the fan base.
Um,
and it's probably 10,
20 years long.
Um,
the challenge within all that,
of course,
is that we still have to stay in the present and we have to,
you know,
our weight has to be by,
playing the way that we want to play,
um,
investing completely in that.
And,
um,
it has to be in,
you know,
being a great teammate and,
uh,
and how do I do that?
And,
and,
um,
you know,
there's not too much responsibility towards those things.
Um,
so keeping the players completely present,
um,
and the impact they want to have on the Carlton football club is really important to them.
Um,
they're a hungry bunch.
Uh,
they're really hungry bunch.
And,
uh,
so I know,
I know when you sort of stay hungry and you have a really strong desire,
you'll get the best out of,
get the best out of them.
You feel that,
that navy blue army,
uh,
is starting to get their voice back.
And we saw a bit of that,
uh,
last year.
I think they've all finished school and doing their thing.
But what are you like on the home front as a leader in the family?
No, my wife's the leader of our family.
Donna's?
Yeah, Donna is the leader of our family.
There's no doubt about that.
Why do you say that?
Well, I rely on her because, you know, I guess the thing with at work,
you know, and she says this to me often, you know, you're so organised,
you're, you know, to-do lists and you've got a schedule planned
and, you know, you're organising things and having all these conversations
and you come home and it's tools down.
And I go, yeah, I know.
I said, because I see you as the leader of this family, not me.
And she does such a wonderful job at it.
And, you know, so I rely on her.
Where are we going next?
What are we doing?
Where are we going?
Who are we visiting?
What have the kids got on?
You know, so it's, yeah, it probably does frustrate her at times,
but I really rely on her to be able to lead
me in that environment.
What a gift in life though, Voss, isn't it?
To have a partner that clearly compliments you.
Yeah.
It's probably about as good a thing as it can be.
Oh, mate, it is.
And I guess the big thing that within, I get asked the question a lot around,
you know, separating work and home and I've sort of, I don't think,
every person I've asked, in fact, we've actually tabled this conversation
amongst it and I think the universe, we're all agreeance that it's,
no one's perfected it.
That when you've got people who are really great in their field,
being able to separate it from time to time is really, really difficult.
But one thing I like-
Separate work and home and get that balance right.
Get that balance right.
It's really difficult.
But the way I guess I always sort of answer that is just be totally present
where you are.
And so if that means if you've got two hours with your family,
spend two hours with your family, both spiritually, physically,
mentally, like, just be totally present.
Yeah.
And that's all that my wife's ever asked of me is just that if you are going to be
here, then just be present.
And so I've tried to stay true to that, but I certainly wouldn't say that I've perfected
that.
So the phone.
Phone down.
Yeah.
So I used to have little things like with the kids when the kids were younger and because
they love these games and it's all about like self-accountability.
So it was $5 in the jar every time that the phone, you know, if I picked up the phone
or the wrong time and I'd take a phone call and it was dad five bucks.
Yeah.
In the, in the jar.
So in the, in $5 goes in the jar for whatever they wanted.
And, um, so they were almost hunting me down around corners.
Getting your mates to ring me.
So when they were kids, but I needed that discipline at that particular time to be able
to see that through.
But, uh, no, I certainly don't perfect it, but, um, I would say if I've got any advice
for anybody, it's just be totally present.
And that's a good lead in bossy to the dimensions of leadership that I love asking, uh, great
leaders like you and starting with self-leadership.
And I see, yeah, enormous self-leadership in, in you and your life.
How do you describe that for you?
Well, it's, yeah, well, it's leading self.
I mean, first and foremost, you, you have to, you have to be able to lead yourself,
um, to be in a position to lead others.
And, um, we probably don't spend enough time on that.
So having, having some really strong self-awareness, um, particularly when you're in positions
like, you know, coaching or, you know, your CEO of a business and you've got, you have
to rely on that.
And, um, you know, I'm, I'm really big on being able to continually ask people about
what's going on and just checking the pulse of the group and the environment and what's
happening.
Cause it's all feedback for you to bear, to, to help you where, where do I need to go next?
Um, but more importantly, I've also, you know, learn around just, you know, stay healthy.
Um, you know, uh, try and find some time for yourself, um, because as the stress is built
up, the more distracted you become.
So, um, that's why I feel is actually really important.
Yeah.
And part of leading self is, you know, having healthy regime.
Um, again, I haven't been quite as disciplined as that as I'd like to be, but it seems to
stack up every time when you find that real sort of health time, um, and personal time
just to be able to relax and what that looks like is really important in being able to
have all the energy you need for others.
Um, when you go in there and you need to lead, you've got the energy to do so.
Stories just coming to mind.
I just hadn't thought about it, but we, um, crossed over, you remember, I think we both
retired the same year.
And we, we're doing, uh, some coaching together at the Institute of Sport, taking the best
young, 30 young AFL players, went up taking them to South Africa a couple of years in
a row.
It was a good, I loved it.
It was a great experience.
It was a good time, wasn't it?
But I, uh, there's a few stories out of that trip, but I remember you, you know, we're
mentoring these young kids and I remember you turning around and going, right, we're
going to catch up in, you know, eight weeks time, go South Africa, skinfold challenge
for the coaches.
And I remember thinking, mate, the war's over.
I said, well, I've just retired.
I don't need to be, to be.
But you know what?
You sowed that seed and it was like, I'm on here.
I'm on, we're training.
You know, is that about your own sense of self going?
I wanted to do that and I'm going to.
I needed, I needed to be, I liked being competitive.
So that was my way of being competitive.
So I actually think I was the only one in that competition, I think, but it was, it
was good for me.
So I didn't, I didn't mind.
You turned up in good nick next time we saw you.
I know, I know that much.
How do you think about positive impact in your environment?
It's probably what your job is, you know, as an AFL coach, but do you
constantly.
Think of that day to day, how do you impact the environment positively?
Oh, absolutely.
You know, there's, there's, there's critical things that you think about to
create that positivity, you know, and, and some of that's been even just the way
I've probably changed the way I've led, you know, little things like looking at
people's strengths, you know, not seeing faults in people all the time.
And in coaching, you almost hide to find faults, right?
You know,
just asking the question, you know, what'd you like and, and having the response of the
group, you know, at all being positive, um, rather than looking at an edit and sort of
picking through the holes of all the things that are wrong in it.
Well, yeah, we can do that all day long.
Cause in every edit, there's something that's wrong.
Um, but I didn't ask that question.
I asked the question, what did we like about it?
Um, and so it's a different type of question to ask.
Um, I'm very big on modeling heroes, um, within your program.
Um, we spend a lot of our energies, um, often on the people that we're working with.
Um, and so it's a different type of question to ask.
Um, but I find that if you're, if you model your heroes, um, then 80% of the group want
to get the same pat on the back.
They want that reward.
They want to be acknowledged for doing the right thing.
No one turns up on a day and wants to be terrible.
Um, they want to learn how to do it right.
And, uh, so very big on those.
So, um, very big on gratitude, um, around focusing on what you have as opposed to what
you don't.
And, uh, so that.
Underpins your philosophy as a coach because, um, you have to provide that.
That doesn't mean you're shy away from performance conversations.
It doesn't mean you don't hold people accountable to the jobs they need to be able to perform.
Um, there are still avenues and opportunities to be able to do that, but there is a balance,
um, to how you go about that.
Yeah.
I love hearing that, that language from you.
I remember as a player and you'd be injured, you might sit in the coach's box and all you
heard was he can't kick, he's a terrible mark, can't trust him on his left foot.
It was just one after the other.
And I remember.
Thinking, isn't the art of coaching, getting players to do what we need them to do and,
and you're right, became this sort of self-fulfilling perpetuation and negativity too much, wasn't
it?
Rather than God, if we coach that person to do that, he's going to be fantastic in his
role.
It sounds like you've got that right at the forefront of your mind, creating and sharing
a vision.
We see leaders like you pretty clear on how they do that.
I think we probably all know your vision at Carlman might've spoken about it before the
success is obvious.
But how do you, how do you go about getting the whole group to buy in on that?
Um, talking about it often, um, what's, what's actually really, uh, important at the start
is that, uh, everyone, every sort of, everyone has a say on the way forward.
You know, like if there's one thing I've learned about, you know, groups now is that they want
to have, they want to belong to something and they want to own, they want to own something
and, uh, and having a say on that direction actually really, um, inspires them to want
to be a part of it.
So at the start, it was quite literally, I said to the players, how do you want to play?
Um, let's, let's scribble it down.
Let's write it down.
Um, and, uh, and they're not far off.
They're smart guys.
They know their footy.
Um, and then, you know, asking, I guess then permission, which sounds like a silly thing
to do, cause that's your job, right?
I was like, oh, can we take that away?
And as coaches, we'll come up with something and we'll come back to you and let's work
through the language and, um, let's really sort of hone in what really sort of sits well
with you.
And, and so that's what we did.
And as, as coaches, we went away, we formulated some plans, we formulated some principles.
Um, we come back, we check with the group.
What do you think?
Yeah, we love it.
We go back again.
Okay.
Can we put some structure in that?
Can we put some roles around that?
What roles would that look like?
And then sort of your themes start to emerge out of that.
Um, so I feel if you, if you can have that approach and the players can buy into it and
they all own it, when you come back as a coach and say, hang on, didn't we all, it's not
going, didn't we say we're all in on this?
Um.
It has much more power and has much more meaning, um, rather than it's just the coach's idea
and it's just the coaches that are running the schedule and we just follow what they
do.
Um, it's important to bring them along on the journey, but also what's really important
is that using as many opportunities you can is to show or talk about your vision and,
um, talk about what it should look like.
Um, because I think we want that.
We want to see what it looks like, but you also then, how is it relevant for what I'm
doing right now in the moment today?
Yeah.
And that's what all the research says for us.
If you co-create it with the team and they are in part of the process of determining
their own vision, it's just so much more, but it sticks, doesn't it?
Yeah.
If you come in over the top and, and, and just, it's your words and not theirs.
So.
Yeah.
I love that co-create.
And, and even just with the training environments, what we try to do is try and enable them to
be able to, um, you know, problem solve and, um, have those conversations about what's
working and what's not working and skill.
Um, skill our leaders to be able to have those conversations because there's no, there's
no stronger conversation than peer conversation and, um, and them getting on the same page.
So we certainly haven't perfected that.
We're nowhere near by any means the finished product on it, but, um, there are some of
the things that actually are really important to us in our environment.
And Vossi, I think that applies so much to every environment that I've ever been in.
You think, you know, you're coaching Patrick Cripps, who's just an outstanding player and
human, but to not think that he's a resource.
You know, which wasn't in the past.
It was hierarchical and there was no, what the coach didn't ask a play, even if he had
300 games experience.
And I think of that in work environments, we've got these highly skilled people who
really know their craft or know their business really well, but the, the, the executive or
the CEO doesn't engage their thoughts.
It's disheartening, isn't it?
You sort of don't feel like you belong in the environment.
And it sounds like you're right on top of engaging the group in that way.
So my curiosities are where we hear a lot of leaders like you.
You know, through their, through curiosity, that's how they, they think about learning.
Does that resonate with you?
Oh, absolutely.
Um, uh, not being fixated on the way that you learn, see things.
Um, yeah, that's, that's extremely important when it comes to learning and being curious.
And, um, if you're going to a course and you have a fixated mindset of the way things should
be done, you really should be thinking about what you're actually doing there.
Um, because you're, you're there to expand your skillsets.
You're there.
You're there to build more capacity.
And, uh, um, and if you're closed minded off to that, well, then, you know, improvement
will be extremely slow, extremely slow.
Yeah.
I mean, so that every day and you communicating with, with clarity, you know, something that
big part of what you do day to day, if you, if you've got a, a strategy around the way
you communicate, not real.
I just think often and timely, um, you know, and, uh, you know, timely conversations.
I think that's, uh, it's an underrated skillset to be able.
To have timely conversations, you know, don't kick it down the road.
Um, don't wait for another time, um, find the time to get it done.
And, um, I think that that's exceptionally important.
And, um, you know, when you, and, and the other thing is too, is that as players, and
I know you'll appreciate this to us, it's just, you know, the honesty behind it.
Um, it just be transparent and be honest and, um, and, and don't, you know, don't try and
sell anything.
You know, I just, it's not real.
It doesn't feel authentic.
Um.
So I guess that's probably the two things, timely conversations and having honest conversations
and, um, and just be prepared to have them, um, with as many people as you can.
And, and out of that creates clarity.
Um, also the other thing is, I don't think you can be afraid of is don't, don't be afraid
that, um, having conversations that are a bit muddy.
Uh, you know, a lot of our conversations with coaches and, and, and in behind the four walls
is that we're, we're the ones that when it's a bit murky and it's a bit muddy and we're
unpacking things and then take an hour.
And a half to come up with the one thing that we actually want to come up with.
That's a great conversation because while it might be a bit murky in here, um, by the
time we walk out, it has to be crystal clear.
So when we communicate back to the players, you know, it's clear for them.
So it's understand.
So we're trying to make complexity into simplicity.
Yeah.
Um, so if we don't make, if we make it complex when we walk out of the room or we're not
on the same page, gee, that can create some issues and certainly more issues than what
it's worth.
Um.
If you just spend 10 extra minutes.
10 minutes in that room to be able to get the clarity that you actually need.
Yeah.
I love the way you pitch that.
Just communicate often and do it, you know, authentically and, and, uh, and sincerely.
It's a, it's a pretty, uh, good path to follow.
Collaborating, Rossi, how important has that been for you now as a leader?
I think that would be one of the main things I feel like I've changed, um, or has evolved
over time, um, is literally that word collaboration.
Um, the other.
You know, the, the collaboration piece is that when we integrate within our programs,
having welfare come together and development come together and line coaches coming together
and collaborate together on what we want that program to look like.
And we don't have people sitting in silos and they're off running their own program
and we've got our, they've got their own program.
All it ends up happening is the end user for us is the player.
And what happens is, is that within the program, everything just duplicates.
Um, and then the feedback you get from the player.
So, geez, there's a lot in the program.
Um, whereas if you can, if you can co-create, as you said, and you can sort of integrate
and you can collaborate, um, your programs, I think they're effective.
They are time, it's time consuming, um, to be able to come up with what that looks like.
But, um, again, I think you get paid back, um, with the players because it's time efficient.
You're much more productive.
Um, it's much more purposeful in, and you have just greater intent in, in what you're
trying to do.
And then often, you know, in footy clubs and artwork.
And well, those silos can then become negative and become resentful because they're not being
collaborated with different narratives come out of that.
And that's where you sort of, that foundation's a discontent, aren't you?
If you don't do it with all the things that you're saying at one, you know, you're not
going to be effective, but two can be the reverse of that too, can't it?
It can get pretty toxic.
Yeah, absolutely.
And, and there's some, um, there's some struggle to through to get it to, to as efficient as
you want it, but it's a, it's a worthwhile, it's worthwhile cause to chase.
Um, but the collaboration.
The collaboration piece, uh, I think that's, you know, a lot of people talk about connection.
I reckon that's been a really big change in the last, probably 10 years.
I'd say the other one has been collaboration, um, and how you get the departments not, not
only just deliver what they need to be able to do, but how do you work together?
And, and it's also with players.
So we just talked about how we co-create a game style.
Well, it's collaborating with them on the way you want to play.
Um, so you have that shared purpose.
And if you can get that shared purpose and it has really great clarity, well, hopefully
never guarantees the success, but hopefully it gives you a greater percentage chance of
being able to do so.
Who has been the greatest leader in your life?
Oh, my dad.
Uh, that seems like a really obvious thing to say.
I think what I've been really blessed with, Dars, is that in different stages of my life,
I feel like I've been surrounded by leaders.
Um, and whether I've naturally gravitated to it, I'm not sure, but even as a young fellow
being at the Morningside Football Club, um, I had a guy called, uh, who was the captain
of the Morningside Football Club named Daryl Burke.
And, um, and Berkey for some reason took a sort of, uh, an interest in me and he gave
him my first brand new Sherin.
So I had a Sherin, but it was that old one kicked on the road a hundred times that was
brown and it lost all its color.
And, um, the laces were starting to come off and cause it had been kicked endlessly between
me and my brother.
And he walked up to me one day and he handed...
He handed me my first Sherin.
And, uh, and I remember picking it up and then I smelled it for the first time.
It's just that unbelievable smell that I'll never forget.
We all love that smell, don't we, mate?
I used to sleep with one when I was a kid.
It's, it's hard.
Yeah.
So he gave me it to me and he said, mate, um, what I want you to do is, he said, you
can have this Sherin.
I've gone, I'm looking at him going, are you telling, are you joking me?
And he goes, mate, I'm going to give you this Sherin.
He said, but what I want you to do is you've got to learn how to spin it on, on, on your
finger.
And I'm guessing the message out of it was.
So him was like, mate, touch the footy, have the footy in your hands all the time.
So I just went away and I was like, oh, mate, unreal.
So I was just like trying to spin the ball and trying to do all these things.
So the fact that he has actually influenced me, um, and just by reaching out and showing
an interest, that was really profound for me.
Um, you know, I had Roger Merritt who went there and we weren't as good as we probably
could have been at the bears at the time, but he was just a really strong leader for
me and scared the bejeebers out of me and everybody else.
Um, he was, he was exceptional.
Um, Lee Matthews, um, was just a, probably the person that taught me how to be a leader.
If you want to sort of converting the talent into hopefully something as a leader, he was
a leader of men.
Um, so he, he was, he was exceptional in that, but it was always in the background was my
dad and, um, my dad helped me out and teaching me about, you know, the values of life and
what was important and wasn't, what was important.
And, uh, without him, I certainly wouldn't achieve what I, uh, where I've got to.
Yeah.
I would have brilliant answer.
I love, I love it.
No hesitation on your dad, but then to, as you said, they're good fortune, isn't it?
If you have few people in your life along the way that, that clearly set you on a pretty
amazing path.
It's a, I'm a, I'm glad you got the chance to, to acknowledge them then I'm, I'm sure
you would have done it before.
Um, you know, in the, in the spirit of collaboration, I like asking this question and you know,
you've got other interests as well, so it may be footy related, but if you can collaborate
with anyone on, on anything, is there a name that springs to mind?
Have you?
No, it doesn't actually, um, no, I don't, I don't think it stands out.
Um, no, I don't think it stands out to us.
I'll keep searching.
I'll put, there'll be an obvious thing when we walk away from this, so I can't believe
I didn't say that, but.
You'll think of it in the car and you can ring me back.
No, no.
It's a, you know, I think that, as you said, your world's diverse, but, um, there's a pretty
clear goal that you've got at the moment, isn't it, to, to bring that success back to
the environment you're in.
Is it, is it sort of feel like, um, when you wake up every day.
Yeah.
You know what you're up for?
I'm reminded every day, I, you know, sort of even last year and what we, what we did
last year and then how it finished, it's, um, you know, I still think about that a lot.
Um, but it reminds me every day what I'm doing here and, um, you know, the purpose is really
clear for me and, uh, you know, and it's, uh, it's, it's extremely exciting opportunity,
um, you know, to be able to sort of leading the, the, the Carlton football club.
I was, uh, you know, when I was a kid.
There was, there was, you know, my pop and me and we'd follow Carlton and everyone, the
rest of my family was pretty much Richmond.
Um, but pop got me under the wing and said, no, son, you're with me.
And, uh, so I remember watching the blue baggers, um, you know, from a very young age.
And, um, so to go full circle on that and then be back here, who are the players in
your use that, uh, yeah, that's easy.
Um, so Kenny Hunter was always a personal favorite Wayne Johnson.
Um, right.
Ashman was, um, was pretty special.
Um, Bruce Dooloff.
Yeah.
Bruce Dooloff back.
Um, so there was plenty, there was plenty of competition in the backyard of Carlton
versus Richmond and that was, uh, versus Dale Waitman and Michael Roach and, um, sort of
those types from Richmond and Jimmy Jess and, uh, those sort of the types.
So yeah.
What a golden era.
You know, the, the Carlton and Richmond sides of that era, weren't they?
Yeah.
I've obviously, I've always, uh, admired you greatly from the very first moment I met you
and not surprised to see you doing unbelievable things and everything you do.
I'm really, um, excited that you're, you're part of a lot of that.
Thanks for all your passion and wisdom and for taking the time today and, and, you know,
I think all of us who love the sport that we both played, uh, so you're at the helm
of Carlton and you know, you feel like there's something special building there and we wish
you all the best.
Thanks to us.
I'm glad I was the last one to, uh, to come on this, but, uh, no, good chat mate.