Well, it is brilliant to be back with you in 2024 on the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Couldn't be more excited for the year ahead and thank you for tuning in.
Some really exciting guests coming up and a great way to kick off the new year.
I hope you've had a happy and healthy start to the year yourself.
But Michael Snyder, the Managing Director of Bunnings, is our first guest of the year.
It's one of the great Australian business success stories and Mike's leadership is revered
amongst the business community in Australia.
I hope you're going to enjoy this chat as much as I did recording it and you're going
to hear some great little nuggets of wisdom from Mike Snyder.
You hear Mike talk a lot about the power of listening as a skill that he values and his
great pride in that 25% of the workforce at Bunnings are over 50.
It is a really happy home for people as they age and want to continue working.
You also hear him talk a lot about his passion for collaboration and some great advice for
anyone who thinks they're the smartest person in the room.
I won't give it away, but he thinks you're setting yourself up for failure if that is
your attitude.
He also really interestingly for me talks about sometimes the greatest teachers are
the ones who've gotten it wrong, that you can learn by really positive example and you
can learn from those that you maybe don't want to be like as well.
It's people like Mike Snyder from Bunnings who inspire the work we do at Alita and a
great way to start 2024 would be to check out alitacollective.com and our signature
Alita Connect program.
Where we bring together unique and bespoke groups of five to six people to learn to lead
and collaborate.
Love you to check out Alita Connect.
Book a discovery call with us today.
Big thanks to Jason Nicholas and his team from Temper for their ongoing support of the
Empowering Leaders podcast.
Temper, a mattress like no other.
To get a good night's sleep is one of the great keys to a happy, healthy and successful
life.
So check out Temper today.
Michael Snyder is the manager director of Bunnings Group Australia and New Zealand.
He leads a team of more than 53.
3,000 closing in on 400 stores with an annual turnover of $18 billion.
Renowned for his genuine care and commitment to team, the wider Bunnings community and
staff are respected for their outstanding culture.
Mike is a great contributor to the not-for-profit world as chairman of FightMND, the Never Alone
Foundation, a board member of Corporate Mental Health Project and Melbourne United.
Mike, great to see you.
Thanks for taking the time.
Thanks, Luke.
Great to be with you.
As a 15-year-old, I understand your first job was at Target.
Yeah.
You fell in love with the world.
You fell in love with the world of retail.
What grabbed you at that age?
Oh, I think for a lot of people, when you start out, you're looking to earn a bit of
pocket money.
And for me, getting into a retail environment was very comfortable from an early age.
Being a part of a team has always been something important to me.
And the engagement with customers is also something that's always been fascinating.
But I didn't really sort of start with a view that I'd spend my whole career in retail.
I studied to be a high school teacher, did a bit of prac teaching, worked out that wasn't
for me, and ran away from retail.
For a few years, I worked at a bank, which also reminded me why I love retail.
So getting back and getting to Bunnings almost 20 years ago has been incredible.
Yeah.
So you go to the Bunnings story straight away.
And as you said, close to 20 years there now, as the managing director.
It's one of the great business success stories Bunnings grew.
What's the key to a success?
Without a doubt, it's the people and the people create the culture.
I think the format's a really simple one.
Three very clear strategic priorities.
Lowest price, widest range, best experience.
It's for our customers and our team.
And I think that when we stick very close to our knitting on those things, then we can
deliver a differentiated offer that resonates with customers.
I think Aussies and Kiwis have a true love for their home.
And I think doing things that can make our homes, therefore our lifestyles better, is
pretty compelling.
I said to you just before we started recording, I was actually in your store yesterday and
my wife was driving.
I said, I've got to drop into Bunnings.
It's good timing.
I'm catching up with the CEO, Mike, tomorrow.
And I could.
I'm going to be the least handy person in Australia.
There's no reason for me to go to a handyman store, a hardware store.
But I walk in, she wanted to get one specific item, and I immediately go, I knew Esky would
be good.
That pizza oven looks good.
That's the only retail experience I ever go to that I actually are happy to stay around
and want to buy things.
How have you created that?
Well, I certainly didn't create it.
I've worked hard to build on what's been done over almost 30 years.
Bunnings Warehouse turns 30 in 2024, which is a...
a great milestone for the business.
But I think it's a...
it's a multi-sensory experience.
It's somewhere where you can be working in the garden, covered in leaves and mud, get
up, jump in your car, go to Bunnings.
We don't stand on any ceremony.
It's a pretty straightforward shopping environment, but it touches your senses in lots of different
ways, from the barbecue at the front of the store on a weekend, to activities for kids
in store, or craft activities for mums or dads, or the family nights we do.
I think when you come to Bunnings, you can feel very comfortable.
You're very safe.
You can bring your four-legged family members.
You can bring your friends along as well, if you want.
And hopefully, you spend a while and spend some money and keep our team engaged and keep
us growing.
And there's genius in that, isn't it?
We can all...
You know, life's prices, we'll beat it by 10%.
The Bunnings jingle we've all got, you know, in our brain.
And even that, I didn't realise you could bring your dog, so you've won my wife over
for life because Dennis, the staff, he's allowed at Bunnings.
And the sausage sizzle is legendary.
I talked to you about that, but for people listening that have got a small business or
they're wanting to create a small business, you've got to bring your dog.
Are there lessons that a scaled business at your size can teach smaller businesses?
I think it's all about being very clear on your why.
I think if you've got a sense of purpose around what you're doing, then whatever it is gets
easier because you've got clarity of where you want to go, keeping it simple, trying
to keep it as uncomplicated as possible.
And that does get challenging with scale.
But if you've got that focus on what you're doing, where you're going, keeping it simple,
and checking with your customers, make sure what you're offering is meeting a need, it's
delivering on expectations.
And I think you earn the right to be chosen.
And if you do that, then you've got the opportunity to scale and grow.
So you think that's where people get lost is that the clarity of message is not there
and people get confused.
And I think the second point you're saying is you've got to ask your customers, is there
a need for what you're trying to sell?
Are they the two big lessons?
Oh, absolutely.
I think so.
I think if you're not clear or you get distracted, then customers will get confused.
And if customers can't see the value proposition or don't understand what it is you stand for,
then you're not really doing anything.
You're not doing anything to be chosen.
You're not doing anything to differentiate.
And there are lots of competing agendas.
But I think coming back to what is it we're doing, why are we doing it, who are we serving,
they're really good foundation elements for any business.
Which is brilliant, isn't it?
Because I understand you've got 45,000 suppliers or thereabouts, and every product known to
mankind is in a bunny's warehouse now.
So you can still keep it simple, even with that array of products?
Oh, look, I think it gets more complex for sure.
We're very clear on where we think we can play and where we think we can't.
When you've got...
When you've got the customer traffic that a business like Bunnings has every week, let
alone every year, you could probably back yourself to sell a range of different things
that aren't really core to what we do.
But we really think about serving you in terms of anything you need from the front gate to
the back fence of your house and anything in between.
That's the lens through which we look at our model.
And if we can serve you in that space to make your home a better home, that's a great place
to be operating.
You just said we could probably, with that amount of foot traffic, just about sell anything.
How many sausages do you sell?
Well, the fundraising, well over 20 million a year that goes back to the community.
So I haven't worked it out in terms of actual sausages, but it'll be in the millions.
I know that we sell something like 7 million cups of coffee through our cafes every year.
So there is a lot of velocity there and a lot of demand.
But the stuff we do for the community is really, really special.
Yeah, and it resonates with people genuinely.
It feels authentic is the word that springs to mind when I walk through.
I hear you talk about it, mate.
Keep it small as one of your real values.
How do you do that when you've got 53?
I think it's got to be accessible.
We're really fortunate we use an enterprise social media tool called Workplace.
That keeps us engaged.
We've got close to 50,000 of our team on that.
We're in our stores.
I spent all of last week across New South Wales and New Zealand visiting teams and listening.
And I think that's the best place to be.
There's no better day than when you grab your red shirt and your apron and you know you're
going to be in stores.
It's a great way to connect.
And then when we're with our support teams or our suppliers, those stakeholders are really
important as well.
So spending time.
Listening, learning.
We just took some of our top suppliers away up to Caravan Park in Ngambi for a couple
of days.
Listening to what's on their mind, sharing our plans for the future.
And it's the same as we roll through our support officers, sit and talk.
And I think listening is a really important and often underrated skill in leadership.
That feels really on brand for a supplier function for Bunnings at Caravan Park in Ngambi.
It's not quite the south of France, Mike.
No, no, no.
We steer away from those things.
And there's a really nice story.
So many people would know that that part of Victoria is smashed pretty hard with the
floods recently.
And our commercial team were able to get in and work with a number of businesses.
And one was the Caravan Park in Ngambi and help them with materials to get the Caravan
Park rebuilt.
So they were backing us, right?
They were buying products from us.
So one way to sort of support a community that's doing it tough is actually to go take
a whole lot of rooms, go out a few nights into some amazing local restaurants and demonstrate
to suppliers that when we're backed, we back you in return.
It's a nice message.
And without a doubt, it's a beautiful part of the world.
I know.
It's stunning.
And Ngambi really well, actually.
Her daughter is a rower and beautiful.
Mitchell and Rhinery, I think, is down that part of the world.
Yeah, we had a night there.
It was fantastic.
Great part of the world.
So go and visit there.
And I love that.
It's great, isn't it?
And I meant that sincerely, isn't it?
If you, you know, values are only worth it if you live them, aren't they?
And you do go back.
And I'm sure that message goes back to the community in a really powerful way.
And speaking of community, we hear that a lot.
In fact, let me go one step back.
Because I was about to ask you, I was thinking as you were talking about 53,000 staff at
Bunnings.
Jeff Harris, who's one of the founders of Flight Centre on this podcast, talked about
doing anthropological studies around size of teams.
And they worked out in their Flight Centre stores, bigger teams weren't more profitable
or more happy or more successful.
And they were really sophisticated about teams of six or eight and then bigger pods.
Have you got a system like that?
Yeah, we're very tribal in our mentality.
So, you know, every store has got its own unique vision and values.
And he's measured against that, you know, once a year.
And, you know, we work.
It's very hard to make sure that the layers or the spans are as simple as they can be
so that we don't have big teams.
But also making sure that even as we get scale, we stay really close to the front line.
And it's a relationship-driven business.
You know, at 18 years into the company, I'm almost feeling like I'm off probation.
There's plenty of team around me with 20, 25, 30, all the way through to 60 years of
service.
Or actually, longest serving team member hit 64 years this month, which is just a remarkable
achievement.
Right.
And I think if people...
If people put down roots and grow and they stay together, then building culture works
because you've got a lot of integrity and you've got a lot of respect from that shared
experience.
And those ingredients are the foundations of a team.
And if you get great teams, then they're going to win and we can celebrate that.
And I've read my preparation for this that, you know, you've been in a store and a customer's
wandering around, looks like they need help and you've jumped in and cut some carpet before
and got on the tools.
I'm not great at all the things.
I'm a bit like you when it comes to handyman.
I'm very lucky that...
One of my kids is a chippy, so he normally bails me out of anything that I stuff up.
But I think it is important.
We have an activity we call Hammer Time, which is actually when we all go out and spend time
working in our stores alongside our teams.
And you're always looking to learn because at the end of the day, we should be able to
do all the different things that our team do to the best of our abilities.
And part of it's role modelling, but actually part of it's because we genuinely care for
the customers that we're lucky to serve.
And you talk about a community at Bunnings and the way your values are shared across
the organisation.
Have you got some examples around how you do that?
Why that works so well for you?
I think the thing we've always worked hard to do is have a very local approach.
So every one of our warehouses, our larger format stores, has a dedicated activities
organiser.
So they have a full-time resource purely focused on community.
And we've got a very strong skew to children, junior sport and older people, people in the
retired space.
So men's sheds.
Often people coming in.
Some nursing homes or retirement villages to do things.
But the idea is to sort of, to the best extent we can, make the store a hub for the community
so that community know they can use the Bunnings environment for doing activities or raising
money.
But we also go out into the community and we'll give makeovers to, you know, so coming
up to Anzac Day or Remembrance Day, often you'll find Bunnings teams around a war memorial
or an RSL club doing things because we know that putting back is a really important element
to what makes the business.
It's a really important element to what makes the business successful, but it's because
it's the right thing to do.
You know, ultimately we live, work and raise our families in the communities in which we
work and we want to be seen as strong members of that.
And I think that that's continued to grow over time.
And we don't, we deliberately don't speak to it.
We don't advertise it.
Once a year we put out a community report card, which is a very high level summary of
what's been done.
But we get the feel good factor from just doing the right thing and knowing that we've
done the right thing is a reward enough.
And I'm always a little bit bemused when I look at businesses that spend a lot of money,
a lot of money advertising the good work they've done.
I always scratch my head and think, just put that money back into doing good work and the
dollar will go further.
And Mike, you know, you listen to this story and I'm always conscious around people will
be saying, well, you know, what a brilliant success and you turn up and another $18 billion
rolls through the gate next year.
But yeah, you've had some failures as well.
Bunnings tried to take on the UK back in 2016, paid 340 million pounds for a chain of 265
hardware stores.
12 in Ireland as well.
And a short time later that hadn't succeeded.
I think you ended up selling out for effectively a dollar.
How humbling was that experience?
Oh, incredibly humbling.
And, you know, I know having been involved in the second of the two years we were with
the UK business, just how humbling it was standing in a room in Milton Keynes in the
north of England, talking to a room full of people and saying, you know, effectively we've
let you down.
We've sold the business where we're going back to Australia.
I think.
Ultimately, what you never want to be in a situation of is, is getting too far in front
of yourself.
And I think sometimes as teams, when you're winning all the time, you can forget a little
bit about what helped you win, but you've also got to understand the fundamentals of
the type of business you're operating.
And, you know, for Bunnings in 2016, you know, we'd had 20, 25 years of unparalleled success.
We'd been very strong in both the Australian and New Zealand market.
We had turnaround experience in our early days.
So, you know, Bunnings bought McEwen's in 1993.
We bought Harbour House in 2001, and both of those were a Royal Wheelock because I wasn't,
I wasn't there for those, but we demonstrated a capacity.
But come 2016, we'd been running a high performing, very successful business and bought an asset
that was fundamentally a turnaround, which is a different set of skills.
So the way I sort of liken it when I talk to our team at Bunnings is, you know, we sort
of took a, took a footy team and sent them to play basketball.
And, you know, it's really hard to do that if you don't have the fundamental skills that
you need.
And that wasn't the best asset in the world.
But with the benefit of hindsight and the market was a bit more challenging and it evolved
in some different ways.
I do think if we'd, we'd stuck with it over the longterm, it might've given us some different
outcomes.
But for me, looking at what we have here and the growth opportunities across Australia
and New Zealand, exiting UK was absolutely the right call, the right call for our shareholder,
the right call for the team there and the team here, and also our suppliers and, you
know, Damien and the team that run Homebase today do a great job of running that business.
And, you know, we've been able to sort of.
We've come back here, get really clear on where we see growth in our B2B business, in
our online business, in some new categories, and really go hard after that and work hard
to offer Australians and New Zealand's the very best in home improvement products.
Would you do it again?
Would you go overseas and take on another opportunity?
I think if the opportunity was right, you'd definitely look at it.
I think it is a challenging market.
We're very close to all of our global peers.
So whether it's Home Depot or Lowe's in the United States or Canada, Sodomac in South
America, Hornbach or B&Q.
In Europe and the UK, we understand those businesses and they are very competitive markets.
What we see in Australia and New Zealand is a really strong runway for growth.
So when you're owned by a company with the disciplines of West Farmers, where, you know,
satisfactory returns to shareholder is the mission of the business, we can see a way
to do that very successfully for many years to come here in the domestic market.
Did the Bunnings message not translate to the UK?
Is that too simple a way to think about it?
It certainly did.
We converted.
We forced stores to Bunnings actually in the UK by the time we left and it was resonating.
What the challenge was that we faced was that the underlying business, the home-based business
was what we would call a very soft DIY space.
So for our listeners here, it's imagining, you know, where Bunnings meets a Freedom Furniture
or something like that, where you've got a lot of softer furnishings and homewares products.
And Bunnings is more of a true DIY player, you know, true home improvement player with
power tools and timber and green life and those sorts of things.
And, you know, customers would come into Bunnings, they liked what they saw, but they were really
yearning for what they'd had, which was more of the home-based model.
And interestingly, the success of home-based today has been going back to doing what they
were doing before, just doing it, doing it better.
And I think those competencies and skill sets are really important learning.
I work really hard to make sure that inside Bunnings today, we never forget that experience
because it is a reminder that you can go out and give it a hundred percent and still get
a thumping and that keeps you on your toes and keeps you hungry for better performance
in the future.
Well, it looks like you live a really full life.
You see you contributing in a range of different areas.
What does success mean to you?
I think success is leaving positive legacies.
You know, I didn't come to Bunnings in 2005 to be the managing director and I like to
get involved in things outside of work.
I think we've all got unique skills.
I like to jump on a barbecue.
I've done plenty of them as my kids came up through junior sport.
I've done scouts and those sorts of things.
So I think being hands-on where it makes sense is important.
But equally, if I can lend networks and skills to raising money, whether it's for research
into MND or support for mental health or any of those things, I think that's what is incumbent
on us to sort of pay forward really the opportunities we've been given.
And I like being busy.
It certainly is a very fulfilling way to get about and live your life.
How do you manage your time?
It's a lot of competing, running a business.
So that scale and, you know, chair a fine MND, a great cause, contribute, see the basketball
as a board member of Melbourne United.
It's a full life.
Do you get the balance right?
Depends who you ask, probably.
I don't think so, but I think that's okay if you're happy with that.
You know, and I think ultimately what I'm really fortunate to be able to do with the
flexibility of my role and the other opportunities I have is live what I'd call a very integrated
life.
So, you know, I can be doing something on a Saturday or Sunday.
That's very Bunnings focused and it might be a Tuesday afternoon doing something with
vitamin D.
And I think as long as you sort of, you know, delivering the outcomes that are there and
you apply yourself in the right way, then you can, you can get things done.
And, you know, to be very fair, I stand on the shoulders of thousands of other people
who do really great work every day and supporting them and coordinating things for them or getting
issues out of the way.
That's really what I'm about.
And if I can do that and, um, and balance it, then I'm having fun.
And that's a great way to be.
Might we say success leaves clues.
And in the leader world, we're seeing different leaders in different areas and fascinated
around the patterns of leadership that we've identified that we think are consistent.
So I want to ask you a range of questions along those lines.
The idea of self-leadership for us is where it starts.
It's hard to lead 53,000 people unless you know yourself well, what does self-leadership
mean to you?
For me, it's very much, you know, a little bit about what we touched on before, which
is a sense of purpose.
So for me, it's about creating environments in which other people can be successful.
I think earlier in my career, it was, you know,
probably more of a sort of a personally driven, you know, I want to see positive change.
And I think as you, you get into a position where you do have a lot of responsibility,
empowering others to do that and holding them to account is important.
And I think you've got to have the self-discipline to, to be able to show that you're putting
in the hours and doing the work.
And that's not just doing the actual work.
It's doing the training to get you ready, whether it's your, your physical health or
your mental health, um, your family health, all those things are important.
And, you know, along the way over the years, I've hit my 50s.
Fair share of speed bumps when it's come to, uh, family or, or work, not everything
is, is plain sailing for any of us in our lives.
And I think, um, learning from that, sharing those experiences, uh, helps keep you real
and, and helps people understand what you're about.
Mike, we see leaders are really conscious around on a daily basis, positively impacting
others in their environment.
I, I suspect you get a chance to do that regularly with the scale of, of your work.
Do you give that thought about that positive impact on a daily basis, how you go about
it?
Yeah, I think, you know, a team teller.
It's very clearly reward and recognition is really important.
And just something as simple as saying, thank you, recognizing people, popping a comment
on someone's post on our internal social media feeds.
Um, you know, when we were in Sydney last week, I had the privilege of presenting a
20 and a 25 year service award, uh, at one of our Sydney stores, you know, those things
are always fantastic.
And, you know, we do what we do because other people have done good things for us.
Right.
And, um, you know, all of us in our careers, if we're successful, can look back at the
people who've helped us.
So that mindset of helpfulness, which leads into reward and recognition is something that
is very important to me.
Yeah.
It's interesting, isn't it?
Those little celebrations are a free hit sometimes, but often overlooked, isn't it?
When the.
Often it's the little things that are actually bigger than the big ones.
It's the thank you.
It's someone just knowing that, you know, they put in an extra bit of effort somewhere
can mean a lot more than making a big deal of someone in a, in a group.
Yeah.
Which I find fascinating at the scale of people that are potentially in contact with you as,
as the head of Bunnings and 53,000 people, you know, it's a, it's a clear vision Bunnings
has got.
And as you said, you've built on the back of it, but how do you go about creating and
sharing that people are constantly coming into that environment?
What are the techniques you use around that, that vision and keeping it real?
Yeah, it's so important.
And, you know, certainly has been tested at different points in time.
Our business grew really significantly during the pandemic years when we were all spending
lots of time at home.
And that meant we recruited a lot of people.
And, you know, I'd be.
Better say we, we did see a dilution of culture because we had such a, a rapid growth.
So we've gone back to a lot of the basics around how we, uh, induct our team, you know,
all of our leaders go through a very consistent leadership experience, uh, leadership development
programs.
We're very fussy about the people we recruit, you know, often joke that having a heartbeat
alone, isn't a reason to get a job at Bunnings.
We want people that want to work with teams.
We want to get people who want to engage with customers are really fortunate that, you know,
over 25% of our workforce raged over 50, they come with a lot of life experience and a lot
of skill.
And, um, you know, that gives you a really strong blended outcome, uh, you know, in terms
of workforce, but it's also making sure that we're actively engaging and listening.
So we're running engagement surveys and those vision and value surveys I touched on earlier.
They're really important because if we're not hearing what the team is saying, then
we're not well equipped to show we've got the processes and the policies and the activities
in place to, to meet their needs and make sure that they see Bunnings as a, as a place
to build a great career.
It's a great contribution.
The elderly work.
And, you know, 50 suddenly elderly isn't, I used to, I used to, I used to sort of have
a little grin on my face when I was under 50, that happened a couple of years ago.
So I'm now part of the, the sort of 26 or 27% of our team.
But, um, you do get so much experience from, you know, having lived life a little bit and,
you know, participated in different activities, whether it's raising a family or doing other
things, uh, professionally, and you can just see the confidence that they bring into, into
the business.
Is that strategic to Bunnings that you actively try and pursue the overview?
50 workforce, or is it just the nature of the business?
It's a little bit of both.
I think we're very, we're very mindful of it and we see the value.
You know, I'm always, um, sad when I, when I talk to someone who's, you know, a little
bit older and maybe he's gone through a redundancy or a change in their career and they can't
find a, a place to start over.
You know, we've got a team with 20, 25 year service who joined us at 50, right.
And they're in their seventies now and they're, they're loving it, but we see the value.
And I think we are a natural home.
If you're a, you know, a chippy or a plumber or a spark, you're a builder and your body
gets a bit sort of.
Broken down or you've run your business successfully, but you don't want to be at home full time.
Uh, then, you know, Bunnings offers a really great place to, to do a bit of work and, you
know, probably share the experiences that you had, you know, in your trade with, with
other people.
We see curiosity as a, as a common thread for the leaders we, we talk to and through
that curiosity, they're, they're constantly learning and wanting to be better.
Is that something that resonates with you?
Oh, without a doubt.
You know, I think putting a sort of a retailer's hat on first, you know, we're very
fortunate to live in a, in a great country here in Australia and you see all the challenges
around the world that that's a constant reminder of that, but we're also a long way from
anywhere else and very easy to believe that, you know, we, we do things, um, the best,
you know, every year we're out with our suppliers in factories, in other retail stores, you
know, I've been to pretty much every continent this year.
Um, we don't have any home improvement stores in, in, um, in the Antarctic region.
So I didn't go there, but pretty much everywhere else, because we are always looking to learn
and we are very curious.
And I think, you know, when you've got a.
A mindset of being the best you can be, um, constant improvement comes from constant learning
and constant learning doesn't happen unless you've got that inherent interest in, in what's
going on around you.
Who's the best retailer in the world?
Oh, I think Walmart or Home Depot are probably the two, um, that are head and shoulders.
And I had the privilege this year of going to both their head offices, Walmart in, in
Bentonville and, and Home Depot in Atlanta and their office in, in Toronto as well.
And, you know, their scale, you know, you talked about Bunnings at 18 billion.
I think Walmart's 660 billion and Home Depot is about 160.
70 billion.
So, you know, there's lots to learn from those businesses and scale gives you some challenges,
but it gives you huge advantages and their investments into technology and data and those
sorts of things has been profound.
Are they up for sharing?
Yeah, pretty much.
Um, you know, we've got good relationships with them.
We've worked hard over the years to not only take ideas from, from these businesses, but
also share ideas back when we were with, uh, the West Farmers Board in, in Toronto earlier
this year, we were walking a store with my counterpart from Home Depot Canada, and we
were talking about a number of different things and he was able to show our board the things
that he'd learned from the relationship with Bunnings, just like we could show them the
things that we'd learned.
And I think when you're not competing, that, that creates a great environment and that's
probably one of the reasons why, you know, we haven't actively looked at other markets
as well.
We actually value the relationships that we've got and we get as much from that as, um, as
anything else.
How, um, have you gone about communicating with clarity in a business like yours?
What sort of processes you put in place to get that right?
Well, it's, it's about the simplicity of the language.
You know, when you've got a workforce our size, the reality is we're going to have people
that can't read and write.
We're going to have people where English isn't, isn't a first language, uh, and, and all the
different challenges that come with learning difficulties and those sorts of things.
So, you know, when we, we talk about our stores, we want, we would just say we want them to
look full clean and tidy.
It's a pretty simple, uh, mindset.
You know, we talk about, um, you know, safety.
We talk about everyone going home, you know, in the same condition they, they came in in
the morning.
We, we'd like to use very simple language.
We want, don't want to get ahead of ourselves.
We take what we do very, very seriously in terms of the work that happens at Bunnings,
but we don't take ourselves, uh, very seriously.
And I think if you can keep the language simple, people get engaged, we encourage questions
to be asked.
We, we share best practice then, um, you know, everyone can buy in.
And if you've bought in then, you know, staying focused on, on what your mission is, is a
little bit easier.
You mentioned some of the collaboration before traveling the world and Walmart and Home Depot
and, and, and learning from, from others.
How important has collaboration been to you?
To your success?
Look, I, you know, when you're, when you're almost an accidental retailer, we talked about
the sort of start of my career, you know, a little while back and certainly, you know,
to some extent, you know, an accidental managing director, you know, as I said, it wasn't the
job I came to do.
And, um, I was really privileged to be given the opportunity.
I think in some ways I have one of the best corporate jobs in the country, just given,
given the brand and the fact that we're part of a great larger company in West Farmers.
We also then don't have to deal with as many of the external factors that other listed
retailer companies have to do.
Um, I think if you're in that position and that collaboration piece is just, is just critical,
right?
And, and making sure that you're learning from others is how you're going to be able
to get the job done because you certainly don't come prearmed with all the skills.
I had big shoes to fill in 2016 when I took over from my predecessor and, um, you suddenly
go from unconsciously incompetent to very consciously incompetent.
You go from not knowing what you don't know to knowing what you don't know.
And the only way you're going to get to have any semblance of credibility is to, is to
collaborate really hard so that you can bring the best of everyone's skills to the fore.
Unconsciously incompetent.
That's a fascinating term.
And I think, yeah, having that openness, isn't it?
You don't know what you don't know to step into a role, but, and that's what we love
about the idea that if collaboration isn't, if you're prepared to say that the answers
are there, aren't they?
If you're, if you're, you know, humble enough to look for them.
And people I've never been, I've never not been surprised at just how generous people
are if you ask for time.
Um, and I've always been very mindful.
If people ask time from me that I, I pay that forward.
Um, but if you're prepared to ask the questions, most people are very willing to jump in and
help you.
Um, but they're just waiting to be asked.
And I think if you've got the, the, the self-awareness to go, I'm not very good on that, and I need
to ask someone, I need to educate myself, then that can be really helpful.
And I think that's where leadership goes off a cliff where someone, you know, merges into
a leadership role.
You describe yourself as an accidental MD of a massive business.
And then you're scared to say.
You're scared to say, I don't know.
And so you push down a lot of things and suppress a lot of things and try and manage up.
And you know, that, that goes pear-shaped pretty quickly, doesn't it?
Very quickly.
And I think anyone who positions themselves as the smartest person in a room is setting
themselves up for failure because, uh, we've all met people like that and normally just
sit back and go, I'm just going to watch the car crash unfold because you've seen it play
out many times.
And, uh, the best leaders that I've ever worked for and, and worked around are the ones that
are looking for buy-in.
Yeah.
Looking for buy-in, looking for feedback, and more importantly, looking for challenge
because we don't have all the ideas and we don't have all the solutions.
I think of, uh, John Bertram, we're lucky enough to collaborate with John in our leader
world and he drops into the various collaborative groups that we're in and, and, you know, John
75, hall of fame, legend in his space, the most curious person I think I've ever met.
And he takes this, um, inside and he's, he shared this on the podcast.
Every room he walks into, I assume I know absolutely nothing.
And, and with someone with that amount of wisdom, it's a, it's a profound way to burn.
You can say, well, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
I don't think there's been anyone.
I think I've worked for lots of great leaders, you know, across, across the years.
Yeah.
My predecessor, John Gillum at Bunnings is absolutely fantastic.
You know, my very first store manager, Van Wilkinson back in the early nineties that are
in target and everyone gives you something, um, to build on.
And I always, you know, often get asked that question when I speak to some of our younger
leaders.
And, you know, I think, I think learning from leaders is a bit like going to a, you know,
a buffet, you take the bit, you, you, you load up on the bits you really like and you
avoid the bits you don't.
And equally, I've worked for leaders that I've learned a lot from, but it's actually
learning what I don't want to be.
Cause I understand the impact of, uh, behavior of language on how it's made me feel.
And I would never want other people to feel the way I felt in a moment.
And I think being aware of that is just as important as being like the, the people you
look up to in terms of the experiences that they've shared.
It's a great answer, Mike.
I haven't had anyone quite answered that way.
And it's true.
Often we sort of push away the people that are at a negative impact on it.
But if we stop and think sometimes, as you just mentioned, they're our greatest teachers,
aren't they?
Because I don't want to reflect that behavior on someone else.
And you can learn just as much along the way.
We are obsessed with collaboration in our world.
And I think it sounds like you are too, and flying around the world.
Is there been one particular pair you probably mentioned already with, with Walmart or have
you gone, that's, I'd love to spend an hour with that person to collaborate and in any
part of your passions.
And you've got me.
I've been spending a bit of time in the last couple of months with a gentleman by the name
of Frank Blake and Frank is the former president and CEO of Home Depot.
So Ted Decker is the, is the current president and CEO.
And Frank was one of his predecessors.
And when you've been there and done it in the industry in which we work and to have
the insights that he's had, I've certainly learned a lot from him and a lot of just
leadership.
You know, one of the things you share with me is that when you're in a CEO or MD role,
you know, to some extent you're the frog in the pot that the organization boils.
And I'd never really thought about, you know, leadership through the lens of once people
get to know you, they work out a little bit of what you like things to be like, or don't
like things to be like, and, you know, over time things tend to sort of migrate to a way
where they, they operate in a way that can almost serve the, serve the leader.
And, you know, how do you sort of step back from that and go, I don't want to be unpredictable
consistency.
It is really important in leadership, but I also don't want to be managed in a, in a
sense of being handled or anything like that.
I want to be able to roll my sleeves up, be a part of the team, get involved in conversations.
And, you know, so you're constantly looking to sort of shape and evolve.
So I think when you can meet people with such wisdom, then, you know, you can just learn
so much from them and take that on board and think about ways that they've engaged.
And if you're really lucky, and I've very much been the case with Frank, they'll also
tell you the things that didn't work.
So the things to look out for, or the early warning.
Warning signs that something might go wrong.
And I think they're always very useful as well.
I've certainly learned a lot this morning, sitting down with you.
I really appreciate you and an incredibly busy schedule, taking some time to share your
wisdom and you can see the passion and the clarity.
And as you described, maybe the great corporate job in Australia.
We all love Bunnings.
And I think it's no small part because of your leadership.
So I really appreciate your time.
Thanks so much, Luke.
Really enjoyed spending time with you as well.
Thank you for listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Powered by Temper, a mattress like no other.
And to make sure you don't miss an episode, click subscribe wherever you get your podcasts.