This week's guest on the Empowering Leaders podcast is broadcasting legend, multi-award winning radio presenter and comedian Michael Whipper-Whipfley.
Whipper is a great champion of using his platform and microphone for good.
And in most recent times, the 36-month campaign to increase the age when children are legally able to use social media from 13 to 16.
Whipper talks with me about his own battle with severe mental health that gave him an insight into the despair that he feels kids are facing when they're online.
The importance of giving those 36 months from 13 to 16 back to our children while their brains develop.
And how his own nine-year-old is already talking about wanting to use Snapchat.
The alarming impact social media is having on education.
And Whipper throws down a challenge to the Prime Minister, who he's already had in his studio.
And the opposition leader, Peter Dutton.
To make the decision now to stop allowing harm to children the same way that we did with seatbelt laws back in the day.
It's people like Whipper who inspire the work we do at Alita.
Love you to have a look at alitacollective.com, our website.
Check out our signature program, Alita Connect, where we bring together and curate groups of leaders from around the globe of five to six people.
Book a discovery call today.
We'd love to have you join our Alita community.
Huge thanks to Jason Nicholas and his team from Temper Bedding.
A great leader.
Understand the importance of sleep.
And Temper is a mattress like no other.
NASA approved.
It's the world's best in bedding.
Have a look at Temper today.
Michael Whipper Whipfley is a multi-award winning radio presenter and comedian who has used his microphone for good over many years.
Supporting and raising thousands of dollars for youth-related charities across Australia, including Ronald McDonald House, Little Wings Flight Service, Cooper Rich Braiding Foundation for sarcoma research,
and BATTA for youth mental health.
To name a few.
Whipper has launched a campaign to change legislation to increase the age when children are legally able to use social media from 13 to 16.
He partnered with Finch CEO Rob Galuzzo to create the initiative 36 Months.
And he's using the platform of his radio show, which has already seen the campaign receive verbal support from the New South Wales Premier Chris Minns and the Prime Minister Anthony Albanese.
Whipper, I've been a great admirer and fan of yours for a long period of time.
Congratulations on all that you're doing.
Thanks, Duff.
We're having a swing, mate.
I mean, there's no other way to do it.
You've done a lot of breakfast shows as well, so a lot of years behind the microphone.
So you do have moments between sort of running competitions like Beat the Bomb and The Fugitive and giving away Taylor Swift tickets where you think, hang on a minute, this thing talks to all these people.
What can we do with it?
What should we be doing with this thing outside of what's your favourite Chinese dish and should there be pineapple on pizza?
You've done them all, Duff.
You've done them all.
I want to say 1-3-3-3-5-3.
Give us a call when you said, oh, I've got a bit of muscle memory back, Whipper.
But in fairness to you, mate, not everyone thinks the way you do.
People think this is a great gig.
You get paid well.
You and Fitzy, you know, you work with great people and Kate Ritchie's joined your show and you get free stuff and you're home three hours later and life's good.
Not everyone's got a social conscience like you.
Has that always been?
Has it always been part of the way you've been or is it something you felt the responsibility of?
Great question because I do think about this a little bit.
And I think, as you know, in this job and when you're in the media or any level of celebrity, I suppose, you kind of become the more your profile grows, the more demand there is for you to be involved in different things, different organisations, be it a charity or a favour to help out or emceeing an event to raise money.
And you kind of, I suppose, you're exposed to more things, you're exposed to more stories, you're exposed to the organisations that might need a little bit of help.
And when you seize and hear about some things that go on, I think it comes with the charity as well and becoming a parent, you sit back and think, well, what can I do?
Because that doesn't seem right.
So how can I get involved?
And I think as we all grow up, we sort of seek more in our life than just the output of what we do on a daily basis.
It's that question of what?
What else can we do?
When you think about the audience that we have out there and then you look at some of the things that go on and at the same time, Darcy, you'd know through radio, you're very lucky to meet a lot of people and your circle widens very quickly.
You would have known that through footy as well.
So all of a sudden you've got this handful of great people that are in powerful positions or with great profile and then you stumble across a need that desires and requires a change.
And you think, hang on, I've got all these pieces.
If I bought them all in, we might be able to do something really special here.
I think that's what we've landed on here.
And again, I've got so much admiration for you, Whipper.
Not many people can get the prime minister to come into their studio and the premier of your state and then actually launch a campaign.
And is this in part, I mean, you've been really open yourself about having some mental health struggles and reading more of that.
I didn't quite understand the gravitas.
I think you've shared that almost to the point staring at a balcony and looking at potentially ending it.
Has that driven this purpose for you around wanting to make a difference, given the nature of how bad the issues with social media are?
Can you share with us a bit of your background and what got you to that point?
Yeah, I mean, I was doing it tough and I think it was a process of growing up.
There'd been sort of a trigger pulled through personal life, which sort of sent me spiralling.
But I got to a point where it was extremely scary to be there.
And I think you kind of dip your toe in that.
And when you realise we...
When you're out at that moment in time, if you're lucky enough to come back and, you know, hopefully you've got a good team around you, if you find yourself in that position.
And there's obviously a lot of services you can call if you do find yourself there.
But I think that plays a part in it because I think about other people that might be in that situation where they think, you know, what would it be easier if I'm not here?
Well, there's a hell of a lot of people around you saying that's the wrong way of thinking.
That's where you've ended up.
But you need it and you want it and you're loved.
So you must be here.
So when I think about people that possibly...
And through a lot of adolescent brains and social media influence, kids are finding themselves in that position.
And, you know, I'm not dramatic by saying kids are killing themselves because that can be the result.
So it does make me very, very aware and I'm very conscious of the mindset some of those kids might find themselves in.
And that scares me like it scared me back in the day.
And with Birgit.
I use admiration because, you know, you're maybe a generation slightly behind me, but we weren't necessarily courageous enough to share those things the way that you have done so openly.
And that allows when you see Whipper, he's got this great life and he's living the rock star life and he's funny and everything's going great to say, hey, I could get to that place.
And it doesn't discriminate for you to be able to use your profile again to courageously share that.
Was that a hard thing to do or did it take you a while to get there?
Yeah, it did.
It took me a long time, to be honest, because I think you're always once you've had sort of that experience and you've found yourself pretty low, you're always processing it.
I think you're always looking back on it and trying to understand how you ended up there.
But at the same time, you're looking for education.
So you know that if you found yourself heading down that path again, what sort of things can you do?
And I've had moments since then where I've started to feel like that.
And I bring in a routine which helps pull me out of that.
It's not always going to be the solution for every position that I find myself in or for other people.
But it's going back to basics.
It's exercise every day.
Exercise is unbelievable.
And you don't need to be doing some sort of preseason workout.
You can just go for a walk, get off the grog, plenty of water and just get the basics right.
And consider all the little things that you've done that day, which are the basics.
To be big wins, they're success stories in your day.
So the fact that you managed to get yourself out of bed and have a shower that day and maybe you didn't the day before, that is a win.
Write that down as a successful move.
And each day it's like lying, it was described to me once like lying in water, where every now and then you lift your head out of the water and you take a breath and you go back down.
And then the next day you take two breaths out of the water and all of a sudden you don't want to be in the water anymore and you can pull yourself out of that.
And I encourage anybody that might find themselves in that position.
Just to get back to the basics.
Make sure you walk, water, sleep, do the basics.
That advice, Whipper, isn't it?
I think anyone, it's a spectrum, isn't it, for all of us around having some degree of mental health.
It's a continuum, isn't it?
And all of us, someone said to me once, you know, you go and take a truckload of drugs, don't sleep for three and a half days, and then you're a chance to be almost at the end.
Life is this thin wedge.
And we're all dancing on the edge of it.
As you said, you get up, you do your morning routine, you exercise, you drink water, you eat.
You feel bulletproof, but you can let that go without even understanding it, can't you?
And suddenly you feel yourself.
It slides really quickly.
Amazing, isn't it?
Yeah, but you know what?
The other part of me coming out and talking about it too was when I saw more and more people, the reaction I would get, I mean, to see Paul Gallen come out and talk about his battle.
And I thought, Paul Gallen, that guy's tough as nails.
You know, there's no weakness in talking about that.
So every time I would see somebody that I admired or looked up to, a professional in the field talk about it, I suppose I reacted by how it made me feel.
And me telling my story is the hope that I could get that reaction from somebody else that might be listening that possibly enjoys the radio show.
And we're in the midst of what is irrefutably a mental health crisis.
And now it's irrefutably linked to the perils of social media for our youth.
Yeah.
Unbelievable spikes in eating disorders, particularly in young teenage girls.
Some of the stats are horrific.
Anxiety, depression, self-harm and suicide in Australia and around the globe are at record levels.
The link is directly to the algorithms that our kids look at on their phones, the unrealistic imagery that's there.
How big a problem is it from the work that you've done to research it?
You know, I was talking to a dad last night and the plan was to get him on the radio show.
And we didn't because it just didn't work.
Because it just didn't feel right.
Because it was just, it was far too, far too confronting what he's had to go through.
He lost his daughter through the online bullying he received through one of the social media platforms.
And he said he lives every day now as if he is numb.
He says he has a son.
So he said, I have something to live for.
But at the same time, I'm completely numb and there is nothing that brings him happiness.
I mean, that's from the dad's point.
What scares me even more is to think of the mindset and the feeling that his daughter must have had and how long it went on for and how long it took for her to come to a point where she felt she was in a situation where there was no way back.
And since putting my hand up, and as I've said, Darsen, why I'm so grateful for coming on the show, like you, I'm saying we've got a problem here, guys.
So I'm representing the parents and the teachers.
I'm representing anybody that thinks this simply.
It doesn't make sense.
Imagine if there was another product out there, Darsen, call it a bloody shampoo.
And one out of two kids that used the shampoo ended up with some sort of psychological impact, anxiety or depression.
But in extreme cases, if you kept using the shampoo, you could end up dead.
Well, that product wouldn't be on the store for more than five seconds.
That would be gone.
And that's what we're dealing with.
And nobody is putting a stop to it.
And I just don't.
I don't understand it.
And, you know, from a parent's point of view, Darsen, with three kids, as you know, you want to be able to parent.
And the parents are being stripped of having any impact or involvement or being able to advise or even prepare and arm their kids with any skills because the greatest influence is coming from some smart algorithm.
It's crazy, isn't it?
I mean, the data's next level.
70% of teens have had a negative experience online in the last week.
One in three have been exposed.
Two disturbing or traumatic content.
One in four have been cyber bullied or sexually harassed in social media.
You've really drilled into something that seems like a no-brainer, doesn't it?
Raising the age limit.
It's not a hard thing from 13 to 16.
So the campaign's called 36 Months.
Can you tell us why you're focused in on that and why those 36 months count so much?
I'm not trying to stop Instagram.
I'm saying that the impact on adolescent brains between 13...
...and 16, or even younger if we can, but my understanding of the platform as far as the law goes here in Australia, and it's a law that's sort of extended from America under their Parental Act from 1998, says that if you're 13, you can land on one of these platforms.
So, yes, the 36 months is that adolescent brain period of development.
And, you know, if I had it my way, it'd be 18.
But, you know, that might be a stretch too far.
So the other thing with the 36 months is...
You've got to think, if we can give that back to the kids and families can reconnect, imagine the teaching and the skills we can put in place over those three years, three crucial years, so when a kid reaches the age of 16 and decides they want to be on social media, that they have the skills to handle what might be thrown at them.
So the curriculum around what can be built in to the 36 months is exciting to think about.
You know, you can come back to the family.
You know, one of the taglines we've been using, Darcy, is...
You know, 36 months to get to know yourself before the rest of the world does.
You know, who knows who they are at the age of 13?
It's madness.
It's insane, isn't it?
You know, as a father of four, it's the biggest issue that you think about every day.
And I'm sure you're in that same bracket of just this new territory that no one really understood previously.
But now you understand what these platforms are doing.
There's a great book.
Johan Hari wrote a book about stolen folk.
And, you know, at the extreme end, we're losing kids to suicide.
And that's happening daily.
And the eating disorder crisis is out of control and the mental health and the anxiety.
But just from an ability to actually think and evolve and be a better person, we're all subjected to these 20-second clips of our life that are reducing us to sort of, you know, domesticated cats almost in our ability to focus.
How do you think about it as your kids are growing up?
It's the fight I have every day.
I had it this morning with a toy.
They get up, they exercise.
They're pretty competitive.
It's like, boys, off the phones.
We're not allowed to have them in the mornings.
At nighttime, we'll get them in a separate room.
That room's locked.
It's a full-time job.
As you said, we're fighting against the legislation.
You're trying to help at the legislative point of view.
But as a parent, how do you think about it?
I mean, Ted's nine years old, my oldest, and he's already talking about Snapchat.
And as a parent also, they are in a position where they continue to find themselves powerless.
And a lot of the feedback is, it's the bloody parents' fault.
They should be able to do something.
Well, they don't because they don't want to create social isolation for their kid at school
who comes home and says, everybody else is on it.
Everybody else is doing it.
You know, that's so the problem we have is the pressure on the kid to join it because everybody else is doing it.
And then the pressure on the parent who wants to try and be a parent that's encouraging of their kid for whatever everybody else is doing.
So we can remove that pressure from the kid and we can remove it from the parent as well.
I think in a situation like that.
And looking at the laws that they have last night, my understanding is it goes through at the moment,
if you talk about the age of 13 on some of the platforms that we have through our e-safety commissioner,
we have a way where the social media platform can be fined if we were to dob in somebody under the age of 13.
You can go down that path.
So I think if we were able to change the law, I think the platforms would evolve accordingly
because these fines could be racked up.
But very quickly, if they were to be enforced, they already exist.
They just need adjusting.
So that's one thing we could do.
If it's the fact that someone listens to this podcast does and it opens their eyes and ears to what the effects of what social media are,
that's a win as well.
So there's many layers of how we can win here.
But having this conversation is such a big part of it.
And when you look at the states, you know, state by state, and they're very different laws over there in the US
because there's different privacy acts, but there's also the freedom of speech.
All this sort of stuff.
They talk about the addictive features of social media,
the different features that are made to keep you on there for as long as possible.
The infinite scroll, the likes, the shares.
I mean, the guy I spoke to who lost his daughter,
to think that she's on that platform effectively ranking herself socially
and then she goes to bed feeling as a failure,
wakes up to see what the impact of maybe her post has had,
so starts her day feeling as a failure.
Yeah.
And then goes to school and it continues on and on.
So that's where we're at.
You know, if we could remove, and I think the fight in the US has been about these addictive features,
like the infinite scroll, if we can come down hard on that,
then there's some creative platforms which are great.
YouTube's an interesting one.
I mean, people have said, but what about YouTube and social media?
Well, it's described as a social media because it has social media,
but it's also described by YouTube as being a search engine
because there's so much content on there.
And there's young kids on there that are creating fantastic content
and little businesses and little entrepreneurs.
And to that I say, fantastic.
Do it with your mum or dad.
That's great.
They can set you up.
They can help you through your business.
Do it together.
We're not trying to stop that.
Whipper, I'd love to introduce you to a remarkable lady called Zoe Kalar.
You might have heard of WeAre8, which is a tech platform,
social media for good.
This is a brilliant story,
and we want to fill you with some positivity in this conversation today.
She's a serial success story in the tech entrepreneurial world.
She created an app that understood where the money goes.
Mark Zuckerberg takes $140 billion a year out of the advertising pool,
going to one person effective.
You can't – it's $10 billion every three weeks.
He could turn off those algorithms of hate in a nanosecond.
Billion.
Every three weeks.
Every three weeks, but won't do it because they want you on that platform longer,
and the more negative things are, our brains are wired to hard.
We continue to look at it, and they just pump as many ads in front of you as they can,
and that model needs to be disrupted.
And WeAre8 is being supported by some of the great athletes and investors around the world.
Pat Cummings and Rio Ferdinand are great champions of it, and it's zero hate.
It is the AI ability.
You can't be fake.
You've got to turn up as yourself, which really reduces the trolling by about 95%.
So there's hope, isn't there, Whipper, that we can include legislation like you're fighting for,
and then as a community, putting some of that money back into the hands of the users themselves
and to charity and to good rather than to some guy who wants to be a UFC fighter
building an island for $50 billion.
Doing whatever he's doing over there, Whipper, is a bit scary, isn't it?
Do you know the other scary thing to think about in this world where money talks is that,
you know, some people have said, well, you're not going to have an impact until it becomes a commercial thing, right?
Until it's money-based, then there's really not going to be any change.
Well, the other thing the government needs to think about,
and some of the teacher friends that I've spoken to in schools is they can't teach anymore
because their entire day is putting out fires that have been created via chat groups on social media.
So, therefore, teachers are leaving in their droves.
So, all of a sudden, now we have a commercial issue because teachers are already underpaid.
They're stressed.
And now they're unable to do their job.
So, what's the point?
So, you know, in one school in particular, they've had three or four teachers leave because of this.
And in an alarming alignment with that, at the same school,
there was 70% of the girls at the school had been involved in self-harm.
So, what the hell is going on here?
And you have to actually get your head around the numbers to reinforce that again.
The end of the lockdown period here in Melbourne, there were 600 new diagnoses a week in Melbourne alone,
600 a week of eating disorders of young girls.
So, the perfect storm of taking them out, training them onto their screens,
sitting on social media, new cases of eating disorders.
No one wants to talk about that is exactly what is happening.
And we know the devastation of that on families and where it leads to.
But I, as I said, I'm a fan of everything that you do and using your platform for good.
And I love these conversations because I see you as a great leadership story.
I've sat in that same chair before and you don't always have to use your platform for good,
but you do that in a great way.
And we love the saying, success leaves clues.
And every person who is a great leadership story, I love asking these handful of questions with us.
I'll fire them your way.
And we feel like it's hard to lead someone else unless you've got a sense of self-leadership yourself.
Does that resonate with you?
Yeah, it does.
It does.
But, you know, for a lot of it too, I think you've got to be brave.
I think you don't go out and say, I'm going to be successful.
Do you?
You don't go, oh, mate, I read this book and I tell you what, I've gone through the checklist.
Number one, come up with a social initiative.
Okay, here we go.
But there's part of you, I think you're just driven to do that.
I think you're driven when you see it and when you feel it and when you hear it.
So, but I would be absolutely honoured if someone was to look at what I'm doing and what we're attempting to do on behalf of everybody
and be inspired to do something similar themselves.
We see that people who do have an impact are really conscious of being positive
and impacting people in their environment in a positive way from a daily basis to what you're doing,
which is changing legislation at a national level.
Do you think about that impact every day of having a positive impact on others?
Do you know, sometimes I don't think about it every day, but sometimes you're beautifully reminded.
I mean, we were talking, I went to Officeworks the other day and a bloke pulled up behind me in a truck.
And he goes, oh, you're bloody.
You're a whipper, aren't you?
I'll get you confused for Mick Malloy.
And I went, oh, not the first time, mate.
And I love you on the back page.
I love you on bloody the front part.
I go, that's not me, mate.
Anyway, anyway, he's got 10 years on me.
And this guy said, I just want to let you know, I've been through a divorce recently.
And when I drive to work, I'm just, I'm beaten up.
I don't want to go to work.
I'm not interested in my relationships falling apart.
And then I find myself having a bit of a laugh with you and Fitzy.
And I think those are the moments where you're reminded of what you're doing, because you know what it's like.
You can sit in the studio and your heart rate doesn't lift.
You're so comfortable and you're enjoying yourself, but you kind of, you're lost in the moment.
But when someone stops you and just reminds you of what you're doing, but I've learned the hard way too, Darce.
I've said the wrong thing and have someone call me an idiot at the same time.
So it kind of goes both ways.
But now that I've kind of knocked a bit of the idiot out, I'm trying to smarten it up a little bit and hope that I can make
some positive change.
You're doing that in a profound way.
And it's a pretty big vision that you've got, isn't it?
To take the prime minister in your studio and say, we need to change this.
It's a serious vision.
We see people who do that have thought about the way they're going to share a vision of that scale.
Did you go into that?
How do you think about sharing this vision to change the legislation the way you have?
With the PM, right?
I reckon whether you're a Dutton fan or you're with Albanese, I think for both of them,
you've got a real opportunity here to become a true world leader where you can actually have a major change.
And I'll tell you what, this topic is hot in every country and slowly, state by state in the US, you see it and other states and other countries will pull the trigger.
But imagine being able to hang your hat on it.
I mean, and that's why I talk and I don't get me wrong, I'm being a bit cheeky and I'm shooting from the hip here when I say, if you made this an election promise, then you would win the vote of every Australian parent.
Now, maybe it's not.
I don't know.
I know, you know, whatever side I vote for, I would definitely jump on that ship if that was on the table out of concern for my kids.
The one thing you love more and care about more than anything else on this planet.
So I'm cheeky when I say that and I understand it.
But at the same time, I think they need a nudge and I think they can also see the opportunity.
So it's fantastic that Albo came out and said, I love that you're doing this.
We see the importance of this and then put some money into some research into tech.
And verification, which is great.
But you know what?
You can actually make that call.
You're the most powerful man in the country and you can pull the trigger on that.
So if we make enough noise, I mean, the prime minister works for us, does.
Does.
You realize that?
He works for us, you and me and anybody else listening.
So we need to remind him of what's important to us.
We're going to tell him what we need so he can lead and implement.
So we just need to remind him.
That's what he needs to do for us.
And I think you've thrown that challenge down nicely.
It's right when election cycles come around really quickly.
I think this is a thing that almost unites every parent.
No one thinks this is a good thing.
And we all need help because, as you said, if you're the only parent removing social
media from your kid, they are going to be the outlier.
We need, this is where governments can do good and do it easily and have no negative
effect.
There is no downside.
What advantage is there to giving a kid social media at 13?
There is no upside.
And we now know irrefutably we're actually harming and losing children as a result of
it.
So that doesn't make sense.
No, it just doesn't make any sense.
That's the other thing.
And I'm sure a lot of parents do.
They'd be going mad when they think, let's just, I mean, let's run the pub test over
this.
And I can't understand why we're okay with that.
And, you know, there was a great quote the other day that we will look back and think,
what were we doing?
What were we doing to our kids?
Did you know that back in the day, there weren't seatbelts in the car and you could
drink as much as you want and drive?
You're all kidding.
Who would do that?
They did.
I used to sit on my dad's lap and steer the wheel back in the day.
Johnny Whipfley used to get behind the wheel and he knew he was going straight because
he could feel the tram lines under the tyres.
Not that long ago, Whipper, is it?
I know.
And people don't understand it.
It was illegal to be gay.
No, I know.
What are you talking about?
Crazy.
So I feel like we have all this data that's been collected over the past 10 years or so.
And now we're in a position to be able to present it.
Let's not, let's not stretch this set of data required.
We don't need any more.
It's all on the table and it's all in front of us.
So let's not consider this trial period of what we're doing to kids to go any longer.
Challenge out there to Albo and to Peter Dutton.
Just make the legislation.
Modi banned TikTok last year.
Last week, literally just wiped it out of India with the sign of one bit of paper.
You can do it and it needs to happen.
You can do it.
Curiosity is a word that we see a lot with people we see as great leaders.
Are you naturally curious, Whipper?
Extremely curious.
I just want to understand things.
I want to be across it, whatever it might be.
I just, I like to make sense of things and I like to look into them too.
And quite often I find myself, the wife's gone to bed and I'm on the internet at night.
Don't let your mind run there too.
Nothing's okay there.
But I'm naturally intrigued by everything.
I think you need to be.
And I think that's all part of being hungry in life.
You know, how does that work and why does it do what it does?
I think that's part of the nature of it all coming together and making sense.
But knowing, and I think as you get older, you kind of realise pretty quickly you're not here for that long.
So part of being a good parent too is to grab as much as you can as far as education and wisdom that you can
and hand it.
Hand it on, hand it over and say, hey, look what I've collected for you because that was my job.
So naturally I try and through love of life and love of the kids, I'm curious.
I'm naturally very curious.
And we see people communicating with clarity as a real strength these days for people who do have, you know,
great achievement.
You communicate for a living.
It's a natural thing to you.
Is it something that you've thought about when you were trying to run a campaign like this?
I was nervous.
Because playing the village idiot, which is quite often the role on the show, I've done sort of 13 years
with Fitzy making fat jokes.
It's okay.
He couldn't make them if I didn't love him.
That's okay.
But you're right, putting your hand up and sort of having a crack at something different,
which is absolutely different for me to do.
Das, I mean, some of the stuff you do on radio is completely ridiculous.
This is off the page.
This is off topic, but you wouldn't believe it.
I quite recently wrote an erotic novel, Das, called The Far Too Personal Trainer.
Very, very erotic, completely off topic, but just using that.
Can we get that title again, please?
That just went through the cover.
The Far Too Personal Trainer.
Genius.
I love it.
The Far Too Personal Trainer.
But that is an element of curiosity because I thought, wouldn't it be wonderful to try and write a book?
What would that be like?
And do that?
What's the?
What's the thrill of that like?
But secondly, that's sort of a more natural place for me to play, to do something ridiculous like that.
So to put my big boy pants on and say, hey, enough of the erotic reading, guys.
Put that down.
Show me two hands in the air.
Let's talk about something serious.
And we probably love that.
That to me is life, isn't it?
That we all want to have fun and play the class clown, but most of us have got another element.
We actually can straighten up sometimes and go, hey,
this means a lot to me.
I'm prepared to be open like you've been in your life.
And I'm going to stand for something here.
And I've got these pieces of the jigsaw puzzle that are available to me that aren't available to everyone.
And I'm going to try and put them together and do something really special, which, again, I'm full of admiration.
Collaboration is something we talk about in this space as well.
I suppose you must have been able to pull on all threads of collaboration in this.
Well, the great thing was a mate of mine, Rob Galuzzo, who you mentioned earlier from Finch.
Finch is a production company.
But at the same time, you know, he's launched an initiative called the Lion's Share, which is about marketing.
If you use an animal in the marketing space at all, if it's a cabriette and there's a gorilla drumming,
well, then 0.5% of that marketing budget needs to go towards the conservation of that animal.
So he's had a lot of involvement in social movement, also in the education space.
But you're right.
When you look at those pieces that you can call on,
on the people you know, straight away, I thought ex-premier of New South Wales, Dom Perrottet,
now a backbencher, a bit of time on his hands.
And also, he's got seven children.
And I thought, if there's one person that's going to care about this topic, it'll be old mate Dom.
So we caught up for lunch and I told him of the idea.
And he said, you don't need to sell it to me.
I get it.
I've heard enough already.
I'm in 100%.
So he's been fantastic at making introductions.
You know, he still talks with the prime minister, also Peter Dutton,
a safety commissioner.
And he's also, he's done 10 years as a lawyer.
So he understands where the law sits on this.
So he's been instrumental in driving a lot of this and making the right phone calls to put the right team together.
Whipper, we love leadership stories.
Who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Oh, my God.
It's a good question.
It's a big question.
Naturally, you fall to your mum and dad, don't you?
Because you're made up of both of them.
And, you know, mum's sort of the funny side of things.
And dad has a giant heart and understands, I suppose, what a gentleman should be.
But he's also great with advice.
You know, he'll let you know when you're jumping your shadows and when to keep the powder dry and all these sorts of sayings that come with it.
So, you know, they're an inspiration.
But I think outside of that, business leaders as well.
Certainly not footballers.
I mean, if we talk about great footballers, we would obviously fall to sort of the Essendon Football Club, the likes of Danaher's.
You know, I saw a photo the other day, and it must have been the premiership winning team from maybe 93?
Paul Salmon.
The general was still there, Mark Harvey.
And it was just amazing to see that group of guys back together again.
And they have something special.
And I can tie that back in because at that moment in time, in that photo, they're able to look back and go, hey, we went together now because we did something back then.
And I think like every radio show, you get together at the end of the year and you look back on what you have achieved.
You know, you've got the power to make a really significant change.
That was the first grand final I went to with Michael Long.
I think I kicked the goal, the first goal with Steve Silvani on the line.
Baby bombers.
And I was a young 17-year-old Bulldog recruit sitting behind the goals.
And I was dreaming that they would recruit me the following year.
So a special place in my heart that year.
So the goal, were you sitting behind the goals that Michael Long kicked straight out of the centre there?
I was sitting directly behind it, sitting next to the great Tony McGuinness.
Yeah, yes.
And I was leaving Footscray to go back to Adelaide.
And they'd sort of had this crossover of a South Australian leaving the Bulldogs.
And it was such a great experience to sit next to him at a grand final and hear him talk me through it.
And there's no way Sauce touched that.
There's absolutely no way.
And I'm trying to, was it Alvin who tried to tackle Michael Long, Tommy Alvin, whatever his name was?
There were so many great moments.
What do you mean Tommy Alvin?
But it was the baby bombers, Smoke and Joe Mercedi.
It was just awesome.
Ricky Ollaranshaw.
David Cowthorne.
Yes, Cowthorne.
A couple of Johnsons maybe, or that could have been afterwards.
But it was an amazing time.
It was great.
Mark Mercurio.
It's all alumni of my era.
They were an amazing team.
And it was great.
Gavin Wanganame played in that grand final.
I remember seeing him stretch out once.
And he bent over and put his elbows on the ground.
And I thought, you really are the rubber man, aren't you, Gav?
I saw him the other night at the airport.
What a true gentleman.
How well has he aged, Gavin?
He looks like he can play now and does beautiful art, Gavin.
Yeah.
Going back to his culture.
And I remember he was a 16-year-old growing up in South Australia.
And he was just such a, and still is such a wonderful person.
This could be another hour.
And we could talk about you playing.
Playing first 18 footy in year 10.
Oh, you don't need to bring that up.
I've done my homework with that.
And I know that your reputation at Saskatchewan College in year 10
precedes you.
I mean, you would know not many kids play first footy in year 10.
So that's quite a significant bit of information you've just shared
with the listeners that does.
It's from Gavin Wanganame to Whipper playing for Scotch
was a perfect transition.
I thought it needed to be said.
The final question for me, in the work we do,
we're obsessed with this world of collaboration.
You're trying to achieve something that I think is in the interest
of all Australians and perhaps in other areas of your life.
You've got a great collaboration with Fitzy, who's just a gem.
And Kate Ritchie's got an incredible history of what she does.
Have you ever looked and thought, God, if I could collaborate
with that one person on this passion, a name springs to mind?
I mean, I think when it comes to collaboration and output,
you consider, if you try, I mean, for a lot of the initial stages,
I think, of any initiative or movement, it's about noise, isn't it?
And if you look at leaders who create a lot of noise,
you'd probably have to jump to somebody like Richard Branson,
you know, ageing but will never age.
You know, he still kitesurfs in the morning.
He still does ridiculous things.
I think I saw him jumping off a, I don't know,
some sort of platform the other day into the water, has his own island.
But when it comes to doing great things,
he knows how to.
He knows how to create a song and dance.
So I think everybody's stumbled over the book,
probably losing my virginity at some stage to hear about how he makes noise.
Because I think a lot of people, what I didn't realize too,
is a lot of people in business, they've had to be extremely creative
to get to where they are because that strategic mind of going,
well, this is going to create this reaction and to pull this off over here,
I need to make that work.
So that strategy required is extremely creative.
I think people sometimes miss that.
I think they consider a business leader to have a product that they've just steered
to the top very well.
But there's a hell of a lot more that goes on.
But Richard Branson, to see the way he continues to make noise
by not being so serious about it, I think that's part of his skill.
You know, there's that great story of him inviting all the CEOs
from different corporations around for a drink by the pool.
And one by one, he ran around pushing them in.
And he's in their suits.
Now, if he just did that to create a story to be told on this podcast,
that's brilliant.
Genius.
Outstanding.
So I do look up to people like that because they don't stop having a go.
You know, you've got to be brave to have a go and they don't stop.
And you know what I love, I can feel the synergy there is that we're talking
about incredibly serious, heartbreaking stories, and I've got a phone full of them as well.
Yeah.
I feel tragically around people who are devastated by this.
But, you know, you can do it with a smile.
You have to.
To have a fit, you've got that great balance of this is a course,
36 months that we all should get behind.
You're going to lobby as hard as you can to make this transition.
But you still had to do it Richard Branson style.
And I think that sums you up, Whipper.
I reckon that makes sense.
At the moment, we kicked it off last night just for the fun of it.
We're encouraging people to, if you go to my Instagram page,
which is Whipper1.
You'll see the 36 Months logo.
But what we're encouraging people is to take that logo, put it on Instagram.
And I can see the conflict there.
But once again, we don't have a problem with Instagram.
We have a problem with adolescents on Instagram.
But include a photo of when you were 13.
What were you doing at 13?
Yeah, you know, we're encouraging people to do that at the moment outside of sort
of just going to the petition at 36months.com.au.
We want everyone to sign up just to make
as much noise to let the Prime Minister know that this is the change required.
I'm on to it, Whipper. I'm in your corner.
It's been great to catch up with you.
As I said, I've been a long time admirer of the amount of effort that you put
in to support great causes and have a lot of fun along the way.
So I really appreciate you telling the story today.
And it's an amazing campaign you're
running and couldn't be more positive about wanting to make it happen.
Thanks again.
Likewise, Dars.
And thanks for acknowledging the year 10 first footy stuff.
I mean, when I sent you the first footy, you said,
I'll send you that email saying on one condition, I'll join the podcast if you
mentioned this, just use that as sort of the selling line of the whatever you get.
I'll leave it up to you, whatever you go with, mate.
It's resonated with me, Whipper.
The headline is it's a multi-talented radio superstar who could have been anything.
Your words, Dars.
Always a great pleasure to catch up with you.
Thanks, Whipper. Thanks, brother.
Thanks for listening to another episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Huge thanks, as always, to our great
team at Temper, and we encourage you to check out our Leader Connect program.
New episodes are out every Wednesday morning at six a.m.