I hope you enjoyed this episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast
with the legendary Mick Doohan, as much as I did recording it.
Mick is one of Australia's greatest ever sportsmen,
500cc, five-time motorcycle champion,
one of the most successful sportsmen in Australian history.
And beyond that, an incredible success story post his sporting life.
Mick's courage to come back from almost having his leg amputated
is an incredible story of bravery, of resilience,
and street-smart success with Mick Doohan.
Fascinating. I'm sure you're going to enjoy the wisdom
that Mick shares in this upcoming chat.
Mick Doohan epitomises everything we love and are passionate about
in the world we created called Alita.
Space co-founded with my great friend Matt Wadowitz,
a friend from the age of 12,
passionate about creating great education and leadership spaces,
and also a world of collaboration, inspiring connections.
We'd love you to check out our Alita Connect signature program
where we bring together a diverse range of leaders
from industry, from sport, from the arts, social venture,
into bespoke leadership forums to lead, to learn, and collaborate.
You don't have to be an Australian sporting legend like Mick Doohan to take part.
We love the passion of getting people together to lead, to learn, and to share ideas.
Love you to book a chat.
Head to alitacollective.com and catch up with us.
The Empowering Leaders podcast is proudly presented by Temper,
a mattress like no other.
And we know that inspiration,
and people like Mick Doohan really understand
the health benefits of sleep and sleeping well.
And to sleep on the world's best NASA-approved bedding
is a decision that I assure you will change your life.
Hope you enjoy this chat.
A few athletes have dominated international sport
like Sport Australia Hall of Fame 500cc motorcycle racing legend Mick Doohan.
Mick won five consecutive world championship titles
from 1994 to 1998, winning 54 Grand Prix's across his career,
including a record.
12 in the 1997 season.
Mick's sporting record is legendary.
Equally impressive is his post-sporting success in the commercial world.
Mick is a serious player in the global aviation world,
owning Platinum Business Aviation Centres at Essendon and Gold Coast Airports.
And his business is the world's largest trader of corporate aircraft.
Mick, great to spend some time with you in town for the Melbourne Grand Prix.
Thanks for taking the time.
Absolute pleasure.
Now, can I start with your record on the briar?
It was incredible.
What were the skills?
When you look back, I mean, it's such a competitive sport on an international stage.
What were the skills that you felt set you apart?
Difficult to know what really made the difference,
but I think just the love of it.
And I think the same with anybody, you know,
to get to the top of their sport or to anything,
you've got to really love it.
You've got to keep working at it
and you've just got to find little loopholes what others can't,
so to dominate it.
But I think it all comes back down to the passion.
If you don't have the passion,
you're not going to...
have the desire to want to put yourself at risk, you know,
whether it be in your game in football,
getting belted by people
or crashing into barriers at 200-odd kilometres an hour.
Well, it's funny, Sam, when I, you know,
and look at your story and you think you're on your way
to winning your first world championship in 1992
and that famous horrific crash happens,
so you talk about, you know, football
and that doesn't seem like a problem.
Falling off a motorbike at 200 k's an hour
feels like a serious problem
and you're close to getting your leg out,
amputated, a lot of medical advice.
I understand it was a Grand Prix medico, Dr. Claudio Costa,
who had the idea that you could sew your legs together
and that would save your leg.
Is that an accurate part of the story?
Yeah.
I guess Dr. Costa, in Holland,
where they butchered it, essentially,
there's no other way to say it, it was malpractice.
They were wanting...
Within 24 hours, they were going to amputate my leg.
I think Costa had heard about this,
so he then come and medevaced me out of there.
Myself and another guy, Kevin Schwantz,
took me back to Italy, to Bologna,
and more he was...
Because they'd thinned my blood that much up in Holland
that he was more concerned about my internal organs failing,
first and foremost,
so he got those back on some...
You know, stabilised, I guess.
And then it was...
It was said about the leg.
And really, the leg, sewing the leg together,
that was only...
That was the quickest way for me to return to riding.
And it wasn't the...
It was also the most barbaric way of doing it.
You know, the logical way for a doctor also was take a year out.
You know, we've got some major issues here.
Take freestanding flaps from either the backside
or your lower back area
and then graft them on to the areas where things have gone necrotic.
So gangrene had set in and all this and that.
So that was a major issue.
So then he...
In the past, they hadn't done that,
sewing the legs together for many years anyway.
And so what was happening when you say sew the legs together,
because I had very little blood supply,
because compartment syndrome,
it sort of happens in all forms of...
Like in football, I'm sure it's happened before.
Yeah.
So compartment syndrome is said...
It's said in.
So my circulation on the lower limb was pretty, pretty poor.
So we fed the...
One, we used the graft from the left leg
to plug the gap I had,
the big hole that they'd spooned out,
physically spooned out.
And then had the blood supply from the left leg feeding the right
to sort of keep it so it actually would take.
Because again, a free flap that early on
and the blood supply wasn't good.
Yeah.
It wasn't good enough for the graft to actually take.
So the legs were sewn together for two weeks or 14 nights.
And on the 15th, the 14th night,
they cut half of it to just cut the supply,
the blood supply area,
to just to see if it was going to survive.
And if it was, it looked like it wasn't,
they were going to then reattach it.
Thankfully it did.
And then I was able to go to the bathroom a lot easier.
I can assure you after that once we were able to cut them completely.
But look, previously they'd also,
they'd bolt the legs together.
In that scenario, when I say bolt the legs together,
put rods through your femurs and the lower limbs as well.
But again, having Swiss cheese for bones
when you're going back motorcycle racing wasn't ideal either.
So they basically put me in a plaster cast,
a scotch cast and had windows in the front and back
so they could actually get in there and clean it and keep it going.
So one, it was uncomfortable.
Two, it was very barbaric.
Costa knew that, but it was the only option.
So I was back on the bike in seven weeks essentially from all that.
So in hindsight, stupidity.
Because at the end of the day, as you say,
I didn't win the championship.
I lost by a few points at the end after losing,
missing five races.
I'm grimacing all the way through it.
I just can't imagine that being an option in the current world.
Going back, so you really,
you got a horrible malpractice at the start.
Is that what set you onto the path?
Totally.
And back in those days of 92 in Holland,
I since learned after experiencing all this
and Holland, everything is a public system anyway.
But had you had a car accident on the motorway,
which is right beside the circuit there
and massive trauma injuries,
they would have medevaced you to Amsterdam or Groningen,
not this little veterinarian clinic
where it would have been approved to host the ass and teeth.
Which was called back then,
which is around the Moto Grand Prix series.
And basically the doctors weren't up to the speed,
to be honest.
And Costa was actually there because he was the track doctor.
But because Europe wasn't like it is now,
he couldn't actually practice in Holland.
But he was in the surgery when it was that evening.
In Holland when that was going on.
So let's say it was a Friday or a Saturday,
I can't remember.
I think it was a Friday when I had the accident.
Friday evening, I'm having the surgery
because it was, in my mind, there was two weekends off,
which was a long time.
So if I bolt it back together, bolt the leg back together,
I could actually compete in the next, you know,
some way, shape or form in Hungary a few weeks later.
So you were seriously contemplating in your mind
on that operating cell, I'll get back into it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
That's insane.
Just put the leg back together, zip it up and away we go.
But, you know, I had American guys
there who were looking after some very specialised surgeons
working for the 49ers in San Francisco,
neurosurgeons.
I had a whole bunch of people just,
Costa said, he said, look, put it in a plaster cast.
It was a spiral fracture.
I broke my own leg actually,
trying to get out from underneath the bike.
But he said, put it in a plaster cast
and you'll be back in Brazil in six weeks' time.
I was back in six weeks' time.
But I should have just done that.
I went to this guy.
I said, I looked around and I said,
who's the best guy here?
Because it was a Dutch guy was there as well.
And just back on that, I should say,
Costa had a mobile clinic, a Clinica Mobile, he'd say.
It was like just a truck with some bits and pieces
would come out the side.
So he could do x-rays.
He could do bits and pieces in there.
So to see what's going on and then,
but then you had to go off to the local
if you wanted to get surgery or whatever.
He could do it back in Italy.
He could do it back in Italy or you'd go somewhere else.
But I'd said to this Dutch doctor,
he was actually in there and I said,
well, who's the best guy?
And generally in my experiences with doctors,
they'll say, you know, it's either me or it's my best.
Actually, I know a guy who specializes in that,
you know, and you generally trust doctor's opinions anyway,
you know, and he said,
which I thought was actually even odd at the time.
He said, we all went to the same university,
you know, meaning that, you know, we're all the same.
We're all as good as each other.
And I thought, well, shit,
but, you know, again, back up.
My mind was I'm leading the world championship.
I missed out just by a few points the year before.
My competitor's injured.
He's actually gone home.
So I want to actually sort of capitalize on this
and I'll be back.
So let's just bolt it together and I'll be back in two weeks.
And that was a wrong, wrong, wrong decision.
And even eight weeks later, Mick,
I can't imagine, you know, horrific pain.
And, you know, you've got what you've been through,
you know, your leg.
You've got your leg sewn together.
Chance you're going to lose a leg.
I mean, how do you get back on a bike at 200 k's an hour?
What do you need in your mind to overcome that sense of fear?
I think it's, it wasn't so much of, um,
you need to understand what happened in the first place.
And so I don't think that your confidence is a knock
because you know why you crashed, you know what happened.
So, you know, if you're physically capable of riding again,
that, you know, the likelihood of that happening again is it's there,
but I mean, it's very remote.
So no dent in your confidence, no dent in your confidence at that point in time,
you know, and, um, but a bit, but by being the biggest problem was six weeks later,
I'd been, been on my back essentially for six weeks and I had no feeling.
So again, the pain wasn't really such an issue because I really didn't have
any feeling from the knee down.
And, um, so it was just like another, it was just,
Yeah.
It was like a prosthetic leg to be honest, but thankfully it wasn't,
it was still attached.
And, uh, so that probably helped me a little bit, but, um, but it's also,
you know, I'd lost the use of my ankle, you know, I haven't got the feel.
I haven't got the strength because these things, you steer them with your legs
and you know, you've got 200 horsepower running through the rear wheel on
something which back then was 130 kilos and the front wheels really just dancing
around, you lean it, you use your, your mid.
Section and your legs to steer the bike, you just operating the, the accelerator
and the brakes and the clutch or the throttle, you know, with, with all that,
the rest of it, it's just the wheels just there to make it look good on the front.
It's basically a, uh, a unicycle.
And then to take half a leg out.
I mean, that's gotta be a serious job.
And then they, they install a, a thumb brake.
So that was the following year.
Yeah.
So I knew what, so for those two races, I came back.
The first race in Brazil was a bit of a, it was a waste of time.
I'd practice.
Actually, the doctor cost her, so I knew back then it was basically had to walk
about, you know, 20 steps from, from a chair to the bike.
And if you could make that walk, you're fit to ride.
So I'd practice that quite a bit, but, uh, you know, I was dead by
the time I got to the bike and, um, but, but yeah, during that race, it
won't bore you with the whole, the way it all worked out, but, but during that
race there, my leg would be flying.
Swinging off the bike cause I couldn't feel it as I say, but you could feel it just
through the seat of your pants and it's not actually sort of on the footrests.
And then you'd look down and, and at 200 odd kilometers an hour and
just place it back onto the bike.
So, so that was a, that was a difficulty.
It was actually physically riding the bike, the way it needed to be, to be
ridden and I had a few other crashes because I couldn't, and then likewise
with the brake, I, I, so I only had a front brake instead of a rear brake.
So the rear brake helps stabilize everything and keep the, keep the, the
balance of the bike.
And especially entering turns and coming off a turn.
And, um, so it wasn't until about, um, the beginning of the following year
that I'd convinced Honda that, you know, let's do a handbrake.
So we, that the Honda had, uh, put on a, a, a, a brake like a scooter.
You've got the front brake and the rear brake on the other side, but you've also
got the clutch and the clutch, as I say, you've got 200 odd horsepower running
through the rear tire and there was no traction control or anything like that.
So if it spun and it'd spin that quick, that rolling out of the throttle wouldn't
stop it spinning.
It'd send you about 15 foot in the air as, as it's kicking you off.
So you needed to use the clutch to disengage the, um, disengage the back
wheel straighter and the power straight out of it.
And so trying to use the, the index finger and then the middle finger
independently is pretty hard.
So, so during that first race sort of went to what is essentially like an
ag bike or a jet ski, a little thumb operated brake, put that on.
And then next weekend I was back on the podium and then that year was a recovery
year and then 94, I won a championship again.
Once I got fully healed, I ended up going back to the guys in the States who were
looking after the San Jose Sharks and the, and the San Francisco 49ers who,
who put my leg back together.
And Mickey, how are you walking today?
And we catch up and, um, beautiful wife, uh, Selena's with you and you, and
there's a noticeable limp and, and that's, you know, your, your life.
I mean, as a, do you look back and think with any regret?
Well, not at all, you know, to be honest, I'm fortunate, um, to one of being
able to put myself in that position, not for the crash, but I mean, to, to, to
be able to have led the life that I have.
Um, and, and, and equally, there's plenty of people who fall downstairs or, you
know, just going through general life, have injuries, you know?
So the thing is, I knew that I could possibly hurt myself at some point.
So I don't regret any of that.
And I don't, I don't, um, dwell on it.
I just got to keep pushing forward.
And for me, it's, as I say, it is, you know, we're 20, 23 now, you know, this
was 1992, so the majority of my life's been like this anyway.
And, um, and as I say, I think the difference between a sports person and,
uh, and, and the average man on the street, we can have the same, or they can
have the same injuries, but you're not actually expecting to have an injury.
We expect to have an injury.
So we tend to sort of just move on pretty quickly.
And you are so short term focused on that, that stage of your life.
You've got this ambition to be.
Well, champion, you, you go on to win five more, as I said, uh, it's an
extraordinary time when you look back, the journos, I understand called you
dead by June doing, which, which when you look back, it's pretty disgraceful,
really, isn't it?
I was, you know, media in those times to have, but clearly they saw your bravery
and your courage as being at another level and your risk taking another, were
you conscious of that and, and how did you feel about that at the time?
Yeah, well, the dead by June thing, I don't know who was, I think a South African,
um, uh, journalist at the time, because I came from Australia.
I was riding a two 50 CC street bike, like a production bike here in 87, 89.
I'm on a 500 CC grand Prix bike or MotoGP bike.
So I come out of obscurity basically.
So nobody really knew who this kid was from Australia.
And all of a sudden I'm on something with 200 horsepower was on something two years
earlier with 35 horsepower, you know, that bike was heavier than the one, you know?
So there was a little bit of trial and error.
I'm more error than trial.
So, uh, and everything up until I hopped on a MotoGP bike was pretty, for me, it felt
pretty easy to ride.
And then once, once I hopped on that, it was like, it was a big wake up call.
And the guys, you know, you back in those days, the Wayne, you know, Wayne Gardner
was, was the man, but you know, Wayne, Wayne Rainey, Eddie Lawson, Kevin Schwartz,
there's a bunch of them in there and it's honestly, they're in a different planet to
be on what I'd been used to even in some of the world, super bike staff, some of the
other things, what I did.
I did in, uh, competed in, in 98.
So it was a wake up call.
And, and, and again, probably I did, um, push myself too far, but unfortunately with,
with, with everything, you know, you learn a lot more by your mistakes than you do by,
by getting it right sometimes.
And, and unfortunately, um, I didn't have that experience coming through when other,
in other, uh, lower disciplines, just from the way I come through so quick.
But, uh, but that said, after June, I very rarely crashed.
And then, um, and then throughout my, for the rest of the, well, even the whole Grand
Prix career, I crashed less than 30 times.
And, um, some, I think the best I did was about 18 months.
And back then we'd do, uh, without a crash back then, we'd do a lot of testing, a lot
of riding.
And so I'm doing about 10,000 kilometers of race miles a year, which is a lot.
And then, um, without a crash.
So today these modern guys are different.
Um, thankfully they're not, they're not doing the big high sides and whatever, but
I mean, some of these guys are crashing 30 times a year, but.
Is that the numbers now, is it?
It is, yeah.
So 30 in your second half of your career is quite.
Well, actually from the start, so the dead by June was the first, um, you know, cause
that was at the beginning, you know, so I've come in, you know, the season started the
beginning of March.
So that's what this South African journo, he lives in Britain, Michael Scott.
And he's like, oh, this kid's not going to, he's going to be dead.
You know, so that's where that, so, but, um, um, so I, I've, I've got through that
season and the next season I was third and then, um, and then, uh, then second and then
second again with the leg and then blah, blah, blah.
So it's sort of, once I got the grasp of it, I was okay.
I just needed to learn those mistakes.
Unfortunately on a bike, every time you make a mistake, you're on your backside, you know,
with a car, you sort of, you know, you can still have a big crash in a car, but you know,
the small.
The ones, at least you just spin, put it back into first and drive off again, you know?
Well, you got so good that, that no one got near you and you won five in a row.
And, and, you know, I remember that era and watching and not knowing your sport, but thinking
God, our Aussie guy is just so much better.
And it seemed like you could get in front and you were so in control of what you're
doing in the end that you could really, you know, just, just ride within yourself.
Is that, was there a period of time where you just felt if I, if I get it right, no
one's going to get near me?
Yeah.
Well, that's the.
Well, that's what kept me going when I had the, uh, the accident, uh, with it, when I
nearly lost my leg, um, is I knew that if I get myself back to fitness, because I ended
up winning with a broken leg still the year in 93, I knew if I could get back, even with
the, the, the, the, my ankle being fused and, um, and using a rear brake on the, on the
handlebar and so on.
So that gave me confidence.
I knew if I got myself some way fit, I'd be fine.
And then, and then that, that was a bit the.
Same that you got to a point where you'd win at the slowest possible speed.
So you just manage where your competitor is.
And then, um, you know, at the end of the day, you only need to win by, by, by, by half
an inch, you know, and you've won the race.
Nobody remembers who finished second.
So, and nobody remembers how much you won by.
So, you know, sometimes you win by, by a lot.
You just, at other times you just manage it and just play with it a little bit.
And, uh, but, um, it's.
Yeah, at the end of the day, it was just all about winning and managing and also de-risking
it.
And so, but I mean, it's the same with any sport.
You've got to keep focused on what you, especially in a speed sport.
So you've, you've got to maintain, um, you've got to maintain that vision on, on not making
a mistake.
And so your mindset needs to be 100% immersed in what you're doing.
Cause soon as you start to have time to think about what's going on, I'm going to actually
slow up a little bit.
You'll slow up and you'll make a mistake, you know, because you're not 100% committed
to being focused on the job.
At the time, you're undisputedly the best motorbike rider in the world and revered around
the world.
The best four wheel, uh, athlete, uh, if you like was Michael Schumacher and you two formed
this great friendship, lifelong friendship.
Tell us, did you learn a bit from each other?
Was there obviously great mutual respect at the time?
Yeah, we'd look without a doubt and we'd push each other off the circuit, uh, you know,
we were, the good thing is we're in different disciplines, you know, the, the, the, um, back
in those days, and it is today that there's still the two largest motor sports on the
planet, but the one you'd have an F1 one weekend and a MotoGP for the next.
And, um, and, um, and in between that we'd be training a bit, but, but we weren't really
competing against each other.
It's not like him.
He's right driving against, you know, Mika Hakkinen or something, and they can't really
share different mindsets.
So we'd, we'd share the way.
We go, I think about going racing and, uh, and, uh, and he equally off, like with training,
pushing each other, you know, you, you, you'd know, we'd, you'd know, you'd be up against
whatever we go training with to be a, it'd be a competition, you know?
So, and it was good.
So you'd push each other.
We become good friends like that.
He was living beside, uh, beside us in 94.
He was world champion.
I was world champion and, and, and likewise, 95, so on.
And, uh, and we had similar sponsors.
And then, um, um, and then, yeah, he was living beside, beside, um, beside me in Monaco.
And then, um, and so it was pretty easy to, to train together and do different things
together.
And we've become and remain friends today.
Did I read, Mick, that, uh, he bought your two kids, Alexis and Jack, their first go
karts?
That's right.
He helped arrange those.
Yeah.
So, uh, so, um, so both of the kids had, and we still got them back at home, to be honest.
And that, you know, it's amazing.
And I love, uh, the way the world works and, you know, Jack's, uh, Formula Two, incredible
success, your, your son and, uh, and, uh, and Michael's son, Mick, you know, um, racing
Formula One.
And I'm sure they've grown up with a great friendship, but it must be pretty special
to see the two of them pursuing the same love.
No, totally.
And, uh, well, you know, Mick, there's probably more pressure on young Mick Schumacher with
a father like Michael, um, in the same discipline, at least Jack's on the four wheel.
So it'd be difficult, more pressure on him, I'd believe if he was trying to race motorcycles
and, and it's much better for us as parents that he's not, it's much easier, even though
it's stressful watching him in a car, but it's a lot easier to watch as a parent, him
in the car.
But, but young Mick and, and, and Jack are great mates and have been for a long while.
But, um, you know, when, when, when, uh, when Mick's in Australia, he's generally sort of
staying with us and the kids go off.
So, well, they're not kids anymore, but the boys go.
They go off surfing and messing around and whatever they do as kids, you know.
It's, uh, it's brilliant, isn't it?
Did I read that you're, you're Jack as a five-year-old fell off a bike on the, on the family property
and broke a leg as well.
And that's right.
And then when.
So that, that pretty, yeah, well it did it.
Um, he, he broke his leg, uh, when he was five.
That's right.
And then, uh, and then he was a bit gun shy of bikes and he got into BMX and, uh, started
racing BMX, but then it was more surfing, uh, rugby.
Yeah.
And, uh, athletics, typical kid stuff.
And then, and then slowly got into karting because his buddies were go-kart racing.
And then, and then the go-karting took off.
He won a few go-kart races.
We won, uh, he won three Australian championships in a row here.
And then, and then, uh, I took him to Europe and he did well.
And then Red Bull picked him up and put him into a Red Bull junior team.
And he started racing cars a year.
He turned 15 in, um, in the UK.
It's, uh, my oldest son is, is, is playing NFL football.
And.
And watching him, I'm surprised by how nervous, you never saw danger out there when you're
playing.
You think of it as a parent, you suddenly, phew, don't do that.
You know, don't run the hair.
It's a, I find it really unnerving.
Yeah, totally.
You feel the same?
Yeah.
A hundred percent.
It's strange, isn't it?
Yeah.
And, uh, and it's difficult for them, you know, we, we can see it and we've experienced
it, but you can't really, you can't tell them because I think you're, uh, you're criticizing
them, but you can tell somebody else to tell them and they'll listen to it.
You know what I mean?
Now Jack's, Jack's, uh, I'm not sure how, how old your fellow, your young, young lad
is, but, but Jack's now 20.
So he'll listen to it, agree now it's sort of past that point, but it's still difficult
to watch as a parent, as I say, cause you know yourself what, uh, what can go wrong.
It's one of the great parenting, my lad Sam's 19 and, uh, it's sort of brilliant at one
level, isn't it?
You know, you clearly, world of motorsport or something that is right in your zone of
expertise, but they need to hear it from someone else.
And no matter what, you just have to, as soon as you realize that.
It's fine, isn't it?
There's a lot of pain if, uh, if you don't, um, uh, it's, uh, it's brilliant to see that,
that coming through.
You're, you're a working class boy from Brisbane.
I just, you know, not necessarily a school wasn't a hundred percent from you, from what
I read.
Um, what, what are the skills that allowed you post-sport?
A lot of athletes struggle in that next chapter.
You've gone on to incredible success.
What do you, what do you think helped, helped you in that part?
Um, I think the same, the same discipline that helped me with the sport.
Really recognizing one, you've got to recognize that sports over, and I think that's a lot
of people sort of can't move on.
They've never sort of planned for an exit of sport and most sports, if you get a decade
at the top of the sport, you've done, you've been pretty, pretty damn lucky.
And, you know, so thankfully I had some good people around me.
We've sort of made, we're able to sort of, to advise me a little bit better on that,
you know, even though you think you're never going to stop.
Um, who said to you, Hey, no, you, you broke your leg again at the end.
I broke my leg again.
That, that really had no, I'd, I'd planned to continue on that.
It was only when I couldn't, um, continue.
Um, and then I moved into a role with Honda as general manager of racing with them and
doing some things within the sport.
Um, so I'd moved, I'd transitioned.
So I was still involved with the sport, but not actually competing.
And I had an offer to come back and a bit like Schumacher come back after a few years
is that, you know, you probably went.
And through it as well, there's a two, three year period, you know, where you're still,
you know, you can still relate to what's going on and you still feel you can, you know, put
your shoes back on away from my case, put the helmet back on and be competitive.
And I knew that, I mean, I'd go, you'd have to go through that same withdrawal process
again, anyway, even if I went back on and I did it again, I was now physically capable
of riding, but I'd, um, I'd thankfully declined that, you know, I, I see, uh, give me a couple
of weeks to think about it.
And I, I actually declined it.
And that was the smartest move to be honest.
And then, and then I just transitioned into, into working with the team and then investments
and then, and then, which is, and then slowly sort of from about the mid two thousands more
into the aviation started to, to, to, uh, I guess started as a bit of a hobby dabble
in aviation.
And then there's now what she's grown into a big part of our business.
I read that, uh, you negotiated and you had a time on the bike, uh, a bonus structure
where it was all about.
Yeah.
You win and you get exponentially rewarded second.
It's a massive decline.
And, and from that moment on, I think you just kept winning and so you backed yourself
in.
I mean, I clearly had a negotiation ability, uh, even in those days.
Yeah.
And again, I think that's just understanding and backing yourself to a degree.
Um, but back, back most of the, I'm not sure what it's like in your sport, but back in,
in, in the motorsport, um, um, arena, especially back then.
I had win bonuses, second and thirds and, you know, um, we're negotiating contract fees
and so on like, Oh, well, let's remove the second and third bonuses.
And we'll put in big, uh, win bonuses, whether it be for championships or whether it be for
races.
And, you know, they're thinking, yeah, of course you're going to have no problem, you
know, cause there's less chance you're going to win that finish second or third, you know?
So, uh, and it doesn't motivate you any, you know, you don't go out there and think, Oh,
I've got to win.
Cause I'm going to earn a couple more dollars.
You know, you want to win cause you want to win.
Yeah.
But certainly.
It helped, um, it helped, uh, on, on the business sense on the business foundation for me of
understanding, you know, the fundamentals of, uh, how I can make things work for myself.
Yeah.
And I, I, uh, reference at the start about, you know, one of your spaces is, is commercial
aircraft and selling them around the world and, and sell more of those than I think anyone
else on the, on the planet.
I'm sure that's a sophisticated area to get into with, you know, people that are high
net worth and understand.
And deal making, how have you found that?
Oh, it's not, it's not easy, but again, it's, it's, uh, it's transitioned over a number
of years, of course.
Uh, I'm a partner in a company called Jetcraft, which as you say, we're the, we're the largest
traders of corporate aircraft.
So we buy, sell, we traditional broke, we help with financing, advise, um, the, the
whole box and die.
So we have 20 offices around the world.
So we've got some good people within the offices to help structure the deals and so on.
But yeah.
But the people want to deal with, you know, with, with myself or whatever.
So we'll structure the deal together and then, and then it'll be handed off to our legal
council or whoever to put it all together and their legal council.
But, you know, when we're talking, um, you know, we're, we're, we sell ultra low, um,
our sweet spot, I guess, is our ultra long range corporate aircraft.
So in Aussie dollars, we're talking up to a hundred plus million dollars space.
So, you know, so these, they're very successful people.
Well, corporations that we're dealing with, um, and so it's not easy, you know, you're
not pulling the wool over any of these guys' eyes very easily and nor do we want to, you
know, we want, we want a lot.
We've got along with the, it's in its 60th year, you know, I'm one of the partners in
it.
It's remained restructured essentially from 08.
Um, there's four partners in there.
Um, but, um, but we want your, we want to sell you one today.
We want to then my back off you.
In four or five years time, sell you another.
So we, we're, we're, we're a solid business and with, with, uh, with a solid, um, ethical
standard practice with goes along with it.
And, uh, and as you say, we've got some other businesses here in Australia that just go
along with the corporate, um, the corporate aviation thing.
And, and, you know, a good year in that space.
How many, how many aircraft do you, do you move in a good year?
On average, we do roughly a hundred aircraft.
So, you know.
We've, um, we're, let's say the past decade we've, we've, um, we've done, um, the past
decade, we've probably done, um, 1500 aircraft or so, you know, so it's not too bad, you
know?
So some years we're 80, some years we're a hundred, some, you know, but I mean, it's
not, it's not a bad little space.
Um, Mick, we, we share a mutual, uh, a friend who, uh, spent some time with you over in,
in Europe and, uh, one of my great old mates.
And, and I know you've, uh, got to know him and he said, it's always fascinating to catch
up with you that there's always eclectic people around McDool and you can come to lunch and
there could be the creator of Riverdance or, uh, someone from a Royal family somewhere.
Uh, he described you as a, as a, as a great connector of people.
Was that, were you like that as a young athlete or has it been the nature of your second part
of your life?
I think, um, I think a bit of both.
I recognized at that point in time, being a young, you know, growing up, enjoying bike
racing or, or sport.
You know, meeting people, you know, rather than, than shying away from meeting people,
I've sort of always been open to meet people.
And then I've been fortunate to meet people of other people.
And, and so, and for me, you know, networking's a load of garbage.
Friendship is everything.
And, um, you know, I've, I've been able to retain friendship with a lot of people.
And I think that's been the key.
And, um, and then you meet through those friendships, you meet other people and, and you meet people,
whether it be a different, a completely, as you say, whether it be Riverdance or whether
it be something else, but the, you know, the, the mindset's much the same, whether it be
a success in a multinational company or, or whatever, the, the disciplines really are
much aligned of what took you to the top of AFL, to be honest.
And I love it.
That's a brilliant, I love what you just said there, you know, networking's a load of rubbish,
but friendships is everything.
And that authenticity, we all know people who are fanatical networkers that, but you
never get a sense that there's anything tangible there, is it?
It's, and, and, and people get that pretty quickly, don't they, that there's a sense
and, and, and, and for you, that's just the nature of you is that you connect because
of the connection and nothing else.
Well, that's, that's really it.
We don't, at the end of the day, I don't want anything else.
It's just about, you know, one interested in, in their story, number one, and then if
something comes of it, but, but, but likewise, you know, they come to, if somebody comes
to Australia and Europe, um, you know.
They'll give you a call, hey, let's go and grab a, a beer or dinner or whatever.
And, and, and the same, the same if, uh, if I'm somewhere.
So, you know, we, whenever, you know, sometimes it's nice to just go somewhere and not, uh,
not catch up with anybody, but it's nice to be able to, to, to, to be able to go anywhere
in the world and be able to catch up with somebody and, and, and be shown a great time.
Is there someone that stands out to me that you think, God, that transition from sport
to commercial success here, was there a mentor or someone that helped you specifically along
the way?
I think there's been a few, but.
But, um, but without a doubt, um, a guy by the name of James Strong, he was, um, he was
CEO of Qantas when I met him, you know, met him at a racetrack, to be honest, and I was
at, uh, one of the, the Australian Grand Prix and, um, we became good, good buddies.
And then, um, we, we did some, some things together and then, uh, people like Bruce Matheson,
the publican, and then we've done a couple of things together and, uh, and just different,
you know, completely two different people.
But, I mean, it's a good to get a broad understanding of the way they think and really at the end
of the day, it's about having a go and backing yourself and, and understanding the product
that would you, what you, what you have.
And, uh, I understand, you know, to this day, still on the fitness, if you, if you jump
on a bike or you, you still got that competitive edge, you're still alive and well, from what
I hear, Mick, is that something you do daily to look after yourself?
I do, you know, I'm sure, you know, when, when sports been such a big, um, period of
your life that, uh.
Yeah, I, I enjoy sort of circulating a bit of blood, plus I don't want to rust, you know,
with all the, all the metal I still have in me, but I don't, honestly, I don't have that
much, but, uh, but no, I enjoy to continue to do it.
But yeah, I think, uh, I know who you're talking about, but yeah, cycling and cycling up hills
because there's, in Europe where we're based, uh, there's only hills around you.
So, uh, if you're not used to it, then it's difficult.
But I mean, when you're doing decades of riding up hills, it's, it's, it's not too bad.
And Mick, I'm fascinated in, um, passionate about what leadership looks like in different
spaces and, and sit down with, you know, your expertise in business and sport or someone
from the world of arts.
And a bit like you said there, you know, Bruce Matheson's expertise compared to the CEO of
Qantas, James Strong, is a different way of thinking, a different logic, but we see there's
a common sort of traits that people who are successful have, uh, and starting with this
idea of self-leadership, Mick, it's very hard to lead anyone else without a sense of
self-leadership.
Does that, does that make sense to you?
Yeah.
Well, 100%.
At the end of the day, delegations, you know, there's a lot of delegators out there.
And so you've got to lead and you've got to show your team what you're doing.
And I think that's where you're going with that, are you?
I'm not sure, but I mean, it's, um, at the end of the day, it's up to you really.
And, um, nobody else is going to help you get there.
And, um, and likewise with the same with your team around you, you know, you've got to,
you've got to help, uh, encourage them to be part of the, part of the, of the process
and part of the team.
And you've got to have a bunch of team players and like-minded, uh, individuals.
So, so leadership, you know, I, I've, I've never really, you know, it comes, people talk
about it.
So I don't even think about it, you know, it's just what I do.
So it's not something that I, you know, I've got to be, you know, uh, an A type or whatever
they, you know, all this stuff.
It's like, what?
You know, I just get, get on and get it done, you know?
So I don't know about the, you know, I'm always thinking about something and what I've got
to be doing and what I want to be doing and where I want to go.
So, you know, there's very, you know, my wife probably doesn't like it that often,
but there's very, there's very little downtime for me as far as switching off.
And, um, but, but that's what I enjoy.
And that's, I guess, what's, what's made me be here talking with you.
And you, and you find that that's, that those passions are there and you, and you, you just
have a process of, I've got to get something done.
It's up to me.
Is there?
Well, it gets to a point where something has to be done anyway.
And as I say, like delegating, it's, it's difficult.
Um, you know, I delegate to the.
Right people, of course, but I mean, you've got to bring them along for the ride, but,
but you're always thinking, and I'm always wanting to do something.
I've always got something I feel like I should be doing.
Um, so just, you know, one day, one day I can imagine that I'll slow things down, but
never completely stop, but, uh, but I enjoy what I do.
And, um, um, so, so I'm always just thinking about what the, what's the next thing.
We see Mick, uh, you know, people with success with a consciousness.
It's about others in their environment, how they impact them.
And it seems to be the case for you that the people around you enjoy their time to catch
up with, with Mick.
Are you conscious around that, around having an impact positively in all the arenas you're
in?
Um, look, I, I'm not sure how to answer that, but, um, um, you know, I, I enjoy what I
enjoy.
I, if I don't enjoy it, I don't enjoy it, but, but, um, but I, you know, I don't, thankfully
I don't have a bunch of employees.
You know, Jetcraft is, is the biggest group.
There's probably about 70 odd in, in that, but they're global around the, around this.
I'm not interacting with each and every one of those.
Um, it's more the, the leadership team in that, um, uh, dealing with them.
Um, at, um, so, so the rest of it, my, my inner circle of staff, I guess, have been
with me for a long while, you know, which means we're all getting old, but, uh, but
I mean, but as far as friendship and that.
We're just, just normal, normal people.
We just get on and have fun.
If we're not having fun, we don't do it.
I love it, Mick.
And I love that it shows up just inauthentically in everything you do.
And it's your way of, of having great success.
I mean, we, you know, to achieve five Grand Prix's in a row, clearly you had a vision
for yourself of being world champion multiple times, and you need a team behind you to do
that.
Were you sophisticated with that team around, right?
You know, I'm riding for, on a Honda and I need you to fix that thumb brake and I've
got this vision and you need to come with me to.
To support that or?
One, 100%.
And the same thing, I've pulled the right team players together very quickly within
a couple of years, sort of got the right crew from, from other areas.
And they, they remained with me all the way through the career.
One of them still works for me in another area.
Um, uh, then Valentino Rossi then, um, took all my team and then he, he hung onto that
same team for a long while.
Was he your, did he come on the bike after you?
So he, I'd signed him to be my teammate in 2000 and then when I didn't come back and
then, um, so I was going to be right alongside him.
And then, um, it was, it would become evident, evident that I wasn't, wasn't able to compete
again in 2000.
So basically I stopped and then Honda, um, took over the program, but then my, cause
we were going to run an independent team beside Honda, but factory equipment and had a different
sponsor.
The sponsor pulled out because I didn't really know who Honda, who, uh, who Valentino, you
know, he's a world champion of the two 50, but I mean, he hadn't made his name in the
MotoGP arena.
And then, so, um, Honda put me in as general manager of the racing side of thing.
Um, my team all become Honda.
Um, my, my team became Valentino's team.
Um, and Nostra Azzurro, the beer sponsor come on board with, with the Italian and then that's
where it went from there.
So, so that was, um, so he transitioned that 99 was my last season.
And then 2000, he, he joined and then stayed with Honda until 2004 or five and then moved
on and then took some of the team, some of my team with him to another manufacturer.
And, uh, one of them, one of them left and one of them, he started working for me, which
he still does today.
Did you see something special in Valentino as a young lad?
Not, well, it was hard.
I was more fun.
I was still competing at that point in time.
So yeah, he was winning and he was doing well.
And I was looking, I, I, I was creating my own race team at that point in time.
And I was looking for the best guy around to, to be a, to be my teammate and then to
help with everything going forward.
And at some point in time I was going and whether it be two, three, four, five years
time, I was going to, to move on whether or not he stayed there as long as that anyway.
But he was, uh, he was the guy and, you know, I was able to, to, uh, convince him at that
time to come with me, um, because again, I was winning at that point in time.
I'd had, um, I had Honda supporting me.
So Honda was the, the, the bike to be on at the time.
So, um, so thankfully he seen something in, in wanting to go that way as well, but, but
equally he then ended up on the bike, what I was riding essentially with my crew.
So it was a good transition from the lower category into the, into the main game for
him.
And then he rewarded them with a bunch of world titles and, and he's gone.
On to be, uh, um, I think the, the, the highest winning, the winningest, um, uh, Grand Prix
winner, but not, I think, um, Agostini, Giacomo Agostini's still got one more world title
than him from, from the sixties and seventies.
Um, and we, we see, uh, another dimension we talk about people who have success like
you consistently, they're curious all the time.
They want to learn, they want to know what's going on.
And, and through that, that's how they constantly get better.
Does that resonate with you?
The idea of constantly trying to find that, that curiosity and things?
Um, yes, less so now, but, but yeah, without a doubt, trying to keep pushing yourself,
uh, when, especially back in the competition days, you keep pushing yourself to try and
find the, you know, you keep pushing that limit and pushing those, that line a little
bit further out.
So that, that, that gray area is, is, is very clear.
You know, the more you keep pushing yourself, they're clear of that.
That, that, that gray area becomes, and I think that's the same with everything.
The more you understand and the more you do, whether we just want to put into aviation
when I'm first in there and you're fumbling through things, you know, and you are fumbling
through things because you haven't done a lot of it in the first time, but after you've
done it a hundred times, it's, you know, it's pretty second nature.
And, and I think that's the same thing as what you're saying, but, uh, but you keep
pushing through, you keep wanting to understand more and more and more, and, and that's just
called being an old fart, I guess, with experience.
Yeah.
Some people haven't got that mindset though, Mika.
They hit a hurdle and they're not prepared to go through that.
We are fumbling around in the, in the day and obviously you just do it.
I don't think you even consciously, uh, think about it.
I think it just seems to be second nature to you.
And it's, I'm, I'm always interested in, in that we see a lot of really consistent in
how they communicate with people as part of their success and communicating with, with
Clary, even just in, you know, I've been chasing you around the world.
Every time I text you, you're in Bahrain or Monaco, it's a, it's a, it's a back in
Queensland or over the world.
But you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you,
you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you, you,
you're very quick.
You always communicate clearly.
Is that, has that been something that's been part of you?
Yeah, I think that's, I've, I've also found with, you know, that's also been something,
you know, it's a pet peeve of mine that people don't get back to you or whatever, but also
I've found, and I'm not putting myself in that basket, but I mean, successful people
come back to you quickly.
Although they come back, they say, Hey, I'm busy at the moment, but I'll come back to
you here.
You know, at least you know where you stand rather than just being left out on the limb
where you don't hear, you don't get a return.
But, but I, I actually didn't, um, I didn't answer your question previously about the
team and communicating with the team and Honda, but we were certainly working on the same
page.
Yeah.
You know, I wasn't an engineer, but I communicate to the, to my chief engineer who then communicate
and then we'd have a debrief with the Japanese engineers because you'd have people, you'd
have Michelin back, back in those days, Michelin, you know, tyre chemists, tyre, tyre engineers,
you know, suspension engineers, carburation engineers, you know.
Electronic engineers, you'd be debriefing.
So you've got to be able to communicate and you've got to piece them all together and make
them feel like we're on a winning team because even though it's an individual sport, it is
a, it's still a, it's still a we, you know, we're doing this and we're, we're winning
and, uh, and we've got to make everyone feel part of that team.
And, and I think that's one of the, the things that sport teaches you in general is one punctuality.
That's why I went back to that.
Yeah.
And, and, and, you know, cause you can't show up five minutes late for kickoff, you know,
you can't show up five minutes late.
Five minutes late for a practice session or a race, you know, you, you finish.
So, and it's pretty easy to keep that going through.
And then, and then, um, and likewise with, with your team, you know, you've got to be
playing with your team members.
You've, they've got to know they're going to be able to rely on you.
And likewise, you can rely on them.
And I think mixed sports people really underestimate the skillset they get out of that professional
part of their life where you're totally obsessed with making sure you're not going to go, well,
one of those engineers lets you down.
You're not sitting here as a five time world champion.
So if you don't communicate clearly.
Mm.
To a Japanese engineer on a specific part of your bike, he can't support that process
for you.
And, and, you know, in, in the world of football, one teammate is having an off day.
That's enough for you to, to not be successful.
So I think that, as you said, you know, that skillset applies to clearly what you've done
in aviation and other areas of your life.
We, we see more than ever now that people are aware of collaboration as a, as a much
more important thing in, in every area of their life to get stuff done, you need to
collaborate more effectively.
Has that been true for you?
Yeah, without a doubt, you know, you can't do anything by yourself at all.
So you, you've certainly, you've got ideas and you've got, um, the bits and bobs, but
I mean, at the end of the day, the day you have to rely on some, some other people at
some point in time.
And, and you've got to, you've got to want to, you've got to have them buy into what
you, you, you're doing.
So, you know, different people have different ways of making that work for them.
But, um, you know, I just do what I do.
And, um.
And as I say, some people, the majority of the people must like it because they've worked
for me for a long while, but the rest of it, uh, um, the rest of it, you know, you're not
going to please everyone all the time, but, but having people buy into what I'm doing,
if they don't buy in, they're not, they're not part of the show.
And it's a good sign, isn't it?
When you've got long held people who are clearly happy in their environment, you're
doing, doing something right.
Um, a couple of final questions, Megan, thanks for taking the time, uh, to do this.
So who's been the, the, the great leader for you in your life?
Um, good question.
I don't, I've never really thought of it to be honest.
So, uh, um, yeah, I, I'm just inspired by people who have, you know, back in the
sporting days, you know, it was people like, um, you know, the, the, you know, I'll
keep it Australian, but your people like Greg Normans, who was sort of number one for a
long while, people who can do things continuously, you know, that, um, because
it's, it's never easy to win something.
Yeah.
Or to be the top of the game, but I mean, to stay at the top is, is it, you know, you
touched on it earlier.
It's a little bit more difficult because you've got to keep pushing yourself and the drive
you have to keep maintain that drive.
And so, and then people, you know, successful people in business, and I'm not meaning, um,
there's a lot of people who have been very successful in different areas who aren't in
the limelight.
And, uh, you know, so people who have achieved what they've set out to, to achieve and built,
built something for themselves, whether it be.
Um, uh, business wise or sport wise, but, but there, there's sort of people who inspire
me to, to, um, to, to, to go on and do good things.
And that's the same, um, um, uh, there was a tennis player back in the day, Peter, what
was his name?
Sampras, you know, he was, he was somewhere here cause he was the man remember back in
the nineties, you know, he was just dominant.
And, uh, you know, so you'd look at him and go, wow, you know, how does he just do this
week in, week out, you know, every, every grand slam he's.
So there's plenty of people like that.
He's like, you know, that's, that's inspirational.
And, um, but I mean, the rest of it, as I say, I couldn't answer the question because
I never really thought about it.
But clearly, you know, those, you know, and the way of your world, you probably spent
some time with the great white shark and, and, and did you, did you find that you were
learning from them and just see there was some, some clues that came out of that sustained
success or.
And that's, that's been the best thing.
And then you, you'd be the same, but you, you meet like-minded people and there's a
lot of, a lot of success.
There's a lot of similarities there, whether it be a different discipline in the sport
or, or even in the business, the same sort of disciplines are there, which again, you're
taught playing sport and that's why sports so good for, you know, kids rather than getting
on their iPhones or PlayStations, you know, just teaches you just basic life skills.
And, but, you know, you take it to another level if you want to take it to that level.
And there's a lot of similarities between, you know, somebody, um, creating a great company
and the leadership, but what he needs to do that.
Yeah.
And the disciplines that he needs.
He needs to do that.
And the passion and desire is the same as, as what, you know, it takes a good football
or a good tennis player or a good motorcyclist or whatever.
Yeah.
And you've probably articulated a bit, the passion of where this conversation comes from.
It's what we do in our leadership space is bringing together people from different disciplines,
taking them out of their silos to learn that crown, whether it's a conductor of an orchestra
who's in front of 500 people, who's the top of their game.
And, you know, you miss a beat, Ben Northey's in one of our spaces, who's legendary
conductor with the same mindset that Greg Norman had to be on top of the world with
someone who's, uh, started an entrepreneurial space from scratch and doing, and we love
the, we're fascinated by where that comes across, Mick.
And, and I suspect you're going to answer this, the final question the same way, because
I get the sense you just do stuff, Mick, and you, and it works because you know yourself
really well, but in the spirit of collaboration and, you know, I've already hinted at a few
of your collaborations with great successful people before, but have you ever looked and
thought, God, on that project, that's the person I'd love to, to connect or collaborate
with because that would, uh, would make it come to fruition or, or you did, I get the
feeling you'd probably just go and do it if it, if the thought arrived.
No, well, there's been a lot of mess ups, I can assure you as well.
You don't win every match, you don't win every race.
So, but, um, you know, I've been fortunate as you'd say to, to have met a bunch of good
people and I've done a few things with some, um, some, some great, uh, successful people.
Yeah.
And likewise, the main shareholder in the Jetcraft group, you know, he's probably the
world's best guy.
That's why the, that's why the company Jetcraft is what it is, you know, so you learn a lot
off somebody like him.
Um, so I've been fortunate in that.
The other spaces where I've played, where I don't know anything, um, is, uh, just teaches
you to stay in your lane.
So, so, um, but, uh, but, uh, to, to, to who would I like and what business would I like,
you know, at the moment?
Um, uh,
again, if I don't know much about it, I don't know whether I'd even want to sort of, okay,
let's go and do this.
And Hey, can you give me a hand here?
You know, I don't think that really works, but, but so thankfully, you know, my, the
passions said, whether it just be investment, we've got the right investment team with the
aviation, which is to set earlier, started as a passion and then has grown into a, into
a, a, a, a solid business.
Um, I've been fortunate enough to fall into, into place with the right players.
And, and, and prepared.
Then to stay in your lane and say, this is what I know.
Well, that's right.
And then, and then, and then if I need some, um, external advice and I'm not afraid to
ask for it, I said, final question, but do you still fly?
Do you still jump in?
Not as much as I like.
Yeah.
But I, I still fly helicopters.
I've, um, I'll go and do a renewal probably next week, a biannual flight test.
Um, but, but as you say, like I was just saying, I'm here, there and everywhere.
So, so that restricts the amount of flying.
I'm doing a lot of flying as a passenger.
I'm like, I'm on a plane every other day, but I'm not, um, I'm not physically flying.
I haven't flown a plane since the two thousands, but a helicopter, I've got two and a half
thousand hours in a helicopter and still enjoy flying a helicopter.
But, um, but it's really only again, a passion.
So you just become Mick, the pilot and you forget about everything else.
So that's what I enjoy about, about that.
And, uh, and it's the ultimate off-road vehicle.
You know, we can pretty much pull up at a pub or you can pull up on a beach, stop here,
there.
And everywhere there is a plane, you need a landing strip.
Mick, it's a fascinating story of, uh, of courage and success and sporting success and
success in life in general.
And, uh, I learned a lot just from sitting down in front of you today.
So thanks for taking the time in your, in your busy world.
Really appreciate it.
Pleasure, Luke.
Great to speak with you.
Thanks, Mick.
Thank you for listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast powered by temper, a mattress
like no other.
And to make sure you don't miss an episode, click subscribe wherever you get your podcasts.