I hope you enjoyed this chat with Mike Dunlap,
one of the most respected coaches in the world,
revered for his ability to get the most out of people.
I found myself writing notes all the way through it
from the brilliance of the Miracle Morning
and his passion for daily routines,
his clarity on what makes Michael Jordan the greatest of all time,
having been the senior coach of the team that Michael Jordan owns,
to his respect and empathy for everyone in his environment.
It's full of gold, full of wisdom,
and came across Mike through the work that we are doing
at Alita, a business founded with my great friend Matt Waterwitz
over seven years ago.
Mike, part of our signature program, Alita Connect,
where we connect great leaders around the world,
and Mike is one of the brilliant examples of it.
He collaborates on a monthly basis with John Alawisi,
Craig McRae from the Magpies,
Andrew McDonald from Australian Cricket,
Anthony Seabold, who's got an incredible reputation
in the world of rugby,
and also on a global scale,
Mike's joined one of the Alita Connect programs we have
with Mikel Arteta from Arsenal,
Matt LeFleur, who you'll hear him talk about,
the coach of the Green Bay Packers in this conversation,
and the relationship that they're building.
George Carl is a mentor of his,
and Eddie Jones from English Rugby
has also been a guest on this podcast.
We love the idea of leaders getting together to collaborate.
You don't have to be a global leader
to join one of our signature programs, Alita Connect.
In fact, our passion is connecting people
from small business,
and the arts, and different areas.
And if you're interested in doing it,
simply head to alitacollective.com to find out more.
Up next, a legend in the world of elite coaching,
Mike Dunlap.
Mike Dunlap is the current assistant coach
of the Milwaukee Bucks in the NBA,
a team that he helped win
only their second ever NBA championship in 2021.
In 2012, Mike Dunlap joined
the Michael Jordan-owned Charlotte Bobcats as head coach,
becoming the only coach in NBA history
to triple a team's win
from the preseason.
The NBA Hall of Fame coach,
George Carl, has this to say about Mike.
Mike Dunlap absolutely elevates every player
and team that he comes into contact with.
He's our guy.
He will take you from good to great.
Name any top-level elite coach in the game.
The only difference between Mike and them
is their address.
There is no higher level of coaching ability than his.
There is absolutely no one better.
Mike Dunlap, it's great to catch up with you today.
Thanks for your time.
I'll see you next time.
I suppose high praise from a Hall of Famer in George Carl.
He may have had some beers before he said that,
but that's okay too.
No, I mean, I've been fortunate enough
to have mentors in the business
that were great teachers.
And as you know, being a player,
a former player,
that the ability to teach is everything.
And then the other part of that is to connect,
you know, the words you use to care,
for more than the performance
and get that across to your players is everything.
You talk about that care and connect.
You've had success everywhere you've gone, Mike.
And we always hear the term, you know,
success leaves clues.
And I'm not surprised you started there.
You know, for us, it feels like coaches
are now very much about the whole athlete.
What's been your success to being a consistently great coach?
I would say you're only as good as the talent that you have.
And in the journey,
many of the places that I haven't had success,
all I have to do is run to the nearest mirror.
And I think that if you're asking accountability
of your team and players,
my point is, is that the sport will drive you
if you're open to it, to humility.
Example given, best on ground,
he could be that week and get the medal.
And then the next week he could,
uh,
tear his anterior cruciate.
So I just think that the, the trail of success is,
is, uh, laden with touchstones of humility,
sincerity, and being open to the fact that players make coaches,
coaches don't make players.
Yeah.
I love the, uh, the fact that you go to humility,
Mike, over, over the time.
And, uh, yeah, that is incredible humility because we also know,
you know, that, uh, that elite coaches have consistency in,
in, in success, but you, you bring it back to, you know,
that you're going to get humility in professional sport,
whether you like it or not.
And, and accepting that,
is that sort of part of the process as well?
I think so.
The thing that blocks learning is ego and what feeds ego is a paradox.
You have success and then the blinders start to come up.
And I think it's really important that, you know,
daily that routine getting up early,
working,
hard regardless of the success you've had,
and then attributing,
uh, that success to others and understanding that it's true.
Uh, and really believing that I think what gets in the way is,
you know,
all the back slapping and the high praise,
um, is something that you have to move through.
I don't think you have to fear it,
but I think you have to have a system to process it and move it away from
yourself because hunger is,
uh, really interesting conundrum.
And so in order to continue to have that appetite as you go on,
you've got a vault,
the success that you've had,
um,
and then go on and just stay thirsty for the cutting edge
because the game changes a generationally,
the parenting is different.
So the players that you're getting still want a clarity
competition,
uh, but they want it straight.
And so again,
I think that you have to be very,
very careful with success.
And you might find some of these questions,
uh,
John,
I think you're gonna deflect a lot of them through humility,
but I love this set about you.
One of your former players had this to say,
coach Dunlop came and built upon what my father had already done in my life.
He ushered a lot of us into adulthood with his values of hard work and
commitment and honesty,
the things he has proceeded to,
and still does the abilities and these principles he lives by still today.
It feels like a beautiful thing for a former player to say about you.
Can you expand a bit,
Mike,
on,
on those values that those that come under your leadership talk about?
Well,
regardless of,
of your values,
I think that the seven habits of highly successful people book written by Covey,
um,
he,
he talks about values are one thing and everybody has,
maybe,
maybe different values,
but you just have to have them.
And I thought that the end part of that statement was quite powerful is that,
um,
they transition you,
whether that's work hard,
uh,
give credit where credit is due,
move with great sincerity,
uh,
and understand that life is to be an enjoyed all of those transitional points as a coach or teacher lead you to
trust.
Because if you're not competent,
the surgeon can be a derelict,
he can be an alcoholic 22 hours a day.
But the fact of the matter is when he's sober for those two hours and your best surgeon in the world,
people really don't care about the periphery.
You know,
they're not going to delve in mightily to your values.
They just want to know that you know your job and can do your job.
Yes,
it's more expansive than that,
but the most important thing to get,
to cross to your players and to your staff is that you know your trade,
you know your craft,
you know how players learn because you know the five laws of learning and can you spit those out?
Can you give examples of what they mean?
And can you speak in metaphors and similes to paint a picture because that's what players want.
And a bottom line is that what drives most players is competition.
They want to know who won,
who lost.
There's a book out a long time ago,
written,
by a guy named Novak called the joy of sport.
And he said that all these seven year olds got in a sandbox.
He was observing,
he was doing his dissertation and he said,
before you knew it,
the kids designed their own game and rules.
In other words,
people like rules.
They want to know who won and who lost.
And so a coach's job is to connect and intrinsically get people tap into that competitive warrior like person and say,
okay,
here we go.
Here's a way of getting about it.
And here's how you get the scalp,
so to speak.
And from my standpoint,
you have once you get that in a player,
then you can bring them back to why and manners are important.
Why opening a door for a young lady is,
is timeless.
Why kindness is something that will make you more than just a competitor and a player,
because those things last a lifetime.
They stay in the soul,
if you will,
when you're taking your prowess at 30 or 28 or 32 and all that winning and you go to a halfway house or you go to people who have less than you do and you give away your gifts to them to give them something special on the day because that may be their best day,
given the fact that they're on an oxygen machine.
Yeah,
a bit preachy.
But the fact of the matter is,
is that I don't care where you go.
You'll find that very successful people typically are very kind hearted.
And really,
when you want to be altruistic,
you want to give all those gifts away.
So much gold there,
Mike,
in in your words,
and I'm picking up and writing notes as as you're talking.
And the Stephen Covey book,
Seven Habits of Highly Effective People,
worth a read if you if you haven't.
And and and the joy of sport as well as it is a great,
and I love that you don't separate kind heartedness and being a good person from high performance and you make that link that that's there and also going back to what you said before about you touched on having good habits and people with good routines.
Can you talk about some of those habits?
Because I think that it clearly applies to your world of professional sport,
but also success in life.
Why are those habits so important?
Well,
again,
credit given to a having great English,
English teachers from grade school on up.
And so at some point in time,
I made a decision to be an English major.
There is a book out small book called The Miracle Morning,
and there's an aphorism and an acronym,
if you will,
called Savers.
And in the morning,
if you get up early of solitude and as you know,
Mr.
Rogers said is back in the day is we have a
noisy world.
And as the medium of,
of,
of texting and,
and,
and the computer and all these things came into play for this
generation.
The point is,
is that all this noise is taking you away from reflection and
thinking the value of thinking is one of those habits.
Okay.
Well,
how do I move myself into a habit of sitting early in
the morning before anybody gets up and using the an acronym and
and savers is simple.
It's S is for silence means that you're going to meditate.
A is for affirmations.
And that could be,
you know,
talk positive,
think positive and act positive and drill that into your head.
V is for visualization,
create your own picture on the act of kindness or opening a
door or doing things.
But you have to have your own picture in order to enact
that.
And then you go to E,
E,
E exercise.
Okay.
I only have 10 minutes,
pop down and do some pushups in the say 60 minutes where
you're away from everybody.
If that's the minimum that you've,
that's all you've got to dedicate to it.
Take a bite of the apple and go on.
All right.
Then from there,
you go to,
you know,
S A V E R read.
All right.
So you want to read every day.
That could be the New York or that could be over here.
The Atlantic.
Okay.
That's kind of esoteric.
All right.
Read sports illustrated read off of,
you know,
something that you get that leads you to an article on Twitter,
go to Instagram and somebody suggests something.
And it can be in a myriad of different forms.
And then finally,
the last S is journaling or scribing.
So what I've done is I've taken it through an acronym and then each
day I'll show you my notebook.
I wrote down what you had said to me,
and I'm only looking,
I'm only looking for the eyes of the fish.
You said success leaves clues.
Okay.
So I'm,
I'm stealing from you.
You,
you know,
I'll give what I've got,
but the humility and the connection of validation of another human being,
all you have to do is write something down that they talk about.
When a child has been abused,
you never go directly at the child.
When somebody has a hard time or they've lost a tough game,
you go to a common,
an object as opposed,
it could be a truck in the sandbox.
It could be a teddy bear or whatever,
but you use another medium to get to what you want eventually.
And that's a methodology.
And so I bring myself back to some habits there.
Personally,
I like to meditate second.
I like to do affirmations.
I like to visualize.
I like to exercise.
I love it.
As a matter of fact,
read,
I love,
love,
love to read.
And then,
finally,
I keep journals.
I keep a personal journal.
I keep a log like everybody does on,
you know,
what my day looks like,
what the week looks like,
what the month looks like,
et cetera.
Most successful people do that.
What do you do?
You know,
and then I keep another one where I just,
there are ideas.
You give me something and I'll transition it from success leaves clue to just a
pure book of what I would call ideas or a book.
I like writing poetry.
So a little bit,
weird little bit different,
but that's my life.
And so my point is,
is that I've given you an,
an acronym of some great habits in there.
And you say,
Hey,
that sounds overwhelming to me.
Well then do two of the savers,
because if I stay in your brain,
you say,
Hey,
I remember this dude on the podcast mentioned about the miracle morning.
And then he talked about this an acronym of savers.
And now I go right to a routine,
that I personally don't always accomplish,
but I I I'm picking off at least three or four of them per day.
I like to get all of them,
but I don't honestly.
And then you go from there,
you build from there.
And before you know it,
before you start your day,
you've,
you've already had some major base hits there.
So that's what I do.
I love,
you know,
the miracle morning and I love the,
uh,
the acronym and what,
and what it stands for.
And I,
I really relate to it too,
Mike,
in,
in lots of ways.
Uh,
uh,
I want to delve into a bit of it straight away.
If that's can,
I'm in meditation.
Mindfulness now,
Mike is,
is really a much more known term and something that athletes consistently do.
I feel really lucky to have found that 25 years ago in the world of AFL
football,
which is quite where rare in the Western suburbs of Melbourne back in that time,
but the habit forming.
And as you said,
you know,
you think of the alternative and a lot of kids start the day.
First thing you're on the smartphone,
you,
you know,
you're overwhelmed,
overwhelmed with all of this material.
And that's the first thing that you do that,
you know,
and to not exercise,
to not give you your mind that think time or to not read for,
for better learning.
So it's so much wisdom in,
uh,
in what you say,
what,
what type of meditation do you,
do you prefer?
Mike,
do you mix it up or,
Hey,
um,
you know,
there are a couple of favorites,
but what's awesome on the topic of the cell phone and then the meditation is,
is that with today's youth,
the cell phone is such an attribute,
but it's gotta have a discipline to it.
So we have a no phone zone at certain times during the day.
It could be the dinner table or it could be the coach says,
Hey,
you know,
put a leash on that and put it in your bag and then see it post game.
But whatever the philosophy is of that building or that adult,
but the main point about the cell phone is it's not the enemy,
but like anything,
it is a secondary to the importance of who you are,
how you act and what you do.
And if you let the phone,
it will end up controlling you versus you controlling it.
And that's why I say you've got to put a leash on it.
You got,
you got to get it in its proper place.
And if you start with young adults or anybody else and say,
Hey,
it's the enemy.
And then you,
then you sound like you're 9,000 years old.
And so I think,
I think a better way to approach.
Young adults and footy players and whomever is,
Hey man,
isn't it great.
Look what it does.
But then you have to have an etiquette to the phone,
the phone.
I mean,
it's ridiculous at restaurants when you go in and you know,
the heads down and nobody's conversing and conversation takes a secondary
interactions,
relationships,
all of that.
It's a,
it's a mechanism for people to hide,
to shield themselves,
to not communicate.
And I,
and I always just tell 10 people,
if you're in a room,
if you understand that about the phone,
then you're going to understand that you can get an edge every day.
If you know how to use the phone to your benefit,
but the phone can be a really negative thing.
Okay.
How is it a positive thing to meditation is there's over seven or 800.
All you have to do is Google and go,
I want a 10 minute meditation.
I want a 20 minute.
Meditation or a longer meditation.
And you can go potpourri and it just comes up.
You scroll and you pick what you want.
Personally.
I like one that's 18 minutes and it's waves.
And it's an Australian who takes you through and get you to your
subconscious.
And he goes through four or five markers.
And I would say I've listened to it a thousand times already.
In other words,
it fits me.
And I'm not a guy who has to look at it and say,
this is what I need.
This is what I need.
I'm not a guy who has to look over the fence.
If you talk to any monk or anybody who talks about the fly wheel or the
simplicity of the hedgehog, learn how to do one thing.
Great.
Jim Collins, good to great, et cetera.
He also wrote built to last a dynamic speaker around the world.
But the bottom line is,
is that what you're trying to do is not do a thousand things.
Well, you're trying to do one thing.
Extremely well find your passion.
And then just keep hitting a button.
Okay.
button and the next thing you know, people are giving you money. It's ridiculous. But to have
the discipline to go to the same meditation and to drill down on it and find iterations
and different avenues of what that man is saying to you or what you can expound upon
within your own imagination is timeless and unbelievable. Now I went existential on most
of your audience. I'll bring myself back. But you've got 700 or 800 of those on Google at least
that will take you to another 700 if you're really adventurous and want to find a meditation.
But just go to Google and just type in meditation and it'll give you any kind, standing on your head,
laying down, swimming. I mean, it's ridiculous. So anyway, mine's an 18 minute shot. I find that
that's a success.
fits my day. And, uh, you know, you know, I'm kind of like this, got it done. I feel good about
that part, but there's other things to do. Yeah. I was taught a mantra based transcendental
meditation, which has stayed with me, but, but you're right. And I love you. I love your language
there around putting the leash on the phone. And as a father of four, I think it's the parenting
conversation we have all the time around, you know, it's the number one driver, but I think
you're right when you demonize it, you're underestimated. I love how the kids connect.
I love how they can get together so much simpler than we grew up, but having some boundaries. And
so the Milwaukee Bucks, you left times where the players will say, Hey, it's dinner time or meal
time. Put your phones in your bag. You guys put some leash around that even at NBA level.
Yes. I think everything is about understanding that freedom is responsibility and responsibility
is freedom. You know, when, when over in the United States, they have graduation talks all
the time. And there's a guy that, that is a brilliant writer called
David.
Brooks. He wrote the second mountain, but anyway, he talks about all these fancy people,
whether it's Bill Gates, or it could be, you know, this guy or this woman who has a resume
that weighs not, you know, uh, weighs it's, it's, it's hefty and they're brilliant people and all
that, but they get up there and they tell an audience of 1000 students that are 21 years old,
that are, you know, literally crapping their pants, wondering what the heck they're going to
do with their lives.
And they're saying, Hey, you be you find your passion. Well, what they're doing is they're
just throwing gasoline on the fire. They're not giving them anything that's credible to,
Hey, tell me what to do in the next six months. They don't want to know what to do with the rest
of their life. They just want to not be scared because I know I was sitting in that chair and
I talked to my buddies and we were all sitting there having a beer after graduation. I have no
idea what I'm going to do. And my, my, my, my, my, my point is that it's, it's, it's really important
that each day that we connect with simple things and understand that the complex, if you're a good
teacher, a good leader is to boil it down and hand the mouth, help people understand that,
you know, you being you and freedom has a responsibility attached to it.
And the more you can teach a younger person, my father made me, and we had five of us,
we had to start buying our clothes in the sixth grade. If we needed a little help here or there,
yeah, but you are, and it was custom in our home to start buying our clothes in the sixth grade.
Well, that meant that you had to paint finishes. You had to cut lawn. You had to have a job.
That was just a given in today's age. I don't care if it's the AFL,
and now you've got 18 to 20, 22 year olds. You say, raise your hand if you've had a job
and you would be stunned by the fact that the majority of the room, they've never worked a
job or paid taxes or done whatever. So it just means that's not necessarily the worst thing in
the world. It's what you're inheriting are a lot of people that have not taken traditional steps
to the word responsibility. And when you have a human being that says, give me, give me, give me
it doesn't make them awful. What it means is somebody didn't teach them that.
And so instead of indictment judgment, you say, okay, this is what I've got. And this is where
we've got to go. And anybody can, you know, take somebody that's gifted. That's been disciplined
by great parents, but can you take somebody that's talented, that's lazy or hasn't been
taught properly or has an abusive father and lead them to the right path?
To a higher plateau where they say, Hey, that's not proper to slap a woman. No, we don't do that.
We never do that. And here's why, you know, and then you go down that road, but their model and
what they saw in the home was opposite that. Well, you're not going to fix that young man in a day
or a week. You have to understand it's going to take a process. Well, it's the same thing as the
phone or it's the same thing as freedom. Freedom is a,
arduous process that is not a give me thing. It is actually a type, well, I've got to do A to B to C
and then the door of freedom opens up. Yeah. Brilliantly said, Mike. I love
listening to the way you eloquently describe the pathway to success. And as you said,
you can sit there in front of someone who's, you know, as you said, got a hefty resume.
And I remember sitting there, how is it even possible to even look at that? But, you know,
when you break it down, you've got to be able to say, well, I've got a hefty resume.
I go back to the miracle morning. If you start your day with some reflection and some mindfulness
and some exercise and some affirmation and some visualization and some journaling, you're probably
going to be on the path to finding that yourself. And so, yeah, incredibly brilliant the way that
you've summed that up. I want to change tack, Mike. There's so much to talk to you about and
go to a moment in your life where the greatest athlete on the planet, maybe the greatest athlete
in history, Michael Jordan, owns his own NBA team. He's the majority shareholder of Charlotte
Bobcats, now the Charlotte Hornets. Can you tell us about that phone call, that experience when you
take the NBA senior role and clearly linked to Michael Jordan's got to be a unique experience?
Well, it was, I would just say, you know, working threes because people can digest threes.
Really, because your question begs, what's it like to be in a room with him? And, you know,
what makes him tick? And being in a room with them is he's really aware,
has a sixth sense about the dynamics of people. And he was a tremendous leader,
is a tremendous leader, and has, I would say, good humility given the accolades of being
bestowed and earning that as the greatest player in a sport. You know, there are others,
but he's definitely at the top. And some people want to argue it. That's fine.
But definitely, he's right up there with the top.
Two or three, and then the argument stops. But I would say that everybody that ever watched him
play, highly, highly competitive. And, you know, people will say, okay, he's competitive,
but what does that mean? He's thorough. When he's trying to be a great owner, whether he's trying to
win a golf game or what he did with basketball is, is that he has a flame within him that if he walks
into a room, he has presence. And it's about competing. I mean, he would show up to anything.
And ultimately, he's going to turn it into competition. He can't help himself.
And that's, he's a warrior competitor. And he's going to turn a party into competition. It could
be quarters, it could be a conversation. But so that stands out. You know, so I would say presence,
competitor, and then three, you know, three is, which he tries to keep veiled, but he's service
related. He gives a ton of money that's not tagged, Michael Jordan money, to a lot of
African American colleges in America, not just one. He's got $100 million tagged over the next
decade to go to educational programs and scholarship programs.
My point is, is that there's a degree of humility. And he doesn't want that to boomerang
back and look at me, look what I'm doing. But the big point there on point number three is he's
community related. And he wants to impact and he's impacted Charlotte, you know, not only with
the employment of more than 1000 people in his building and what the Hornets mean to the community.
But he also takes his stack of money,
and gives it away quietly, quietly. So those are the three things that in presence of MJ that
were noticeable to me, there's more and more and more of stories and this, that and the other thing,
but to highlight that is presence, competitor, and community related.
So Mike, to sort of reflect the documentary that he produced was, you know, again, everything he
does becomes, you know, bigger than...
Than anything previously. And that, you know, without understanding the Netflix numbers is a
global phenomenon. And people then got a look on the inside at that last year of Michael Jordan
and him sitting down reflecting back. I mean, a remarkable thing and a time piece to have in lots
of ways. But I think all of us then got a sense of just the drive. And then also, perhaps that,
you know, again, the barroom conversation, you know, did he end up with great camaraderie with
his teammates?
Was that a cost of doing business to be that good? I mean, how did you reflect on looking at that? Did
you think, well, that's just his path to being the best of all time? Or did that come at a cost
in some way in your mind looking at that as well? It always comes at a cost for everybody. You know,
leadership is a lonely role and it's not for everybody. And so if you think you're going to
sit in that chair and, you know, be all things to all people, you're sadly mistaken and you've
never sat in a chair.
You know, whether you're running your own company that's a high-end company, elite, and you're wanting
to be the best, there's a price to be paid. He paid the price. At the moment, you know, when he was
running down the trail and he was a bull, I would say the camaraderie was contentious at times, but
there are other times where he went out with his team, he paid for the bills, they had a great state,
etc.
And they had a really good time. But the vapor of that was an indictment on that he was a roughneck
and that, you know, he was hard to be around at times. It's complicated, but I would say that
I'm on the side of MJ. You know, he didn't hesitate in the documentary to say, this is who I was,
this is what I did. And I thought some of the things that were said about him were,
cowardly, you know, and I'll say it to Pippen, I'll say it to BJ Armstrong or whatever. Not that
they shouldn't have their opinion, but, you know, fly and go see him in his living room
and break it down for him. You know, easy to be filmed and say that, and they wouldn't have said
it the same way had they been in his presence. And so my point is that I'm for him because
if you're going to say what you say, you're going to say it the same way.
And the way you said it, then give the rings to him. Because, you know, I think that also is that
Phil Jackson allowed and wanted him to do part of Phil Jackson's job. You know, some of the
admonishing and going harder and, hey, that's not good enough, should have been in Phil Jackson's
lap, not Jordan's. But Jordan took over and he,
you know, six championships, etc. And everybody said he was the lead dog. Well, when 10 or 20
years goes by, you got to understand that you can't have just all good. You know, there's a
trade-off. And if you want those rings and want to look at them and brag about them and that,
you got to understand that the lead dog did his job. Did he not? Did he not do his job?
Did he do his job? He did his job.
Better than anyone's ever done it before, Mike. And I,
and I thought, you know, I'm going to have to do it.
Very much into your cab. And I think, imagine the privilege of being a teammate. Imagine being
swept up on that train. It would have been brilliant. And as you said, everything comes
at a cost. I think I, you know, wrote that down again and I bring it back to an Australian
connection for me. Luke Longley was part of that. And as Australians, we got to live through the
Chicago Bull era and through Luke Longley and who didn't feature heavily. But I did see,
and a lot of people won't understand this, Michael Jordan sat down with the ABC afterwards
and, uh, I'm having trouble thinking of the, uh, Australian story is the, um, famous program
that does documentary type story. And he sat down with them. And as you said, in terms of curry and
said, Hey, look, you know what? If I look back, we probably did miss out on it, but we're filming
a documentary. You can't tell every part of it. And Luke was a big part of, uh, of the team.
And I'd go and play with Luke anytime again was, was the words that, that he used. So, uh, you
know, I think, um, I think it's a, it's a brilliant. Well, the, the great thing about Luke Longley
is what,
he was a piece of clay. And if we're talking directly about Jordan, uh, Jordan said, here's,
here's the road that we're going to travel, hold onto my hand and I'll take you to a place
that you've never been before. And Luke would admit that. And, um, so Jordan was the bright
light in the room and, you know, there's there, it's not all going to be peaches and cream.
And when you are a dynasty,
it is the hardest thing in the world to do. And if it were easy, everybody'd be doing it.
And the thing that, that, that excellence and living a 1% life means that four in the morning
is four in the morning. You know, I was at an ice cream shop below a hotel in the basement.
And there's a guy named Marinovich, who's a famous weight coach for pro athletes. He had
a son that played at USC and,
went on to play in a very controversial life for the Raiders, et cetera.
Nonetheless, the ice cream shop was a napkin that had Jordan's autograph on it
and said, have a great day, something along those lines.
And that led me down the basement corridor to the weight room,
and he said whenever Jordan came in to Anaheim, he would lift on game day here,
and the things that he did with his weight coach on game day were crazy.
You know, he was doing supersets, squats, lunges, and the whole thing.
And the point of that is that Jordan tortured himself to be the best of the best.
And when you get into that thin air,
it's really hard to explain to anybody who's never lived
the best of the best.
The 4 a.m. life and the 16 to 18-hour day and the pressure of the media
and holding form when you're injured, and to do that and be number one,
I don't care who you investigate, whether it's Steve Jobs or it's Bill Gates
or whatever, they all have their pimples.
They all have their pimples.
But when you look at their work day, when you look at their ability
that they see life differently.
And they have the discipline of free time to say, no, I'm not going to do that.
No, I'm not going to do that.
That, you know, time will speak for eternity on how remarkable Michael Jordan is
and was and will be and a standard for all time.
I mean, Bill Russell, same deal, standard for all time.
Donald Bradman, standard for all time.
Those things are hard.
You know, to do.
And as you know, you can name the best footy players that ever played the game.
Barry Robbins.
I mean, you know, there it is.
I mean, there are only so many greats out there and it comes at a severe price.
Yeah, that's why we love understanding that geniuses and all trying to.
And you described Jordan as the bright light in the room.
The bright light in the room, you're probably around in the NBA at the moment.
Giannis Adedokumbo, who is a two-time.
NBA MVP delivered in lots of ways.
The MVP of the final series 2021 for Milwaukee's second ever championship.
Has he got that sort of genius we just heard you talk about?
Is he in that sort of conversation?
Yeah, he'll move himself to, you know, in the conversation of the top five
in the next couple of years.
If injury doesn't visit his doorstep, everybody knock on wood.
But.
Yes.
I mean, if there's no question, he's 6'11".
He does things on the court that nobody has ever done other than maybe as an athlete.
Wilt Chamberlain was the only one in terms of stride distance is a kind of a scientific thing.
But he has things that he does both physically and mentally and spiritually that are at the highest level.
I mean.
As a competitor, he's like Jordan.
Physically, the ball in his hand is like a golf ball.
That's how big his hand is.
His arms are 7'4".
You know, all of that stuff.
So he has the physical attributes.
And then his free time is consumed in the weight room.
Consumed with shooting.
Practice.
Another session.
And then he does a mental session every day with our sports psychologist.
He's willing to pay the price to have his name eventually put up there with the greats.
Mike, it's a great insight.
We appreciate it.
And also a great reflection, clearly, on the culture you've got at Milwaukee.
You know, to keep a player of that quality.
He's been there for nine years.
You know, the world would be at his door enticing him elsewhere.
I mean, can you speak to that?
Culture, that's a significant achievement to keep him at your club for such a long time.
Yeah.
The Milwaukee Bucks, whether it's John Horst, our general manager, our owners, or everybody else,
our medical people, Coach Bud, Jason Kidd before him, all of that is a village, as they say,
that connected with him.
People would probably want to ask or know, well, what was the one?
Fred, that maybe made him go small market and be loyal.
And it was the fact that he was in abject poverty, sold sunglasses along with his brothers in order to give money back to his family so they could eat.
So doing that at a young age gave him a love for stability.
And he understood the underdog.
The small market, you have to have an ability not to want to go to New York.
Or Miami or L.A., the easy road.
He was raised hard.
You know, like I said, he had a job that taught him how to work hard and also is somewhere along the line.
His mother and his father taught him the value of loyalty.
And what he's getting back from the community and the city of Milwaukee is wherever he goes, he is loved.
And again, he has a set of manners on him.
He understands that, you know, he was given something by the stars and he's going to take full advantage of it.
But if you said, what's the one thing away from the physical attributes that he has is that he is an incredibly humble human being and has a set of manners on him.
Yes, sir.
No, sir.
I don't care who's talking to him.
And whenever he warms up at home.
We have ball boys that rebound for him under the basket.
They could be six years old.
They could be adults or whatever.
He shakes a hand.
He gets done with his routine.
And I've never seen him miss shaking a hand.
I mean, he just knows how to say thank you.
So that makes him very special.
Well, a great story to share, Mike, isn't it?
At that level, I love hearing the words humility come through a lot in the great people that you've had the privilege of being around and working with.
This podcast, Mike, was based on a partnership with one of my oldest friends, Matt Wadowitz, in a leadership business we founded called Alita.
And our signature program is Alita Connect.
And we are really passionate about collaborative groups of leaders from different backgrounds getting together.
And it was your great friend, Brian Gorgian, who's got a huge reputation in Australia for his incredible legacy with Australian basketball and sport and referred you into the world.
And the fact that you can hear the lifelong learning in your language.
You're constantly open to learning.
And you've collaborated with some of our great Australian coaches in recent times.
Craig McRae is doing an incredible job at Collingwood.
Andrew McDonald, Anthony Seabold, John Aloisi from the world of the roundball game.
Can you tell us about your passion to get together and connect with other leaders?
Yeah.
Back to Brian Gorgian.
If you guys, and you probably already know this.
But if you do your homework, take every coach that's ever coached in the history of your life.
Land.
And he's number one.
I'm talking tennis.
I'm talking Charlie Walsh.
I'm talking Lindsey Gaze.
Nobody has a better win percentage or more wins than Brian Gorgian.
And the only reason I mention that is, is that I played for his father.
And at 21, I started going over to Australia and working in Albert Park over in a corner with some of his peers.
And that blossomed into working and being the head coach of the Adelaide 36ers.
I was fortunate enough to be there three years.
But my point is that, you know, I have great friends.
And your selection of friends is everything about who you are.
And even being with, and I don't mean that even being.
But with Matt, he has opened the door to the best of the best in Australia.
And young coaches that are actually.
They're actually in the theater now.
I jumped on that.
Brian provided that for me.
And so I want to give credit to Brian and Matt for bringing me to you, Luke.
So thank you.
But I'm just a hunter of people.
I don't think you have enough friends.
I've heard people say I have enough friends or the ones I really trust.
I can count on one hand.
I'm not that guy.
I don't believe that.
I want to keep opening new cupboards.
I want to keep opening new cupboards to new friends.
Because I think there's an energy to it.
There's a warmth to it.
And I would tell every coach, as you age, start collecting younger and younger friends.
You know, as a coach of college, I was always working between 18 and 22, basically.
So I was infused with youth my whole life.
And so I have all.
And they're going to have marriages.
They're going to have kids.
And so I'm going to all these weddings and stuff.
You know, as.
Somebody who's now 65.
But my point is, is that Pete Newell, who was a great, great basketball coach at the same level as John Wood.
He's Mount Rushmore coach in terms of what he did and all that.
I worked his big man camp for 20 years.
But the one lesson he taught me is he said, young man, having lunch with them.
He said, the one thing I'm going to give you as a gift is this.
You listen to me.
You're going to be fine.
You don't.
You're going to auger in and become old and bitter.
Keep an open mind.
He said, when you go to a clinic or you watch somebody have a notebook, pay homage to them, ask them questions.
Never think you know it all.
And if they're telling you something you already know, write it again because it will reinforce what eventually you'll forget.
And I'm just sitting there.
And I said, you know, like I'm meeting you today for the first time.
It's another opportunity.
It's another opportunity to learn.
And that's the way I look at it.
And then the second admonition is as you get older, you are your experiences.
And then you always want to talk about yesterday.
And I think, again, you have to flush that stuff and codify it and put it on a bookshelf and say, I don't know anything.
Whenever I walk into a room, first thing I say to myself, I don't know anything.
And I always say that person and that person smarter than me.
And it's a really great place.
It's a really great place to start because it puts the antennas up and you're willing to listen to a seven-year-old say something that is profound, Forrest Gump-like.
Or it's somebody that is talking and you think, well, because they have never won a national championship or world championship, why bother?
That's ridiculous.
I went to a class.
My wife stimulated this, but in love and logic.
I tell coaches all the time.
The best class you can ever go to is never the greatest coach of all time.
It's parenting class because in love and logic, whoever is up there, it's their 1200th class.
So that means that they're teaching something in terms of concepts and they've dealt with trouble and problems for 1200 classes.
And so they're dealing with methodology of raising children.
And so I had no idea about.
Phases of children, the fair phase, the phase where the shutout phase, daughter to mother here, it happens at this time here, it comes where the father has to enter and be there on site for two years.
I had no clue of any of this stuff.
But then if you understand parenting, then you're going to understand any player that comes across your radar and they don't all come across.
I, sir, they're going to come across troubled.
They're going to come across.
As a different learner, they're going to come across with a whole host of things where you say, I don't understand them.
Why won't they run hard?
And then now you go to somebody, say, oh, I see what's going on.
There's something that they came to the paddock with.
That's a problem.
So now I'm just going to start giving them a hard one.
And yet they have something there.
It doesn't mean I'm going to give them an out, but how about we call them the assistants take over and put my arm around it.
And I say, Hey.
You know, Graham, what, what, what, what, what happened out there, you know, and then he says, Hey, you know, my girlfriend did this and say, Hey, we're going to get to that later and I'm going to take you to lunch.
But that's no excuse for going from A to B because you wouldn't allow that with a high risk surgeons are going to work on your son.
What's he going to start talking to you about the fact that his wife served him papers for a divorce.
So he's going to stop surgery.
I mean, come on.
And so, I mean, this is the kind of thing you have to be aware of.
And it all goes back to, am I a good learner?
And am I open to the fact that if you want to know how somebody operates, there's a whole nother world underneath that are called triggers where you hear them speak and you go, okay, there's something else I need to get to.
Hey, I noticed that you said this word over here.
Like, uh,
you were struggling with getting your car going, you know, whatever that was.
Well, what did that struggle?
I mean, what's that about?
Well, I'm behind on my bills.
You are.
Well, what are you doing with your money, man?
You got plenty of money.
And now he says, well, you know, I really liked the casino.
Oh, okay.
All right.
So my point is, is that there's always another investigation to be done.
And you have to be open to people.
Who will help and know more than you and almost every aspect of life.
And that's where you go and you ask questions and you listen, you button your mouth and let them teach you.
I love the brilliance of what you said, Mike relates clearly, you know, in sport, dealing with athletes, but in anyone who might be running a business, listen to this or anyone who's managing people is you're not forgiving the behavior of A to B, as you said, but we're going to acknowledge that and we need to work on that.
But let's also find out personally, because all of us have a bad day with the past.
I know all of us, you know, make a mistake at some point in whatever area of our life.
And so, you know, it's where the, the opportunity is and, and, you know, we're coming back without the name dropping element to this, Mike, because I know the humility is, but you have opened up this world of connection and I love it.
And I do it for a reason as well, because when people, you know, your schedule at the Milwaukee Bucks doesn't lend itself, you would think to self reflect and take the time, but you're now, you know, connecting into Matt LaFleur.
As the coach of the Green Bay Packers, who's one of the most revered coaches, Mikel Arteta from Arsenal.
I know you've got another collaborative group going, George Carl, who's obviously a great mentor and friend of yours, Eddie Jones from English Rugby.
So the fact, and we, we just get as excited, Mike, as someone who is running a small business with two people in it, who wants to get together and continue that learning journey and share with others.
And these brilliant young female leaders that in their twenties that we're learning from who are doing things that we couldn't have even dreamed about.
And so for us, our passion is collect, connecting and collecting was probably the wrong word, but in some ways it is these groups of people who want to reflect and learn.
And so when people like you do it, who've had success, it really does, I think, offer a window into lifelong learning, as you said, and your story about keeping an open mind, you know, really resonates.
So thank you for, for A, joining the world we love of a leader, but also your, your, your input and your knowledge has been clearly profound.
So, so thanks again, Mike.
Mike, we've been, for us, identifying what we think great leadership looks like in, in the context of, of the people we've had this great privilege of working with and, and, and spending time with like you.
And we think for us, there are dimensions that are really clear coming out.
The first one is self-leadership that we think most leaders have a real sense of self-leadership.
Does that term resonate with you?
Yeah.
I mean, accountability.
When you say self-leadership is the doorway has got to be, be an accountability.
To walking your talk cliche, but you definitely have to provide an example as, as people are digging in for a long run with you.
And it could be 25 year business could be 40 years, et cetera, is that the connector would be that you have an employee and their child goes to the hospital because they got burned or whatever.
There is no excuse for the leader.
Either.
You know, uh, using zoom FaceTime or going to the hospital to see that child, to show that kind of love, if you will, that, yeah, we have a bottom line and we want to make money, but intrinsically, if you want to connect with somebody forever, those are actions, not words.
And so self-leadership is about what you do, not what you say.
We've seen ladies, another dimension are really conscious now.
And we've heard that in your words already about how they positively impact people in their environment.
You just shared a story of doing that in real time.
That idea of positively impacting others on a daily basis, Mike, does that resonate as well?
Say that one again, please.
Positively impacting others in your environment, latest conscious of, uh, of, you know, really sophisticated about how they on a day-to-day basis have a positive impact.
Is that something you've given thought to?
Yeah.
It, the aura of being positive is validating.
In other words, it'll fizzle out extrinsically on the person, uh, if it's just happy days and you bypass their suffering, every one of your workers, every one of your players has something going on, uh, that, that isn't pleasant.
And to assume the other thing and be, you know, throwing bouquets of flowers all the time will, they will die and wilt.
It's imperative.
Then in order to be that and have great impact.
Energy that you'd be empathetic and have compassion.
And yet you have to get to, Hey, look, we've got a hump of today and we got to get going, you know, but I think that the positivity is a validation of, Hey, this is going to be a hard today.
This is hard because you got something else going on, but yes, we can.
And yes, we will.
And then you roll up your sleeves and whatever that is, they see you also as a hard worker.
As somebody who's not hypocritical, uh, et cetera, because as a leader, your talent has to be to delegate.
You, I mean, you, you know, when I say hard worker, if, if you're constantly down in the engine room, then you have no sight of where the ship is going.
And so you have to, you know, modulate, you have to be up there.
Then you kind of got to move down there, get into the boiler room, be empathetic, validate.
I'm going to say, Hey, that's a great.
Especially when things are good.
We call it praise prompt and lead.
The prompt is, Hey, there's what you did with the shovel to get the coal in the stove.
Let me show you a better way, you know, and now you show it.
So you're kind of being critical because you say you've got a better way that he might slope his shoulders or she might slope her shoulders.
And so you have to say, Hey, you see that body language there?
That's not going to play well because we're going to move through a couple of buyers here.
And so we need to, to have a better shoulders back, eyes up, greet them.
You're important.
And I, I think you're damn good at what you do.
I think you're the best, but I'm going to tell you right now, you got to do better with those shoulders back and give me some eye contact.
We got that boom.
And then walk away from them.
You don't have to sit there and admonish them and you praise them.
You gave them a compliment.
You prompted them, you told them and showed them what you want and now get away from them, you know?
And so those are all methodologies.
So positivity sounds good, but it's amoeba-like and you have to be more specific with it.
And you have to have techniques and skills in order to distribute it so that it's not just a puff of smoke.
Brilliant.
I love that idea of validating the negative, isn't it?
Because that false positivity, yeah, people see through that, you know, really quickly, really quickly.
And I love your method of being able to deliver it in that particular way.
Okay.
Leaders.
We see, you know, in this.
21st century style who have great impact like you are really conscious about how they create and share their vision.
How have you gone about creating and sharing your vision?
Well, ask questions.
Example given is that if you're, you know, running your own corporation or you're a coach, you know, you go in and you paint your vision, but there's no connection.
You're going to end up a dud.
My point is, is that an I am she.
So now your first meeting, you hand out an I am sheet to your team, say six workers, whatever your company, a startup, whatnot.
Within the three pages, you say, hey, worst tragedy in your life, favorite possession, favorite food.
You know, some of those specific questions that might take you 10 years to learn about your wife.
It's amazing.
All of a sudden, you know, you're at a party and it's 10 years later and you hear your wife say something.
You go, oh, I didn't know that.
Well, why the hell did you?
You know that, you know what I'm saying?
Because I think too many times we don't take inventory.
And I think that it's really important, one, to know how to ask great questions and how to note it before you get started on the vision of here's how I want our family to be.
Here are the customs because it has to be collaborative.
It's got to be we, not me.
All those things that we know.
But you better in this day and age, you better say that this is horizontal leadership.
I'll.
Be vertical when you want me to lead, because you know what?
Players and employees don't want horizontal leadership all the time.
They want leadership when the storm comes by the leader.
And so, I mean, you know, you've got it's a balance of horizontal and vertical when the time is right.
You know, like I said, is but you want to rotate the leadership example given.
David Halperstam wrote a book called The 20 Years of Leadership.
20th Century.
He went over to Japan, hung out for a year, wrote a tiny little book.
He's a Pulitzer Prize.
You know, he's dead now, but he he wrote this book.
And in essence, he was saying that the leaders came down on Fridays and that they would be on the conveyor belt and then they would sit and have lunch with the guys.
They actually worked the conveyor belt.
And they said, what idea?
How can we take that step out to be more efficient?
And then they would go back up to their towers, so to speak.
With those.
With those ideas of the workers, plus the workers saw them down there and they got to know their first name, et cetera, et cetera.
So when we're talking about, again, methods and and how you do that, I think you you got to know what you're doing and you got to be confident again about what you're doing and what the vision is.
But and saying that it's a we vision.
Hey, I remember you said that.
Give credit where credit's due.
So like if you're an AFL coach or you're an NBL coach.
You get all this information and you say, hey, I found out a Malcolm Gladwell outlier, blank, the tipping point.
These are all books that he wrote.
The only thing in all those books really that I got from him was common denominators, large amounts of information and saying, hey, what are the four or five bands of they had similar answers all the way through with a tragedy, for example.
He's fatherless.
So they have no model of what it really means to be a male, you know, in terms of a responsible male.
There's a little boy in there and he's got a lot of dysfunction.
And now you may be the first person that he's seen that expects him to be responsible in a way that you're asking him.
And you're talking about this highfalutin vision and that poor guy's in there and he's 12 years old, even though he's in a 22 year old person's body.
I mean, you know, how am I going to bridge that gap and what am I going to do to build trust when everything about the male is trust?
Well, all of a sudden you bring in a female as a sports psychologist and that's his he has a good feeling about, well, that's an avenue to, you know, my mother or a female that helped him.
And now he's with the sports psychologist and the sports psychologist is downloading you, not snitching, but saying, hey, you're going about this the wrong way with your.
Star player. And so my point is the vision has to be inspirational.
It has to be like, hey, we're all competitors.
Does anybody in this room want to be the best of the best?
You know, and everybody's going to raise their hand on that.
That's a layup. Well, start with things that are easy.
Inspirationally, don't start with something like, hey, you want to be a hard worker?
I mean, that's not going to really, you know, get them going.
But if you say, hey, we want to be the best of the best.
And now let's say you had a champion with you on your first meeting and it could be another sport.
And he takes five minutes right from there.
He's a champion. Hey, tell me how it felt when you had the confetti coming down.
What was the parade like? What was that medal like for you?
And all of a sudden he starts talking and you watch the eyes, the pupils.
Man, they just, you know, they're like golf balls and then they go to balloons and then they go to helium balloons.
I mean, my point is, is that, as you can see, I've had the luck of being around Magic Johnson for 10 years.
I worked his camp. I watched him walk in when he was 23.
I mean, you want to talk about a thoroughbred that had a sheen on him and the way he did it with the kids and the competing and the way he talked and the way he didn't know what he was saying and structure.
In my opinion of, hey, here's how to do footwork.
What he did was he calculated.
He captivated them with somebody who came from abject poverty, who had a smile that lit up the earth.
And now he all of a sudden he's with a six year old and he's, you know, taking the ball off him, giving the ball back.
And all of a sudden there's 500 kids around him and he's high five and that.
Well, what's that word? That's vision of inspiration.
And like I said, is if you're not inspirational, get a speaker in front of the group that's inspirational and then go from there.
But ultimately, that's.
That inspiration is going to flare out if you don't go underneath it and say, I care about you for more than a competitor.
There is the aha moment when all of a sudden that allows you to get underneath that.
And you say in your first meeting painting the vision.
Hey, man, close your eyes.
We're going to put it through the uprights.
And it's five, four, three.
And all of a sudden you get to it and you say, can you see it?
Can you see it?
All right, man, we've got a lot of work to do.
Open your eyes.
Boom, boom.
Now that's one mechanism of creating a vision.
And now you have the guy who's won the medal behind you to say, OK, what was your hardest day?
And all of a sudden he starts talking about just a monster day of what he did, say, five, eight years ago.
And they go, God dang, we already did that, you know, or we're doing it harder than that.
Well, that's good.
And if you're not, he is also enhancing the picture of those lock steps that you've got to go through in order to put that ball through the uprights.
That's pretty cool.
So, again, as you can tell, I can go ad nauseum, but it's because of all the other people that have shown me the way.
So much gold everywhere, Mike.
Again, I love the I am sheet, isn't it?
The sort of leapfrog, maybe 10 years of trying to get to know.
Luke, here's what I challenge you to do.
Make three pages of questions you want to ask your wife.
And, you know, write the question down and say, all right, what's your favorite book?
OK, what's your favorite meal?
What if you had one song and it's the last song you ever listened to?
What's it going to be?
And you're going to get answers off of those three pages of whatever you make up.
You can't be wrong.
And I promise you seven of the 10 answers you didn't know.
I promise.
You know, that's that's that's a great day.
That is a great day.
There's nothing to be embarrassed about.
I can do that today.
I've been married 35 years and I promise you, if I start making up random questions, really random questions, I would probably be on the same strike rate.
So my point is, you know, dare to be different.
Dare to build your own dream.
Dare to say stuff that is outrageous.
Hey, if you fall over.
It's all part of the process.
But not daring and not dreaming and not going after it.
It's bullshit.
I love it.
Married 20 years coming up this year.
I will take up your challenge.
It's and you're right.
I've already there's questions that are coming to mind.
And there was something I just picked up when you're talking about that.
I interviewed a brilliant guy that I'm sure you'd be interested.
Dr.
Arnie Rubenstein is bringing back rites of passage to the Western world.
Thousands and thousands of years where we're sophisticated.
Particularly at bringing boys through, because tribes worked out in Arnie's words, he was a GP for 12 years and saw the trouble with adolescent boys and now also girls that if you didn't usher young boys into manhood properly, then civilization didn't work and he was bemoaning the fact that so many leaders around the world has still got that childlike way about them.
They haven't become healthy males and he's got a sophisticated way of making sure we bring back those rites of passage.
And I saw a language very.
Similar to what you were talking about dealing with athletes that had never been led in a way with a healthy understanding of, of how it is to be a proper male in the environment you're talking about.
Um, I wanted to move, uh, to curiosity because it's a word that we see come up with leaders a lot.
And, and, and I tell you what, I mean, the curiosity coming out of you is explosive.
You know, is that, is that a word that resonates?
Yes.
I mean, I'm curious about you.
I'm curious about 20 years.
I'm curious about your son.
Your daughter.
I mean, yeah, they're noted first note on, but you know, uh, yes.
You know, and, and, and asking questions and nurturing questions and also saying, Hey, I don't have the answer to that.
Let me go about getting the answer.
But the trust is built on follow through of saying that it took me two weeks to get to the bottom of that, um, a week, but the follow through the act of saying, Hey, I went out and I said, Hey, I'm going to do this.
I searched that.
And here's what I've gotten.
I don't know if it's the right answer.
You've got humility in there.
You've got the search, but the key to all of it is follow through.
Trust is built on the backs of, uh, a woman of her word, a man of her word.
And when your word breaks, it's okay.
I mean, you're not, it's understandable, but not excusable, but you say, Hey, you know, I let you down here.
And so this thing about I'm a man.
I'm a man.
My word really, well, let's put the video on you for 20 years and see where you broke it.
And, you know, and, and everybody does.
So my point is, you know, your word is your handshake.
Okay, fine.
But where you clench the deal is the follow through.
Okay.
I bagged the groceries on there.
The lady thanks me.
And you, you put the groceries in her car.
All right.
And, and she say, she, she, she gives you a $5, you know, and she says, thank you.
And you look her in the eye and you say, everything.
Every time you're here, Martha, I got you.
All right.
So now the third time she comes through three months later and you don't got her.
Well, you know, you broke your word.
I mean, if we look at ourselves in the mirror, it happens all the time.
So what you're trying to do is win the percentages of the follow through.
And so, you know, being curious is one thing, but be curious with essence and be curious with purpose.
Don't be curious just because you're going to ask a rhetorical question.
Cause you want everybody to think that, you know, I'm curious and that means I'm going to be smart.
Yeah.
You're a smart ass is what you are.
It's, it's, it's brilliant.
The next dimension I wanted to talk to you about, we see leaders are really conscious of communicating with clarity.
You're an English major.
Uh, you went down a path and, and, you know, clearly you've got a way of communicating that, uh, is outstanding.
And how have you thought about that in terms of your leadership?
Um, you already pointed to it, but I'll, I think it's, it's worth repeating is that it's important with your language that you understand that it's a tool and you have to have discipline of tongue, a well-placed F-bomb or, uh, BS or whatever.
I love it.
You know, and I'm, I'm, I'm not.
I'm not going to be stodgy about that, but I have discipline of tongue.
If I'm around young ladies and at a party, I'm, I have discipline of mouth.
I'm not cursing and I'm not, you know, gonna, gonna just tell a body joke after body joke, but a good body joke with everybody leaning in is awesome.
You know?
So, I mean, you have some shouser to you.
I would rather be known as shouserian and slapstick than I would, you know, like, Oh, aren't I witty?
You know, I, I know there's a place for wit, but I'm not that guy.
Um, but you know, uh, offer me red wine.
I can drink it.
But if you say, Hey, I'd rather have a beer and a Barbie that's, I mean, teach his own.
And yet I can dress up and, and, and, and, and have a pinfold Grange with anybody, you know, who couldn't and who wouldn't.
But my, my, my point is that I think that you, you have to modulate, uh, with your language.
Language is the bouquet, uh, to the heart, if you will.
Um, language allows you to open a human being up.
Understanding does, um, if you have to tantalize or poetry or prose that, that is hits a nerve, uh, is the essence.
Like I said, is the example I said is you got a guy suffering at practice.
His body language is an aberration.
And then you,
you take them off to the side and your arms around me and say, Hey man, what gives?
And he said, Hey, I had a really bad day.
And he said, Hey, you know, Graham, I want you to know that that very same thing happened to me.
There's going to be an explosion within that young man.
If you're authentic and you're truthful about that shared experience.
Well, the language of connecting and triggering and igniting people.
So that they want to talk to you again.
That's it's everything.
So the study of vernacular metaphors, you gotta be a great storyteller and we're none of us are when we start out.
But example, given Brian Gorgian, you know, I wanted to know when they won the Rose gold, the game before what happened to Mills.
Mills goes in there with Joe Ingalls and Brian Gorgian walks in and they are, I mean, they.
They had been forth two times over and now it looks like they're going to be forth again.
Here comes Brian through the doors, you know, and everybody is hang dog.
It's dark in the locker room.
All right.
And then here he comes.
Hey, get your head up.
We just almost beat the United States of America.
We will revel in that later.
And you know, Joe Ingalls was looking at him.
Oh, have you lost your mind?
And he goes, no, man.
That is a.
Staging and he looks right at Mills and he says, you will lead us to the promised land.
All right.
I feel that you percolated against the American USA dudes.
We're going to do something nobody has ever done in the history of basketball for Australia.
The flag is high.
And this is an American.
This is not somebody that was born in Australia, but he loves Australia like it's his own.
And so he hits a nerve.
And Mills does something that nobody else has done in the history of the Olympics.
I don't care if he's white, he's brown, he's, you know, he's, he's purple.
He gets 42 points and they broke the sound barrier.
And in the history of the books, when Mills and, and, and Patty's dead and Joe's dead,
God forbid, and Brian's gone, somebody is going to have to read about that team and
the coaching staff that was.
The first of all time for Australian basketball.
And so my point is that inspiration, uh, didn't know if you were going to win, but put it
on the line with his players, got their heads up.
You saw the performance that's magic.
And to me, that happens every day you go into a supermarket or you go down the street.
You can tell when somebody's suffering to take five minutes, you know, and tell,
you know, male or female and just say, Hey man, what, what do you got?
What do you got?
What's going on?
And to take that five, 10, 15 minutes, you mean to tell me you're more important than
that, but, and then you could lift that person and get them to another day.
There's nothing better than that.
That rose gold, uh, the world championship to me, helping somebody else on the same level.
You can have the ring.
I gave my ring to my wife.
She's responsible for the ring.
So when they gave it to me and, you know, Adam Silver's there, and then the owner's
handing the ring, the ceremony, and we're going back to the locker room.
I, well, I actually, I did it before.
There's still the ceremonies going on.
I just got the box and I said, it's yours.
She couldn't get back to her seat.
All the fans in there wanted to take pictures with the ring, all of that.
Some of the other guys were pissed off because I gave my ring to my wife.
And I said,
you know, they were going, God, man, you made me look bad, you know, but my point
wasn't that, that my point is get your priorities straight.
You know, that's a great goal.
And that's what is, but is that where we're going to stop?
And is that who I am?
No, it's a great little thing.
And I want excellence and I want the ring like everybody else, but it's not the essence
of what it's about.
And that's what I'm saying is there's Brian Gorgian.
He's my best friend in the whole world.
I played for his father.
And so I've got a great, great role model who's teaching me how to be humble and understand
that there's much thing, you know, been, been trophies and, and giving somebody life on
the day of saying, Hey, you're, I, you know, that's bad.
That's bad.
And that's bad.
But I want you to know that me stopping here was because of that purple dress that you've
got on.
Stop me.
I think you look pretty good.
And I'm going to say that straight up.
All right.
Second is I love your energy.
You're here today.
You've had these three devastating things happen to you, but here you are.
And to me, that's the essence of a good day, you know, and that's what I'm saying is get
base sense.
Forget about the home runs.
Language is the bouquet to the heart.
That, uh, that is brilliant.
And my hair stands on the back of the neck when you tell, uh, you know, gorgeous story,
the great Brian Gorgian.
I've had the great privilege of doing this, sitting down with him in the podcast and,
and hearing, uh, that story, uh, you know, come to life and seize that moment, you know,
history in Australia.
And as you said, through language and talk about a great storyteller, Brian Gorgian,
uh, is world-class on that.
And, um, it is a great moment.
And, uh, he's the funniest human being in the world.
I don't, he is.
Oh my God.
Oh, and, and put a beer in him.
It is like fireworks.
It's fireworks.
He, I love him.
I love him.
We, we mentioned the collaboration that, uh, probably brought this conversation to life
and clearly a passion about collaboration.
We see leaders value that more than ever.
I mean, how important is collaboration been for you?
Uh, it's everything.
And that's why the, the, the, the payback on collaboration is don't you dare.
If you've had other people help you make sure that your door is always open and, you know,
the word yes comes out of your mouth a lot.
You can't always say yes, because sometimes you're just busy and those things come up,
but sure.
Share your information without charge, be fearless and understand that if you really
believe in your self-esteem and who you are, there are no secrets.
I don't think you have to give everything away.
That's not my point, but my point is be generous and be open and, you know, understand that
you're no big deal.
You know, nobody's a big deal.
Don't do it that way.
You know, do it the other way.
And like you said, is I, was it Rubenstein Rubenstein?
You were talking about earlier.
Yeah.
And what he's talking about are missing chips and building those chips within, uh, young
men in particular, there's been an, uh, uh, you know, uh, an emasculation unintentionally
of, of, uh, uh, generations now of young men who need to be shepherded through to, like
I said, is know how to act and do certain things.
But the problem is, is that the imprint or the modeling is, is broken.
So you, you have to go through these arduous steps in order to reclaim that soul and who
that young man ultimately is going to be because it's worth it.
It's absolutely worth it.
Uh, beautifully, uh, said my, but asking these two questions of all the leaders, I've had
the great privilege of sitting down with like yourself, uh, who has been the greatest leader
in your life?
Uh, in my life, uh, is Ed, Ed Gorge and Brian's father.
Uh, and, and, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh,
uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, and, uh,
I can't leave out my own father.
My, my father was a high-risk surgeon, OBGYN, started his clinic in a log cabin and ended
up being, uh, 55 doctors, Tenenau Valley Clinic.
It's, you know, timeless.
It's still in Fairbanks, Alaska.
And he was the essence of serving your community.
Chief of staff, you go, uh, four years.
He did it for 24 years.
They vote you into the chair.
He retired out of that chair with the Fairbanks Memorial Hospital.
If you go into Fairbanks and you at the time, he was delivering almost every baby in a community of 30,000.
So he gave his heart and soul to a community.
Then you go to Ed Gorgian and just, you know, from being a model as a father to how he raised his sons to coaching me at a tender age where I was very vulnerable.
I would say without question, those two.
And then finally, you know, being with my wife, Molly, for 35 years, you know, you have to be lucky.
But I mean, so she as a leader of our family and the way she's done things to keep everything together, a full credit for her as well.
Well said again.
I love, as you said, the fortune to have great leaders in your life.
And you went straight to it.
There was no hesitation.
And yeah.
Fascinating to hear that in the spirit of collaboration and clear, that's a huge part of who you are already.
And you're connecting with extraordinary leaders around the world, as we mentioned, and our passion for early.
If you could collaborate with anyone in the world, Mike, in any of your areas of passion, is there someone that springs to mind?
Oh, in a global way, John Wooden was in my life as a young man.
And I hung on to his coattails and just kept learning from Coach Wooden.
Pete Newell, who.
I had mentioned it is unbelievable.
I, George Karl, I worked for him and he was phenomenal.
Obviously I mentioned Ed Gorgian, but if you want to talk about people that of fame, those three, George Karl Hall of Fame, Pete Newell Hall of Fame, and Brian Gorgian, again, he's a Hall of Famer in Australia.
Everything that award that they have.
They have over there for the highest awards that they give Brian's in that, that, that stratosphere and then I could go on and on because I have the underpinnings of moving out once a week, Matt LaFleur.
I mean, he's a young coach in the NFL and I seize the opportunity to go to his practice and shadow on we're building a relationship.
So, I mean, I could go probably.
At least 30 minutes and give you a pyramid of, of, of, uh, people, uh, within, uh, David Wheaton, you know, uh, what he introduced me to all these people in Australia and rules footy.
And so Eddie Jones, I was up at the, you know, Canberra and I met Eddie Jones.
He talked to the national team for, and I was helping the national team with Brian.
And so I sat in on him.
So when we see each other on the, the zoom meeting with the world.
Symposium, it's like old home week, you know, and Hey Eddie, how you doing?
Hey, Mike, how you doing?
And so my point is Eddie Jones is very, very, very special.
Charlie Walsh, you know, the greatest cycling coach that Australia has ever had.
Somebody wants to argue that that's okay.
Cause I don't know it like that.
I just know that he was phenomenal with the Olympic team, Bill Nelson, who was the assistant coach with the national swimming team out of Newcastle.
And I mean, I was all over Australia, you know, anybody that, that, that had something, I was, was, was on it.
Um, so yeah, I mean, um, you know, Pat Riley, um, for five years, I watched him coach cause they used our gym at Loyola Marymount.
So I was the caretaker of the key that let them in for their practices.
And I didn't know really who he was.
He was the announcer before he became the head coach.
And so I just.
Sat in there and had a little yellow pad and made notes, you know, on stuff and I knew magic Johnson.
So, I mean, if I go into these places, it's like a bunch of capillaries.
I've, you know, I'm a wanderer in terms of knowledge and, uh, you know, things, you know, I, I think every sport women's volleyball, I can tell you that I used some netball.
Routines on hand.
Eye coordination.
And, and pivots netball teachers.
And, and in particular, the women.
That's why they have such a high rate of anterior cruciate tears is because of the jump stops and netball.
But that's another story, but Jan Sterling, the best female coach in Australia that I ever, ever saw.
And then I would put her in the top five male coaches for sure in Australia and her adroitness, the way she did what she did.
When she was in Adelaide.
Phenomenal.
And so as you see, I feel terrible by leaving out another name.
I can just go.
I mean, Graham Corns was so good to me and I did go to a crow's practice and I watched him do what he did.
And he has anybody who knows Graham Corns knows that he is really good with people.
I mean, he makes you feel good when he walks away from a conversation because he's, he's upbeat.
It's really hard for Graham Corns to be.
Negative.
You know, he's an upbeat human being in the way that he does what he does.
But, you know, so my point is, is that everybody has a little bit to offer.
And my guy, I think it's probably in some ways the, the, my favorite answer.
And I've heard that from, from many people, but you can just say as a life of collecting knowledge and engaging with people, you know, an Australian netball coach to, you know, the, the highest levels of, of your sport and others.
And, and some of the best in the world.
You've clearly got a passion for that continued sharing and learning and, and the humility that comes across in everything you say, Mike, has been inspiring to listen to.
I thank you so much for, for taking the time and it's been a great pleasure to spend the day with you.
Thanks a lot.
Yeah.
Thank you, Luke.
And thank Matt.
And it's one of the best interviews, most insightful and laser like, and I, I can tell you really, really, really prepared.
So I enjoyed it and good health to your family.
I hope we get a, a beer with Brian Gorgian one day would be a lot of fun.
So, well, I need to make that happen the next time we're around.
So thanks again.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me, Luke Darcy, produced by Matt Dwyer with audio production by Darcy Thompson.
Start your leadership journey.
I encourage you to go to elitacollective.com, take our Empowering Leaders Indicator tool and understand the impact you have on your environment.
Join us at Elita to learn, lead and collaborate.
Listen up.
Learn more at elitacollective.com.