If you invest in these young people and you've made them feel good about themselves and you've found positive things and you've connected with them on a personal level,
you know their family and you know their mind, you know what's going on in their life.
Then when you do have to turn the screws and challenge them, I guess I kind of created an atmosphere where be good to them, positive to them, where they don't want to let you down.
You know, you're in a tough stretch and some of your seniors or captains come by, you know, hey coach, man, we got to be better, man.
Well, if you can get it coming from there, man, I think you're more than halfway there.
I always used to say, I used the phrase, can you get a group to take ownership of itself?
That is 85% of it.
Hello and welcome to another episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
At Alita, we are passionate about inspiring connections and creativity.
Creating a world of collaboration.
Our signature program, Alita Connect, curates groups of five to six leaders from diverse backgrounds in sport, industry, social venture and the arts who come together to learn, to connect and to collaborate.
Dr. Troy Flanagan, Vice President of Performance for the Milwaukee Bucks.
I've probably had some of the most radical changes out of that leadership group.
The significance of their work and how much it's really about helping others.
It made me think, what else could I be doing?
And I approached our own.
And within a few weeks, we'd raised $5 million to try and solve obesity in the underprivileged community in Milwaukee.
So that's one spark that that leadership course has caused to contribute and leave the world as a better place.
Umrah Omer, founder of Safari Doctors.
It defines the word creativity for me.
The ability to see connections where none seem to exist.
And I think that's the magic of education.
Definitely not my usual, you know, workshop panels like humanitarian spaces, but more of an intentional dissection of leadership.
The Empowering Leaders podcast is proudly brought to you by Victoria University, where cutting edge sports and exercise science facilities like heat chambers, performance labs and altitude environments mean VU is ranked seventh in the world for sports science.
VU, uniquely you.
As always, a big thank you to Jason Nicholas and his team at Temper Bedding, a mattress like no other.
If you enjoy listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast, be sure to subscribe.
And please, if you have a moment, we would love you to leave a review so we can reach more listeners and empower more leaders.
If you ask anyone in the world of college basketball about Mike Bray, you'll hear a common theme.
He's one of the most respected and most successful coaches of his generation.
Mike inherited a program.
It had been absent from the NCAA tournament for a decade and turned it into a perennial contender.
His impact on the game is the stuff of legend.
The all-time winningest coach in Notre Dame history, he guided the Irish to 13 NCAA tournament appearances, three Sweet 16s, back-to-back Elite Eights and a historic AACC championship.
And across 23 seasons, his team played with a signature confidence, freedom and resilience, an extension of the man that was leading them.
Beyond the wins, Mike's impact.
Mike extends far beyond the court, a mentor to countless players, a leader in the coaching community.
He's helped raise millions for Coaches vs. Cancer, served as president of the National Association of Basketball Coaches, and built a reputation as one of the most likable figures in the game.
After more than two decades leading Notre Dame, Mike has taken on a new challenge, joining the Atlanta Hawks coaching staff as an assistant coach in June 2023.
Mike, they say you're the loosest coach in America and one of the finest basketball minds.
Great to have you on the show today.
Thank you.
Luke, it's great to be with you.
I'm honored.
And, you know, you can be a lot looser when you're assistant now instead of a head coach.
You know, my blood pressure is a lot better as an assistant.
Hey, Mike, when I hear that back, it just sounds like a full life.
When you hear all of your history read back to you, what's the feeling that comes to you?
You know, I look and go, you know, as I was listening to you, I'm flattered and I have been one lucky dude.
I've been I've had great mentors and I know we're going to get into that.
And and and I've been able to get to some amazing programs and universities.
And what's neat about this NBA experience is I was in the game 40 years and I felt the last two years like it's professional development.
I'm learning again because the NBA is a different style than college and it's run differently.
And I have been.
I've been like energized again to be learning about the game of basketball in year 45 in the game.
Well, I love that, Mike.
We might just go straight down to that road as a jumping off point.
As you said, 45 years of history and your reputation has an extraordinary history to it.
But can you tell us a bit about the difference from coaching NBA professional athletes to to the college athletes you spent your life with?
You know, the question I got last year.
In my first year with the Hawks was what's the what's the biggest difference?
The neat thing about the NBA, it's it's really all basketball.
You are digging in the college game here in the States is only 25 percent coaching the game.
And the other 75 percent is recruiting and now raising money for name, image and likeness and being an ambassador for the university, which which I enjoyed and I loved and respected at Notre Dame.
But to dig into the game X and O wise, you're not recruiting.
The front office is handling the acquisition of talent in the NBA.
You're not raising money.
The owner certainly has got plenty of money if he wants to spend it.
And so it's from that point of view.
The other side of it was I don't know how many guys said, well, why would you want to coach in the NBA?
And you hear this through the States because those guys don't want to be coached.
They've made all their money.
They don't want to be coached.
I have found that to be completely untrue.
And I have been energized seeing our particular roster just want to be engaged.
How can I be better?
And this is their craft.
You know, this level of athlete has been kind of probably tracking toward this since 12 or 13 years old.
And they're very serious about their craft.
And so I have found them to be amazingly receptive.
To coaching.
And that old wives' tale that people say in the States, oh, they don't want to be coached.
They got their money.
Not true.
Well, nice to spell one of those rumors out off the top.
And I want to dive back into your history.
And you mentioned the great mentors you've had.
Your story starts well before Notre Dame.
You grew up in a family of elite athletes and educators.
Played college basketball at Northwestern State and George Washington.
And you learned the game.
You played the game under the legendary Morgan Wooden at DeMartha.
And it sounds like a pretty idyllic upbringing in the sport that you love.
Can you go back and tell us a bit about all of that?
I was so fortunate when I think about my mentors.
And I start with my parents who were both educators.
You know, the dinner table talk was what they did in their class or with their teams.
And a shout out to my mother because she came to Melbourne, Australia in 1956
and swam for the U.S. Olympic team.
And she was an Olympian in Melbourne.
So Australia has always been very special in our family's heart because mom had pictures
and videos of the training facilities were a lot different in 56.
If you can imagine, Luke, I look at the videos sometimes and it was just amazing.
But they were both educators and teachers and coaches.
And what struck me was their students many times came up to me and would say,
without my parents.
Man, I love your mom.
She's awesome.
You know how she's helped me or your dad's been great.
And I was like, you know, I want to do that.
I want to have that impact on young people.
And I think it started there in the home family of educators.
I played for Morgan Wooten at DeMartha High School, who he's in the Hall of Fame.
But he was truly an educator.
Yes, he was a good basketball mind, but he was an educator.
He was a he was someone who helped young people.
And I was so fortunate, Luke, that I played for him.
And then when I finished playing at George Washington University,
I came back and coached with him.
And his selling point to me was because I almost took I almost took a college
graduate assistant job at GGW.
And he said, you know, you need to come back with me because if you want to really do this,
you need to have your own team.
I'm going to give you the JV.
And at 22, I had the junior varsity.
At DeMartha High School, I taught six classes of history.
Catholic high schools, they wear you out.
They don't pay anything.
We ran bingos on the weekend to raise money.
You know, the Catholics are unbelievable about how they can raise money.
And I learned to work my backside off, helped him and was there for five seasons before
I went to Duke.
So my DeMartha experience as a young person around Coach Wooten and then as his right
hand man, you know, he had an unbelievable.
And he was truly an educator, a positive guy, a an educator who made young people feel good
about themselves.
And it sounds like that's been a theme for you across your life.
And I love these conversations because often people can pinpoint they are lucky enough
to have someone in their life like you described Coach Wooten as and or a great educator or
teacher that really was a sliding door moment who just believed in them and invested in
them.
Has that been something you've been conscious of the amount of young people that have come
through your world that you can really change someone's life?
Yeah, there's no question.
I've been so lucky starting as a high school educator and, of course, being around my parents
who were high school educators.
I've always felt, even though I was a college coach at a high profile university, to kind
of be that teacher and confidence giving educator that I witnessed with my parents and certainly,
with Coach Wooten.
My mom used to have a saying, you know, make them feel like a million bucks.
You know, if you can do that with your young people, and I used to laugh at it, I think
back now, and it's really kind of how you've tried to work with young people and help them
and help them to be more confident.
Well, it's interesting, Mike, isn't it?
Because sometimes your reputation in sport and I certainly grew up in an era where coaches
were pretty hard.
They were pretty, you know, I would say mean-spirited at times and you got abused and if you could
cope with that, that was a generation that we sort of grew up with here in Australia.
But the term, the loosest coach in America, but loose is really your calmness under pressure
and you see you on the sidelines.
There's chaos going on everywhere, but you've got this calm, relaxed demeanor.
Is that just you or did you work on that?
Well, there's no question that sometimes you are having to fake that.
Let's be honest, Luke.
When it's hitting the fan during some times or you've lost three in a row and I was inside,
you may be a lot different, but I always felt what I projected was going to really affect
my group and the crowd and the whole bit.
And I think when I came into that, we were talking with the media after a game once and
uptight, are you nervous?
And they were, it's a big game or I said, look, I'm the loosest coach in America.
Well, that thing ran, I mean, it went viral.
And so I've run, I ran with it.
There is no question that there's days I was extremely firm with my group, probably behind
closed doors.
I never wanted to embarrass anyone in a setting of, certainly a setting of 15,000 people and
on ESPN.
Never wanted a young person to be put in that spot.
Yeah.
You know, you, you had some standards and you had your firmness and you had to show those
days.
And there were days where you knew you had to be a little edgy and I would wake up that
morning and go, son of a gun is one of those days I'm all have to do it.
And three o'clock was practice and I'd work myself up to it and, uh, and be a pain for
maybe 30 minutes of a two hour practice and see if you could get a message.
But I never let them, I never let them leave on a bad note.
I was always trying to find a way to end it positively and, and end it with hope.
Especially if you've lost a couple and young people are searching and we're all wondering
and we're dying for a win.
How do we leave them with some hope and some confidence and that type of thing.
But, uh, yeah, the loosest coach thing is stuck and what the heck I run with it now.
The worst things to be known as, uh, I want to go back to your mom's wisdom, make people
feel like a million bucks and, you know, I love the opportunity to sit next to a legendary
coach like you.
So that when is it for you, if you build all that confidence and you build all that trust,
when you need to be hard, you've got a lot of equity in that relationship and people
are going to take that feedback a lot better because you've invested in them over the time.
Is that sort of a way of framing the way you've gone about it?
Luke, you nailed it right there.
If you invest in these young people and you've made them feel good about themselves.
Yeah.
And you found positive things and you've connected them, connected with them on a personal level
and you're at, you know, you know, their family and you know, their mind, you know, what's
going on in their life.
Then when you do have to turn the screws and challenge them, I guess I kind of created
an atmosphere where be good to, you know, be good to them, positive to them where they
don't want to let you down, where they feel bad when they let you down and you could show
a little bit of, you know, you kind of let me down tonight, fellows, and if you have
established some leadership and, you know, that can permeate through a locker room and
you have trust with your guys and my assistant, I used to have assistants say, you're too
good to them.
You're going too easy on them.
There's a bigger picture here.
This is a long road.
And so, you know, I kind of, when I think back, guys, you're in a tough spot.
You're in a tough stretch.
And some of your seniors or captains come by, you know, before head coach, man, we gotta
be better, man.
Well, if you can get it coming from there, man, I think you're more than halfway there,
you know, with a group that has, I always used to say, I use the phrase, can you get
a group to take ownership of itself?
That is 85% of it.
Can they take ownership of themselves?
And I used to add on that phrase and I use it at coaches clinics.
Now, who's selling your stuff coach, when you ain't around, who's selling my stuff?
Do I have the relationships with my senior captains who, when I ain't around or I leave
the locker room and I've challenged them, they go, he's right, man.
He's right.
If they give it this one or roll their eyes, then we probably got a problem, you know,
but who, who's selling your stuff and have you nurtured those relationships where those
people.
Can help take control of the ownership, uh, of a group and might the evidence is there,
the sustained success you enjoyed over a long period of time.
And you voted the national coach of the year on a, on a couple of occasions in your words.
And I, I suspect you're gonna be too humble to, to delve too deeply, but putting all that
together, what was the thing that enabled you to have that continued sustained success?
You know, I, I think you have to have great energy every day.
And then how do you pace yourself?
I got better at it as I got a little more experienced as a head coach.
How can I be at my best from four to six when we practice this afternoon and you know, in
a college job, you're putting out a lot of fires, you're recruiting, you're doing, there's
things you're doing maybe during the day, but when you get to four o'clock, you better
be mentally ready.
And there are days when you're thoroughly wiped out, exhausted, and maybe not in the
best of places.
Yeah.
Buddy, you have to fake it.
Those are the days you got to come out and where they actually look at you like, how
in the hell is he doing that today?
Now you go pass out as soon as they leave the gym, you can go pass out in your office.
But when they're, when you're up in front of them and they're feeling you, you know,
and, and I, I always tried, you know, it was interesting.
Your guys are stretching before.
I always 15 guys, it's easy to do 12 guys really on a college team, bump every one of
them.
And while they're stretching, we have a five minute stretch and they're on, they're doing
a thing.
Jimmy, what's up?
How are we doing?
How'd you have that Tesco today?
Nothing bad.
You know, you good.
You're going to smile today or you're going to play any defense today.
Oh, coach, what are you talking?
You know, just bump everybody before we get to the group huddle and we get into our stuff,
just kind of touching everybody up so that you have that personal thing.
And, and, uh, uh, and that, you know, that was always on my, always on my mind.
Yeah, brilliantly said.
And that, that personal touch, it makes a lot of sense.
Could you sum up your coaching philosophy, uh, in a, in a, in a few sentences?
Is there a way to, to articulate it?
Yeah.
And it, and I'll give a coach Wooten, Morgan Wooten, we would work his basketball camp
and I was a little young to understand this, but he used the phrase, we were working with
young people.
He said, Hey, be the kind of coach you'd want your own son and daughter to play for.
And I thought to myself, my son played college football, my daughter played volleyball.
And when I think, and I use that in coaching clinics now, and it's, and it, it hits home.
You can tell when you say it, the high school educator coaches, like, you know, be the kind
of coach you want your own son and daughter to play for.
And, and if you kind of start with that basis, I think you're going to handle young people
the right way.
Uh, find power.
Positive things, encouragement, those types of things.
And that was a Morgan Wooten back in 1975.
And I still hang on to it.
It's a, it's a great one line statement, isn't it?
Because it sums up so much, doesn't it?
And, and I want to jump into, you know, as you said, your kids go and play college sport
and you get to see from the other angle, tell us about your parenting style as someone who's
lived that world.
How did you allow them to have the space?
achieve their dreams you know my son played college football at the university of buffalo
he's a high school coach down in florida now and you know when he played when he was growing up
and he played byo bad he played everything i just made a point to be really in the background
low-key sit at the top of the bleachers and not bring anything up unless he asked me and and
certainly the great blessing was that he played football and i couldn't screw him up because i
don't know football but i have i've dealt with a lot of parents you know handling parents is part
of it in in high school and certainly college the parent situation is part of it and i think i have
a lot of experience with it many very good ones some that were nightmares but you got to manage
it because you're managing the young person and one time
i slipped into bad parent so my son was a tight end h-back blocking tight end they never threw to
him because he couldn't really run but he could block his backside off so one summer he's home
and we're sitting there at dinner i go hey kyle you ever talk to your like tight end coach that
maybe they put you out in the flat now i'm going to be an expert right now i'm going to be
put you out in the flat just pop it to you for a little five yard out and he turns me goes dad
i got my scholarship
scholarship because i blocked just shut up and i go lesson learned i'm back in my right parent
mode i'm going to shut up but even i creeped into that world yeah why don't they throw to
you a little bit he's like dad i'm a blocker that's the only time i'll ever play isn't that
a great story my and i love that you said the one moment that you slipped because you know i'm going
to be a little more blunt i i see crazy parents at junior sport yeah who do ridiculous things
and i it makes me sad because i just see the impact it has on their kids and they take away
the joy of sport now they're well-meaning like you and i and and we love our sport and we love
our kids but you're so subtle and and i hope i've parented the same way with my four it's exactly
how i've tried to it's like this is your life you don't need you've got coaches you've got people
around you i don't need to be your coach i want to be your dad i want to be uh in the background
like you sitting there and being supportive but you just see the parents through what they're
i think has been loving to their kids but they're really micro managing them they're over the top
they're screaming from the sidelines and it seems pretty destructive to me mike i i think it's a bit
of an issue we've got that i don't know how to put the genie back in the bottle but i think you
probably answered it before it's really a problem luke i mean it it's it's sad to see and when i
would be in the recruiting college circuit the aau circuit and yeah i know scholarships are on
the line heck now money's on the line with name image and likeness so it's
really it's really an issue but you know that story with my son i would have parents concerned
parents my son's not playing enough my son's role and when i would meet with them i would use that
story sometimes to kind of show how my son shut me down just to kind of send a message indirectly
to my players parents like you know even i had a big mouth and my son told me to shut up because
in a lot of ways the young person especially the cop they they
they're very uncomfortable when their parents get involved you know and that was a dynamic
you know you had to manage i know i many times i'd have a player we're talking and he said
what coach my dad didn't call you did he said no no no now i i would never tell him the truth
you know unless it got really crazy but my dad my dad didn't call you right no no this is me and you
man to man he's 20 year old college i gotta you know deal with you and and that's really kind of
Notre Dame i'll talk to the parents about academics if we have some issues health whatever
but we are not going to talk basketball with parents my assistants i told my assistants you
diffuse the parents and every now and then just give them a call check in every two weeks now
you're going to get you're going to get some lightning probably because i've been an assistant
in college and got lightning from a parent after a game and nobody hit me harder than Bobby Hurley's
father a couple times and he was starting
every game from his freshman year on. But as the head coach, you've got to have that layer
of protection and really make it about the young person and it's me and you. We're going to have
to work this out. I'm going to ask you about the deep involvement you've had, coaches versus cancer,
and you've put an enormous amount of your own energy and resources and time into something
that's clearly inspired you to take action. Tell us about your passion for that.
Well, you know, my dad had a malignant melanoma in the late and mid-90s when I was at the
University of Delaware and this coaches versus cancer program, which is sponsored by the National
Association of Basketball Coaches here in the United States. That is the chosen charity. It
got started back in the mid-90s and so I jumped in on it at Delaware. We raised some really good
money. The neat thing about the charity, 95% of the funds stay in your community.
And so then when we went to Notre Dame, it really exploded. And the cool thing is,
I think we raised enough money at Notre Dame and the coach that replaced me, Micah Shrewsbury,
has continued the charity, which is awesome, but it's sponsored five or six grants at the
Harper Cancer Center on the Notre Dame campus, which was really cool. And as we know, cancer
actually got a shot at kind of beating it up a little bit the last, what, 10, 15 years,
per se. We may be able to win this thing, so let's keep doing it. But what it did also,
it was certainly a great charity and a great thing, but it got me involved in the community
and seen in my community in a different way, not just the basketball coach at Delaware at Notre
Dame. And I think that's really important in your community. These are your season ticket holders.
These are your supporters. These are the people that when you have a tough season are either going
to go, oh, I'm going to go to Notre Dame. I'm going to go to Notre Dame. I'm going to go to Notre
Dame. So we got them or we don't got them. And when they see you and you in a different light,
other than just the coach, the more human side and get to know you, I think it's very powerful
from that standpoint as well, not just the great deed of trying to kick cancer's ass.
It sort of leads me to another, your whole world has been, you understand the coaching landscape,
you're now in the...
Incredibly competitive world of professional basketball, one of the most elite sports in the
world. And the pressure that comes on senior, from those stakeholders, that it's unrealistic.
You either win a championship or you fail, it seems, and you can go into the English Premier
League or sports all around the world. And you've got these hyper media, you lose three games and
you want to sack one of the great coaches of all time. What's your advice to coaches listening on
that amount of stakeholder pressure that comes their way?
This is what I'd say to guys. And I see young guys on the road or we meet for a game and are
struggling and they go into this and that. I said, hey, this still beats a real job. Remember,
this still beats a real job. They're like, yeah, yeah, coach, you're right. You're right. You're
right. Now I had to remind myself many times, you lose four or five in a row and a South Bend,
Indiana winner, it gets a little dark, you know, and you could go to some dark places.
But, you know, we're, everybody's been well compensated in the coaching profession.
And I use the phrase too, we all know what we signed up for. Like we know what we signed up
for. Now this is high risk, high reward business. The highs are amazingly high. The lows can be
amazingly low. Can you find a little bit of a midpoint and a balance point and keep it in
perspective? And I think I got better at that as I got a little more experienced.
Yeah. As a coach.
It's a great answer as it always felt. Your worst day as a professional athlete is
probably someone's best day. Even when you're injured, you're in the gym, you're surrounded by
community and great perspective is not always an easy thing to see, but when you can, it changes
your life. We all are born different. As we grow, the experiences we have develop into outlooks,
uniquely our own.
No one sees an idea, opinion, or opportunity like you. And no one sees you like VU. Victoria
University. Uniquely you.
Hi, my name's Mim. I do a Bachelor of Social Work. I got this tattoo done for my 20th birthday
present because I was born as a twin, but she passed away because my mum had ovarian cancer
during pregnancy. So my name's Mirian Deer.
My name is Mirian Deer, which means rainbow. And it means the bridge between, for our ancestors
to reach their afterlife, which is what my sister was called, which is the Wadatutti,
which is the Milky Way. And that's where they go as the stars and they live there.
VU is very supportive. It doesn't matter if you're an Indigenous student,
wouldn't they bother to make sure that you're very well taken care of?
At Alita, our signature program, Alita Connect, is something we're really passionate and proud of.
We bring together groups of five to six people.
Around the globe from diverse backgrounds, sport, industry, social venture, and the arts,
we come together to learn, to connect, and to collaborate.
Vanessa Ford, Chief Operating Officer at Kukua.
The Alita Connect experience for me has been transformational. I met people that I would
never have met from totally different spheres. It's very basic. It's all about relationships.
It's all about how we communicate. And what the Alita Connect group does that is so powerful
is when you bring two people together, you're able to connect. And that's what Alita Connect does.
It's all about how we communicate. And what the Alita Connect group does that is so powerful,
From two totally different worlds together, there's no ego. It just leaves room for the real you.
And I think that's what Alita gave me, was bringing back the real me and really connecting
to my own leadership style. I've got to delve into a young
athlete under your care at the moment at the Hawks, a young Australian by the name of Dyson
Daniels, who's having a great season and making a big impact. Tell us a bit about him.
You mean the great?
The great barrier thief, as he has been dubbed here in the United States. And I know you have
a connection to the family. And he has been, first of all, if he doesn't get defensive player
of the year, I'm going to go on a major protest to the NBA offices in New York. But he has been,
for a young player, a young prospect, he's kind of found himself here. I think Quinn Snyder's done a
fabulous job. He's done a fabulous job. He's done a fabulous job. He's done a fabulous job.
He's done a fabulous job with his psyche and getting him more confident. And what he's doing
defensively, I'll say this, Luke, and you probably saw it over there as a young player. I have been
around this game 45 years. I've never seen a player with the defensive instincts to get a hand
on a ball, anticipate a steal. You can't teach it. There's no way. And he'll come up with, he comes
up with, he's averaging three a game, which leads to, he's averaging three a game, which leads to,
but he'll come and the assistant that sits next to him, we just look at each other and go,
are you kidding me? Like, that's unbelievable. And he's done it at crunch time many times. Now
he's become a more aggressive and comfortable offensive player. He's scoring, he's shooting
that floater that I think has front spin on it. That must be an Australian rules football kind of
fundamental. And, you know, so when I dap him up, you know, when you, when he loves golf, as you
know, he loves golf. He loves golf. He loves golf. He loves golf. He loves golf. He loves golf. He loves
to play golf. So we always dap up with the golf grip before the game, you know, I always hit him
with the golf grip, but now that's my way of kind of trying to loosen them up. Even though the man
is so steady, he shows no, he just is right there physically durable. I have been so impressed. And
he, you know, you think about the future of the Hawks with a rock solid player person, he's going
to eventually become a voice.
And I, I just, you gotta be awfully proud. I mean, watching him, it, it's a, it's an amazing
story. And here's, I saw when I was an assistant coach at Duke university, I saw his dad play in
high school. That's how far we go back. What a great, great story. And, um, sorry,
as a 12 year old, he was a beautiful athlete then. And it's a, it's great to say, what a,
what a way to endear yourself to your teammates by being one of the great defensive players and
doing the team things.
I love asking these sets of questions to people with your wisdom and, and history and these
patterns of leadership that we're a bit obsessed about in, in the world of a leader. We start with
this idea of, uh, you know, self-leadership. Is there one thing that's always worked for you as
a leader that you would never change? Being, um, always accessible for your players. Um,
my door was always open in the office. And I told my administrative assistant,
I'm on the phone or I'm in something. And a player happens to walk into the offices,
stop me and have a channel him through channel him through it. And maybe 30 seconds. Hey, what's
that? How was class test? Whatever. Oh, by the way, today, defensively, just get a little plug
in pick and roll defense. We're going to got, you know, just how's mom. How's your brother doing?
He played last night, something touching them when they come through and, and having that
personal touch. And then, and then, you know, can you be, can you be, can you be, can you be
humble and they feel it's about them. And, you know, I never wanted to be on the media guide.
It, you know, they used to do, they don't do it anymore. They're all online, but they used to
print these big old media guides and there's, well, coach this year, we want you with the
captain's. I don't, I don't want to, I don't want to be on that. No, no, no. Have them on there.
You know, can you, can you have it even at press conferences when it'd be the coach and two players,
they would ask me a question. And I, a lot of times,
would turn to Pat, what, what do you think? And have them be the spokesman. So they feel like,
man, he's, he wants us to be on selfish. He's amazingly coaches on selfish, man. You know,
we would fly in the NCAA tournament. We would charter bigger planes. There was a first class
section players always sat up there. I'm in the back man. There's I'm always a no, no coach.
There's an extra one. Nope, nope, nope. You got it. Put the senior manager up there.
Um, you go in to eat, eat last one. There there's a great book entitled leaders eat last
stand in the back. We'll get there. Let everybody, you know, just, just so they kind of feel, you
know, it's, it's, it's them. It's not about you and that they know you really got their back when
they've been punched, you know, and that you can say in front of them and to the media cut fellas.
I, I, I screwed up. I should have helped you more tonight.
We, now we got to do these three things better, but I, I I've screwed up with that and we're going
to address that tomorrow. And, you know, and, and, and not I coach good. They play bad. I mean,
when you get into that buddy, you're going to lose them. You know, I love the, the, the pattern
of that, Morgan, you described in such a brilliant way, but leaders that take accountability together
or put their hand up if it didn't go right. And also that, that common thing around that genuine,
authentic care for people.
In whatever discipline, it seems something you've been brilliant at for, for 45 years.
How do you fill your own cup up, Mike, to make sure that you can lead others the way you want to?
You know, who was it? Tony Blair was on a thing that CNN did about five years ago. It was a
leadership thing. And he said, most leaders don't take or make the time for creative thought
because when you're running the thing, it's coming at you so fast and you can get caught up,
you know, in the little things and the minutiae and things that hopefully you can learn to
delegate. But where do you get away to kind of think creatively? Mine has been swimming. My mom,
you know, she tried to make a swimmer out of me. Great story, Luke. She caught me sneaking out of
swimming practice when I was 10 years old and I begged her to go to basketball camp and the rest
is history. And she, I was sneaking. I was like, mom, I'm not, now my sister swam and she was an
LSU, but there was no way I was doing that like her. Now I do it. And when I, when I, what I loved
it, cause I would swim in the morning when I was at Notre Dame and I could, you know, what's great
when your head's underwater, no one can talk to you. Nobody can talk to you. Nobody can interrupt
you. And I would swim for 30 minutes and I would think about my day practice plan this, who do I
touch? And so that was kind of not only get your cardio, your physical stuff, but also get your
mental stuff. But it was my mental stuff too. And, and in a, you know, so that, that, that was a
nice routine when I was a head coach, you know, I, I would always go to breakfast by myself. I had a
spot I would go. I didn't want to, you know, I would sit in a corner. They kind of would hide
me out in this one restaurant in South Bend. I got a few here in Atlanta and you could kind of
think a little bit and get your day organized. Mark, can you tell a story of a visionary later
inspired you to follow their vision? You know, I was so lucky with Morgan Wooten and then I did
eight years with Mike Krzyzewski and, and that was, you know, such a masterclass in leadership
and preparation. And one of the phrases that I think I picked up many, but, but the one theme was
as a college coach, you're running your program, just, we got to compete every day and you may be
competing more in May and August in recruiting.
Or what you're doing then, then during the season, just wake up ready to compete every day.
And, you know, that, that was a theme and, uh, uh, that, that Mike K I think really instilled in it.
He, he lived it. And, and I think as young assistants, and there were many of us that
came through and went on Quinn Snyder being one of them, um, as well. And, and you kind of learned
how to really think about in the morning, you know, what are we doing?
Today to get better. And it made it's May. It's not a practice day. What, what are we doing today?
Are we doing it in recruiting? Are we doing it in marketing? Are we doing it? And as we sit down
and talk about our attack against his own defense, you know, and, and that was, um, that was a great
vibe for me to be around as an assistant for eight years.
Mike, you mentioned Tony Blair and, uh, carving out time for creativity. And we, we see
inherently curious people have success like yours.
How do you find time to fill that curiosity cup up for yourself?
Yeah. And I'll tell you the last two years, what's been great is the NBA has been such a new world.
I was a college coach for 35 years and then to go to the NBA and I watched the NBA, but I never
really dug into it. I would watch the playoffs after our season, but now you have different
coaches, different styles of play, philosophically, 24 second shot clock. The rules are different. The
game is 48 minutes, not 40, like in college. And there's it. So it was almost in a way like a
different sport and it was energizing on a daily basis. Okay. We got Charlotte tonight.
What do they do? What's this coach known for? I knew that in the ACC, I knew that you got to know
the guys and how they played and that what their style of play was. So that has been like amazingly
refreshing to learn. The neat aspect of being in the NBA is the players,
most, I saw most of these guys. You talked about seeing Dyson when he was 12. I saw these guys when
they were 13 and 14 playing on the AAU circuit. I recruited many of them. I have like a reference
point with them and I'll say, Hey, I remember when you played into Peach Jam, which is a big
Nike tournament in Georgia. I remember seeing you in a coach. You saw us down there. I said,
Oh yeah. I saw you guys play against that team from New Jersey. You were rolling that night.
You saw that, didn't you coach?
Yeah.
Remember that? You remember that? And, you know, so it's been really, for me, I've been able to
connect with these, these guys. And then when we play, you know, our opponents, you know,
the guys will come up after the game, Jalen Brunson, the Knicks beat us at like the buzzer
and I'm walking off and Jalen Brunson comes over. He was a Chicago kid who we didn't get.
We tried to get, he went to Villanova. He comes up, coach, how you doing, man? I said,
Jalen, I'm so proud of you. And, you know, so that's been really kind of cool.
To see them as men now and, and what they've become when I saw them when they were 14 or 15 years old.
Mike, we've got this small obsession with the idea of collaboration when you put great people
together and the sum of that knowledge becomes often a fascinating thing to watch. Have you
got an example of a great collaboration in your life?
You know, and maybe, maybe more so, and I can't think of a specific one off the top of my head,
but just the, you know, the, you know, the, you know, the, you know, the, you know, the, you know,
the theme of, you know, it's been interesting for me because I was a head coach for 30 years
and now I'm assistant again. And, you know, learning that role of being supportive of the
leader. I tell, I tell people I'm a listener. I'm a great listener to the, I've got a young staff
and I just want to listen a lot of times. And maybe I'll come back the next day
with the young assistant who said, you know, and I think, you know, I'm a great listener.
And even with the head coach, Quinn, who I coached at Duke, he, when I was an assistant at Duke in
late eighties, he was the point guard. I was the mediator between Mike Krzyzewski and 20 year old
Quinn Snyder. I was 27 at the time. And it's funny how our relationship now, 40 years later,
sometimes I'm mediating between him and a player just like I did back in the day. So it's been,
it's kind of been full circle. But knowing,
you know, I think, especially as an assistant being secure and doing it for the group and not
worried about whose idea it was or who gets the credit. And, and, and I think that's something
that, that, you know, kind of, I had to go step back into that role, but luckily I did it before
for eight years as an assistant at Duke for five years as an assistant with Morgan Wooten at De
Mathis. So it was, it was kind of comfortable to get back in it.
Mike, do you have a mantra when it comes to communication in your leadership roles?
Mentor wise, you know, it's sad. Coach Wooten passed, you know, a while ago and he was such a
great guy to bounce things off of. I still communicate with Mike Krzyzewski and it's
interesting because Mike had Quinn and I both, you know, so there's a little bit of a, of a
connection there as far as communication and thinking it through.
And, and then, you know, there's some guys that I coached against in college that I still stay
in, in, you know, in touch with, you know, Tom Izzo at Michigan State and we banged, you know,
you, you share stuff when the off season, you bounce things off of, of people and they'll call
and go, Hey, what are you guys running? Or I'll watch something. And, and so you still have,
you still have that, the network. Most of my network are college guys. I'm still early in
the NBA thing, but a lot of those college guys are college guys. And so, and, and, and, and, and,
college guys are veteran dudes who've seen it all. And I mentioned Izzo, but a Bill Self and a
John Calipari and a Jay Wright who coached at Villanova is now retired. Those were kind of
my era of guys. And I think we still kind of share things at times and vent at times too.
Mike, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Well, you know what I would have to say, I would have to say my parents and, and,
you know, I would have to say my parents. And, and, you know, I would have to say my parents.
You know, probably I look at my mom who somehow got into women's swimming in the 1950s when there
was no opportunity for women's sports. My grandfather to have the wherewithal,
he sent her to New York from the coal country of Pennsylvania. And she swam at the YMCA in
Manhattan and took the train all the way back. And, you know, to, she was an unbelievable inspiration.
And it was always a tough act to follow because whatever I achieved, she was an Olympian. And I
dang sure never got close to that. And, you know, so, you know, that, that's a tough act to follow
when your mom was an Olympian and an all American. And then she was the great dynamic, which was
really neat loop. When I was at GW finishing, she was the women's swimming coach. And so I'd go by
her office and, you know, then she,
come watch us play and watch practice. And so I got, got my undergrad degree in 82 and she got
her master's at say, I couldn't even, I couldn't even have graduation day. I had to share that
with her. She got her master's. I mean, it's unbelievable, but, but an amazingly intense
competitive. I mean, you don't get where she got, she, you know, and I, and just seeing her edge
and her game day and she swam masters. So she was like 70 and was pissed off at her time,
and she knew who she had to beat. I'm like, mom, just calm down. But, you know, she created a
monster. I'm, I, I think, I think, you know, I blame her. I blame her for some of my issues.
It's a great story. I love the, I'm sitting in Melbourne, Australia now, and I know the 1956
Olympic pool very well. It's the old glass house. That's now a home base for the biggest sporting
club in Australia and the Melbourne cricket ground where she would have walked around as an athlete
in 1956.
We, we think is a bit of the Mecca for sport here in Australia and to think your mom and to
understand what it would have been like, as you said, for a young woman in the 1950s to pursue
a sport. I don't think people in 2025 could really understand how big a hurdle she had to overcome.
It's a, it's a remarkable story. I love hearing all about it.
My latest mission is, so she was a butterflyer and she swam butterfly in the fifties when it
became the fourth stroke. There were only three strokes for a woman.
So her and an East German woman were breaking each other's world records, you know, cause it was a new,
but she didn't qualify to swim it in Melbourne. So she swam the freestyle relay. And so she swam
all the preliminary events, but not the final. They won the silver in 1970. They said, moving
forward, anyone who swims the preliminary events gets a medal, even if they don't swim the final.
Well, my mom is on a,
on a list of about 170 athletes from all kinds of countries who didn't get their medal. And to her
dying day, she was pissed off that she didn't get that medal. And I have been working USA swimming
and my sister and I like, if we can someday get that medal.
Well, let's put that out into the ether. Now, if anyone deserves that for a life of,
of contribution. And I love that you and your sister are still fighting hard for that.
Final question, Mike, and it's been a great pleasure to spend some time with you,
but we are, uh, as I said, a bit obsessed in our leader world about collaboration and,
and to hear your wisdom today is something to celebrate as well. Has there been anyone in
the world? You've got to connect with incredible people right across your working life. God love
to have collaborated with that coach or someone else in another passion of your life. Is there
a name that springs to mind? Yeah. You know, I, I, we were talking,
I was watching some NFL stuff earlier today and I don't know him well, but you know,
John Harbaugh would be a guy I'd love to spend some time with. Uh, his daughter actually played
lacrosse at Notre Dame and I just missed on some of the weekends when he would come into town,
but to like have a beer with him or any kind of, you know, and, and, you know, I, I just love his
style and he's been there and he's been doing it and he never panics and he's just always poised.
He's one of those guys. I love watching the Ravens play. Certainly they're a good team, but
they're a good team. And then I watch his press conferences and his message and I'm like, you
know what? That, that, that I'd like to hang out with him.
That would be a fun night at the bar having a beer and I'm sure there'd be some great, uh,
wisdom shared. Uh, Mike, I know the schedule of your life is, uh, is, is full on as an NBA
coach. So I really appreciate you giving us some time and, uh, sharing your life history. I've
loved every minute of it. Really appreciate you joining me.
Well, Luke, it was an honor to be with you. And I will tell Dyson Daniels, uh, tomorrow,
at our shoot around, we got the Clippers tomorrow night. We've won four in a row,
but I'm going to tell him, uh, I hung out with you and I do give him when he makes a three,
I do give him the Australian rules football official thing sometimes. And he goes, where
did you see that coach? I said, I sold out a couple of years ago. Those guys are dressed so
good and they give the goal. I love it. It was he and my, my son who plays sport for a living
here in Australia. We're, we're in a, in a junior state team together. And, uh,
my son's an obsessed, obsessed golfer and they've remained friends. So he'll know,
uh, Sam, we're on the sidelines. It's a, it's a great thing to watch young people
fill their dream, isn't it? So, um, he's in good hands having you on the sidelines.
So thanks again, Mike. Great to see you. Great to be with you, Luke. Take care.