I hope you enjoyed this chat with Mike Dunlap,
one of the most respected coaches in the world,
revered for his ability to get the most out of people.
I found myself writing notes all the way through it
from the brilliance of the Miracle Morning
and his passion for daily routines,
his clarity on what makes Michael Jordan the greatest of all time,
having been the senior coach of the team that Michael Jordan owns,
to his respect and empathy for everyone in his environment.
It's full of gold, full of wisdom,
and came across Mike through the work that we are doing
at Alita, a business founded with my great friend Matt Waterwitz
over seven years ago.
Mike, part of our signature program, Alita Connect,
where we connect great leaders around the world,
and Mike is one of the brilliant examples of it.
He collaborates on a monthly basis with John Alawisi,
Craig McRae from the Magpies,
Andrew McDonald from Australian Cricket,
Anthony Seabold, who's got an incredible reputation
in the world of rugby,
and also on a global scale,
Mike's joined one of the Alita Connect programs we have
with Mikel Arteta from Arsenal,
Matt LeFleur, who you'll hear him talk about,
the coach of the Green Bay Packers in this conversation,
and the relationship that they're building.
George Carl is a mentor of his,
and Eddie Jones from English Rugby
has also been a guest on this podcast.
We love the idea of leaders getting together to collaborate.
You don't have to be a global leader
to join one of our signature programs, Alita Connect.
In fact, our passion is connecting people
from small business,
and the arts, and different areas.
And if you're interested in doing it,
simply head to alitacollective.com to find out more.
Up next, a legend in the world of elite coaching,
Mike Dunlap.
Mike Dunlap is the current assistant coach
of the Milwaukee Bucks in the NBA,
a team that he helped win
only their second ever NBA championship in 2021.
In 2012, Mike Dunlap joined
the Michael Jordan-owned Charlotte Bobcats as head coach,
becoming the only coach in NBA history
to triple a team's win
from the preseason.
The NBA Hall of Fame coach,
George Carl, has this to say about Mike.
Mike Dunlap absolutely elevates every player
and team that he comes into contact with.
He's our guy.
He will take you from good to great.
Name any top-level elite coach in the game.
The only difference between Mike and them
is their address.
There is no higher level of coaching ability than his.
There is absolutely no one better.
Mike Dunlap, it's great to catch up with you today.
Thanks for your time.
I'll see you next time.
I suppose high praise from a Hall of Famer in George Carl.
He may have had some beers before he said that,
but that's okay too.
No, I mean, I've been fortunate enough
to have mentors in the business
that were great teachers.
And as you know, being a player,
a former player,
that the ability to teach is everything.
And then the other part of that is to connect,
you know, the words you use to care,
for more than the performance
and get that across to your players is everything.
You talk about that care and connect.
You've had success everywhere you've gone, Mike.
And we always hear the term, you know,
success leaves clues.
And I'm not surprised you started there.
You know, for us, it feels like coaches
are now very much about the whole athlete.
What's been your success to being a consistently great coach?
I would say you're only as good as the talent that you have.
And in the journey,
many of the places that I haven't had success,
all I have to do is run to the nearest mirror.
And I think that if you're asking accountability
of your team and players,
my point is, is that the sport will drive you
if you're open to it, to humility.
Example given, best on ground,
he could be that week and get the medal.
And then the next week he could,
uh,
tear his anterior cruciate.
So I just think that the, the trail of success is,
is, uh, laden with touchstones of humility,
sincerity, and being open to the fact that players make coaches,
coaches don't make players.
Yeah.
I love the, uh, the fact that you go to humility,
Mike, over the, over the time.
And, uh, yeah, that is incredible humility because we also know,
you know, that, uh, that elite coaches have consistency in,
in, in success, but you, you bring it back to, you know,
that you're going to get humility in professional sport,
whether you like it or not.
And, and accepting that,
is that sort of part of the process as well?
I think so.
The thing that blocks learning is ego and what feeds ego is a paradox.
You have success and then the blinders start to come up.
And I think it's really important that, you know,
daily that routine getting up early,
working,
hard regardless of the success you've had and then attributing,
uh, that success to others and understanding that it's true.
Uh, and really believing that I think what gets in the way is,
you know,
all the back slapping and the high praise,
um, is something that you have to move through.
I don't think you have to fear it,
but I think you have to have a system to process it and move it away from
yourself because hunger is a,
really interesting conundrum.
And so in order to continue to have that appetite as you go on,
you've got a vault,
the success that you've had,
um,
and,
and go on and just stay thirsty for the cutting edge because the game
changes a generationally,
the parenting is different.
So the players that you're getting still want a clarity,
competition,
uh,
but they want it straight.
And so again,
I think that you have to be very,
very careful with success.
And you might find some of these questions,
uh,
John,
I think you're going to deflect a lot of them through humility,
but I love this set about you.
One of your former players had this to say,
coach Dunlop came and built upon what my father had already done in my life.
He ushered a lot of us into adulthood with his values of hard work and
commitment and honesty,
the things he has proceeded to,
and still does the abilities and these principles he lives by still today.
It feels like a beautiful thing for a former player to say about you.
Can you expand a bit,
Mike,
on,
on those values that those that come under your leadership talk about?
Well,
regardless of,
of your values,
I think that the seven habits of highly successful people book written by Covey,
um,
he,
he talks about values are one thing and everybody has,
maybe different values,
but you just have to have them.
And I thought that the end part of that statement was quite powerful is that,
um,
they transition you,
whether that's work hard,
uh,
give credit where credit is due,
move with great sincerity,
uh,
and understand that life is to be an enjoyed all of those transitional points as a coach or teacher,
lead you to trust.
Because if you're not competent,
the surgeon can be a derelict,
he can be an alcoholic 22 hours a day.
But the fact of the matter is when he's sober for those two hours and the best surgeon in the world,
people really don't care about the periphery.
You know,
they're not going to delve in mightily to your values.
They just want to know that you know your job and can do your job.
Yes,
it's more expansive than that.
But the most important thing,
the most important thing to get across to your players and to your staff is that you know your trade,
you know your craft,
you know how players learn because you know the five laws of learning and can you spit those out?
Can you give examples of what they mean?
And can you speak in metaphors and similes to paint a picture because that's what players want.
And a bottom line is that what drives most players is competition.
They want to know who won,
who lost.
There's a book out,
a long time ago written by a guy named Novak called the joy of sport.
And he said that all these seven year olds got in a sandbox.
He was observing,
he was doing his dissertation and he said,
before you knew it,
the kids designed their own game and rules.
In other words,
people like rules.
They want to know who won and who lost.
And so a coach's job is to connect and intrinsically get people tap into that competitive warrior like person and say,
okay,
here we go.
Here's a way of getting about it.
And here's how you get the scalp,
so to speak.
And from my standpoint,
you have,
once you get that in a player,
then you can bring them back to why manners are important.
Why opening a door for a young lady is,
is timeless.
Why kindness is something that will make you more than just a competitor and a player,
because those things last a lifetime.
They stay in the soul.
If you will,
when you're taking your prowess at 30 or 28 or 32 and all that winning and you go to a halfway house or you go to people who have less than you do and you give away your gifts to them to give them something special on the day because that may be their best day,
given the fact that they're on an oxygen machine.
Yeah,
a bit preachy,
but the fact of the matter is,
is that I don't care where you go.
You'll find that very successful people typically are very kind hearted.
And really,
when you want to be altruistic,
you want to give all those gifts away.
So much gold there,
Mike,
in,
in your words.
And I'm,
I'm picking up and writing notes as,
as you're talking.
And,
you know,
the Stephen Covey book,
seven habits of highly effective people worth a read.
If you,
if you haven't and,
and,
and the joy of sport as well as it is a,
is a great,
and I love that you,
you know,
don't separate kind hardness and,
and being a good person from high performance.
And you make that link that,
that,
that that's there.
And I,
and also going back to what you said before about you touched on having good
habits and people with good routines.
Can you talk about some of those habits?
Cause I think that it clearly applies to your world of professional sport,
but also success in life.
Why are those habits so important?
Well,
again,
credit given to,
um,
a,
uh,
having great English teachers,
teachers from grade school on up.
And so at some point in time,
I made a decision to be an English major.
Um,
there was a book out small book called the miracle morning.
And there's an aphorism,
uh,
and an acronym,
if you will,
uh,
called savers.
And in the morning,
if you get up early,
you have solitude.
And as you know,
Mr.
Rogers said is back in the day is we have a noisy,
see world.
And as the medium of,
of,
of texting and,
and,
and the computer and all these things came into play for this generation.
The point is,
is that all this noise is taking you away from reflection and thinking the
value of thinking is one of those habits.
Okay.
Well,
how do I move myself into a habit of sitting early in the morning before
anybody gets up and using the anachronism and,
and savers is simple.
It's S is for silence means that you're going to meditate.
A is for affirmations.
And that could be,
uh,
you know,
talk positive,
think positive and act positive and drill that into your head.
V is for visualization,
create your own picture on the act of kindness or opening a door or doing
things,
but you have to have your own picture in order to enact that.
And then you go to E,
exercise.
Okay.
I only have 10 minutes,
pop down and do some pushups in the,
say 60 minutes where you're away from everybody.
If that's the minimum that you've,
that's all you've got to dedicate to it.
Take a bite of the apple and go on.
All right.
Then from there,
you go to,
you know,
uh,
S A V E R read.
All right.
So you want to read every day.
That could be the New Yorker that could be,
uh,
over here,
the Atlantic.
Okay.
That's kind of esoteric.
All right.
Read sports,
illustrated,
read off of,
you know,
something that you get that leads you to an article on Twitter,
go to Instagram and somebody suggests something.
It can be in a myriad of different forms.
And then finally,
the last S is journaling or scribing.
So what I've done is I've taken it through an acronym and then each day,
I'll show you my notebook.
I wrote down what you had said to me,
and I'm only looking,
looking for the eyes of the fish.
You said success leaves clues.
Okay.
So I'm,
I'm stealing from you.
You know,
I'll give what I've got,
but the humility and the connection of validation of another human being,
all you have to do is write something down that they talk about.
When a child has been abused,
you never go directly at the child.
When somebody has a hard time or they've lost a tough game,
you go to a,
a common object as opposed,
it could be a truck in the sandbox.
It could be a teddy bear or whatever,
but you use another medium to get to what you want eventually.
And that's a methodology.
And so I bring myself back to some habits there.
Personally,
I like to meditate.
Second,
I like to do affirmations.
I like to visualize.
I like to exercise.
I love it.
As a matter of fact,
read,
I love,
love,
love to read.
And then finally I keep journals.
I keep a personal journal.
I keep a log like everybody does on,
uh,
you know what my day looks like,
what the week looks like,
what the month looks like,
et cetera.
Most successful people do that.
What do you do?
You know,
and then I keep another one where I just,
or ideas,
you give me something and I'll transition it from success.
Slave's clue to just a pure book of what I would call ideas or a book.
I like writing poetry.
So,
or a little bit weird,
a little bit different,
but that's my life.
And so my point is,
is that I've given you an,
an acronym of some great habits in there.
And you say,
Hey,
that sounds overwhelming to me.
Well then do two of the savers,
because if I stay in your brain,
you say,
Hey,
I remember this dude on the podcast mentioned about the miracle morning.
And then he talked about this,
an acronym of savers.
And now I go right to a,
a routine that I personally don't always accomplish,
but I,
I I'm picking off at least three or four of them per day.
I like to get all of them,
but I don't honestly.
And then you go from there,
you build from there.
And before you know it,
before you start your day,
you've,
you've already had some major base hits there.
So that's what I do.
I love,
you know,
the miracle morning.
And I love the,
the,
an acronym and what,
and what it stands for.
And I,
I really relate to it too,
Mike,
in lots of ways.
I want to delve into a bit of it straight away,
if that's can.
I mean,
meditation mindfulness now,
Mike is,
is really a much more known term and something that athletes consistently do.
I feel really lucky to have found that 25 years ago in the world of AFL football,
which is quite rare in the Western suburbs of Melbourne back in that time,
but the habit forming.
And as you said,
you know,
you think of the alternative.
Now,
a lot of kids start the day.
First thing you're on the smartphone,
you,
you know,
you're over,
overwhelmed with all of this material.
And that's the first thing that you do that,
you know,
and to not exercise,
to not give you your mind that think time or to not read for,
for better learning.
So,
so much wisdom in,
in what you say,
what,
what type of meditation do you,
do you prefer Mike?
Do you mix it up or.
Hey,
you know,
there are a couple of favorites,
but what's awesome on the topic of the cell phone and then the meditation is,
is that with today's youth,
the cell phone is such an attribute,
but it's got to have a discipline to it.
So we have a no phone zone at certain times during the day.
It could be the dinner table or it could be the coach says,
Hey,
you know,
put a leash on that and put it in your bag and then see it post game.
But whatever the philosophy is of that building or that adult,
but the main point about the cell phone is it's not the enemy,
but like anything,
it is a secondary to the importance of who you are,
how you act and what you do.
And if you let the phone,
it will end up controlling you versus you controlling it.
And that's why I say,
you've got to put a leash on it.
You got,
you've got to get it in its proper place.
And if you start with young adults or anybody else and say,
Hey,
it's the enemy.
And then you,
then you sound like you're 9,000 years old.
And so I think a better,
a better way to approach young adults and,
and footy players and whomever is,
Hey,
man,
isn't it great.
Look what it does.
But then you have to have an etiquette to the phone,
the phone.
I mean,
it's ridiculous at restaurants when you go in and,
you know,
the heads down and nobody's conversing and conversation takes a secondary
interactions,
relationships,
all of that.
It's a,
it's a mechanism for people to hide,
to shield themselves,
to knock,
communicate.
And I,
and I always just tell 10 people,
if you're in a room,
if you understand that about the phone,
then you're going to understand that you can get an edge every day.
If you know how to use the phone to your benefit,
but the phone can be a really negative thing.
Okay.
How is it a positive thing to meditation is there's over seven or 800.
All you have to do is Google and go,
I want a 10 minute meditation.
I want a 20 minute meditation.
Or a longer meditation and you can go potpourri and it just comes up.
You scroll and you pick what you want.
Personally.
I like one that's 18 minutes and it's waves.
And it's an Australian who takes you through and get you to your subconscious.
And he goes through four or five markers.
And I would say I've listened to it a thousand times already.
In other words,
it fits me.
And I'm not a guy who has to look over the phone.
It fits me.
I'm not a guy who has to look over the phone.
If you talk to any monk or anybody who talks about the flywheel or the
simplicity of the hedgehog,
learn how to do one thing.
Great.
Jim Collins,
good to great,
et cetera.
He also wrote built to last a dynamic speaker around the world.
But the bottom line is,
is that what you're trying to do is not do a thousand things.
Well,
you're trying to do one thing extremely well,
find your passion and then just keep hitting a button.
And the next thing you know,
people are giving you money. It's ridiculous. But to have the discipline to go to the same
meditation and to drill down on it and find iterations and different avenues of what that
man is saying to you or what you can expound upon within your own imagination is timeless
and unbelievable. Now, I went existential on most of your audience. I'll bring myself back.
But you've got 700 or 800 of those on Google at least that will take you to another 700 if you're
really adventurous and want to find a meditation. But just go to Google and just type in meditation
and it'll give you any kind, standing on your head, laying down, swimming. I mean, it's ridiculous.
So anyway, mine's an 18-minute shot. I find that that fits my day. And, you know,
you know, I'm kind of like this. Got it done. I feel good about that part. But there's other
things to do. Yeah, I was taught mantra-based transcendental meditation, which has stayed with
me. But you're right. And I love your language there around putting the leash on the phone. And
as a father of four, I think it's the parenting conversation we have all the time around,
you know, it's the number one driver. But I think you're right. When you demonize it,
you underestimate how brilliant. I love how the kids connect. I love how they can get together.
It's so much simpler than we grew up.
But having some boundaries. And so the Milwaukee Bucks, you'll have times where
the players will say, hey, it's dinner time or meal time. Put your phones in your bag.
You guys put some leash around that even at NBA level.
Yes. I think everything is about understanding that freedom is responsibility and responsibility
is freedom. You know, when over in the United States, they have graduation talks all the time.
And there's a guy that is a brilliant writer called David Brooks. He wrote The Second Mountain.
But anyway, he talks about...
All these fancy people, whether it's Bill Gates or it could be, you know, this guy or this woman
who has a resume that weighs not, you know, it's hefty and they're brilliant people and all that.
But they get up there and they tell an audience of 1,000 students that are 21 years old that are,
you know, literally crapping their pants, wondering what the heck they're going to do
with their lives. And they're saying, hey, you be you. Find your passion. Well, what they're doing
is they're going to do it. And they're going to do it. And they're going to do it. And they're
just throwing gasoline on the fire. They're not giving them anything that's credible to,
hey, tell me what to do in the next six months. They don't want to know what to do with the rest
of their life. They just want to not be scared. Because I know I was sitting in that chair and
I talked to my buddies and we were all sitting there having a beer after graduation. I have
no idea what I'm going to do. And my point is that it's really important that
each day that we connect with simple things and understand that the complex, if you're a good
teacher, a good leader, is to boil it down and hand them out, help people understand that,
you know, you being you and freedom has a responsibility attached to it. The phone
has a responsibility attached to it. The more you can teach a younger person. My father made me
and we had five of us. We had to start buying our clothes in the sixth grade. If we needed a little
help here or there. Yeah. But you are. And it was custom in our home to start buying our clothes in
the sixth grade. Well, that meant that you had to paint finishes. You had to cut lawn. You had to
have a job. That was just a given in today's age. I don't care if it's the AFL. And now you've got
18 to 20, 22 year olds. You say, raise your hand if you've had a job. And you would be stunned by
the fact that the majority of the room, they've never worked a job or paid taxes or done whatever.
So it just means that's not necessarily the worst thing in the world. It's what you're inheriting
are a lot of people that have not taken traditional steps to the word responsibility.
And when you have a human being that says, give me, give me, give me entitlement,
it doesn't make them awful. What it means is somebody didn't teach them that.
And so instead of indictment judgment, you say, okay, this is what I've got. And this is where
we've got to go. And anybody can, you know, take somebody that's gifted, that's been disciplined
by great parents. But can you take somebody that's talented, that's lazy, or hasn't been taught
properly or has an abusive father and lead them to a higher plateau where they say, hey, that's
not proper to slap a woman.
No, we don't do that. We never do that. And here's why, you know, and then you go down that road,
but their model and what they saw in the home was opposite that. Well, you're not going to fix that
young man in a day or a week. You have to understand it's going to take a process.
Well, it's the same thing as the phone, or it's the same thing as freedom.
Freedom is an arduous process. That is not a give me thing. It is actually
I've got to do A to B to C, and then the door of freedom opens up.
Yeah, brilliantly said, Mike. I love listening to the way you eloquently describe the pathway
to success. And as you said, you can sit there in front of someone who's, you know, as you said,
got a hefty resume. And I remember sitting there, how is it even possible to even look at that? But,
you know, when you break it down, I go back to the miracle morning. If you start your day with
some reflection and some mindfulness and some exercise and some effort, you're going to be
and some visualization and some journaling, you're probably going to be on the path to finding
that yourself. And so, yeah, incredibly brilliant the way that you've summed that up. I want to
change tack, Mike. There's so much to talk to you about and go to a moment in your life where
the greatest athlete on the planet, maybe the greatest athlete in history, Michael Jordan,
owns his own NBA team. He's the majority shareholder of Charlotte Bobcats, now the
Charlotte Hornets. Can you tell us about that phone call, that experience when you take the
NBA senior role and clearly linked to Michael Jordan's going to be a unique experience?
Well, it was, I would just say, you know, working threes because people can digest threes.
Really, because your question begs, what's it like to be in a room with him? And, you know,
what makes him tick? And being in a room with them is he's really aware, he has a sixth sense
about the dynamics of people. And he was a tremendous,
is a tremendous leader and has, I would say, good humility given the accolades of being
bestowed and earning that as the greatest player in a sport. You know, there are others,
but he's definitely at the top. And some people want to argue it. That's fine.
But definitely he's right up there with top two or three. And then the argument stops.
But,
I would say that everybody that ever watched him play highly, highly competitive. And, you know,
people will say, okay, he's competitive, but what does that mean? He's thorough. When he's trying
to be a great owner, whether he's trying to win a golf game or what he did with basketball is,
is that he has a flame within him that if he walks in a room, he has presence. And it,
it's about competing. I mean, he would show up to anything and ultimately he's going to turn it
into competition. He can't help himself. And that's, he's a warrior competitor and he's going
to turn a party into competition. It could be quarters. It could be a conversation, but so that
stands out. You know, so I would say presence, competitor, and then three, you know, three is,
like, a box for him.
You're going to have to make flexible decisions. You're going to have to whether you're going
to get a promotion or a promotion is, is what you need. So I think it's the first way to
do that.
And the, the one that comes up here is I would say he's a good partner with Michael Jordan,
which he tries to keep veiled, but he's service related. He gives a ton of money that's not
tagged, Michael Jordan money, to a lot of African-American colleges in America, not just one.
All right. He's got a hundred million dollars tagged over the next decade to go to educational
programs and scholarship programs.
My point is, is that there is a degree,
of humility and he doesn't want that to boomerang back him look at me look what i'm doing but the
big point there on point number three is he's community uh related and he wants to impact and
he's impacted charlotte you know not only with the employment of more than a thousand people
in his building and what the hornets mean to the community but he also takes his stack of money
and gives it away quietly quietly so those are the three things that in presence of of mj that
that were noticeable to me there's more and more and more of stories and this that and the other
thing but to highlight that is presence competitor and community related so mike to sort of uh you
know reflect the the documentary that he produced was uh you know again everything he does becomes
uh you know bigger than
anything previously and that that you know without understanding the netflix numbers is a global
phenomenon and people then got a look on the inside at that last year of michael jordan and
and him sitting down reflecting back i mean a remarkable thing and a time piece to have in lots
of ways but i think all of us then got a sense of just the drive and and then also perhaps that you
know again the the bar room conversation you know did he end up with great camaraderie with his
teammates
going for was that a cost of doing business to be that good i mean how did you reflect on looking at
that did you think well that's just his path to being the best of all time or is did that come at
a cost in some way in your mind looking at that as well it always comes at a cost for everybody
you know leadership is a lonely role and it's not for everybody and so if you think you're going to
sit in that chair and you know be all things to all people you're sadly mistaken and you've never
sat in a chair you're not going to be in that chair you're not going to be in that chair you're not
you know whether you're running your own company uh that's a high-end company elite and you're
wanting to be the best there's a price to be paid he paid the price uh at the moment you know when
he was running down the trail and he was a bull i would say the com the camaraderie was contentious
at times but there are other times where he went out with his team he paid for the bills they had
a great state etc.
and they had a really good time but the vapor of that um was an indictment on that he was a rough
neck and that you know he was hard to be around uh at times uh it's complicated but i would say
that i'm on the side of of of mj you know he didn't hesitate in the documentary to say this
is who i was this is what i did and i thought some of the things that were said about him
were cowardly you know and and i'll say it to pippin i'll say it to bj armstrong or whatever
not that they didn't shouldn't have their opinion but you know fly and go see him in his living room
and break it down for him you know easy to be filmed and say that and they wouldn't have said
it the same way had they been in his presence and so my point is that i'm for him because
if you're gonna say what you're gonna say you're gonna say what you're gonna say you're gonna say
what you said and the way you said it then give the rings to him because you know i think that
also is that phil jackson allowed and wanted him to do part of of of phil jackson's job
you know some of the admonishing and going harder and hey that's not good enough should
have been in phil jackson's lap not jordan's but jordan took over and
he
you know six championships etc and everybody said he was the lead dog well when 10 or 20 years goes
by you got to understand that you can't have just all good you know there's a trade-off and if you
want those rings and want to look at them and brag about them and that you got to understand
that the lead dog did his job did he not did he not do his job did he do his job he did his job
better than anyone's ever done it before mike and i
and i
they fall very much into your cab and i think imagine the privilege of being a teammate imagine
being swept up on that train it would have been brilliant and as you said everything comes at a
cost i think i i you know wrote that down again and i bring it back to an australian connection
for me i look longley was part of that and as australians we got to live through the
chicago bull era and and through luke longley and uh who didn't feature heavily but i did see
a lot of people won't understand this michael jordan sat down with uh the uh abc afterwards
and uh i'm having trouble thinking of the uh australian story is the um famous program that
does documentary type story and he sat down with them and as you said in terms of curry and said
hey look you know what if i look back we probably did miss out on it but we're filming a documentary
you can't tell every part of it and luke was a big part of uh of the team and i'd go and play
with luke any time again was that was the words that that he used so uh you know i think um i
think it's a it's a brilliant well the the great thing about luke longley
is what he's done is he's done a lot of work and he's done a lot of work and he's done a lot of work
he was a piece of clay and if we're talking directly about jordan jordan said here's here's
the road that we're going to travel hold on to my hand and i'll take you to a place that you've
never been before and luke would admit that and um so jordan was the bright light in the room
and you know there's there it's not all going to be peaches and cream and when you are a dynasty
it is the hardest thing in the world to do and if it were easy everybody be doing it and the thing
that that excellence and living a one percent life means that four in the morning is four in the
morning you know i was at an ice cream shop below a hotel in the basement and there's a guy named
marinovich who's a famous weight coach for pro athletes he had a son that played at usc and
went on to play and he was a great athlete and he was a great athlete and he was a great athlete and
a very controversial life and and for the raiders etc nonetheless is and the ice cream shop was a
napkin that had jordan's autograph on it and said have a great day something along those lines and
that led me down the down the basement corridor to the weight room and he said whenever jordan
came in to anaheim he would lift on game day here and the things that he did
was
his weight coach on game day were crazy you know he was doing supersets squats lunges and the whole
thing and that the point of that is is that jordan tortured himself to be the best of the best
and when you get into that thin air it's really hard to explain to anybody who's never lived
the 4 a.m life and the 16
to 18 hour day and the pressure of the media and holding form when you're injured and to do that
and be number one i don't care who you investigate whether it's steve jobs or it's bill gates or
whatever they all have their pimples they all have their pimples but when you look at their
work day when you look at their ability that they see life differently and they have the discipline
of free time to start working and they have the discipline of free time to start working and they
say no i'm not going to do that no i'm not not going to do that that you know it time will speak
for eternity on how remarkable michael jordan is and was and will be uh and a standard for all time
i mean that bill russell same deal standard for all time donald bradman standard for all time
those things are hard you know to do and as you know you can name
the best footy players that ever played the game very robin i mean you know there it is i mean
there are only so many greats out there and it comes at a severe price yeah that's why we love
understanding that genius isn't or trying to and you you describe jordan as the bright light in the
room the bright light in the room you're probably around in the nba at the moment janice added a
who was a two-time nba mvp delivered
is uh the mvp of the final series uh 2021 for milwaukee's second ever championship uh
has he got that that sort of genius we just heard you talk about is he in that sort of conversation
yeah he'll he'll move himself uh to you know in the conversation of the top five in the next
couple years if injury doesn't visit his doorstep or everybody knock on wood but
yes i mean if there's no question he's 6 11
he does things on the court that nobody has ever done uh other than maybe as an athlete
wilt chamberlain uh was the only one uh in terms of stride distance is a is a kind of a scientific
thing but um he he he has things that he does both physically and mentally and spiritually that are
at the highest level i mean as a competitor he's like george
uh physically the ball in his hand is like a golf ball that's how big his hand is his arms are
seven four you know uh all of that stuff that so he has the physical attributes and then the his
free time is consumed in the weight room uh consumed with shooting uh practice uh another
session of stretching and then he does a mental session every day and then he does a physical
day uh with our sports psychologist uh he's willing to pay the price to have his name
eventually put up there with the greats uh mike it's uh it's a great insight we appreciate it and
also a great reflection clearly on the culture you've got at milwaukee you know to keep a player
of that quality he's been there for nine years you know the world would be at his door enticing
him elsewhere i mean can you speak to to that culture that's a significant achievement to keep
him at your club for such a long time yeah that the milwaukee bucks whether it's john horst our
general manager our owners uh or everybody else our medical people uh coach bud jason kidd before
him all of that is a village as they say that that connected with him and what the people would
probably want to ask or know well what what was the one thread that maybe made
him go small market and be loyal and it was the fact that he was in abject poverty
sold sunglasses along with his brothers in order to give money back to his family so they could eat
uh so doing that at a young age gave him a love for stability and he understood the underdog the
small market you have to have uh an ability not to want to go to new york or miami
or la the easy road um he was raised hard uh he you know like i said he had a job that taught him
how to work hard and also is somewhere along the line his mother and his father taught him the value
of loyalty and what he's getting back from the community of and the city of milwaukee is
wherever he goes he is loved and
he has a set of manners on him he understands that you know he was given something by the stars
and he's going to take full advantage of it but if you said what's the one thing away from
the physical attributes that he has is that it he is an incredibly humble human being
and has a set of manners on him yes sir no sir i don't care who's talking to him
and whenever he warms up uh uh at home or on the road we have ball boys that
he actually has the best leave of the day i mean i just i think that's incredible how
they get through that the best thing they achieve is
to have a chance at winning the game and winning the most important game and you know he's
still a youngster he's got a you know he's a youngster the kids can be very young at
home so i'm going to have to give him aentaric um i think he's going to be a youngster
uh so i'm going to give him a little extra and um i'm not just saying i know i'm a youngster
but i'm a youngster if i'm a well-mannered man i'm a youngster then i'm going to give
him a chance to play in the game i think he's gonna be a youngster in the future uh so
yeah i mean there we go
um
was based on a partnership with one of my oldest friends, Matt Waterwitz, in a leadership
business we founded called Alita, and our signature program is Alita Connect, and we're
really passionate about collaborative groups of leaders from different backgrounds getting
together, and it was your great friend Brian Gorgian, who's got a huge reputation in Australia
for his incredible legacy with Australian basketball and sport, and referred you into
the world, and the fact that you can hear the lifelong learning in your language, you're
constantly open to learning, and you've collaborated with some of our great Australian coaches
in recent times, Craig McRae is doing an incredible job at Collingwood, Andrew McDonald, Anthony
Seabold, John Aloisi from the world of the round ball game, can you tell us about your
passion to get together and connect with other leaders?
Yeah, back to Brian Gorgian, if you guys, and you probably already know this, but if
you do your homework, take every coach that's ever coached in the history of your land,
and he's number one, I'm talking tennis, I'm talking Charlie Walsh, I'm talking Lindsey
Gaze, nobody has a better win percentage or more wins than Brian Gorgian, and the only
reason I mention that is, is that I played for his father, and at 21, I started going
over to Australia and working in Albert Park, over in a corner with some of his players,
and that blossomed into working and being the head coach of the Adelaide 36ers, I was
fortunate enough to be there three years, but my point is that, you know, I have great
friends, and your selection of friends is everything about who you are, and even being
with, and I don't mean that even being, but with Matt, he has opened the door to the best
of the best in Australia, and young coaches that are actually...
I mean, you know, I've been in the theatre now, I jumped on that, Brian provided that
for me, and so, I want to give credit to Brian and Matt for bringing me to you, Luke, so
thank you, but I'm just a hunter of people, I don't think you have enough friends, I've
heard people say, I have enough friends, or the ones I really trust, I can count on one
hand, I'm not that guy, I don't believe that, I want to keep opening new cupboards, and
to new friends, because I think there's an energy to it, there's a warmth to it, and
I would tell every coach, as you age, start collecting younger and younger friends, you
know, as a coach of college, I was always working between 18 and 22, basically, so I
was infused with youth my whole life, and so I have all, and they're going to have marriages,
they're going to have kids, and so I'm going to all these weddings and stuff, you know,
as somebody...
I mean, who's now 65, but my point is, is that Pete Newell, who was a great, great basketball
coach, at the same level as John Wood, he's Mount Rushmore coach, in terms of what he
did and all that, I worked his big man camp for 20 years, but the one lesson he taught
me is, he said, young man, having lunch with him, he said, the one thing I'm going to give
you as a gift is this, you listen to me, you're going to be fine, you don't, you're going
to augment...
and become old and bitter, keep an open mind, he said, when you go to a clinic, or you watch
somebody, have a notebook, pay homage to them, ask them questions, never think you know it
all, and if they're telling you something you already know, write it again, because
it'll reinforce what eventually you'll forget, and I'm just sitting there, and I said, it,
you know, like, I'm meeting you today for the first time, it's another opportunity for
me to learn, and that's the way I look at it, and then the second admonition is, as you
get older, you are your experiences, and then you always want to talk about yesterday, and
I think, again, you have to flush that stuff, and codify it, and put it on a bookshelf,
and say, I don't know anything, whenever I walk into a room, first thing I say to myself,
I don't know anything, and I always say, that person and that person's smarter than me,
and it's a really great place to start.
Because it puts the antennas up, and you're willing to listen to a seven-year-old say
something that is profound, Forrest Gump-like, or it's somebody that is talking, and you think,
well, because they have never won a national championship or world championship, why bother?
Hey, that's ridiculous.
I went to a class, my wife stimulated this, but in love and logic, I tell coaches all the time,
the best class.
The best coach you can ever go to is never the greatest coach of all time, it's parenting class,
because in love and logic, whoever is up there, it's their 1200th class, so that means that
they're teaching something in terms of concepts, and they've dealt with trouble and problems
for 1200 classes, and so they're dealing with methodology of raising children, and so I had
no idea about phases of children.
The fair phase, the phase where the shutout phase, daughter to mother, here it happens at this time,
here it comes, where the father has to enter and be there on site for two years, I had no clue of
any of this stuff, but then if you understand parenting, then you're going to understand
any player that comes across your radar, and they don't all come across, I, sir, they're going to
come across troubled, they're going to come across as a different learner, they're going
to come across with a whole host of things where you say, I don't understand them, why won't they
run hard, and then now you go to somebody and say, oh, I see what's going on, there's something that
they came to the paddock with that's a problem, so now I'm just going to start giving them a hard
one, and yet they have something there, it doesn't mean I'm going to give them an out, but how about
we call them, the assistants take over, and I put my arm around, and I say, hey, you know, Graham,
what happened out there, you know, and then he says, hey, you know, my girlfriend did this,
and say, hey, we're going to get to that later, and I'm going to take you to lunch,
but that's no excuse for going from A to B, because you wouldn't allow that with a high-risk
surgeon who's going to work on your son, what's he going to start talking to you about the fact
that his wife served him papers for a divorce, so he's going to stop surgery on you, I mean, come on,
and so
I mean, this is the kind of thing you have to be aware of, and it all goes back to,
am I a good learner, and am I open to the fact that if you want to know how somebody operates,
there's a whole nother world underneath that are called triggers, where you hear them speak,
and you go, okay, there's something else I need to get to, hey, I noticed that you said this word
over here, like you were struggling with getting your
car going, you know, whatever that was, well, what did that struggle, I mean, what's that about,
well, I'm behind on my bills, you are, well, what are you doing with your money, man, you got plenty
of money, and now he says, well, you know, I really like the casino, oh, okay, all right,
so my point is that there's always another investigation to be done, and you have to be
open to people who will help and know more than you,
in almost every aspect of life, and that's where you go, and you ask questions, and you listen,
you button your mouth, and let them teach you. I love the brilliance of what you said, Mike,
it relates clearly, you know, in sport, dealing with athletes, but in anyone who might be running
a business, listening to this, or anyone who's managing people, you're not forgiving the behavior
of A to B, as you said, but we're going to acknowledge that, and we need to work on that,
but let's also find out personally, because all of us have a bad day with a partner, all of us,
you know, make a mistake at some point.
Whatever area of our life, and so, you know, it's where the opportunity is, and, you know,
we're coming back without the name-dropping element to this, Mike, because I know the
humility is, but you have opened up this world of connection, and I love it, and I do it for
a reason as well, because when people, you know, your schedule at the Milwaukee Bucks doesn't
lend itself, you would think, to self-reflect and take the time, but you're now, you know,
connecting in to Matt LaFleur, who's the coach of the Green Bay Packers, who's one of the
most revered coaches, Mikel Arteta from Arsenal, I know you've got another collaborative group
going, George Carl, who's obviously a great mentor and friend of yours, Eddie Jones from
English Rugby, so the fact, and we just get as excited, Mike, as someone who is running a small
business with two people in it, who wants to get together and continue that learning journey and
share with others, and these brilliant young female leaders that, in their 20s, that we're
learning from, who are doing things that we couldn't have even dreamed about, and so, for us,
our passion is connecting, and collecting was probably the most important thing for us.
The wrong word, but in some ways, it is these groups of people who want to reflect and learn,
and so, when people like you do it, who've had success, it really does, I think, offer a window
into lifelong learning, as you said, and your story about keeping an open mind, you know,
really resonates, so thank you for, A, joining the world we love of a leader, but also your input
and your knowledge has been clearly profound, so thanks again. Mike, we've been, for us,
identifying what we think great leadership looks like in the context of,
of the people we've had this great privilege of working with, and spending time with, like you,
and we think, for us, there are dimensions that are really clear coming out. The first one is
self-leadership, that we think most leaders have a real sense of self-leadership. Does that term
resonate with you? Yeah, I mean, accountability. When you say self-leadership is, the doorway
has got to be being accountable to walking your talk, cliche, but you definitely,
have to provide an example, as, as people are digging in for a long run with you, and it could
be 25-year business, could be 40 years, etc., is that the connector would be that you have an
employee, and their child goes to the hospital because they got burned, or whatever. There is
no excuse for the leader, either, you know, using Zoom, FaceTime, or going to the hospital
to see that.
That child, to show that kind of love, if you will, that, yeah, we have a bottom line, and we
want to make money, but intrinsically, if you want to connect with somebody forever, those are
actions, not words, and so self-leadership is about what you do, not what you say.
We see leaders, another dimension, are really conscious now, and we've heard that in your
already, about how they positively impact people in their environment. You just shared a story,
of doing that in real time, that idea of positively impacting others on a daily basis,
Mike, does that resonate as well? Say that one again, please.
Positively impacting others in your environment, leaders conscious of, you know, really sophisticated
about how they, on a day-to-day basis, have a positive impact, is that something you've given
thought to? Yeah, the aura of being positive is validating the negative. In other words,
it'll fizzle out extrinsically on the person,
if it's just happy days, and you bypass their suffering. Every one of your workers,
every one of your players, has something going on that isn't pleasant, and to assume the other
thing, and be, you know, throwing bouquets of flowers all the time, well, they will die and
wilt. It's imperative, then, in order to be that, and have great energy, that you be empathetic,
and have compassion, and yet you have to get to,
hey, look, we've got to hump it today, and we've got to get going, you know, but I think that the
positivity is a validation of, hey, this is going to be hard today. This is hard, because you've got
something else going on, but yes, we can, and yes, we will, and then you roll up your sleeves,
and whatever that is, they see you also as a hard worker, as somebody who's not hypocritical,
et cetera, because as a leader,
your talent has to be to delegate. I mean, you know, when I say hard worker,
if you're constantly down in the engine room, then you have no sight of where the ship is going,
and so you have to, you know, modulate. You have to be up there, then you kind of got to move
down there, get into the boiler room, be empathetic, validate, and then say, hey,
that's a great job, especially when things are good. We call it praise, prompt, and lead.
The prompt is, you know, you've got to be up there, you've got to be up there, you've got to
say, hey, there's what you did with the shovel to get the coal in the stove. Let me show you a
better way, you know, and now you show it, so you're kind of being critical, because you say
you've got a better way. He might slope his shoulders, or she might slope her shoulders,
and so you have to say, hey, you see that body language there? That's not going to play well,
because we're going to move through a couple buyers here, and so we need to have a better
shoulders back, eyes up, greet them. You're important. You're important. You're important.
And I think you're damn good at what you do. I think you're the best, but I'm going to tell you
right now, you've got to do better with those shoulders back, and give me some eye contact.
We got that? Boom, and then walk away from them. You don't have to sit there and admonish them,
and you praised them, you gave them a compliment, you prompted them, you told them, and showed them
what you want, and now get away from them, you know, and so those are all methodologies. So
positivity sounds good, but it's amoeba-like, and you have to be more specific,
with it, and you have to have techniques and skills in order to distribute it so that it's
not just a puff of smoke. Brilliant. I love that idea of validating the negative, isn't it? Because
that false positivity, yeah, people see through that, you know, really quickly, and I love your
method of being able to deliver it in that particular way. Leaders we see, you know, in
this 21st century style who have great impact like you, are really conscious about how they create
and share their vision. How have you gone about creating and sharing your vision? Well, ask
questions. Example given is that if you're, you know, running your own corporation or you're a
coach, you know, you go in and you paint your vision, but there's no connection, that you're
going to end up a dud. My point is, is that an I am sheet. So now your first meeting, you hand out
an I am sheet to your team.
Say six workers, whatever your company, a startup, whatnot. Within the three pages, you say, hey,
worst tragedy in your life, favorite possession, favorite food, you know, some of those specific
questions that might take you 10 years to learn about your wife. It's amazing. All of a sudden,
you know, you're at a party and it's 10 years later and you hear your wife say something,
you go, oh, I didn't know that. Well, why the hell did you know that? You know what I'm saying?
Because I think too many times, we don't take
inventory. And I think that it's really important one to know how to ask great questions and how to
note it before you get started on the vision of here's how I want our family to be. Here are the
customs because it has to be collaborative. It's got to be we, not me, all those things that we
know, but you better in this day and age, you better say that this is horizontal leadership.
I'll be vertical when you want me to lead because you know what players and employees
don't.
They don't want horizontal leadership all the time. They want leadership when the storm comes
by the leader. And so, I mean, you know, you've got, it's a balance of horizontal and vertical
when the time is right. You know, like I said is, but you want to rotate the leadership. Example
given, David Halperstam wrote a book called The 20th Century. He went over to Japan, hung out
for a year, wrote a tiny little book.
He's a Pulitzer Prize, you know, he's dead now, but he wrote this book. And in essence,
he was saying that the leaders came down on Fridays and that they would be on the conveyor
belt. And then they would sit and have lunch with the guys. So they actually worked the conveyor
belt and they said, what idea, how can we take that step out to be more efficient? And then they
would go back up to their towers, so to speak, with those ideas of the workers, plus the workers
saw them down there and they got to know their first name.
So when we're talking about, again, methods and how you do that, I think you got to know what
you're doing and you got to be competent, again, about what you're doing and what the vision is.
But in saying that it's a we vision, hey, I remember you said that, give credit where credit's
due. So like if you're an AFL coach or you're an NBL coach, you get all this information and you
say, hey, I found out a Malcolm Gladwell.
Outlier, blank, the tipping point. Those are all books that he wrote.
The only thing in all those books, really, that I got from him was common denominators,
large amounts of information and saying, hey, what are the four or five bands of they had
similar answers all the way through with a tragedy, for example, he's fatherless,
he's fatherless, he's fatherless. So they have no model of what it really means.
to be a male you know in terms of a responsible male there's a little boy in there and he's got
a lot of dysfunction and he now you may be the first person that he's seen that expects him to
be responsible in a way that you're asking him and you're talking about this highfalutin vision
and that poor guy's in there and he's 12 years old even though he's in a 22 year old person's body
I mean you're right how am I going to bridge that gap and what am I going to do to build trust
when everything about the male is trust well all of a sudden you bring in a female as a sports
psychologist and that's his he has a good feeling about well that's an avenue to you know my mother
or a female that helped him and now he's with the sports psychologist and the sports psychologist
is downloading you not snitching but saying hey you're going about this the wrong way
with you.
With your star player and so my point is the vision has to be inspirational it has to be
like hey we're all competitors does anybody in this room want to be the best of the best
you know and everybody's going to raise their hand on that's a layup well start with things
that are easy inspirationally don't start with something like hey you want to be a hard worker
I mean you know that's not going to really you know get them going.
But if you say hey we want to be the best of the best and now let's say you had a champion with you
on your first meeting and it could be another sport and he takes five minutes right from there
he's a champion hey tell me how it felt when you had the confetti coming down what did what was
the parade like what was that medal like for you and all of a sudden he starts talking and you
watch the eyes the pupils man they just you know they're like golf balls and then they go to balloons
and then they go to helium balloons.
I mean my point is is that as you can see I've had the luck of being around Magic Johnson for 10
years I worked his camp I watched him walk in when he was 23 I mean you want to talk about a
thoroughbred that had a sheen on him and the way he did it with the kids and the competing and the
way he talked and the way he didn't know what he was saying in structure in my opinion of hey
here's how to do footwork what he did was he
captivated um with somebody who came from abject poverty who had a smile that lit up the earth
and now he all of a sudden he's with a six-year-old and he's you know taking the ball off him giving
the ball back and all of a sudden there's 500 kids around him and he's high-fiving them and that
well what's that word that's vision of inspiration and like I said is if you're not inspirational
get a speaker in front of the group that's inspirational and then go from there but
ultimately
that inspiration is going to flare out if you don't go underneath it and say I care about you
for more than a competitor there is the aha moment when all of a sudden that allows you to get
underneath that you say in your first meeting painting the vision hey man close your eyes
we're going to put it through the uprights and it's five four three and all of a sudden you get
to it and you say can you see it
I can see it can you see it all right and then we've got a lot of work to do open your eyes
boom boom now that's one mechanism of creating a vision and now you have the guy who's won the
medal behind you to say okay what was your hardest day and all of a sudden he starts talking
about just a monster day of what he did say five eight years ago and they go god dang we already
did that you know or we're doing it harder than that and then you're like oh my god I can't see it
at. Well, that's good. And if you're not, he is also enhancing the picture of those lock steps
that you've got to go through in order to put that ball through the uprights. That's pretty cool.
So again, as you can tell, I can go ad nauseum, but it's because of all the other people that
have shown me the way. So much gold everywhere, Mike. Again, I love the IM sheet, isn't it?
You can sort of leapfrog maybe 10 years of trying to get to know. Luke, here's what I
challenge you to do. Make three pages of questions you want to ask your wife. And write the question
down and say, all right, what's your favorite book? Okay. What's your favorite meal? What if
you had one song and it's the last song you ever listened to, what's it going to be? And you're
going to get answers off of those three pages of whatever you make up. You can't be wrong.
And I promise you seven of the 10 answers, you didn't know. I promise you. And that's a great
day. That is a great day. There's nothing to be embarrassed about. I can do that today. I've been
married 35 years. And I promise you, if I start making up random questions, really random questions,
I would probably be on the same strike rate. So my point is, dare to be different,
dare to build your own dream.
Dare to say stuff that is outrageous. Hey, if you fall over, it's all part of the process,
but not daring and not dreaming and not going after it, it's bullshit.
I love it. Married 20 years coming up this year. I will take up your challenge. And you're right.
I've already, there's questions that are coming to mind. There was something I just picked up when
you were talking about the, I interviewed a brilliant guy that I'm sure you'd be interested,
Dr. Arnie Rubenstein, who's bringing back rites of passage.
To the Western world, thousands and thousands of years where we're sophisticated, particularly
at bringing boys through because tribes worked out in Arnie's words. He was a GP for 12 years
and saw the trouble with adolescent boys and now also girls that if you didn't usher young boys
into manhood properly, then civilization didn't work. And he was bemoaning the fact that so many
leaders around the world has still got that childlike way about them. They haven't become
healthy males and he's got a sophisticated way.
Yeah. I think that's a great point. I think that's a great way of making sure we bring back
those rites of passage. And I saw a language very similar to what you were talking about,
dealing with athletes that had never been led in a way with a healthy understanding of how it is to
be a proper male in the environment you're talking about. I wanted to move to curiosity because it's
a word that we see come up with leaders a lot. And I tell you what, the curiosity coming out of
you is explosive. Is that a word that resonates? Yes. I mean, I'm curious about it. I'm curious
about it. I'm curious about it. I'm curious about it. I'm curious about it. I'm curious about it.
I'm curious about you. I'm curious about 20 years. I'm curious about your son, your daughter. I mean,
yeah, they're noted, first note them, but yes. And asking questions and nurturing questions and
also saying, hey, I don't have the answer to that. Let me go about getting the answer. But the trust
is built on follow through of saying that it took me two weeks to get to the bottom of that.
A week. But the follow through, the act of saying, hey, I went out and I searched that. And here's
what I've gotten. I don't know if it's the right answer. You've got humility in there. You've got
the search. But the key to all of it is follow through. Trust is built on the backs of a woman
of her word, a man of her word. And when your word breaks, it's OK. I mean, it's understandable,
but not excusable.
But you say, hey, I let you down here. And so this thing about I'm a man of my word. Really?
Well, let's put the video on you for 20 years and see where you broke it. And everybody does.
So my point is, your word is your handshake. OK, fine. But where you clench the deal
is the follow through. OK, I bag the groceries. I'm there. The lady thanks me. And you put the
groceries in her car. All right. And then she,
say she gives you five dollars, you know, and she says, thank you. And you look her in the eye
and say, every time you're here, Martha, I got you. All right. So now the third time she comes
through three months later and you don't got her. Well, you know, you broke your word. I mean,
if we look at ourselves in the mirror, it happens all the time. So what you're trying to do is win
the percentages of the follow through. And so, you know, being curious is,
is one thing. But be curious with essence and be curious with purpose. Don't be curious just
because you're going to ask a rhetorical question because you want everybody to think that,
you know, I'm curious and that means I'm going to be smart. Yeah, you're a smart ass is what you are.
It's it's it's brilliant. The next dimension I wanted to talk to you about, we see leaders
are really conscious of communicating with clarity. You're an English major.
You went down a path and, you know, clearly you've got a way of communicating that
is outstanding. How have you thought about that in terms of your leadership?
You already pointed to it, but I think it's it's worth repeating is that it's important
with your language that you understand that it's a tool and you have to have discipline of tongue,
a well-placed F-bomb or BS or whatever. I love it, you know, and I'm I'm not going to be
stocked. I'm not going to be stocked. I'm not going to be stocked. I'm not going to be stocked.
But I have discipline of tongue. If I'm around young ladies and at a party, I'm I have discipline
of mouth. I'm not cursing and I'm not, you know, going to going to just tell a body joke after
body joke. But a good body joke with everybody leaning in is awesome. You know, so I mean,
you have some schauser to you. I would rather be known as Schauserian and slapstick than I would,
you know, like, oh, aren't I witty? You know, I,
I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I,
I know there's a place for wit, but I'm not that guy. But, you know, offer me red wine. I can drink
it. But if you say, hey, I'd rather have a beer and a barbie. That's, I mean, to each his own.
And yet I can dress up and, and, and, and, and have a pinfold grange with anybody, you know,
who could and who wouldn't. But my, my, my point is that I think that you, you have to modulate
with your language, language,
which is the bouquet, uh, to the heart, if you will. Um, language allows you to open a human
being up. Understanding does, um, if you have to tantalize or poetry or prose that, that is
hits a nerve, uh, is the essence. But like I said, is the example I said is you got a guy
suffering a practice. His body language is an aberration. And then you take them off to the
side and your arms around me and say, Hey man, what gives? And he said, Hey, I had a really bad
day. And he said, Hey, you know, Graham, I want you to know that that very same thing happened
to me. There's going to be an explosion within that young man. If you're authentic and you're
truthful about that shared experience, well, the language of connecting and triggering and igniting
people so that they can have a good time. And I think that's, I think that's, I think that's
they want to talk to you again. That's it's everything. So the study of vernacular metaphors,
you gotta be a great storyteller. And we're none of us are when we start out, but example given
Brian Gorgian, you know, I wanted to know when they won the Rose gold, the game before what
happened to Mills Mills goes in there with Joe Ingalls and Brian Gorgian walks in and they are,
I mean, they had been fourth.
Two times over. And now it looks like they're going to be forth again. Here comes Brian through
the doors, you know, and everybody is hang dog. It's dark in the locker room. All right. And then
here he comes. Hey, get your head up. We just almost beat the United States of America. We
will revel in that later. And, you know, Joe Ingalls was looking at him. Have you lost your
mind? And he goes, no, man, that is a staging.
And he looks right at Mills and he says, you will lead us to the promised land. All right. I feel
that you percolated against the America, you know, USA dudes, we're going to do something. Nobody has
ever done in the history of basketball for Australia. The flag is high. And this is an
American. This is not somebody that was born in Australia, but he loves Australia like it's his
own. And so he hits a nerve and Mills.
Does something that nobody else has done in the history of the Olympics. I don't care if he's
white, he's brown, he's, you know, he's, he's purple. He gets 42 points and they broke the
sound barrier. And in the history of the books, when Mills and Patty's dead and Joe's dead,
God forbid, and Brian's gone, somebody is going to have to read about that team and the coaching
staff that was the first.
Of all time for Australian basketball. And so my point is that inspiration, uh, didn't know if you
were going to win, but put it on the line with his players, got their heads up. You saw the
performance. That's magic. And to me, that happens every day you go into a supermarket or you go down
the street, you can tell when somebody's suffering to take five minutes, you know, and tell, you know,
male or female and just say, Hey man, what do you got? What do you got? What's going on? And to take
that five, 10, 15 minutes, you mean to tell me you're more important than that. But, and then
you could lift that person and get them to another day. There's nothing better than that. And that
rose gold, uh, the world championship to me, helping somebody else on the same level. You can
have the ring. I gave my ring to my wife.
She's responsible for the ring. So when they gave it to me and, you know, Adam Silver's there,
and then the owner's handing you the ring, the ceremony, and we're going back to the locker room.
I, I, well, I actually, I did it before. There's still the ceremonies going on. I just got the box
and I said, it's yours. She couldn't get back to her seat. All the fans in there wanted to take
pictures with the ring, all of that. Some of the other guys were pissed off because I gave my ring
to my wife. And I said, you know, they were going, God, man, you made a mistake. You made a mistake.
You made me look bad, you know, but my point wasn't that, that my point is get your priorities
straight. You know, that's a great goal. And that's what is, but is that where we're going to
stop? And is that who I am? No, it's a great little thing. And I want excellence and I want
the ring like everybody else, but it's not the essence of what it's about. And that's what I'm
saying is there's Brian Gorgian. He's my best friend in the whole world. I played for his father.
And so I've got a great, great role model who's teaching me how to be humble and understand that
there's much thing, you know, then, then trophies and, and giving somebody life on the day of saying,
Hey, you're, I, you know, that's bad. That's bad. And that's bad. But I want you to know that me
stopping here was because of that purple dress that you've got on. Stop me. I think you look
pretty good.
Pretty good. And I'm going to say that straight up. All right. Second is I love your energy.
You're here today. You've had these three devastating things happen to you, but here you
are. And to me, that's the essence of a good day, you know, and that's what I'm saying is get base
sense. Forget about the home runs. Language is the bouquet to the heart. That, uh, that is
brilliant. And my hair stands on the back of the neck when you tell, uh, you know, gorgeous story,
the great Brian Gorgian. I've had the great privilege of doing that.
I mean, just sitting down with him in the podcast and, and hearing, uh, that story, uh, you know,
come to life and seize that moment, you know, history in Australia. And as you said, through
language and talk about a great storyteller, Brian Gorgian, uh, is world-class on that. And,
um, it is a great moment.
Oh, he's the funniest human being in the world. I don't, he is. Oh my God. Oh, and put a beer in
him. It is like fireworks. It's fireworks. I love them. I love them. Yeah.
We mentioned the collaboration that, uh, probably brought this conversation to life and clearly a
passion about collaboration. We see leaders value that more than ever. I mean, how important is
collaboration been for you? Uh, it's everything. And that's why the, the, the, the payback on
collaboration is don't you dare, if you've had other people help you make sure that your door
is always open and you know, the word yes, comes out of your mouth a lot. You can't always say yes,
because sometimes you're just busy and those things come up, but share your information,
without charge, be fearless and understand that if you really believe in your self-esteem and who
you are, there are no secrets. I don't think you have to give everything away. That's not my point,
but my point is be generous and be open and, you know, understand that you're no big deal.
You know, nobody's a big deal. Don't do it that way. You know, do it the other way.
And like you said, is I, was it Rubenstein Rubenstein that you were talking about earlier?
Yeah. And what he's talking about are missing chips and building those chips within, uh, young
men in particular, there's been an, uh, you know, uh, an emasculation unintentionally of, of, uh,
generations now of young men who need to be shepherded through to, like I said, is know how
to act and do certain things. But the problem is, is that the imprint or the modeling is, is broken.
So you, you have to go through these arduous steps in order to reclaim that soul and who that young
man ultimately is going to be because it's worth it. It's absolutely worth it.
Uh, beautifully, uh, said my, but asking these two questions of all the leaders,
I've had the great privilege of sitting down with like yourself, uh, who has been the greatest
leader in your life? Uh, in my life, uh, is Ed, Ed Gorge and Brian's father. Uh, and, and, uh,
I can't leave out my own father. My father was a high-risk surgeon, OBGYN, started his clinic
in a log cabin and ended up being 55 doctors. Tanana Valley Clinic, it's timeless. It's still
in Fairbanks, Alaska. And he was the essence of serving your community. Chief of staff,
you go four years. He did it for 24 years. They vote you into the chair. He retired out of that
chair with the Fairbanks Memorial Hospital. If you go into Fairbanks and you, at the time,
he was delivering almost every baby in a community of 30,000. So he gave his heart and soul to a
community. Then you go to Ed Gorgian and just, you know, from being a model as a father to
how he raised his sons to coaching me at a tender age where I was very vulnerable.
I would say,
without question, those two. And then finally, you know, being with my wife, Molly, for 35 years,
you know, you have to be lucky. But I mean, so she, as a leader of our family and the way she's
done things to keep everything together, a full credit to her as well.
Well said again. I love, as you said, the fortune to have great leaders in your life. And you went
straight to it. There was no hesitation. And yeah, fascinating to hear that.
In the spirit of collaboration and clear, that's a huge part of who you are already. And you're
connecting with extraordinary leaders around the world, as we mentioned, and our passion for
relief. You could collaborate with anyone in the world, Mike, in any of your areas of passion. Is
there someone that springs to mind? Oh, in a global way, John Wooden was in my life as a young
man. And I hung on to his coattails and just kept learning from Coach Wooden. Pete Newell, who I had
mentioned,
it is unbelievable. George Carl, I worked for him, and he was phenomenal. Obviously, I mentioned
Ed Gorgian. But if you want to talk about people of fame, those three, George Carl, Hall of Fame,
Pete Newell, Hall of Fame, and Brian Gorgian. Again, he's a Hall of Famer in Australia.
Everything that award that they have over there for the highest,
uh, awards that they give, Brian's in that, that, that stratosphere. Um, and then I could go on and
on because I have the underpinnings of moving out once a week. Matt LaFleur, I mean, he's a young
coach in the NFL, and I seize the opportunity to go to his practice and shadow him. We're building
a relationship. Uh, so, I mean, I, I could go probably at least 30 minutes a week. I could go
30 minutes and give you a pyramid of, of, of, uh, people, uh, within, uh, David Wheaton, you know,
uh, what he introduced me to all these people in Australia and rules footy. And so Eddie Jones,
I was up at the, you know, Canberra and I met Eddie Jones. He talked to the national team for,
and I was helping the national team with Brian. And so I sat in on him. So when we see each other
on the, the zoom meeting with the world symposium,
it's like old home week, you know, and Hey, Eddie, how you doing? Hey, Mike, how you doing?
And so my point is Eddie Jones is very, very, very special. Charlie Walsh, you know, the greatest
cycling coach that Australia has ever had. Somebody wants to argue that that's okay. Cause I don't
know it like that. I just know that he was phenomenal with the Olympic team, Bill Nelson,
who was the assistant coach with the national swimming team out of Newcastle. And I mean,
I was all over.
You know, anybody that, that, that had something I was, was, was on it. Um, so yeah, I mean, um,
you know, Pat Riley, um, for five years, I watched him coach cause they used our gym at Loyola
Marymount. So I was the caretaker of the key that let them in for their practices. And I didn't know
really who he was. He was the announcer before he became the head coach. And so I just sat in there
and had a little yellow pad and made notes, you know, on stuff. And I knew magic Johnson.
So, I mean, if I go into these places, it's like a bunch of capillaries. I've, you know,
I'm a wanderer in terms of knowledge and, uh, you know, things, you know, I, I think every sport
women's volleyball, I can tell you that I used some netball routines on hand-eye coordination and,
and pivot.
It's netball teachers. And, and in particular, the women, that's why they have such a high rate
of anterior cruciate tears is because of the jump stops and netball. But that's another story,
but Jan Sterling, the best female coach in Australia that I ever, ever saw. And then I
would put her in the top five male coaches for sure in Australia and her adroitness,
the way she did what she did when she was in Adelaide.
Speaker 2
phenomenal. And so as you see, I feel terrible by leaving out another name. I can just go,
I Graham Korn's was so good to me.
And I did go to a crow's practice and I watched him do what he did. And he has anybody who knows
Graham corn's knows that he is really good with people. I mean, he makes you feel good when he
walks away from a conversation. Cause he's, he's upbeat. It's really hard for Graham corn's to be
negative. You know, he's an,
upbeat human being in the way that he does what he does but you know so my point is is that
everybody has a little bit to offer and my guy i think it's probably in some ways uh the my favorite
answer and i've heard that from for many people but you can just see as a life of uh collecting
knowledge and engaging with people you know an australian netball coach to uh you know the the
highest levels of of your sport and others and and some of the best in the world you've uh clearly
got a passion for that continued sharing and learning and and the humility that comes across
and everything you say mike has been uh inspiring to listen to i thank you so much for for taking
the time and uh it's been a great pleasure to spend the day with you thanks a lot yeah thank
you luke and thank matt and it's one of the best interviews most insightful and laser like and i
i can tell you really really really prepared
so i enjoyed it and uh good health to your family i hope we get a yeah a beer with brian
gorgin one day would be a lot of fun so yeah oh my god i need to make that happen next time we're
around so thanks again empowering leaders was presented by me luke darcy produced by matt
with audio production by darcy thompson start your leadership journey i encourage you to go
to a leader collective.com take our empowering leaders indicator tool and understand the impact
you have on your environment join us
at a leader to learn lead and collaborate listener