A Listener Production.
G'day, it's Luke Darcy.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership both on and off the field
has been a lifelong passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective
and have had the privilege of working with thousands of leaders
in education, sport, industry and the arts
that have helped shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership
where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
Mim Bartlett is a champion for strong, authentic leadership and well-being.
She's a qualified lawyer, psychotherapist, a sought-after coach facilitator,
human rights champion and gender equality advocate.
As a fluent Chinese speaker, she spent six years living and working
in China, Hong Kong and Singapore in law, sales and marketing.
In 2015, Mim was recognised as one of the Financial Review's
100 Women of Influence.
Mim's work focuses on connecting people, ideas and resources
that can lead to a better future.
It's a personal fulfilment and social change in today's world.
In her work at Mim Bartlett Consulting, she challenges people
to define their unique passion or intersection, maximise their potential
and generate positive change for themselves, their work, their families
and the communities they serve.
Mim, it's great to catch up with you today.
Thank you, Luke. It's wonderful to be here.
I'm always actually a bit nervous.
I'm reading out someone's bio hoping that I...
I was looking at you going, have I got that accurate?
Have I missed out something important there?
I feel like it might have been short-changing you.
So, at the start...
Luke, I'm feeling a little bit embarrassed as I'm sitting here
hearing you say all that.
So, yeah, beautiful. Thank you.
It's you with all your accolades.
It's straight back at you.
Well, I look at your life.
It's an amazing story of leadership and contribution.
I wanted to start by asking, where did that sense of drive come from
and also that sense of purpose and giving back to the community?
Yeah, it's a really good question.
Mum was really involved as a volunteer at a number of, like, hospitals
and also in Melbourne and did a lot of fundraising herself.
And then, you know, Dad did that in his own way.
I think going to Loretto, a Catholic school,
which had a really strong sense of social justice.
So, you know, not that I'm aligned with everything around Catholicism,
that's for sure, but certainly their values around social justice
really, I think, stirred something inside me.
And so it was very easy for me to kind of do more
of that as I got older.
And, yeah, I think it really, like, invoked my passions.
Chatting to people in preparation for the catch-up,
they had this sense of you, even as a teenager,
that you were someone that looked like you were going to be
the best version of yourself, that even from the youngest possible age
there was this sense that you were on a path to constantly be the best.
Is that your recollection even at a young age?
Yeah.
That's funny.
I think I know who you've been speaking to.
You can be.
Look, I have.
I've always been really driven and motivated and, yeah,
have wanted to be, I guess, the best I can be.
And I even remember when my parents sat us down and said
that they were going to divorce and I said to myself, you know,
after that conversation, I'm just not going to let this get in my way.
I've kind of, like, stopped me from, I don't want to kind of collapse
and be that kid.
Yeah.
So it was interesting.
Yeah, it has been.
Look, I have been really driven.
Not around, like, title or status, but more around really just performing
at my best and being at my best, whatever I wanted to do.
And, no, I haven't always achieved that.
My God, I was a terrible lawyer.
I was terrible in marketing.
I don't think I was a great therapist, but I've really,
so I did work for a brief time as a psychotherapist,
but I really feel I found my sweet spot in the work I do over the last 21 years.
But certainly my early years, I really don't feel I excelled at all
in my career.
I worked with some great companies and some great, you know,
law firms and things, but I don't think I did a great job.
Which is interesting to hear, isn't it?
Because you're, like anyone, there's always the ebbs and flows of life.
What age were you when mum and dad separated?
So I was in year seven.
Yeah.
And it was interesting, at a school like La Roche, a Catholic school,
I was the only girl in my year.
You know, like, I was pretty, pretty, you know, that wasn't common then.
You know, so it was, yeah, it was, I mean, thankfully,
there's more of that reflected now.
So, you know, kids whose parents come from a divorced or single family
don't feel that stigma.
Yeah.
But, yeah, no, it was more on the unusual side, particularly Catholic school.
You forget how nuclear an event that is, isn't it?
For even now that it's, you know, 50% or more is the stat,
so we know that that's happening to half the population,
but it's still a massive part of your child.
And your memory was, that's pretty impressive at that age.
This is big, but it's not going to affect who I am.
Yeah, that's, I really, I mean,
I only kind of later reflect back and think of that.
That's right.
But there are also so many single-parent families these days
and single mothers and, you know, different types of families,
blended families, but same-sex families, you know, we didn't see that.
Yeah.
I didn't see that growing up at the school that I went to,
so it's lovely to see more of that.
And then you go on and you do a double degree,
Law and Arts at Melbourne University,
but your major in Mandarin Chinese, you know,
you humbly said that you weren't,
you weren't necessarily a great lawyer or great in sales,
but that is an amazing path to follow.
Where did the passion come to go down that path?
So I really enjoyed debating at school.
And so I thought I got good marks, you know, in HSC and thought,
why didn't I do law?
Because I wasn't really sure what I wanted to do
and I might be a barrister.
And I'd done French in year 12.
I'd enjoyed it.
I'd done well at it.
And I thought, now I've done a European language.
I'd love to do a different language.
And so at Melbourne Uni I went and interviewed the head
of the Russian, Chinese and Japanese departments,
just to kind of talk to them about the possibility
of me studying that language to get a feel for it.
And so in those days, it was the mid-80s.
Japanese was the flavour of the month
and everyone was studying Japanese.
And so I thought, I don't want to do that.
I want to do something a bit different.
And then I really liked the Chinese department head.
And so that's really why I chose Chinese.
But it was tough.
Because in first year, I was in the department head.
And I was in the department head.
And in my first year uni studying Chinese,
I was put in the same year as all the kids
who'd gone to schools like Caulfield Grammar
and Melbourne Grammar,
where Chinese was offered through school,
whereas Loretto didn't.
So I had to kind of catch up with them in the same,
you know, and they've done like 12 or six years of Chinese.
So it was pretty challenging that first year.
Like, and really hard,
because the characters are really hard to draw.
It's not like European language.
It's just the speaking.
You've got to do the characters as well.
So my friends teased me about how much I'd study
and all these.
But it was fantastic.
It opened so many interesting doors and opportunities,
particularly China was communist, very communist then.
And so it was really interesting
because there weren't many women
and many people studying it in those days.
It's an amazing mindset to take that on, isn't it?
Without any background and then to become fluent in Chinese
is an amazing achievement.
To jump forward to a bit of Min Bartlett Consulting,
and I, you know, reading a lot about it
and love the language that,
the use, and I reflect a bit of it back to you.
Inspire and support personal transformation,
authentic leadership, as I said in the intro,
coach people to lead more purposeful lives,
to have a greater clarity in all aspects of their life.
It's a global business.
You work across Asia, UK and Europe.
Your passion for authentic leadership,
can you talk about that?
Yeah, look, that's such a big question.
It's for me about really being yourself.
And I think there's so much pressure in our culture
to be yourself.
To be something that other people want you to be.
And so I really want to empower and encourage people
to be truly themselves, which takes a lot of confidence
and to also really be intentional about how they want to lead
and who they want to be, not just professionally,
but also in their personal lives.
And really, because we know that when you're flourishing
in your personal life, you bring all that engagement
and joy to work and kind of, I'm probably going,
I'm a bit ahead of myself, but, you know,
corporates and employers are now understanding
that we need to like reflect and consider
and invest in the whole person.
And so that's been a big shift by corporates,
I think, aided and abetted by COVID,
really seeing the impact of mental health
and what that's meant to people
and the way they show up at work.
And so, and I think leadership has really evolved
over the last couple of decades.
And it's been great seeing that EQ and kind of,
just self-awareness has come much more to the fore
than in previous years where IQ has been, you know,
the dominant kind of, you know, the it factor.
Yeah, it's brilliant, Mam.
It's exactly what we sort of identified
as that real shift in leadership.
And, you know, you sum that up beautifully.
In my mind, it's sort of, you know,
away from the old hierarchy and command and control
and the boss with the big corner office
who intimidated people and, you know,
you either towed the line, you didn't get a voice,
you didn't get a,
and now we're seeing this whole generation
of people understanding exactly your language.
If you care about people authentically
and you look after them
and you've got a bit of your own self-awareness
and a bit of your own self-reflection,
it's not only is it a more harmonious environment,
it's a more productive environment as well.
And is that what you're seeing,
that the opportunity's there for us, you know,
to share that message in a more powerful way?
Absolutely.
People leave organisations because of poor leaders
and people,
go to organisations because of great leaders
and leadership has been really tipped upside down
and it is exciting because also there's,
organisations are much flasher in their structures now
and so, you know,
employers are kind of not like waiting to kind of
to anoint people to be leaders
but they're wanting them to step up as a leader
kind of regardless of what level you're at,
that whole piece around self-leadership
that I know that you're big on at a leader
and just knowing that,
every time, you know,
everywhere you behave,
you have an impact on culture
and so to be really intentional and mindful
about the impact that you can have,
both personally and professionally
because whether you like it or not,
you are impacting others
and you are, you know,
creating culture and impacting culture.
So, yeah, I think to be really purposeful about that.
And we're seeing that, Mim,
in the sporting world,
which is, you know,
where I've spent a fair bit of my working life.
It's a massive shift.
The era that I grew up playing in,
it was really blunt and brutal
when you either coped or you didn't.
And we sort of laugh a little bit
about how ridiculous it was, you know,
someone standing at the front
personally abusing you on a regular basis
and you either could cope with that or you couldn't,
but pretty sad really
because you look back and you think,
and in fairness to those guys,
they didn't know any different.
They didn't have any skills really to do any better,
but it probably pushed a lot of people away
who haven't had great experiences.
But there is,
it's spawned a new generation.
These next generation of senior coaches,
they've got great care and great,
and they just worked out it's smarter and it's better.
If you buy into someone
and you care about them as a whole person,
they're going to perform better.
Absolutely.
No, no question.
That would have been pretty, pretty brutal.
And I think there are, you know,
there's some cultures in corporate
that still have got those old remnants
and particularly more the male dominated industries.
Because I think as more women
get into more senior leadership positions,
they bring a slightly different type of leadership
and more collaborative, compassionate,
dare I say loving.
Yeah.
They actually really care and they bring more of that.
And that's not to put men down.
It's more the men have been more socialized
to be a certain way and to hide their vulnerability
and to not share emotions so much.
So it's very understandable,
but it's very important that the culture's changing.
And I honestly think that with the change,
recently in the federal government,
that a more inclusive, collaborative,
like compassionate leadership is being modeled.
And I saw that a couple of days
after the election result already in corporates,
very senior leaders talking about
how they already feel that a different type of leadership
is being modeled,
which will trickle down into corporates.
Yeah, which is brilliant, isn't it?
Even my own experience in recent times
being around many more female leaders,
it's just,
the ego's gone immediately.
It's just taken that heat out of the room
and the intelligence and the sense of just wanting
to get on and do a great job.
And I think it's an interesting conversation, isn't it?
The fact that it's taken so long to get here
and there's still such a long way to go,
but clearly that is something that you're doing.
And I want to talk about so many things with you.
There's so much to get through,
but I mean, to me, you teach about purpose and passion,
but you live it in everything you do.
And, you know, catching up with you in recent times,
straight away, you're onto the things that matter
and that are purposeful.
And I wanted to share a few of them.
And one of the first things we sat down last time,
you mentioned it's Time We Talk,
which is a violence prevention project
that supports young people and parents and schools
and communities in general
to address the influence of pornography.
And it's not an easy topic to discuss.
I found it confronting.
I found it even as, you know, as a parent of four,
it's like, God, there's an elephant in the room there
that a lot of us don't know where to start,
but it's one of many things you're passionate about.
Can you tell us about why you delved into this space?
Because look, I forgot to ask you,
did you read that article I sent you,
the Mamma Mia article?
Yeah, I did.
Yeah, yeah.
It's confronting.
It's really good.
That's such a good one to share.
So I found out about it in 2012.
I have twin boys, Nick and Rich,
and they were in year seven.
And they came home and told me about
the large number of kids who are watching porn
on their iPhones and iPads at school.
And so they were in year seven.
And that really shocked me.
And I thought, look, I need to do something about this.
So I researched and found out about a project
called Reality and Risk.
And you'll write the website, itstimewetalk.com.
And the Victorian Women's Trust,
which is a fantastic not-for-profit in Melbourne
advocating for women's rights,
they were working with them to raise funds
because they needed more funds.
And so I sourced an introduction
to them and was really shocked
when I found out where pornography had gone.
So I don't watch porn, so it was all very new to me.
But what I learned was that mainstream porn
has become so much more violent these days.
And so just kind of a few stats
to kind of bring that to life.
So the best-selling porn, 48% of best-selling porn
is verbally aggressive to women.
So you're whore.
You're whatever.
88% of best-selling porn is physically aggressive.
So choking, slapping and gagging.
And then 94% of it is being directed at females
who express pleasure whilst being treated that way.
So porn not only suggests that violence against women is sexy,
it's like, it's erotic.
So it's really eroticising violence against women.
And so because it is the most prominent sex educator
for young people,
and it's not just for women,
and the stats around 90% of boys and 60% of girls
have seen porn often before they've often first kissed.
Yeah.
So, and it's such a,
it's just really shaping their idea of sex and relationships.
So I wanted to do something about that
because I was really appalled at that.
And 30% of all internet traffic is porn.
So it's such a big industry.
So I was really excited to hear about Marie Crabb
and Dave Corlett's work.
And so what I did was they were looking to raise money
for their secondary school's education kit,
which is brilliant,
which I brought into a number of schools
and got friends kind of to, you know,
mobilise friends such as our mutual friends,
to bring it into other schools
and to educate parents and young people about it.
Yeah.
And what I love about you, Mim,
is that, you know, people see this challenge,
you go and do something about it in almost every sense.
And that is a whole other podcast on its own to deal into.
And as you said, it is, in some ways,
you're left in the room, but, you know, me included,
it's, I was telling you one of my oldest,
you know, I think he was 11 or 12,
came home and just said, I've seen something I can't,
I don't feel well, you know, it's, you know,
growing up someone might've had a magazine
that you might've been able to see,
which was a nude picture of a woman or,
which might've been the,
what you're now getting access to
is this incredibly hardcore violent,
that's shaping, you know, the next generation.
So.
So again, I'm going to move on to your other,
because there's so many of them
and that's not to discount
how important that conversation is.
And it certainly has me thinking on a whole heap of levels,
but you throw yourself into incredible causes
and I wanted to mention them.
You mentioned to me as well last time,
the rites of passage for young people
and how that's now become something
that's missed really in our lives.
Dr. Arne Rubenstein is someone that you've connected with.
Can you just share a little bit on that one
and why that's so important as well?
Well, firstly, Luke, good on you
for having the conversation
because it is a really hard conversation,
but it is so important.
And it's important that the fathers
are having these conversation
as well as the mothers
or whatever same sex relationship you're in,
especially with the young boys
that their fathers are also talking about this.
And there are some great resources
on that website to help you
because a lot of people are highly uncomfortable
talking about this.
And yeah, you know, my boys are squirming,
you know, even though like they're used to
kind of me bring up all this type of thing.
Um, so, uh, the Rites of Passage program
is just wonderful.
It's a work, as you say, of Dr. Arne Rubenstein,
who is globally recognized and an author and speaker.
And he goes into hundreds of schools worldwide,
as well as running these Rites of programs
on his property in Mullumbimby, New South Wales.
And he is a doctor and he felt quite,
he was a GP and felt quite disillusioned
with the number of,
you know, teenage boys
that would come into his practice
that he knew as young boys
who were like, he would describe
a shell of their former selves.
And he wanted to do something different
about how they were kind of marking
their turning point from young boys,
from teenagers into kind of young men
and felt that our Western culture
around drinking and kind of risk-taking behavior
wasn't a great initiation.
And so he did some research globally,
best practice, indigenous cultures
and psychology and created this incredible five-day program
where fathers and sons or carers,
if you don't have a father, go with them.
And he works with about 20 young men
and 20 adults at a time.
And it's really bringing them together
in a very safe psychological space
where the men do a lot of sharing
about very intimate and very important topics
that you wouldn't normally discuss with your son.
And the young boys hear different perspectives
from all sorts of men.
But once again, very, very,
very important.
And then there is an actual rite of passage
that's obviously secret,
kind of secret men's business,
but it's held really safely
where the young men have to do something
to kind of move into the next stage.
And there's beautiful acknowledgement
by the older men.
And it's extremely bonding
and it's great for everyone's self-awareness.
And I love it because for many reasons,
but often the fathers think they're going for their sons
and that's incredible.
But what happens is that
it opens up a new world for them.
It opens up the men's hearts
for many of them who haven't done any work
or themselves
and it increases their self-awareness
and that has a ripple effect
when they go home to their relationships
and the way they parent their other kids
and the way they are as a leader in the work.
So it has so many other ripple effects.
Yeah, it's brilliant, isn't it?
As you said, lost their way
in the Western space so much.
I'm having spent,
lucky enough to spend some time out
on the Indigenous communities
and it's thousands of years old.
The secret men's business is really,
an amazing cultural thing
that we haven't really learned from
and it's the village raising the child
as we hear that term,
but we don't know how to do it anymore
and it feels like you're surrounded
by more people than ever,
but on your own more,
if that makes sense, isn't it?
It's such a brilliant thing
that you're championing again, Mim.
It's one of the great,
we talk about, Beck and I,
a lot about the outside role models
and trying to facilitate that,
but it's a lot of work
in trying to do that outside,
out of the family, isn't it?
It's not an easily accessible thing.
It's been lost.
So another great,
a great passion project.
Luke, I look forward to you doing it
and having a conversation with you after.
Yeah, that's right.
And you can always chat to Mike about it
or anyone,
bring up my husband,
have a chat about it
because some people feel a bit nervous about it,
but Mike's a pretty,
you know, mainstream type of guy
and he's done it with all our three boys
and just loved it.
So he's always welcome to talk to men
who are a little bit nervous about it.
And since you've mentioned,
there's a couple of friends of mine
who didn't know had done it
and who have done it
who share the same experience,
which is,
which is great.
So maybe practice on the older two.
The younger two are still in that zone
where I could maybe,
maybe get them up there.
I do want to keep moving through
because I love what you do
in which is,
you know,
create so many opportunities for change
in spaces that,
that you're passionate about
reading about a couple of others.
She,
EO,
addressing another huge problem,
isn't it?
That female founders,
I think reading some of your work,
only two and a half percent
of venture capital funds
go towards female founders
and,
and again,
you put your money,
your time,
your passion
and your intelligence
towards things that count.
How's that project unfolded?
Look,
that's great.
I'm not,
I'm not super involved
in it,
but it's,
I'm very honoured to be part of it.
And it's because of that statistics
that less than 2.5%
of venture capital funding
go to female led startups.
And it was created by Vicky Saunders,
who's an incredible Canadian,
super kind of moving shaker.
She,
wanted to right that kind of injustice.
And so it's a global movement.
And what's wonderful
is it is,
we're called activators.
We put in a thousand dollar
non-refundable loan
that goes into a pool
and female led ventures
that are making an impact
in terms of hitting
those sustainable development goals.
They apply for funding
and we vote on them as an activator.
Five,
there are five winners in Australia.
They get to take that money as a loan
and they get incredible support,
they get a huge connection.
They get mentoring for some,
from some really fabulous senior women.
And so it's an incredible community.
So it's women supporting women.
And we find out about these incredible businesses
that are actually having fantastic social impact.
And, and, you know,
if you don't have a thousand dollars,
you can put in,
get 10 friends and put in a hundred dollars each,
but you're part of this community.
They do incredible Zoom get togethers,
face, you know,
face to face get togethers.
There's so many different topics
that you can learn from and share with each other.
So once again,
it's creating community amongst women
and supporting other women.
It's, it's really a beautiful initiative.
As I said,
all of these feel like their own podcast
in their own right, ma'am.
I feel,
I recommend you.
Well, that's right.
Yeah, I will follow up
because they're incredible stories.
You know,
you've, you've supported the Man Cave
and Hunter Johnson's work,
the Asylum Seeker Resource Centre.
But I wanted to touch,
you know,
again,
our conversations,
both of those,
to skim over them.
Doesn't seem to do it justice
in any way,
shape or form.
But Mental Walks,
I was looking at that.
That is another brilliant initiative.
And can you tell us a little bit
about what you're doing there?
Yeah, wonderful.
So that's,
once again,
that's also a bigger global movement
and the founders in Australia,
a Bobbi Marlab and Adina Jacobs,
and they're in Shanghai on a,
at a business conference.
And someone said to them,
hey,
there's a group of women,
you know,
mentoring,
walking for an hour,
you know,
tomorrow morning,
would you be interested?
And that's how they found out about it.
And basically,
we have some incredible mentors
across Australia.
We're in every capital city
and some regional spots as well.
And as a mentor,
you need to be,
you know,
asked to be part of it.
So there's Successful Women in Business,
Government,
and the Entrepreneurial World.
And as a mentee,
you pay $30.
We are a not-for-profit,
so it's covering the admin costs.
And you put your kind of burning question
in the website,
what you would love some guidance on,
whether it's confidence or networking
or managing
a difficult boss
or how to start up a new business
or how to move industries,
whatever it might be.
And we will match you with the best mentor
that we feel would support you
around that question.
We meet in Melbourne outside the NGV
around the TAN once a month
on a Friday morning,
7.15 a.m.
We generally get around 30-35 mentees
and we match one to three mentees
with a mentor.
And then we set off around the TAN
and it's like a group coaching session
where you ask insightful questions,
give some advice and suggestions
and then the bonds that the mentees create,
they often stay in touch with each other
and often returning mentees do come back often
and then we'll always pair them
with a different mentor.
So it's incredible networking
and incredible community once again.
It's so simple walking and talking.
And there are a lot of women
who don't have any networks
or don't have people to ask,
ideas and guidance.
What should I do?
How should I do this?
So it's once again a very simple
but really powerful initiative.
That's brilliant, Mim,
and I love it.
And as you know,
I've done a little bit of homework
from a mutual friend
and she said,
you know,
if you want to describe Mim,
she, you know,
her leadership is so incredible
that all of her work she does
is basically about
how can she contribute more
and, you know,
I often say to people doing interviews like this,
you actually reflect and go,
I need to lift my game seriously
because you set the benchmark so high.
But when you look at your passion for that,
I mean, people who live the way you do
feel as though that's what makes you tick.
And as I said,
there's so many great causes.
I mean, is that what really the essence
of what you're doing
is all about trying to support
these great community projects?
Yeah, absolutely.
And also living an integrated life around it, Luke.
So in the past,
I would never mix my personal and professional life.
But once I started,
to do it,
I saw that there are so many kind of win-wins.
A lot of my corporate executives
that I was working with,
they were looking for more purpose
and meaning in their lives.
And so when I started to share examples
of what I was doing,
kind of in the community,
they were really interested to learn more about it.
And so by combining those two parts of my life,
you know, it's been incredible
for the different not-for-profits
and community initiatives
I've been involved in
because I have more resources
and more money
and more kind of mental,
more resource or involved in those organizations.
And it's been great for my clients
because they now have more purpose and meaning.
They're giving back
and they're feeling more fulfilled
and they're connecting with more people.
And so it's had a lot of win-wins
just leveraging the different parts of my life
to kind of, to support the different,
to support the different parts of my life.
And I think it's a great segue, Mim,
because, you know,
what I wanted to touch on as well,
and maybe the greatest
achievement, you know,
I look at, you know,
your life and what you've done
is the fact you've been able to do that
and raise this incredible family.
And I've had the great pleasure of meeting Mike,
your husband, who is a legend
and brilliant in everything he does in his own right.
And Nick and Rich, the twin boys are, you know,
captain and vice captain of Melbourne Grammar.
They both have gone on to study at Cambridge.
Tom, the younger brother,
also captain of Melbourne Grammar,
studying at the University of Pennsylvania,
I think at the moment, if I've got that right.
I mean, for someone listening to that, Mim, you know,
there's so much going on in your world.
What's been the secret to be able to balance family life
and have these incredibly healthy
and successful high-achieving boys as well?
Oh, look, and Luke, I mean, you know,
regardless of their achievement,
like I don't want to kind of place too much with you.
They are really beautiful boys.
Look.
They're amazing achievements.
I mean, you have to, I mean,
you want everyone to follow passion, Mim,
but that is remarkable to have three boys
that have got the dedication to go and pursue further
studies overseas.
It's incredible, you know.
It's kind of heartbreaking too, Luke,
because I'm so happy they're following in their dreams,
but it's really hard as a mum and I'm sure you can imagine
if all your kids lived overseas.
Yeah.
But they are very fulfilled, which is fabulous,
which is part of the reason I'm expanding my business overseas.
Look, I think having a very supportive partner where,
you know, we've both kind of been able to pick up
the domestic and caring responsibilities together
and we've been on the same wavelength
around parenting.
We've had similar values around parenting
and it's been really important to Mike as well.
Certainly marrying Mike, who's 12 years older than me,
meant that he'd kind of, he worked at Morgan Stanley
kind of for 15 years globally and he worked,
you know, basically his ass off so hard.
So by the time he had kids, he had kids a bit later,
being a bit older than me, it meant that he could devote
more time to the kids.
I think his presence, you know, in the boy's life
has been really profound.
And he hadn't done any personal work,
any self-awareness work when I met him in Hong Kong
and I kind of brought him along on the journey
and he was so open, Luke, and that's just been terrific.
So he did a Gestalt therapy part-time course
when I was studying Gestalt therapy and he's done
all sorts of, you know, different personal awareness.
We've done therapy together and I think it's actually
really good to normalise that like it's,
we don't have to be in a bad place to do therapy.
It's like going to the gym, getting in-person training,
you don't have to be super-informed.
You just want to be, kind of, improve where you're already at
and I think, so that's why I like to kind of be open
that I do therapy and Mike and I have done therapy.
It's a great conversation, Mimi, because, you know,
I know you're a fan of the positive psychology world
as well with Martin Seligman put on the agenda,
but I'll go back, you know, to your own reference to sporting.
A reference was if you were going to see the club sports psychologist,
everyone would be like, jeez, he's in real trouble, you know.
He's breaking up with his marriage or his girlfriend
or, and that's been transcended so much more to,
that is a performance tool and, in fact,
probably the best place you can get going
because physically you can't improve, you know,
tiny percentages really, but emotionally and mentally
and the idea of, you know, being a really happy couple
but wanting to expand that makes sense, doesn't it?
That stigma was there for so long.
Oh, and look, I don't want to, I don't want to kind of sugarcoat,
like we've had issues like everybody.
Yeah.
So, I'm not saying like we're in a bad, you know,
we're in like in the depths of just about to separate,
but more just to kind of, if we wanted an external person
who, you know, is objective.
Yeah.
And, you know, can support us both and can hold that space
and that's, you know, they're, they're the experts.
So.
Yeah.
It is such a good thing to do.
Yeah, amazing.
I'm sort of a role model for our boys.
Yeah.
If they, you know, having anxiety or depression
or just want some, just want some support in their life
that they then can go off and see a therapist without any shame,
just wanting to improve themselves
because it means then they'll be, you know, more self-aware
and hopefully be a better partner and a better parent
if that's what they choose to be
and a better leader in whatever they do.
I mean, I feel compelled to tell Rich's story.
It's an incredible, and I know you're open to share it
as Rich has been as well.
And it's an amazing story.
As a 17-year-old, Rich stands in front of 800 people
at Melbourne Grammar, the whole school community
and comes out as an openly gay young man.
His twin brother is alongside of him
to a standing ovation in the end and he goes on to deliver,
deliver that speech around schools all around us.
I mean, I'm blown away by the leadership
and the courage of your young, young man at that stage.
I mean, it must have been an incredibly proud moment.
Yeah, look, it was kind of nail-bitingly
because I only found out that he was going to come out that way
by delivering a speech at the Pride Week service
that they had at Melbourne Grammar.
And I only found out the night before when my other,
his twin brother, Nick, our other, one of our other sons said,
you know, did you know that Rich is going to come out tomorrow?
I've just seen his, you know, his speech kind of printed out
on the computer, on the printer.
So I was so nervous because I didn't know how that would be received
because no one had been so openly kind of out at Melbourne Grammar.
I think that was part of Rich's, the premise behind his decision
to do it so publicly so that there would be kind of no shame
and it was okay to be, to be a gay man.
Yeah.
I mean, he was a gay, a gay boy at an all-boys school.
I think it, you know, at a mixed co-ed school, probably less stigma.
But that, that was really important for him.
And he, and he, you know, he, he was a great debater
and he loved public speaking and he, you know,
really wanted to take this message more broadly.
So just to make it easier for other kids to be more open
about who they are and their sexuality.
And a lot of kids would come up to him or contact him later at schools
and say, thank you so much for kind of just normalising that at my school.
It's an amazing effort.
It's just, you know, as I said, I, I can't imagine having the courage
at that age to, to, to, to blaze that trail.
It's, it's, it's such an amazing thing.
It's, you know, there is some, it's worth having a look at if you,
if you have.
And I love the fact that then to go around and understand
the standing ovations at schools all around the state.
I mean, that in itself again is, you know, what he has done
for, for so many people where, as you said, going through
that would have had enormous challenge.
And again, the stats for, for young people who are working out their sexuality,
it's horrific.
It's, it's, it's been a car crash really.
So it's an amazing legacy.
Is it, does he look back on it now and, and, and understand his own courage?
Is it, is it just?
I'm not sure.
He, he's now, he's now in, and, and look, and look, Luke,
to say that there are so many other young people doing that as well.
So there are so many great stories of young people owning their sexuality
in a more public way.
So Richie's one of many, but, but thank you.
Look, he's over in London now and he's doing some,
so he works full time.
I'm for corporate, excuse me, but he's working for an LGBTIQ
not-for-profit over there, just like us, where he goes into corporates
and schools to talk about sexuality and, and being gay
and kind of what that means.
And, and so he, you know, he's still really continuing that work
and loving that work and writing articles for the Gay Times,
which is a, an LGBTIQ news platform over there.
And he's on the LGBTIQ International Committee at the corporate he works for.
So he's very, he's, you know, still feels really strongly about that
and talks about just, you know,
he talks about just not wanting to have shame around who he is.
And, and yeah, so yeah, no, we are proud.
We, we love him very much.
And his twin brother was instrumental in instigating the,
the pride round as part of the first 18 footy community as well.
And so the support and the, you know, even not being in touch,
I remember that story just reverberating around the city
as this incredible, you know, positive experience.
So, you know, you can hear listening to you,
you're not surprised that it took a family like yours
to allow that space for someone to do something,
you know, which we think probably, you know,
all these things should have happened many years ago,
but they haven't.
It takes, you know, as I said, amazing leadership to, to get there.
It's incredible.
Thanks, Luke.
But the more we can just accept our kids, whatever they might be,
whatever diversity they have, whether it's learning abilities
or just anything just to love them for who they are.
Because if you don't, then you set them forth in the world with,
you know, a lot more insecurities and baggage.
That we all need.
Yep.
It's the ultimate leadership, isn't it?
Absolutely.
To do that.
I mean, there's so many questions and places to go,
but fascinated given your passion for this space to get you,
we see these dimensions of modern leadership appearing regularly
in different shapes and sizes and different diversity as well.
And we've been asking leaders these same questions,
starting with self-leadership.
I mean, we see that as being something that, you know,
the leaders who are self-reflective are really conscious of.
Does that term resonate with you?
That's right.
I love self-leadership.
Leadership is like from an inside-out perspective.
And so really acknowledging whether we have a title or status
or platform as kind of a leader.
We all are leaders in every part of our life.
And I think the more intention or mindfulness that we can bring to that
and think about how do we want to show up as a leader in our family
and our friendships.
How do we want to show up as a leadership group, community and professionally?
Because then the impact will be more positive that we can have.
I think we all underestimate our influence and impact.
And so I think it's a really beautiful term.
And it's becoming so much more commonplace, which is great.
So people are stepping up more into their leadership without having to,
as I said, kind of be anointed.
Yeah, having a title isn't necessary anymore.
And that ability to, as you said, to impact yourself first and others.
You mentioned mindfulness.
I know we share a passion for the meditation space as well.
Is that part of your daily world?
Is that something that you still value?
Yeah, it is.
So when I was 16, mum and dad did TM.
And so from quite an early age, they introduced us, which is quite,
that's a long time ago now.
So that's quite kind of, they were really at the forefront in terms
of their community around that.
So that's early 80s, was it?
Yeah, no.
Yeah.
For Transcendental Meditation, you know,
Melbourne in that period of time was,
and that's the same practice that I've used for over 20 years as well,
as it turns out.
Mantra-based meditation, for those that aren't listening,
it's a word that doesn't have a specific meaning,
but there's a lot of independent studies published on the research around,
you know, what that does.
And so you learnt that through your parents at a young age?
Yeah.
So that's a good thing.
And I've done some courses over the years.
And now, so I try, you know, I'd say I'm about a five dayer.
Yeah.
And I do it, I do it where I can in the afternoon,
which is my kind of more sleepier time, low energy.
And I find that it gives me energy as well as perspective.
And I'm quite a hyper person.
So it's actually really good just to kind of calm me.
So I find it hugely beneficial.
I love it.
Yeah.
And I actually, whenever I start a coaching session or a group session,
or even like a team, they have three, four, five, six, seven, eight,
a team, they have three, four hundred people, will always start with a couple of minutes
of mindfulness.
And even a couple of minutes, like people who just are so resistant to this, just can't
believe the difference a couple of minutes can make.
Yeah.
It's incredible, isn't it?
I mean, I was, you know, for a long period of time, it was pretty out there in the late
nineties in the Western suburbs of Melbourne for an AFL team to have access to that.
And, you know, it just stuck with me because you're routine based and I didn't quite realise
how beneficial it was.
And a lot of people, oh mate, golf is my meditation or riding a bike's my meditation.
And I said, you know, great pursuits and very worthwhile and I need to play more golf and
go for a run more.
But this is in a different bracket.
This is in a different category.
And I love now that it is a much more open space, isn't it?
From guided meditation as to whether you want to learn mantra based, but to have that account
open, we're not saying it's for everyone, but the benefits are enormous.
If you can slow down your nervous system a couple of times a day, it's incredibly powerful.
I've been blessed to have that in my life as well.
And I feel like one more thing, I think it's great.
So you know, just to kind of broaden the scope, just for your listeners, I think to introduce
your kids to this at a young age, and I was talking to my brother about this recently,
even if you just like lie on the bed with them, you know, when they're young and you
just do five minutes of like a beautiful guided meditation for kids, there are so many meditations
available to instil that practice in your body.
That practice in your kids is so important because, you know, kids face a lot of challenges
as they grow up.
And so for them to have that kind of bedrock of somewhere that they can go to will support
them in their mental health and stress as they have.
The younger we are, the easier we'll adopt that practice.
I think it's great to start early.
Yeah, beautifully said.
I couldn't agree more.
And, you know, part of the passion I've had is to try and actually, you know, spread that
knowledge.
There's some great awareness now, but literally, you know, in our house.
Yeah.
We, we, we sort of legislated that they were going to learn and there was a few eye rolls
as you'd imagine.
We used to bribe them on a Sunday night, you know, Uber Eats, if you, we do a family meditation
and there was, you know, as long as you don't tell any of our friends, but I've watched
them all over time when there's important things going on, they have got a space to
go to that's interesting that they can use and can self-regulate.
And it's, it's just part of who they are now and, and it's a, it's a brilliant tool and
we know just how powerful it is.
So.
That's great.
Look, I love that story.
We need to keep, keep spreading the message.
We see leaders, Mim, like you're really conscious of how they positively impact others in their
environment.
Your life, every bit of it is about positive impact.
Have you been really conscious about that?
Yeah, I really think regularly about, you know, the difference I'm making.
What can I, you know, how can I kind of dial it up or what can I do differently?
My mum, who is, you know.
One of the rocks of my life and incredible woman.
She died of a heart attack, you know, fit as a fiddle on a morning walk at 62.
And so I've, I've kind of got this thing that I could like just any moment I could die.
Yeah.
And so like, just what can I do now?
How can I live my best life now and to make the most of, of every moment.
So that, that's kind of my attitude.
Yeah.
It's brilliant.
It's a, it's a great reminder, isn't it?
That all those things that we're delaying and worried about and the stress.
Yeah.
It's, um, I think that's been brought to reality in recent times.
We've had some really high profile people, you know, Shane Warnes brings to mind and
others that, you know, in the prime of their life in their early fifties, a lot of males
have, uh, have had exactly that, you know, experience, which I know was tragic losing
your mum in that circumstances.
It's brilliant to bring back straight away, isn't it?
To, you know, what's happening now that we can, we can improve.
It's a, it's a great thing to share, uh, creating and sharing your vision is something that
we see, uh, modern leaders are really, uh, very good at and conscious of, Mim, and I,
you know, you only have to look up Mim Bartlett, uh, consulting to have a look at how clear
your vision is, how clear the language is.
Is that been something you've really been thoughtful on?
Yeah.
Well, working in this space, it's kind of forced me to think about, you know, if I'm
working with executives around what's their vision and what's their legacy and how do
they want to make an impact and step more into their influence to have more of an impact,
then, you know, I've got to be really clear.
And so I, you know, do quite a lot of personal professional development courses to keep
kind of me on my toes and making sure that I'm doing the work because it's, it's, it's
so much easier and I, I feel nicer to kind of be guided by someone else around my process
and also to learn from others.
So I try to do that just to keep learning and growing myself and to kind of, yeah, keep
challenging myself and not just holding space and supporting and challenging others.
And I should jump in and say, uh, uh, appreciative of, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh,
well, I'm so appreciative of, uh, you've invited Matt, uh, who's my, uh, my great friend
and partner in the, in the world of a leader to, uh, to take your change up, uh, uh, course.
So I'm, we're really excited about the opportunity to, um, to learn from you, which we're doing,
uh, today as well.
We, we see leaders, uh, curiosity is a really common trait that we're seeing that, that
the, the great leaders that we're talking to a lot are really curious and they approach
their learning and, and development through that lens.
Does that, does that resonate with you as well?
Yeah, absolutely.
So, yeah, I mean, one, I want to kind of make sure I've got like the cutting edge research
and best practice around psychology and mindfulness-based behavioral therapies and leadership in my
work, but also for me, because I want to keep growing and learning.
And look, I think I have, you know, dad really to thank for that.
He started, you know, Norman Vincent Peale kind of, you know, it's very different to
kind of now, but, you know, positive kind of thinking and things, you know, when I was
very young.
So he was always on the self-help kind of improvement.
So as a young person, you know, that really was a great motivator for me.
And so, you know, I'm always wanting to kind of learn and grow and, yeah, see how I can
improve in different ways.
You can see the pieces coming, you know, learning Transcendental Meditation in your
teenage years and having those influences and the influence of your mum.
It sort of makes sense how you've unfolded in all the incredible work that you've done
with so many people.
I mean, communicating with clarity is another dimension I wanted to ask you about as
someone who's clearly an amazing communicator.
Have you been strategic in how you've communicated your message?
Well, I hope so, Luke.
It's working well.
I hope so.
Yeah.
Have you thought about it?
I mean, debating was a passion and the fact you can, I mean, I'm blown away by the fact
you take on Chinese and speak fluent Chinese as well.
So clearly you're open to learning, you know, different ways to communicate as well.
It's clearly a strength.
Oh, that's kind of, look, look.
Yeah, debating and public speaking when I was young and at school and then also kind
of more recently post that, you know, Woman of Influence Award, I started to do some
keynote speaking around stepping more into your impact and influence around leadership.
And so, yeah, I have been quite thoughtful about it and I've worked with different
communications people to kind of help me in that area.
And then it's also really handy too when I've got three young men to kind of,
you know, argue and debate against whatever it might be.
I've got to be very on my toes.
That would be an interesting dinner party.
I think the boys would hold their own pretty well from...
Oh my God, Luke, it's exhausting.
You told me you got a bit of feedback from one on the way in here today, which I love
as well.
Collaboration, we see leaders are really acutely aware of collaboration as a real strength
and something that they seek out.
Has that been a big part of the way you've gone about your leadership?
Yeah.
So, absolutely.
So, certainly with the social justice.
Social impact work I've done, always trying to kind of galvanise my community around the
different kind of not-for-profits and issues, causes that I'm working with so that they
then can, if they're interested and it resonates with them so that they can use their influence
and mobilise their resources and networks around and step up if it interests them to
push it forward.
So, very much in my social justice space and certainly around my professional life, I've
had different collaborations with different people.
For me, there's...
There's benefits of having the autonomy and kind of just doing it kind of the way I want
to do it and also having flexibility around that has been really important.
But I also do love working with other people and learning from them.
And, you know, you feel less lonely kind of in your work when you've got someone to and
others to bounce ideas off.
It's really lovely.
Yeah, beautifully said.
I've been asking these two questions, Mim, of all the ladies.
I've had this great privilege of sitting alongside and I've loved catching up with you today.
Who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Yeah, it's a really good question.
I'd say my mum around love and generosity and energy and zest that she'd bring to every
situation.
And then actually more kind of a little bit further afield, but Gloria Steinem, an incredible
feminist in America, the way she mobilised women and kind of empowered them to step up
and stand up for what they're worth.
And I think that's something that's really important for us to be able to do and to
believe in themselves and a whole lot more is absolutely one of my role models too.
It feels like you're passing that on in all of the work that you're doing.
Is that inspiration from there?
I'm trying one step at a time, but there's some incredible women who have gone before
us and I feel so grateful for them.
I'm just, I'm like a drop in the ocean.
So many people have just done incredible things and I love being inspired by them.
Yeah, and it's brilliant.
You know, whenever I have these conversations with you and people,
you know, think about being a father of a teenage daughter and not really knowing where
to go a lot of the time.
And so, you know, when there are people out there leading the way you are, it's the great
resources.
It's, you're fumbling your way through.
I'm sure I'd get that feedback from her if she was here.
In terms of collaboration, in the spirit of collaboration, is there anyone in any of your
varied and brilliant work that you've thought, if I could collaborate with that person, anyone
in the world on any issue, is there anyone that springs to mind?
Wow, that's a great question, Luke.
Well, probably someone like Gloria Steinem, because she's such a big visionary and she's,
and the impact that she's had just in so many areas of her life, but on such a big scale,
that would be amazing.
I went and heard her speak when she came to the Melbourne Town Hall and
Mai came with me and I mean, it was just incredible.
So yeah, that would be amazing.
I'm sure she'd feel exactly the same, Mim.
It would be a great collaboration.
And once again, I thank you for your time, but also extending the opportunity for us
to go through the ChangeUp program.
You can check out Mim Butler Consulting.
It's extraordinary work that you're doing.
I'm really looking forward to learning up close and personal in the work that you do.
It resonates so strongly with everything we're passionate about.
So thanks for your time, Mim.
Great to see you.
Thank you so much, Luke.
Loved it.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me, Luke Darcy, produced by Matt Dwyer, with audio
production by Darcy Thompson.
To start your leadership journey, I encourage you to go to elitacollective.com, take our
Empowering Leaders Indicator tool and understand the impact you have on your environment.
Join us at Elita to learn, lead and collaborate.
Listener.