I guess when you come in as a young kid and your father's playing cricket
for Australia and your brother's currently playing cricket for Australia,
there's a lot of expectation externally.
But my dad's just my dad, you know, and my brother's my brother
and my sister's my sister.
That's all I see them as.
And I often joke with dad that if I can't sleep at night,
I just put on his highlights and I fall straight to sleep.
So there's plenty of banter within the family.
This week's guest on the Empowering Leaders podcast is Mitch Marsh,
the most recent Allen Border medalist and the current T20 captain
of Australia heading into the World Cup.
Mitch has got some great stories.
I know you're going to enjoy them.
He referenced a meeting with Sir Alex Ferguson at the Ashes in 2023
and some direct advice he got from the legendary Manchester United manager.
He also spoke of another encounter as a 17-year-old aspiring young AFL player
and being at the Australian Open.
The Australian Institute of Sport having a coffee with AFL legend Nathan Buckley
and getting some unique advice from Bucks as well.
You want to hear more of that story.
Mitch's path to being his true authentic self and how that has provided him
with the happiest and most successful period of his sporting life
and his life in general is a great story worth listening to.
We're really privileged to have Mitch Marsh as part of our Elite Connect program
where we bring together groups of five to six people from around the country
and around the globe to learn, to share and connect.
Mitch.
Mitch is a great champion of our Elite Connect space.
He's a lifelong learner and it's something that we are really proud of at Alita
to inspire connections and create a world of collaboration.
Book a discovery call today.
Head to alitacollective.com.
Big thanks as always to the team at Tempa, to Jason Nicholas from Tempa Australia
and their great support of bringing conversations like this to fruition.
We really appreciate their ongoing support.
Investing in a mattress from Tempa is a decision you won't regret.
Mitch Marsh in 2023.
2023 was awarded Australian Cricket's most prestigious prize,
the Alan Borda Medal, recognising him as the most outstanding cricketer of the year.
Mitch has represented his country in 41 tests, 89 one-day internationals,
50-40-20 internationals and the Marsh family are sporting royalty in Australia.
His dad, Jeff, and brother, Sean, both played more than 100 internationals for Australia
and his sister, Melissa, is a Western Australian Basketball Hall of Fame.
Mitch, it's great to see you. How are you?
Yeah, very well, Darce. Thanks for having me on here.
Well, congratulations, mate. It's been an unbelievably successful time.
You're part of the team that retained the Ashes.
You won the one-day International World Cup in India in the most incredible style,
one of the great sporting wins in recent history, the World Test Championship.
And in that time, as I said, you were the Alan Borda medalist.
You must be really proud.
Yeah, it's certainly been an incredible, I guess, couple of years for this team.
We're very lucky.
We've got a lot of experienced players that have played a lot of cricket for Australia.
And I think the last 18 months with the trophies,
that we've won, it's all accumulated into that.
And it's been a real pleasure to be a part of it.
And Mitch, one of my favourite quotes, and I wanted to run this past you,
Oscar Wilde said, be yourself, everyone else is already taken.
And when I look at you, that's exactly what I think of someone who's absolutely themselves.
I want to play back a little bit of your speech from the Alan Borda medal night.
Have a listen to this.
I'd like to pay a particular thank you to Ronnie and Paddy.
You just...
You believed in me.
And I don't really know.
I can't thank you enough for just believing in me.
I'm a bit fat at times and I love a beer, but...
But you see the best in me always.
And you just...
Yeah, you've changed my life.
So for your support, Paddy, and your leadership, playing under you is an absolute dream.
So, yeah, thank you very much.
It was beautiful to me.
There were tears, there were humour.
And as I said, you've just been authentically you.
Have you always been that comfortable?
Your own skin?
Absolutely not, is the truthful answer to that.
I think it certainly took me a while to, I guess, find my feet,
playing cricket at the highest level from a young age,
being on a little bit of a journey as to finding out who I am as a person
and being able to separate that person as a cricketer.
And I think the last probably 18 months, those two have come together
and I've had my best probably two years of cricket
and most certainly the best two years of my life.
That's just a brilliant...
That's a brilliant thing that I want to ask you more about, isn't it?
That often we're trying to be something that we're not
and then you're always probably living an uncomfortable life there.
Can you describe more of that?
Did you feel like you had to be a certain type of person
and now that you are the relaxed, chilled, authentic cat
that you probably always have been, that that's been the happiest time?
I've certainly been the best version of myself and I've grown into that.
But as a young kid and I feel like a lot of young athletes
and what people in general go down this road,
but when I first started playing cricket,
when cricket was going well, I was the king.
And when it wasn't going well, I was not down in the dumps,
but I really battled and a lot of that came with, I guess,
not being able to deal with failure
and understanding what failure looks like for me
and how I get better in those situations.
And there's certainly times I would get into a bit of a rut
and I'd do a lot of work on the mental side of my game
to get to a point where I was not necessarily okay with failure,
but understanding that I'm going to fail.
Working out ways to prepare as best as I possibly can
to give myself the opportunity for a great outcome.
And if that doesn't happen, then end of the game,
I can look myself in the mirror and say,
well, I've done everything I can and that's okay.
And I think detaching myself from the outcome
allowed me to review better, to move on to the next game
or to the next ball.
And yeah, it's been a really cool journey.
Yeah, I'm curious about more of that.
As you said, if we're all outcome focused
and make 100 and life's great,
then you're going to fall into a hole.
How did you get the skill set to do that?
Did you seek out some professional help with that to, as you said,
let the outcome sort itself out?
I'll just go and be the best I can be.
Is there anyone that helped you in that space?
Yeah, I had some great people in my corner.
I think every young kid who starts playing for Australia,
you've all got a dream that you're going to finish your career
averaging 50 with 25 test hundreds.
And for me, maybe 100 wickets, although bowling's too hard.
And when it doesn't pan out that straight away,
I didn't necessarily know how to deal with that.
So as I said before, I had some great people in my corner,
Maddy Bergen, Michael Lloyd,
two great psychologists that worked for Cricket Australia
and WA Cricket at the time,
helped me a lot with, I guess, detaching myself from the outcome
and not letting cricket define me as a human being.
I guess going through that journey of preparing as well as I can
for every game, trying to get better,
trying to keep improving,
but understanding that if I fail, I can still be a great husband,
I can still be a good family man,
and not letting that eat away at me.
And I think I've found that really nice balance now
over the last couple of years where I still love competing,
I still love winning games for Cricket for Australia
and Western Australia when I'm there.
But ultimately, the most important thing for me
is being a good husband, looking after my family
and enjoying, I guess, the fruits of the labour outside of cricket
and, yeah, enjoying life.
Just a smile for me to hear, Mitch,
you're around and you've become that person in Australian sport
where you want to be around and be like Mitch Marsh
and it's incredible.
It's great to see and you look at spending four years
out of the test side and that must have been incredibly challenging
because I'm sure deep down you thought,
I know I'm good enough, I know if they give me another opportunity.
Can you tell us about how challenging that time was?
Yeah, I mean, it was, I think at the time when I was dropped
and I was out of the team, it was probably the best thing for me
at the time.
You're almost at a point where I'd failed so much as a test batsman
that I knew it was time for me to, I guess, reset
and try and start the journey of getting back.
I didn't think it would take me four years, but it did.
So it was a long time and I'd be lying if I said there was times
where I thought I was done and I actually got to a point
where I accepted that I was probably never going to play
test match cricket again.
And in a way, that probably helped me really start to enjoy
my cricket again and there wasn't this element of waking up every day,
just trying to chase something that was probably out of my reach
at certain times.
So, yeah, it's been an incredible journey to just get that one more crack
at it, which I said to a few people in my close circle that I was okay
if I never played again, but gee, I just wanted to have one more crack
at it and, yeah, I guess the last nine tests have been thoroughly enjoyable
and I certainly don't take any of them for granted now.
And now I'm sitting here talking to Mitch Marsh, the Ellen Borda medalist,
alongside the all-time greats of the game.
We've won that prestigious award and recently announced
the ICC T20 World Cup captain for Australia.
I mean, it's an amazing, isn't it, trajectory to go through,
maybe thinking that you'd never play test match cricket again
for Australia and now you're sitting here as the captain.
Congratulations.
You must, again, feel really proud.
Oh, immensely proud.
You know, the opportunity to captain Australia at a World Cup
is something that I never thought I'd do.
I'm very, extremely grateful for the people that we've got around us
in the team at the moment and some of the other leaders within our group
that will hopefully make the job easy.
It's not always going to be easy, but I've got some great people around me
and I dare say I've probably been a reluctant captain at times
because I just love playing and getting around the lads,
but I think my style and who I am as a person, yeah,
I feel really comfortable that I'm going to be able to lead the group
my way and be myself and that's one of the biggest things
I've learned about leadership.
And Mitch, you referenced,
Pat Cummings in your Alan Bordermedal speech
and the influence that he's had on you.
And again, I love that you're now saying,
I feel comfortable because I'm comfortable in who I am.
Can you tell us about Pat's influence on you and your style as a captain?
Yeah, look, well, Paddy and I go back a long way now.
We first toured, our first tour was together.
I was 19.
Paddy was about 12 at that time.
It feels like that anyway.
In South Africa?
In South Africa, yeah.
Yeah.
And we instantly became great friends
and I've watched Paddy's journey as a leader
over the last couple of years very closely
and just so proud of the way he's gone about it.
And he's taught me probably the most about staying true to yourself
and your values and staying the course as a leader.
So, yeah, I'm looking forward to working closely with him.
We're great mates and, yeah, as I said,
we've got a lot of great leaders within our team that, yeah,
make it a lot of fun.
And Mitch, we've been incredibly privileged to collaborate with you
in a space that we call,
Leader and our Leader Connect program.
We curate groups of five to six people often around the country
or even around the globe.
And you've got a really fascinating group of other sporting legends.
Paddy Cripps is in your group of Brownlow medalists
from Carlton.
The daily Cherry Evans is a superstar of the NRL,
Jeeva Mentor, world-class in her field test match
in the Australian Basketball.
Captain, can you tell us a bit about what that's been like
sitting amongst that group on a monthly basis?
It was something that Pat had done.
He had a few groups.
And he mentioned that it would be worthwhile me getting stuck in
and getting involved.
And I've had the best time.
It's, yeah, a great group of people that I was involved with.
You know, it probably took us two sessions to really open up
and get to know each other.
And then what I love most about it is I formed a real connection
with the group to the point now where you just bounce ideas
off each other and learn.
And, yeah, it's something that I look forward to.
Every session has got better and better.
And I've just had the best time.
I understand that, again, you're that great connector.
I think you've been authentically you as just something that pours out.
Is that even in a group that you perhaps hadn't had the experience
with before, do you find it easy again to sort of show up
and share the way that you do?
The whole connection piece is a really important thing for me
in anything I do in my life.
You know, my family, my friends, my teams, and now my leader crew.
And, yeah, I certainly opened up as we went along.
Yeah, the few little gaps.
And I got a few laughs every now and then, which is good.
Stace is always my number one.
She gave me a few laughs, which is good.
But, yeah, just got a real connection.
And, look, that crew now, I'll catch up with them forever,
wherever I'm in Sydney or Melbourne or now England for Jiva.
Yeah, I've got some great friends there.
Mitch, you've grown up in an era as a professional athlete where the world
of social media provides incredible opportunities and also incredible
challenges at the same time.
How have you navigated?
How have you navigated that and handled it?
It feels like an issue that every young kid's dealing with and you're
about to be a parent yourself.
Is it something that you've got to handle on and can you describe
how you've thought about it?
I mean, yeah, as a young kid, it was something that I battled with.
I took a lot of it personally.
And at times I took that out in the field with me, the fact that I wanted
to prove people wrong.
And that mentality works for some people, but I realised that it didn't
work for me and it took me away from what I was actually good at.
And it took me away from actually just competing on the field.
And that's when I play my best cricket.
So I've learned not to take that personally.
I respect that in the world of social media, everyone's got an opinion
and they're allowed for that.
Some go overboard and there's a lot of people out there that deal
with worse than me.
But I get a lot of love these days, which is also nice.
I did not see the hard yards.
That's the story of your life, Mitch, isn't it?
You've battled through.
I understand you had a great gatekeeper, your sister, Melissa.
You used to fire back on behalf of the Marsh family from time to time.
Is that true?
I said in my Alan Bordermill speech that if anyone's ever abused me
on social media, that my sister will find them eventually and get them.
So she's a very protective sister.
And, yeah, we've got a great relationship.
Can you tell us a bit about growing up in the Marsh family?
I grew up when your dad was the opening batsman for Australia
and we idolised him and what a legend he was.
And Sean had such an incredible career.
I mentioned your sister's sporting exploits.
And I love it when you're out there in the middle and we pan back
and you might see dad having a beer and Sean's next to him.
And can you tell us a bit, did you initially feel the pressure of all that
or just the support overwhelms any of the pressure?
Yeah, I just had incredible support.
I think all of the pressure came externally and that's a given, I guess,
when you come in as a young kid and your father's played cricket,
played cricket for Australia and your brother's currently playing cricket
for Australia, there's a lot of expectation externally.
But my dad's just my dad, you know, and my brother's my brother
and my sister's my sister.
That's all I see them as.
And I often joke with dad that if I can't sleep at night,
I just put on his highlights and I fall straight to sleep.
So there's plenty of banter within the family.
I love it.
One of the all-time greats, Geoff Martian.
Maybe not as free-flowing as his youngest son.
Certainly not.
Mitch, I remember meeting you as a 17-year-old and you were a big full forward
for Western Australia, potentially going to play for Australia
at under-18 level.
You were a WA State player as an AFL and you were a big bison
even as a 17-year-old.
Was there any chance that AFL football was going to take you hard
or was cricket always going to win?
Oh, gee.
I loved footy.
And like most kids, I played cricket in the summer and footy in the winter
and I played the State under-16s and then I was a bottom age at 18s.
So I still had another year until I sort of had to make that decision,
re-footy.
But I think deep down it was always cricket.
I remember going to the AIS for a camp and Nathan Buckley was one of my mentors
and I had a typical cricketer's body.
I was a bit sloppy.
Yeah.
His kids at the time were getting ready to be drafted.
They'd done a full pre-season.
They're ready to go.
Buck sat me down at the cafeteria at AIS and he said,
do you like chocolate?
And clearly baited me and I didn't realise at the time and I just said,
oh, mate, I love chocolate.
Love it.
And he said to me, well, I haven't eaten chocolate in 10 years.
That's the sort of discipline you need if you're going to be an AFL footballer.
And right then and there, it was cricket, mate.
There's an intensity about Nathan Buckley.
That doesn't surprise me, but maybe he might have learnt how to celebrate
from you, Mitch, as well, which is a lesson to learn.
I love asking these questions because we think that success leaves clues
and I love your story.
It's such a unique, authentic story that you've carved your own path
out to great success.
I think it's hard to lead anyone else.
You're about to captain Australia without a sense of self-leadership.
What does that mean to you to lead yourself first?
Yeah.
Yeah, well, I think the most important thing for me is just staying true
to who I am, looking after my people, which, you know,
within cricket is the team and creating an environment where people feel
really trusted to just do their thing.
And within our team, that's been one of the biggest things
that's led us to success.
And I think that starts with me.
You've got to lead that yourself and stay true to yourself.
Mitch, we see.
We see people who are successful consistently are really conscious
about the impact they have on others in their environment.
You play in that tight-knit team that travels around the world
and you're constantly having an impact on each other all the time.
How have you gone about that?
I mean, I think it's really down to relationships.
You know, we're all here for different reasons.
We all have different family backgrounds, come from different cultures
within our group, and I guess having relationships with everyone
that are meaningful.
Understanding who they are.
So I guess that when they're under pressure, you know the person
and not just the cricketer, and trying to get the best out of people.
So I'm new into this role as a leader within our team,
but I've learned from so many great people like Paddy
and like Andrew McDonald.
The relationships are so important.
And Mitch, I'm assuming you don't win the World Cup,
you don't win the World Test Championship or retain the Ashes
without a really good relationship.
Do you have a really clear vision around what you and your team
are trying to achieve?
We're curious about how you go about creating and sharing that vision,
you know, particularly in your role now.
Cricket throws a lot of challenges at you.
We play a lot of different conditions.
We travel to different cultures.
Some places are hot, some places are cold.
So every tour looks different for us, but we sit down at the start
of every tour and we speak about what we want the tour to look like
and feel like as a group, and we all commit to that.
So that's it.
That brings freshness to our group.
Every tour is a little bit different.
The core things around trust and looking after your mates
is vitally important, but that's brought a real freshness
to each tour for us.
And I think, you know, we travel pretty much 12 months
of the year now.
We play all year round.
So for people to start fresh every tour and come together,
it's worked really well for us.
So going into the T20 World Cup and you're captain,
you'll really have a clear project and mission and this is how we want
to create the environment.
We've got some similarities from other experiences,
but it's a really different set up for every challenge
that you want to face.
Is that the sort of detail you get into?
Yeah, absolutely.
The other thing too is keeping it really simple.
We've got a really experienced group now and it's about trusting guys
that are going to prepare really well.
We've got guys that are coming from the IPL later than some.
We'll give them a few days at home, but it's understanding
that we'll come together and tournament play is about peaking
at the right time.
So we'll hopefully build in the World Cup.
Yeah, get to the point at the end.
Mitch, we see people who have the sort of success we're talking
to you about are really curious and through curiosity,
they're constantly trying to get better.
Are you a curious type of person?
Yes, I am.
For me, it was more, I guess, the mental side for me rather
than like the skill stuff.
I'm always striving to get better and there's always areas
and different shots that you can play to get better.
But for me, it was about I really need to work on learning
to deal with failure.
And being really present.
So the curiosity side for me within cricket has been
around breathing during games, staying calm.
You know, if I play a false shot, moving on to the next ball
straight away and forgetting the rest of it and done a lot
of work in that space to, yeah, hopefully be able to stand
up there with a trophy in a couple of months' time.
Looks like you've got it in a great place.
Communicating really clearly is another dimension we love
talking about.
And again, you seem to have your own authentic style.
I love this.
That's why I wanted to play the speech at the start because it made
all of us smile that followed you closely and it was off script
and it was you being you.
Have you thought about it, Mitch, or is it just, again,
just being authentic?
Well, yeah, that speech was, yeah, it was unplanned.
I certainly knew there was people I wanted to thank, sorry,
but, yeah, probably got away from you a little bit.
But, yeah, a few tears and a few laughs, that's all you need
when you're speaking.
I think, yeah, communicating, I think that's one of the biggest
challenges as a leader is communicating things that everyone
resonates with.
And I think with an experienced group like ours, a lot of guys just
need to do their thing and they don't need to listen, but there's
a certain percentage of guys that, you know, like to be communicated
with and for cricket it's about being really clear with your
communication and plans with bowlers and then being, with batters,
it's just about being really clear in their role and allowing them
to express themselves.
So it's been, yeah.
It's been a hallmark of our team and Andrew McDonald is one
of the best communicators I've ever had and we're lucky to have him
as a head coach.
Can you give us a bit on that?
I just find that with him he's really consistent with it and that helps
the team.
Is there any specific things that he does that you can share?
I think he's got a great ability to leave emotion out of high-pressure
situations when he's communicating with you.
You know, for me over the last two years I've never been clearer
as to what my role is within the team.
When I'm batting it's always been communicated to just be myself
and that's allowed me personally to have, you know, some of the best
cricketing years of my life and there's plenty of other examples
of that within our team.
So, yeah, strong, clear communication is probably the most important
thing that I've learnt.
You mentioned some of the collaborations that you had with the mental
skills coaches at Cricket Australia and your great friendship
with Pat Cummings.
How important has collaboration been for you?
It's vital.
Just learning.
Building relationships with people and opening doors has been one of the
biggest things and I guess that's probably something that I was reluctant
at doing earlier on.
I sort of stayed in my own lane but now I've realised that the more I can
learn off others and take snippets from to build a better team around me
has been really cool.
And like I said before, my group with the Alita Connect team was just,
yeah, some of the great people and there's no doubt that they're all
playing in really successful teams.
And I understand that.
Yeah.
It may be an international collaboration that you're going to join on the
Alita Connect front as well, Mitch, is what I hear.
Yeah.
So Stace gave me a call before she even told me the group I was already in.
I just, yeah, I just loved it.
You know, it's given me, you know, being on the road as well gives me a bit
of purpose outside of just being on the road for cricket and having something
to look forward to every couple of weeks.
So, yeah, I'm stepping into, I've got a few NBA player, EPL player,
basketball player and one other.
Yeah.
Remember, I'm very fresh.
It's only a couple of days.
So, yeah, can't wait for that.
And I think I'll have a few early wake-ups.
But once you're in, you're in.
I love your attitude, Mitch.
Who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Oh, gee, I've been extremely blessed to play under, to have great role models
within my life.
I think, I mean, my dad is someone that I've got a great relationship with.
And dad's a little bit old school in a sense that he's not a big talker.
But all of his actions that he's instilled into me about around looking
after people, caring for people, it's been one of my, you know,
he's just, he's the best dad, but one of the best leaders I've ever come
across and, yeah, I'm grateful to have him in my life.
Pretty lucky start in life, isn't it?
Getting that sort of relationship, isn't it, with your dad?
And I feel exactly the same.
We're a bit obsessed with collaboration and we talk a lot about inspiring
connections.
Connections and creating a world of collaboration.
Mitch, you've got a lot of great passions.
I see you out fishing.
I see you loving a beer with your mates.
I see life looks like a lot of fun.
Has there been, in any part of your life, it might be cricket,
and you thought there's someone you'd like to collaborate on any
of the passions in your life?
Is there a name that springs to mind?
Yeah, I thought, I think, long and hard about this, I'd love to go back
to the height of Manchester United with Sir Alex Ferguson.
And just be a fly on the wall.
You hear so many great stories about him being hard, being caring, and just
driving this team to ultimate success.
So, yeah, I'd love to go back to, what is it, early 2000s or 90s when
United were on a heater and even just sit down and have a glass of red with
him.
I met him at a game, a Manchester United game during the Ashes.
And the first thing he said to me was, I hate cricket.
It's boring.
So, I probably got that collaboration wrong there.
But, yeah, he was someone that, obviously, would be amazing to sit down
and talk all things leadership, I guess.
You know where you stand with Sir Alex, don't you?
Right off the bat, that's...
You hear so many stories about, you know, you knew exactly where you stood
with Sir Alex, so there you go.
Won't be no free tickets for him next Ashes.
Yes.
And were you a round ball Manchester United fan as a kid?
Were you growing up?
Growing up, my brother was big time, so I followed them.
I followed them just like, so I could stay up the show and watch, but I'm more of an
AFL man.
Hey, Mitch, I think your life story is a great lesson to me in being authentically yourself
and the path to finding that.
It's such a great thing to see someone, as I said earlier, so comfortable in their own
skin and every success that comes your way, you've earned.
And it's brilliant.
I have followed you closely since that early encounter as a 17-year-old.
To see you now as captain of Australia is just one of the great success stories of all
time.
And we wish you all the best.
Thanks for joining me today.
Thanks for having me, Darce.
It's been a pleasure.
Thanks for listening to another episode of the Empowering Leaders Podcast.
Huge thanks, as always, to our great friends at Tempur, and we encourage you to check out
our Leader Connect program.
New episodes are out every Wednesday morning at 6 AM.