I hope you enjoyed this conversation on the Empowering Leaders podcast with Nathan Parris,
an unbelievable Australian success story. Nathan's business, Emerge Capital, is responsible for many
of the biggest real estate transactions in Australia. I love this chat with Nathan. He
gives great advice for everyone considering the entrepreneurial path. He talks about the
untapped potential of empowering young people within your organisation and also how to get
incredible efficiency in your space to go through the roof when you get company culture right.
Worth hanging on to the very end of this podcast because Nathan talks about
his dinner party with former exiled Thai Prime Minister Thaksin Shinawatra and also his dealings
with the Walton family from Walmart fame, the richest family in America in their pursuit of
doing business in China. It's a fascinating conversation full of a lot of wisdom. Nathan
Parris has been a great champion for us in our Alita Connect groups.
Alita Connect is our bespoke facilitated leadership forum where we curate and bring
together diverse thinking in peer groups that support, share, learn and connect together.
Nathan was generous enough to say in this conversation that Alita Connect
has literally changed his life. We love the idea of brilliant people coming together
and able to support each other in ways that perhaps they haven't before in peer groups that
we think are really, really powerful. We'd love to connect with you. Book a discovery call.
Head to alitacollective.com today.
Huge thanks as always to Jason Nicholas and his team at Temper, a mattress like no other.
We are incredibly grateful for the support of Temper for the Empowering Leaders podcast that
enables us to bring stories like Nathan's to the table. All great leaders understand
the importance of great sleep and investing in a mattress like Temper is a life-changing decision.
Nathan Parris is the managing partner of Emerge Capital, an independent real estate advisory firm
that has executed more than $30 billion worth of transactions
over the last year. Nathan, thank you so much for joining us.
Thank you.
Prior to this, Nathan had gathered a wealth of experience in roles for Capital Land in
Singapore, Morgan Stanley in Japan, the Torben Company in Hong Kong, and Lendlease in Australia.
Nathan has a reputation for being humble, understated, and he's a unique leadership success story.
Nathan, it's a fascinating life that you've lived and an intriguing story. And it's fair
to say, pretty private person, took a bit of convincing to get you to the table today.
So firstly, I appreciate you taking the time to share your story.
Thank you.
No, thank you very much, Luke. It's a real honour.
You studied international business out of school. You had a dream that you wanted to
work overseas, but credit working in pubs while you're at uni with developing a lot
of the skills that have helped your success. Can you explain why that's the case?
Yeah, it's interesting. And I really do reflect a lot on the early part of my life in terms of I had
jobs that involved a lot of interaction with people. And so starting out in pubs,
obviously, when you're young, you don't quite appreciate that you're managing
intoxicated people most of the time. And you learn soft skills. And that's really stuck with me
really throughout my whole career, because at the end of the day, what I do more than anything else
is interact with people and try to influence positive outcomes. And so I really now reflect
on those years and appreciate that because I just can't imagine how I would have got to
where I am now. And so I really now reflect on those years and appreciate that because I just
can't imagine how I would have got to where I am now. And so I really now reflect on those years and
if it had not been for learning how to deal with people, and particularly in difficult situations.
That resonated with me a lot. I grew up in a family of publicans, and we used to live upstairs in the
old pubs back in the day and watch mum and dad working downstairs. And if we wanted to earn some
pocket money, you had to go and pick up glasses. But you're constantly around people. And literally,
the hospitality industry taught you, you had to say hello, and mum and dad were always on
to you to be hospitable if you were going to be part of the family.
And our kids have all worked as glassies, as part of a bit of a rite of passage. It's a good start
in life, isn't it? It's not a bad grounding to get going. It really is. And in fact, it's funny you
say that. I remember my first day working, it was Valentine's Day. It was a Friday night in a sort of
big pub in Brisbane called Friday's. And I was turned up in a bow tie, white shirt, black slacks.
So you had to, you know, you had to dress up. And my job was to basically look after a section. There's
probably a couple of thousand people in the pub slash club. And I had the toilets, the male
toilets. Never cleaned a toilet in my life. And I think in that first night, I had seen everything
that you could possibly see in a toilet. But you know, going forward, it was really the beginning
of then I had to clean the tables at the end of the night. And I was so fastidious about it. And
it just never left me to sort of take pride in my section. And then as you probably know,
you go from being a glassie to behind the bar.
To being a manager. And it's almost a little career before you start your career. And as I said,
you are literally learning on the job. And it's almost like mini crisis management all the time.
And I just, I literally couldn't imagine doing what I do today without that experience.
Mentioned the dream to work overseas. And you certainly realize that work dream pretty early
on in your life. And you go over to places like Taipei, the world's tallest building,
Taipei 101. You work on that. You become a fund manager and establish
Singapore's first ever real estate investment trust. You head on to Tokyo to work for Morgan
Stanley. You've crammed an enormous amount into your life. You're not even 50 years of age yet.
Can you tell us about the chapter working through Asia?
Yeah. I mean, look, it was a dream come true for me. There was no rhyme or reason why I studied
international business at university other than to get out of Brisbane. And it's not because I
don't like Brisbane. I just felt like I just had something in me to go and explore the world. And
I was very, very excited about it. And I was very, very excited about it. And I was very, very
fortunate to join an organization that one, got me out of Brisbane and into Melbourne as my first
job. But within three years, I was just given this incredibly unique opportunity, as you say,
to go to Taipei. And Taipei, this was back in 1999. So it wasn't really a market full of expats.
And my background was shopping centers or shopping malls. And we were building the podium of what was
what is now the world. Sorry, it was at the time the world's tallest building, Taipei 101. It was big
thinking. I'd never been around that environment where you're so bold in terms of the vision of
what you're trying to create. And at an early age, I had to really expand my mind to think about,
you know, the world of possibility. And I guess the big thing for me was really,
at that point, learning to work in a cross-cultural environment,
which I've got to say, as a young guy, nothing prepared me for that.
The organization I worked for didn't prepare me, not that that was their fault, but you literally
got dropped in. You know, you've got language barriers, you've got cultural barriers,
and you do things differently as well. So it was a baptism of fire. But at the same time,
it was just, it was like living on another planet. And it was the sensory experience was just unreal.
Unimaginable, because growing up in, in Brisbane, you just, you just could never have imagined that
there was a world like that. And then as you say, then sort of things move start quite quickly,
because what I realized being a young expatriate is you are a minority. And so therefore,
opportunities come fast at you. And, and I really took advantage of that. You know,
I think you commented there, I joined an organization called,
Capital Land, and we established the first real estate investment trust, which was
massive, because it completely transformed the real estate industry in Asia. Now, where there's
hundreds of billions of dollars of funds under management in these real estate investment trusts.
And I was a 26 year old guy, I had some credentials that happened to suit that organization. Next
thing I know, I'm on global roadshows, raising capital from, you know, large foreign institutional
investors. And, you know, I've just seen there the whole time, pinching my fingers,
pinching myself going, you know, how did I land this, but then equally, you know, really being
challenged, and at times really struggling with the cross cultural element. And again, that
experience a bit like talking about the pub experience has stuck with me and really is a
massive factor in terms of, you know, where I am today, and where the business that I run is today,
because, you know, we specialize now in cross border investment from overseas,
to Australian real estate. And you think of the unique experiences that you've been able to
gather and Singapore's reputation as a country without many natural resources at all, but had
to find a way to be pioneers in spaces like you. And as a 26, 27 year old, to be at the front of
that is quite remarkable. And, and then you go to Japan, and you read a lot about the work culture
in Japan of no work life balance at all, and 80 to 100 hour weeks, and you get swept up in that.
And, and, and, you know, I hear you,
talk about that, giving you these elite work habits, but maybe teaching you to be a workaholic.
Is that something that's still part of you that you've got to manage a little bit working too hard?
Yeah, it was that I mean, going to Japan and joining, you know, Morgan Stanley,
and at that time, when I joined them, they were the most successful global real estate investor.
They were certainly the largest foreign real estate investor in Japan. And they were doing
very, very substantial deals, and making the firm and its
investors a lot of money. And it was a tempo that that just smacked you in the face like you did,
you turn up and the is just real time management. And I never really had that in my career. Obviously,
I, you know, as as what they call a lateral hire, because I didn't start as a graduate,
I had subject matter expertise in the areas that they wanted to pursue in Japan. But yeah,
this this tempo was it was almost like, what I would describe as,
perfect rhythm. Everyone knew their role. Everyone was smart. And, and everyone got out got on and
you almost opted out, if you couldn't keep up. And I saw that with people like, you know, just
literally opting out because you were just exposed if you couldn't, if you couldn't keep going.
And for me, it was I call it sort of my PhD, not even an MBA, because I had to lift. And you know,
had to push hard and, and, and, you know, discover things.
Things that I, you know, didn't know that I was capable of. And I was very fortunate to work with
some not only really bright people, but just some genuinely amazing people who, to this day,
I consider as good friends, and have gone on to be just ridiculously successful. You know,
I loved it. I really did enjoy that experience. As I said, it did turn me into quite an elite
professional. And I realised that there was no limits to what you can do.
Particularly in a good team environment. And I, you know, as you know, Das, I participate in a
couple of the elite groups. And, and I actually recognise similar patterns in, you know, some of
the peers in my group, that those that are elite athletes. And it's interesting how I observed that,
you know, there is a very high level of crossover between, you know, business and, and, and athletes,
professional athletes.
And so,
you know, and then your overlay, as you touched on, just the cross-cultural element of that,
working in Japan. I mean, it is one of the most interesting, but challenging environments to work
in from a, from a cross-cultural perspective. And you're working for an elite American organisation
that has very high standards. And not that they were unforgiving, but, but, you know,
you needed to deliver, which required an enormous influence over, you know,
the Japanese members in your team, or even, you know, the people that you're interacting,
emerging outside of that business, but, you know, it, it was an amazing opportunity.
And, and to your point about, you know, it did see me into a workaholic and as I said, it uncovered
aspects in, in my sort of personality that, that lives with me today.
And I would dearly love to sort of figure out how I can unpick some of those
aspects, but, but, you know, if I'm brutally honest, I wouldn't be where I am today,
certainly that experience to know how hard you can push yourself we're looking forward to coming back
and talking about our shared passion for the elita groups that we're really uh wrapped that you're
part of but it sounds to me looking at your story that you you you go really hard and and you've got
this capacity to push yourself and as you said you you get into an elite environment morgan stanley
and you you can find that level but then it seems like your life has had a number of sabbaticals
along the way where you go okay i'm going to take the time right out now and including
putting yourself into a mai tai kickboxing camp in phuket as part of a sabbatical what were you
thinking there tell us about that one um look you know uh having this conversation with you sort of
made me realize to some extent at the time how i was quite self-centered um you know it was all
about my career me and as a result of that i you know it i never got into very serious relationships
um because i just prioritized
my work over everything and i didn't quite appreciate that that was the case at the time
but it certainly resonated with me as i was sort of getting towards the end of my career in asia
and i remember having a conversation with my mother and she said look you know we're very
proud of you we we love what you're doing but do you think there might be a little bit more to life
than what you are doing and it was a period uh you know certainly in asia leading up to the gfc where
you know there was just a lot of money
there was just a lot of money and there was a lot of very hedonistic um times and experiences
and it took for about six months almost like water finding its way through a rock in my brain from
what my mother said and i thought you know what it's time to move on i've been blessed to have
this incredible career and opportunities that i was afforded in my time in asia and
i knew that i had to detox and not not detox from from alcohol or anything like that it was just
from the lifestyle and uh and i ran into this guy in hong kong one night and he told me that he'd
spent time in a in a thai muay thai um kickboxing camp um in phuket and i'd done a little bit of
that when i was younger a bit of boxing and that really resonated with me i thought this is what i
need jesus it's amazing how you know life is a sliding door moments and um so i resigned um i
had a chance to go to phuket in thailand and next thing i know i'm training five hours a day
and just literally getting the shit kicked out of me and i was i was old by those standards you
know most of the guys there were in their late teens early 20s you know from all over the world
they're pretty elite um and um and you know honestly i found it a little bit boring because
it's so monotonous when you're doing the same thing over and over again and i guess that's
the sport right that's what you got to do muscle memory um so now i was doing that and um look it
was working in terms of the detoxification of the of the lifestyle but um you know it was
similarly it was actually valentine's day again in 2009 and it was it was raining outside and
tropical rain in thailand and um and the water was spraying onto the canvas where i was sparring
with my trainers
who happened to be like an ex-world champion kickboxer and i was a boxer right i got quite
heavy legs um and uh so i i didn't kick a lot and uh anyway just did a sweep kick and uh my
body's gone one way my leg's gone the other and my knee fully dislocated and fortunately you'd
appreciate this being an ex-afl player remember watching a sydney swan player do it on on on um
in a game and he punched his knee back in and they're incredible
that was famously yeah i remember that very well yeah slap your kneecap back in after it was
dislocated yeah yeah mine was a kneecap mine was a sort of the full dislocation in any event
i just started punching it and my trainer had the presence of mind to lift my leg up
for some reason it went back in and and he said to me oh nathan that's okay why don't you just do
you know 500 knees and you know the corner of the ring and his name was pot and i said pot i don't
think you understand like you know my knees buggered and then he said oh that's okay then
you know why don't you just go and do 500 sit-ups and meanwhile my knee is just swelling up quite
badly but fast forward the story um had a full knee reconstruction torn acl torn meniscus and
because of insurance reasons i spent the next few months in in rehabilitation but that dust was what
basically brought me back down to earth um so it's amazing you know i see silver linings now
because i've i've had that much disappointment challenge all those things in life um at the
appreciate that was a silver lining but but that that was it and that was what was the catalyst for
the change in my next part of my career well i love sharing stories like yours nathan and appreciate
you doing it so openly because you always read the headlines and you think you know what a blessed
life and and nathan paris life comes easy to nathan he's you know having huge success and
running this extraordinary business but you don't really understand along the way the serious hurdles
that are there tearing your acl and your meniscus is a way to teach you to come back to earth a
little bit but you also shared with me that you know you went to hochman city did some gold futures
trading that didn't end so well and effectively for all that brilliant experience in asia 35 years
of age you come back home to australia and you're back living with your mom and dad i'm assuming
that's a pretty humbling experience as well yeah look it was it was surreal you know you you go
from being you know probably not the right description but a high flyer you know you'd
you know you've come back down to earth and then you've realized you've got to get to it you know
the funds over as sabbaticals i'm a big believer in um you know i think i've had three years off
in my career the sabbaticals um but you've got to get you've got to get to it and look you know
one of the things that i now recognize that i didn't at the time is an innate you know ambition
that i have and drive again another characteristic that i see in my peers in in the groups i'm doing
um and uh and i you know it's professionally the hardest thing i've ever done was incredibly
humbling people you know go you know great to see you nathan but you know there's no job
and uh you know took me you know i'd gone from being headhunted for every role i'd ever had
um and and going up the curve and and now it was no no no no no and actually on a you know
snakes and ladders falling to the bottom and starting all over again
i was just so determined it was almost like something had over like overcome me and um i
even reflect on it and just can't believe how hungry i was um and what i again silver lining
and all of that at the time there was so much disappointment but what i was doing
was creating a network and and that network is actually what served me when i then went on to do
my own thing but i didn't appreciate that at the time and nor could have i ever appreciated but
to me as i often do for career advice and what they should do when they should stay or leave
their job i always say use this as an opportunity to go out and connect and network and that's what
you've done you decided that the corporate world and the politics of that wasn't necessarily for
you but still a big leap of faith isn't it to go down the entrepreneurial path and put it all on
the line and say okay i'm not working for morgan stanley anymore it's it's nathan paris and i'm
going to do it myself and and the end result you know emerged capital
largest real estate transactions in australia it's an extraordinary australian business success
story but to those listening that are thinking about taking that jump what's your advice to
to the next entrepreneur uh well first i'd just say just do it i i i don't know if you've heard
of this sort of concept of limerence it's like you know when people get into a relationship they
they don't see any of the negative stuff you know like i often use the expression you can
kiss each other without brushing your teeth and it doesn't you know you don't
it feels good and then you know two years later you just and if you knew what you were getting
into in small business um you know you really knew you wouldn't do it in saying that you know
it's just profoundly satisfying the one thing i value more than anything is the independence
to wake up every day and to truly know that you control your own destiny and i find that
liberating um that you can actually have an idea and you can act on that idea and you can do that
obviously in an organization but you really need to be skilled and that's you know as you mentioned
sort of about politics and stuff like that i i found it highly frustrating because i want to do
because i'm more of a doer than a thinker and uh and i'd always come up against sort of you
know internal challenges for whatever reason but you know with a business that that you lead
and if you sort of get turned on by the idea of you know um doing what you think you want to do
it's it's just so empowering but i don't read a lot but i remember reading elon musk's book
years ago and he said being an entrepreneur is like chewing glass and staring into the abyss
because you just now now like you know fast forward god what is it you know 12 years
i used to sort of go oh why me why is this happening
to me and all of that now it's sort of a bit sadistic like you go okay where's the challenge
like you know this is all going too well i'm waiting for something to go wrong because you
know that's that's what it's about and and that's where i come back to that point around silver
linings i'm now convinced in every difficult situation there is definitely if you're putting
everything into it um something positive will come out of it whether it's at that time or in
the future because if you're putting the effort in
and you're doing your best to put your effort in something inevitably comes out of that but
it's been so rewarding but it's been bloody tough and uh and i would just as this why i come back to
your question just just do it and um it's going to be hard it's a common thing now that i i'm
fascinated to hear that a lot people that have got to the sustained success level you know like
you have with emerged capital and they look back at the the fights and the struggles is almost the
most joyful time because you're in solution mode and you're in the moment and you're in the moment
you're coming up with ideas and you're meeting great people and you're putting it out there and
i think when you talk to anyone who's at the startup phase all they want is the sustained
success period so it is interesting you're chasing uh that regularly and you've mentioned uh very
generously a leader which is the entrepreneurial space that matt whatowitz and i are incredibly
passionate about um we've been really privileged to to connect with you and and love your story
and you're one of the great legends of our space because you're so curious and love learning that
and for those that are listening you've heard me talk about it before you know we've uh emerged
into these bespoke groups of five or six different people and nathan brings your story you've just
heard before like a unique wealth of experience i said before we start i feel like it's a shantaram
style uh story and you talked about living in india for a period of time as well but uh to me
bringing your thinking alongside elite sports people and i'm sure the guys won't mind me
mentioning who's uh who you collaborate with leon camera is one of my great friends in life the 10
year coach at gws and i'm sure you've heard a lot of people talk about how they've been
uh i'm biased but one of the great people uh i've ever met one of my closest friends ivan cleary who's
just got a remarkable reputation in rugby league gus warren you don't meet a more beautiful guy
than gus with gotcha for life and he's just doing incredible work jack trengove is just a special
person as well in in that group youngest ever captain of melbourne but what he's doing with
his finance world and then the second group uh he's equally fascinating for me zach merritt the
captain of essen and james tedesco an nrl legend manis labashane kurt zerber who was one of the
senior executives from westpac bank it's a fascinating uh thing can you tell us what
you get out of it and why it's been a good thing for you oh look darce it's it's been immense
it's been life-changing for me um you know i i do need to thank leon and and yourself and
matt for giving me the opportunity to participate uh it was sort of surreal um you know as i said
most of the members in those groups are elite sports people
you start out thinking what do i have in common with these people
you know am i going to be able to participate at all and uh you know you fast forward to today
and it's it is arguably one of the most gratifying experiences that i've had
uh first my first comment is that you know being a business owner at times can be lonely um you know
i've got a lot of industry peers as i'm sure probably you do darce from your playing days and
you've got lots of friends and peers from that.
But what I really have struggled with in my career as a business owner
is a peer group and a peer group just to share.
And I actually recall listening to a podcast with you
and Stacey Morlinson, she was sort of summing it up around
that you're talking to a peer group that have no bearing
on your day-to-day life.
And that is powerful because you're just genuinely there
to help each other, to listen, to learn from each other.
You know, this environment, because it's so trusting,
it's just full of nuggets.
And you're lifted every time you have one of these conversations.
And that's just given me a lot of confidence
that we're all in the same boat.
It doesn't matter whether you're in real estate,
you're an elite sports person, you're a senior executive
in one of Australia's largest banks, you know,
we all walk the same path.
We all breathe the same earth, we all breathe the same air,
we drink the same water, and we've all got the same problems.
You know, and equally, we've all got similar aspirations
to be better people.
And so, you know, it's been a real eye-opener for me
and I can't believe that it took to be my age to be able
to connect with peers like that and to be able to share
so openly and I keep coming back to a very trusting environment.
So, no, I would go so far as to say it's just,
it's changed my life.
It's very generous of you to say that, Nathan.
And I look at the sort of the wheel of life and you think
you've got these incredible skill sets that show up
when you talk about your story and consistently able
to do things that other people find really hard.
But like all of us, there's the deficiencies, isn't there,
that we're all trying to fill to make sure that life
is balanced and happy and successful.
And when you put diverse thinking together,
you often get clues on how to balance that out.
Athletes, genuinely, that was,
my life as a kid all I wanted to do.
But we often, as a group, struggle financially
to get the decisions that probably come easy to you.
And so that shared economy and then obviously the discipline
and the team aspect and putting back in and taking feedback
and working in a team is something that probably comes easy
to us because that's our grounding.
So, you know, we love the fact that then you get brilliant
female leaders in who see the world in such a beautiful way.
And I think it's great that that's been,
what it has for you.
And I think you've described it, isn't it,
the different thinking actually can be a bit life-changing at times.
Yeah, look, I mean, what it's taught me is just, again,
the world of possibility of sharing.
I actually think that it's a catalyst to something else.
You know, it certainly piqued some curiosity in me in terms
of getting fulfilment out of things beyond what we do day to day.
And so, you know, it's something that I'm keen
to explore further because I've now realised
that I'm not going to be able to do it.
I'm not going to be able to do it.
You know, there's that possibility outside of, you know,
what I've been doing.
And, you know, I go back to being a business owner.
Well, it's not lonely.
So, you know, I don't mean it like that.
But the lack of ability to share about your journey
and not to talk about what you do because that's sort
of the technical aspect.
But I just genuinely feel like through sharing
with a peer group, it just opens up, as I said before,
this world of possibility.
And I'm very, very...
I'm very keen to explore that further.
And one of the things that, you know, I've been discussing
in one of our groups is just sort of like, you know,
there's a book that Matt shared was, you know,
The Second Mountain.
Where to now?
So firstly, you know, you have a corporate career,
then you have the business owning career and you sort
of go, okay, well, what's the next stage of fulfilment?
And in my view, that is definitely giving back.
And that's, I think, the enjoyment out of being
in these groups.
Given your life history and story,
that second mountain will be fascinating.
I guarantee it won't be boring given the way you've
approached life.
And I'm looking forward to asking these questions
because we do think success leaves clues and to see it turn
up in a story like yours and your language you speak
about in such a clear way.
And as you would know, talk about self-leadership a lot
and that idea that you don't get to run a merged capital
and have a business like yours without a sense
of what self-leadership means.
Can you describe that for you?
Yeah.
I was very lucky.
The founding partner of the firm that I now run was the most
brilliant person that I've ever met.
He was young at the time, one of the brightest,
if not the brightest person that I'd ever met,
just believed that you could do anything.
But quite literally, it wasn't just like a, it wasn't rhetoric.
It was just like, just do.
And what I learnt was that you can do anything,
but particularly if you have young,
bright people, and I didn't quite appreciate this
because I didn't have high intellect as a student,
but if you've got young, really bright people
that are curious and conscientious,
you can literally do anything.
In terms of leadership, certainly what I've learnt is if you,
and this is a very commonly used word,
but I just sort of mean it when I say it,
but when you empower young, bright people,
it is just scary what they can do.
And so, you know, we work in this,
what I think is very unique environment because as you touched on,
when I left corporate, I wanted to create a safe environment
free of politics so that people could say what they wanted to say
as a question or a statement and feel comfortable saying it
because what I'd observed is that if they do that,
their confidence grows quickly and they begin,
they begin to discover that they can evolve their skills
and thinking at a rapid rate.
And as a result of that, talk about leadership,
I mean, I lead a group of very young,
elite people that exceed their expectations almost on a weekly basis.
And I believe, you know, and I think if I were to sort of talk about
what have I uncovered as being a leader and an owner of a business,
which is the untapped potential in these young people,
given the right environment and the right opportunities.
And as a result of that, you then get invigorated by them.
And it just spreads beyond your organisation.
I often reflect on this and I haven't landed on,
is it a formula?
Is this something that others do?
I wouldn't know.
It'd be worthwhile actually having a conversation in my leader groups
about it.
But, you know, I just think, Darce, that's something that I value immensely.
I don't know if I'd be a good leader of peers, to be honest,
if I'm really honest with you, but certainly young people,
I just get maximum fulfilment out of seeing them reach their potential
because I do believe that they have untapped potential.
Yeah, so much wisdom in that, Nathan.
I love you sharing it.
You know, someone said to me recently, you don't build a great business,
you actually...
Yeah.
...find these incredible people and then they build it with you or for you
or collaborate with you.
And we've seen that in our own space.
You know, Matt Waterwood, who you know really well,
who's a great friend of mine, an incredible partner
and just does things incredibly well.
But he's had the foresight to find these brilliant people.
And you've met Stacey and Marlee and Steph,
who've joined us in recent times as well.
It was so much smarter than me.
Talk about being invigorated by people.
You just, you actually want to be better for them
because you can see the bar so high and it resonates so strongly.
And I'm not surprised to hear you articulate it in that way.
And that sort of leads to having a positive impact on people.
When you bring young people into your environment,
I'm assuming on a daily basis,
you've got a consciousness around how you impact them positively.
Yeah, look, I mean, it's a...
But I've got to be really honest to us, it's a brutal environment.
I'd say that in a positive context, on a negative context,
but it's not for everyone.
You know, a lot of the lessons that I learned in my career, I apply,
to what we do, we, you know, we work on very serious stuff.
And I wake up every day and never, ever take that for granted
in terms of the opportunities that we're afforded.
Like I literally just cannot believe sometimes the things that we get to do
and we're trusted to do.
And so I take that just so seriously.
And as a result, I embed that in the team literally every minute of the day.
But this culture of, you know, being direct,
but having no, there's no malice in being direct,
but it is highly confrontational.
And as I said, it's not for everyone.
But at the same time, because it's not personal,
we're always picking up the team members each day
and making sure that, you know, it's understood that it's not personal.
But when you can actually crack through that,
and that becomes your, the way, you know, your operating rhythm,
your efficiency goes through the roof.
It's like a vertical curve.
Because you're not trying to have to explain things.
You say what you mean.
If you're not saying it fast enough, you'll be sped up to get to the point.
And then we thrash out, we will rigorously debate.
If you weren't part of our organisation,
you'd find that it was almost offensive the way that we talk to each other.
Not in terms of language, but like, what do you mean?
That doesn't make sense.
You know, say what you mean.
And then what happens is this, just this beautiful sort of cycle of ideas,
comes out of it, and it gets tested at a rapid rate.
And then all of a sudden, you've got a solution.
And so, as I said, it's not for everyone.
But those guys that are in the team that can handle it, thrive in it.
And then they create that culture for the next generation
that comes through the organisation.
Because we're literally plucking kids out of university.
Yeah, it's brilliant.
And the sporting analogy is alive and well, for me,
isn't the best teams I've played in, you know, if you looked at the,
on the field, you haven't got time.
So, the conversations are as direct and as clear,
but always done with respect because you have that expectation of each other.
And that does translate to then off the field,
you just give and receive feedback instantaneously,
because you know you live and die by your teammates.
It sounds like that's, you know, in a world I don't understand,
but it's a highly competitive world, isn't it?
The world of real estate.
And to be good, I'm assuming you have to be at the cutting edge all the time.
Yeah.
Yeah, you do.
I mean, look, you know, these are billion dollar plus projects
and investments that we oversee and, you know,
require like hundreds, if not thousands of decisions to,
you know, make these investments successful.
And so, as a result, it's relentless.
And, you know, we go back to, you know, that sort of the workaholic phase
and sort of, you know, the pursuit of excellence.
I mean, you just can't stop.
And, but again, if you, if you push hard and you use your smarts,
it's amazing the outcomes that you can achieve.
As I go back to that point, I believe that there is a solution for everything.
You just got to, you just got to put it through the,
you know, the filter or not even the filter.
You just got to, you just got to smash it and there'll be a nugget in there.
And so we see ladies are really conscious.
How they go about creating and sharing a vision
and understanding a bit more of your story to do these transactions
across different continents and different languages.
And to do that successfully is a pretty bold vision.
I mean, how have you gone about, you know,
we got a bit of an insight into how the team communicate,
but how have you gone about sharing and creating that vision?
Yeah, look, it's interesting.
The opportunity to do what we do came about,
really when I came back to Australia and I realized like one of the things,
you know, a lot of us don't appreciate is how attractive Australia is as an investment destination.
You know, from a sovereign risk perspective,
we rank amongst the highest in the world in terms of our GDP and GDP per capita.
We're one of the wealthiest countries in the world.
It's just a great place to do business and particularly invest in real estate.
I also realize that at the time,
our competitors didn't really talk to each other cross-border.
So they might have a business in Australia or businesses or offices throughout the world,
but often they didn't communicate effectively with each other.
And so I sort of really tapped into that and,
you know, I guess had this vision of,
you know, facilitating cross-border investment into Australia
and really leveraging all of my institutional experience because it's a certain language in a way that you speak,
to institutions versus privates or individuals like you and I,
and that was my background.
And so, you know, I think in the early days,
it was definitely trial and error and just believing and turning up every day.
And, you know, I look at some of our former credential packs and you just go far out.
We're really, really sort of, you know,
it was a long bow we were drawing back then.
That's what you do, right? To get ahead.
But now I think the vision is really clear.
You know, we've got such a strong,
track record as you touched on,
you know, over $30 billion in transactions.
The team, because we're,
you know, we've got a lot on,
they understand intrinsically what we do.
I think the big thing,
Das, when I think about vision,
and we only spoke about this as a team last week,
was how do we take what we've done and how do we build on that?
Because I almost feel like, not that we're complacent,
but, you know, organizations evolve.
It's like me talking about being in your leader groups.
I sit there and I think, well, this is incredibly powerful.
Where do you take that?
And so similar sort of situation for our business.
I sit there and go, got this incredible team,
got this incredible track record.
We've got, you know, incredible relationships and all these things.
And I now ponder, what is the vision?
Is it more of the same, which there's nothing wrong with that,
or is it more of the same, which there's nothing wrong with that?
Or is it more of the same, which there's nothing wrong with that?
Or, you know, is there something that we can tap into?
Because markets change, you know,
we're heading into some pretty big headwinds, I think.
And so how do we adapt?
Because we've had one of the best cycles,
certainly from a real estate perspective in history.
But, you know, things like rising interest rates
are starting to cause some pain and we're going to have to adapt.
So for me now, it's thinking about the vision.
And then as a team,
how we set that vision and importantly,
because we're doers, importantly,
I just think about how does that translate into an executable strategy
that you can, like we have to-do lists and they're very long
and we go through them because we action everything.
We're all about execution.
And that leads to curiosity,
which we see shows up a lot in these conversations.
And through curiosity, it's that constant learning and development.
You can hear that in your world, isn't it?
You know, the world's changing.
What do we do next?
How do we continue to get better?
Is that thought of curiosity something that resonates with you?
Oh, absolutely.
But, you know, I'll be very honest with you.
And I've had this my whole career in a way,
and probably everyone does,
but I initially approach it with fear.
You know, even just talking to you about it,
sort of like makes me sort of nervous
because you don't know where to start, right?
And then we all know to start,
it's been like I told you when I came back to Australia,
I had to find a job where you start by making phone calls
and meeting people and, you know, all of that.
So, yeah, it makes me nervous and, you know, fearful of what if it,
you know, what if it doesn't work and all of those sorts of things.
But I guess, hey, that's if you reflect on your life
and as you and I have had several careers,
that's how it all starts.
And it's probably a good feeling to have
because if you didn't have that,
then you'd just be probably too comfortable.
And I think it's great that you get to share that.
And I certainly feel the same way, isn't it?
That just because you've achieved a level of success
doesn't mean that that doesn't bubble up in all of us, does it?
To think, you know, can I keep doing it?
What can happen next?
And what does the next chapter in the second mountain look like?
It's, you know, I certainly feel that the same way.
I've been doing a certain role in sort of mainstream media calling footy.
There's other passions that are there,
but that always burning, you know, touch of,
can we actually make this work?
Keeps you alive, doesn't it?
You don't always like the uncomfortable part of it,
but it keeps you getting out of bed, doesn't it?
I mean, you asked my wife.
I mean, there's no better person than I'm sure,
you know, a lot of us are similar that lives and breathes it.
It's intense.
And, you know, it can be a curse,
but also it's your greatest strength.
You know, as I think I've said to you,
it's in some ways getting comfortable with it
and being able to turn it off as well.
And again, that's something that I've spoken about in my leader groups,
but at the same time,
it's just this burn that you have inside you,
but that's who we are, right?
But at my age now,
I've got to learn hopefully some tools
or hacks as Matt or Stacey would say to try and also,
you know, manage that because,
you know, I think as I shared with you prior to this call,
when you have a business or when you set,
the direction,
you know, you can take things wherever you want to go.
And if you understand the power of that,
it's just bloody cool.
But you know, there are consequences to that as well.
We've heard a bit about your communication
and the other formula of being really direct and clear
and you know, an outsider coming in might almost find it offensive.
I mean, you've obviously put some thought into communicating with clarity.
Can you share a bit more on that?
Yeah, look, I mean, I think for me,
I was very, very lucky.
I've worked under some great communicators
and it was embedded in me quite,
or instilled in me at quite a young age,
the importance of communication and,
you know, we go back to those early jobs,
go back to the cross-cultural element.
I mean, I had to reinvent the way I spoke
because I'm a Queenslander and,
you know, generally shorten words.
And so I wasn't understood literally,
just linguistically, people didn't understand what I was saying.
In Asia or in?
In Asia, yeah, probably in Melbourne and Sydney too.
But yeah, look, I mean,
so I was fortunate at a young age to be very clear
in how you communicate, to say what you mean,
to always stop and pause and think about who you're talking to,
to not talk in implied language.
I often find that people,
they don't intentionally do that.
They start talking as if they know what you're talking about.
And that's, again, one of the great things about our organisation.
Our team aren't afraid to sort of,
you know, politely sort of stop that person or interrupt and just say,
look, I actually don't understand what you're talking about.
But yeah, communication,
certainly in the business that we're in is everything.
Because we are communicating ideas,
we're communicating direction,
we're communicating recommendations.
And, you know, a lot of the time we're influencing, right?
We're influencing outcomes because, you know, we're advisors.
So, you know, you're paid to provide advice.
And so whether it's written or whether it's, you know,
oral, it is absolutely paramount.
So, and I believe that it's like training.
And I say to the guys in our business,
see every opportunity, whether it's an internal team meeting,
as an opportunity to practise how you communicate,
because it is something that you get better at doing.
And I look at athletes, for example, that play,
and then they, like yourself, they go into media.
But if they look back to their playing days and, you know,
some probably can't string a couple of words together.
And then you see them in media and they're like some of the most articulate,
you know, you love listening to them talk.
And that's just practise, right?
And so, yeah, I think communication is everything.
How important has collaboration been for you as well, Nathan?
Yeah, look, it's massive, right?
And it's not easy because, you know,
I believe in chemistry between people.
And you can't, you know, some people you just gravitate to.
They're probably your best friends.
And then there's people that you may never gravitate to,
but you have to do business with or, you know,
you may be in a community with them.
And so, you know, I often reflect on how I feel in those situations
when I'm collaborating with people that I don't necessarily gel with.
Because the value of collaborating versus not is, it's immense.
I mean, it's the difference between success and failure,
or not even success and failure,
whether something can be an opportunity or not an opportunity.
And so, you know, the way I guess my style is to be transparent,
to, you know, to openly share not just the positives of a situation,
but also the challenges, to build rapport and trust and to go forward.
But, I mean, you know, as I said, communication is everything.
But, you know, you can't achieve outcomes if you can't collaborate.
Otherwise, you know, maybe you're a surgeon
and you operate or something like that on your own.
But in terms of what I do, it's a vital part of everything.
And I love what you just said then because collaboration is easy for us,
as you said, with the natural group that are your people
and you love being around and you find that synergy.
But you're right, isn't it?
If the ones that we don't naturally gel with, that's hard.
I find that really hard because you're grinding the gears.
But, you know, the worst part of me is, you know,
I don't want to have anything to do with that person
because in reality, it's a pretty narrow life you live, isn't it?
If you can't find a way, you know.
Darce, you're right.
And, you know, as I get older, I struggle with it even more
because of the energy that it takes to put into those relationships.
And from experience, you know, how challenging that can be.
But again, you come back to it's just essential.
You can kind of just get old and just, you know, close your mind too,
which is completely fine too.
I don't have an issue with that where you just say,
I just want to hang around my people.
I get that.
But at the same time, you know, I just remember as a young person
because I used to push so hard and want things so bad
that I would force relationships.
And I remember some of my early bosses in Asia,
one in particular who was a Singapore lady,
who we just butt heads.
Like, you know, I was this young upstart.
She was this proud, older, you know, Singaporean lady.
And we really did not like each other, but yet she was my boss.
But fast forward towards the end of that professional relationship
and even, you know, after we sort of finished working together,
we became really close.
And what I learned is that you can't,
just because they may not be one of your people,
you can't be quick.
Quick to form views because often, you know,
there's a lot to people and you've got to have patience.
And so you've got to give the benefit of the doubt.
And it's bloody hard to do, particularly when you're in a rush.
So, yeah, look, it's not easy.
And to this day, like one of the things I hate more than anything
is going to conferences and people go,
but Nathan, you know, you get on with everyone,
you know, you're so talkative and you can talk about anything, whatever.
But I like fear, you know, those sort of environments.
That's funny, trying to do some research for our chat today.
And you're not an easy man to research, by the way.
But I was looking at your LinkedIn and there's so many,
every time it wasn't about you beating your chest about you,
it was about congratulating someone else.
It's just a, hey, well done, great work.
I looked as though a lot of those projects,
maybe some of them I'm sure you were behind,
but others it looked like maybe even some rivals that you were, you know,
congratulating and that's unique, you know, is that just you being you?
Yeah, look, I mean, I just love seeing people do well.
I just genuinely do.
You know, my industry is small.
I think every industry is probably small when you get to,
you know, our age and our level.
And, you know, we're all part of the same community.
And so, you know, from my perspective,
you just, you do,
you do just want to see people do well.
That's the bottom line.
I mean, look, you know, we've all got people I'm sure.
If we're being honest, we don't want them to see do well.
But, you know, again, I go back to that relationship I had with the boss.
You know, time in my view just sort of heals everything.
And I guess I'm at an age now where, you know,
I just generally want to see people do well.
And I think because it's just good for society.
And, yeah, it's just positive.
It's generally a healthier way to live, isn't it,
when we get it right most of the time.
Who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Oh, mate, look, there's a handful.
You know, I often don't talk about it very much,
but I'd certainly probably start with my father.
He chairs my organisation.
His influence on my life has been profound.
And, you know, time's been a challenging relationship.
Not bad at all, but, you know, I guess young bull, old bull type thing.
But his influence on my life has been profound.
And I'm only just realising that at my age now.
And it's interesting.
We got a really special time together in Italy recently and, you know,
just got to reflect on a few things in life.
Not deep because he's not a deep guy.
But, you know, it's just I'm so blessed
to have someone like that.
To have someone like him in my life.
So I'd start with him.
You know, some of my early bosses who clearly recognised talent in me
that I didn't see because I didn't certainly see it for about two decades
that gave me the opportunities and, you know, instilled in me things
like thinking strategically, communicating,
all those things that we've really touched on on this call.
And then also, you know,
my former business partner who founded Emerge Capital.
If it wasn't for him, I literally wouldn't be here today.
As I shared with you offline, he deconstructed me from an institutional
and corporate person.
And, you know, I thank him every day to myself.
Probably not enough to him in terms of giving me the opportunity.
And then I just think lastly, Das, is just, you know, your friends.
You know, again, as you get to our stage in life,
you really do value, you spoke about Leon and your relationship with him.
I just feel blessed to have great friends that make your life just so much better.
And then lastly, mate, is, you know, I just can't thank my wife
and my son enough because they are, they're everything, right?
They are.
They literally are the good times and the tough times.
And my wife's just, you know, she's a superhero.
And I don't know anyone that should have to put up with me because I'm so intense.
But she's a very special person, mate.
So, yeah, there's a few.
And I'm sure everyone would have similar stories.
Well, beautifully said, Nathan.
It's something I do love asking because, you know, I know I'm sure your dad
and your family.
And your family and your mates will love hearing that because we don't often
take the time to do that, do we?
And I know I don't.
You know, I was going for a walk the other day and Bec asked me the same question.
He said, you're good at asking everyone else.
Over to you.
And it is, it puts you back in your reflective moment, doesn't it?
So great people in your life.
It's nice to take that time.
You do business around the world in a unique space to work through Asia and Europe
and the Middle East and incredible success across Australia.
We love collaboration in the elite world.
We find it's a bit of a superpower.
Has there been someone you thought of I could collaborate with on any part
of your life that would jump out, a name that springs to mind?
From all of those experiences?
From anything that appeals to you.
It's a diverse life you've lived.
Has there been a person you thought that's the person I'd love to spend some time
and collaborate with on any of your passions?
Oh, Darce, I'm going to have to take a rain check on it because, you know,
when you just said all of that, I just had this vision of my life literally
run through me.
And when you're going through all those markets that I've worked in,
I mean, I've just met some profound people, like truly profound.
And when I was young in particular and I was put in these positions that I really,
you know, people shouldn't have entrusted me because I was just so young,
but it gave me the opportunity to meet.
You know, I'd read an article the other day about how Thaksin Shinawatra
has just moved back to Thailand after being in exile for 10 years.
I remember a dinner I had with her.
I don't know, probably 10 years ago when I was at Emerge Capital,
and I'd lived in Thailand, right?
And, you know, people get up in the cinemas, like before they start,
and they pay homage to the king and even to the leader.
And here I am sitting at dinner with Thaksin Shinawatra.
It was profound.
I mean, not that there was collaboration in that sort of dinner,
but I just come back to, you know, those opportunities and people
that I've met and have collaborated in.
There's so much we haven't touched on,
but some of the things that I did in China with some of the Chinese,
you know, I was there when they opened up.
They were admitted into the World Trade Organisation,
and, you know, I was working with Walmart, rapidly opening stores
because Walmart's the largest retailer in the world.
And, you know, just that collaboration with them, you know,
the Walton family flying in.
To China on their jets along with others, you know.
So, mate, so much.
Yeah, I'll just stop there because I'll just ramble.
Well, there's a three-part series in this, Nathan.
I loved it.
You just mentioned the Walton family and doing business in China.
We didn't even touch on India, so we might have to do a round two
at some stage.
It took a bit of work to get you to the table the first time round,
but we are really grateful to be able to collaborate with you
in the elitist space.
And you're a great champion for us and telling that story
as you did so beautifully today.
And I love, yeah, you spoke about people giving you an opportunity
when you were young when you probably didn't feel like looking back.
You had earned it.
But I love that you're passing that on to people the same way.
And a fascinating story.
Really appreciate you spending the time, Nathan, today.
There's been a lot of wisdom in it.
Thanks a lot.
Thanks very much, Darcy.
As I said at the beginning, I appreciate the opportunity,
particularly to Matt and Stacey who run my groups.
I mean, I'm sure if it wasn't for them, I wouldn't be here.
If it wasn't for them, I wouldn't be in this position today with you.
So thank you.
Thank you for listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast
powered by temper, a mattress like no other.
And to make sure you don't miss an episode,
click subscribe wherever you get your podcasts.