I think that's been a good part, too, because sometimes, as you know, in this world, in
this game, your ego can get struck a lot of the time, and you can think you're bigger
than what you are, and it's always good to have those people sort of pull you back down
to your place and realize that you're just a person out there entertaining, and sometimes
you do it well, sometimes you do it not so well.
Nick Natanui is this week's guest on the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Nick is an absolute champion on and off the field, really inspired by the story he shares
of his mother looking after Nick and his twin brother in an immigration detention center
as a single mum following the tragic death of his father, how the Buller 3G spirit of
community and family shapes his outlook on life, and really all of the decisions that
he makes.
He shares the dream that he, Michael Sonny Walters, and Chris Yarrant all had as kids
growing up.
In the same street in Perth of using AFL football to become the first members of their family
to buy a home, and wanting that for their mums more than any other goal in life.
It's a brilliant story.
Nick Natanui is an absolute champion on and off the field, and we are really privileged
to have Nick in Alita Connect.
He and Nick talk about how the diversity of his group, media producers, property experts,
social venture entrepreneurs, have all helped him in his life post-professional sport.
Book a discovery call.
We'd love you to join Alita.
Alita Connect, head to alitacollective.com.
Big thanks to Jason Nicholas and his team from Temper Bedding.
Alita athletes like Nick Natanui absolutely understand the value of getting a good night's
sleep.
We spend a third of our life in bed, so having a look at a Temper mattress is something you
should check out today.
Nick Natanui's legacy as an Australian rules footballer is as significant as anyone in
the modern era.
The overall number two draft pick in 2008 of Fijian heritage went on to be a three-time
All-Australian, a two-time West Coast Eagle.
He was best and fairest and played with athleticism and power the likes of which the game hadn't
seen before.
A genuine cult hero who from his very first game became one of the most recognised high
profile and loved sports stars in Australia.
Nick, great to see you.
Congratulations on an amazing career.
Thanks, Stas.
Thanks for having me.
I love the intro.
I'll have to cut that out and put it at home, I reckon.
Well, mate, it's all true and it's such a great story.
It's one of the most enjoyable ones to tell from an AFL point of view.
Can I go back?
Mum and Dad were born.
You were born in a small village near Suva in Fiji.
Your parents emigrated to Australia and I understand you tragically lost your dad to
cancer, leaving your mum with you and your twin brother.
You're just one years of age at the time.
Can you describe how hard that must have been for your mum?
Yeah, tough transition.
I think as a child, you don't know any different and that's probably a credit to mum for making
it so seamless and you just think it's normal, your day-to-day stuff.
You don't think of what's actually happened or what's sort of transpired in the months
or years.
Yeah, it was tough.
I guess being in Australia at that young age, mum wasn't an Australian citizen.
She was still applying for a permanent residency, which I found out later on in life.
Having no Australian citizenship and my old man passing away meant we had to spend time
in a detention centre.
We spent a good part of a year and I'd love to tell you I remember it, I don't, because
I was only a toddler in there.
I was a kid in Sydney and yeah, just through the, I guess the grace of people out there
in the community who reached out and had a home in New South Wales looking after us and
helping us go through the sort of government and legal system and putting us up in their
house for a long time, we're able to be out in the community and I always look back at
those days and go, it must have been real tough for mum, but to get to where I am now,
it's been a long, long journey.
Yeah.
And Nick?
I understand it was a family in New South Wales that really supported your mum and the
family, as you said.
So a year in detention centre for your mum, coming to Australia to forge a better life
for you and your twin brother.
Yeah.
And then, as you said, the generosity of a family to really make life in Australia possible.
You must be grateful for that.
I am.
And it's something that I'm very passionate about away from football.
A lot of the immigration stuff and new migrants and I guess knowing how hard it is and how
hard it was for mum.
I always think back to not only was she trying to find a way for us to have a better life
in Australia.
But, you know, she's also grieving at the same time.
So to be able to do that with, you know, I've got two under two at the moment, not quite
twins, but to do it with twin boys who are running a mark would have been really hard.
But like you said, the generosity, I've always been a big one on giving back to those that
need it more.
Not those that need it, but those that need it more.
And yeah, that's always been mum's sort of mantra.
And I think, yeah, that's because it's come from those who did it to us when we were such
little kids.
Your mum, I believe, is she returned back to Fiji in later life?
Yeah.
Was that tour always back to her?
Her home and upbringing?
It does.
Yeah.
My sister had some kids, so she wanted to be around her grandchildren.
And yeah, I guess mum, you know, always had a connection with home.
We'd try to go back to Fiji whenever we could, back to the village lifestyle.
And, you know, I've got 300 odd family members in this one village.
So when they say it takes a village to raise a child, it actually does.
Because I find how tough it is over here when you're looking for a babysitter.
Over there, it's just, you know, drop them off at a house here, go there.
And mum always wanted to go back.
But, you know, she wanted to make sure that, you know, her boys were settled here in Australia
and had a good job.
So, yeah, I was about 24, I reckon, when mum moved back to Fiji.
And, you know, obviously in the AFL system for a number of years, mum thought, you know,
he's okay, he's set to go.
My brother finishes his plumbing apprenticeship and, you know, had a good job.
So she was back to the islands.
But, yeah, that was always on the cards for her.
And I'm glad she got to do it before, you know, before she passed in 2015.
You can't believe the commitment, can you?
Yeah.
Two boys are settled and then feel comfortable to go back home.
You eventually settle in Bushby Street, Midlands, which has become, Midvale, sorry, about 30
minutes out of the CBD of Perth, if I'm correct.
And it's become famous in the AFL world.
Can you share us about the unique neighbourhood that you eventually settled in?
Yeah.
People ask me about Midland and I try to explain Midvale, Midlands, the same suburb to people
in their respective states.
I think in Victoria, you'd say, oh, Frankston back in the day is Midland.
No disrespect to Frankston.
No disrespect to Frankston or Sunshine, those type of areas.
In Adelaide, it's probably the Elizabeths, those type of places.
Working class.
Working class, rough, solidly earth people, but yeah, very rough.
There's a lot of, you know, a lot of problems and issues in those places, but you also get
a lot of genuine, you know, raw reality of the way life is and the way, you know, but
for us, like I said, we had a pretty rough time and, you know, mum was always grateful
just to be in Australia.
So that stuff wasn't hard.
Like, you know, like growing up in a village with no hot water and, you know, and all this
sort of stuff.
And no TVs and no electricity.
It's, um, but anything was a luxury.
So I didn't, we didn't care, but it was tough.
We had a lot of people struggling around us, which I think was the biggest thing.
I think if we were in a better suburb, it would have, you know, sort of exacerbated
how poor, how broke we actually were.
But to have everyone struggling around you just made it feel normal and then made you
feel comfortable day to day.
And then you have this incredible stroke of genius from an AFL point of view where Michael
Walters, who's become a legend of the Fremantle Dockers and played 234 games.
Yeah.
Chris Yarram.
Chris Yarram was a number six overall pick and Nick Natanui in the same street to go
on and combine, be close to 600 AFL games.
It's, it's a lightning strike, isn't it?
Of growing up really.
Yeah.
It's like someone planted us there and it was there for a reason.
I always pinched myself because I don't think as well, if I didn't live next to those guys,
I'd be playing AFL football.
So, and it wasn't just living on the same street.
We actually all live next door to each other.
So yeah, I'm a bad advocate for Auskick football because we always skip training as kids to
play footy at home.
We used to use our rubbish bins, the green and yellow bin as our goals and shut the street
down.
My neighbors used to hate us, but it's funny when you go back, some of those oldies still
live there and they, they're the first ones to say, yeah, I loved it when these kids played
on the street, they claim and embrace us.
So they, they loved it.
But I remember they used to hate us and I don't blame them, but yeah, we used to, we
used to train and you know, it's funny.
There's always one guy that gets missed out.
The guy at the house behind us on the next street, but their back fence was on the back
of Chris Yarram's one was, was Jeff Garlett.
So, um, so we had a pretty talented little.
Little team, little street team.
And, um, yeah, as we sort of, uh, got talked into by a local coach to come down and, um,
you know, his wife worked at our primary school and said, come to this local footy club, Midvale
and, you know, learn how to get a bit of structure in your life.
But, oh, I'm so grateful that they came along because they taught us a bit about planning,
not just about football, but you know, how to budget that.
They brought my family in who, you know, we sort of kept to ourselves and little pockets
and taught us, you know, the Aussie way of life.
Um, and you know, what a barbecue was.
I didn't know what bangers were.
It was a mash, all this sort of stuff was.
And, but yeah, having those two boys next to me, um, probably, you know, reflects a
little bit on the way I played my football as well.
Your athletic ability could have taken you anywhere, probably to basketball or, you know,
with the Fijian history and rugby would have made sense, but you had these brilliant indigenous
Australians who, as you said, they played the game with a gift that you couldn't believe.
And you probably, uh, you know, a 200 centimeter version of that was probably how it played
out.
Is that how you feel?
Yeah, I think so.
Yeah.
I used to come up with a lot of flack over the years around not playing like a big man.
Like I could tap the ball and stuff, but you know, your rucks around taking marks around
the ground and doing those sort of things.
But I learned off those guys who are, you know, they're the zippiest small fours.
They're the civil realities of the, of the AFL.
And they were just so skillful and talented.
They had a ball on the string.
Like they made it look so seamless.
And, you know, you see guys, you know, of indigenous background who do the same thing
and they've been doing it for years.
So I picked up, that was my introduction to football.
I didn't have the structure and bouncing and the technique, um, down pat.
It was just go and have a bit of flair.
And, you know, we never had such.
Shots from 10 meters in front.
We used to try and dribble it from the boundary and things.
So sometimes, yeah, I used to get frustrated because I'm like, this is my version of footy.
It was never the, um, you know, the basic fundamentals.
It was always the Larry stuff, but it wasn't showing off.
It was just the way we learned to play.
And yeah, I'm, I'm so grateful for it because otherwise I think I would have been two, three
years into the game and I wouldn't have made it as far.
I think some of the highlights that I've been able to produce.
Yeah.
Sonny and Chris are probably the reason why.
And thank God no one got hold of you and bored you out of, uh,
existence.
Which probably would have happened.
You would have been overcoached and someone would have no Nick, you got to go and play
this way.
And you brought something to the game that makes us smile, uh, that no one else could
do before.
And, and, and when you were doing that at your best, you were unstoppable and we loved
every bit of watching it from, from afar.
The thing I've always, your athletic achievements are next level, Nick, but anytime I've ever
seen you or been lucky enough to be in your company, it just feels like you bring this
great energy and this happy, uh, vibe.
What do you think has been the key to being happy and successful?
Oh, I think it's just the Fijian way of life.
Like everyone's just the, the bullet smile is just like happy.
Like, I don't know.
It's funny living.
I always have to like base my life in Australia to my back, my life.
When I go home to the village where no one, I think the humility that you have back there
is a, is a big part of it.
No one cares.
There's no status.
There's no hierarchy.
You know, I go home back to my village and they'll chuck a mop or a broom and say, Hey
mate, like get to work.
Like, I don't care if you earn and, you know, a couple hundred grand or you're on TV on
the weekend, you come and you do, you come and chop some of the stuff in the, in the,
in the gardens and that.
So I think it's that sort of thing.
And everyone's so welcoming back home.
It's, it's, and I could go back to the start coming to Australia.
I'm just grateful to be over here and to be able to do what I've done.
So people reflect on my career sometimes and talk about the injuries and, you know, disappointments
in, you know, footy and things I missed out on.
But I always think of the things I got to do and some of the people I got to reach and
influence as well.
And I see that as just as, just as powerful, but I don't know.
Sometimes you can get caught up being so stressed playing this game because it is a big business,
but.
I love going out to, like, I just got back from a remote community, um, you know, a couple
of hours east of Broome and just seeing some of those indigenous kids in the bush who don't
have footy boots or just play footy for the love and passion of it.
I always thought that's what footy was about.
So yes, there's nice playing in front of 80, 90,000, but seeing the sort of grassroot,
like core essence of footy has always given me a drive and happiness.
So I always think back to that and that makes me the happiest person on earth.
I love your perspective, Nick.
And you're, you know,
a beautiful twin brother who's a plumber and I've heard you say it before, he's cleaning
toilets and I'm kicking footies for a living, getting paid really well.
And so sometimes we don't always have that perspective, but as you say, when you put
in the content, your worst day of a knee injury, isn't that bad when you think about it, is
it?
No, no.
And like I said, my twin brother was the first to say it all the time.
Like he was up at 4am, you know, elbow deep in someone's toilet, cleaning it out.
And you know, every time I'd whinge about, you know, I'd, I'd complain and I'm not gonna
lie to you.
I'd complain about someone coming up and bothering me for a photo sometimes, or,
you know, I'd complain about someone coming up and bothering me for a photo sometimes, or,
you know, we've got a session and then we've got to go and sit in a meeting for two or
three hours or something.
And he'd just laugh because he'd be like, mate, you don't know what the real world's
like.
And he laughs now that I'm finished, you know, that I'm, I'm out in the real world and I
see how hard it is.
You're not getting paid half as much as what you are as a footballer.
And, you know, you're required to work at least nine to five.
And, um, but no, I think that perspective and, you know, has, has kept me grounded and
having people at home that, you know, my football's not, my family's not a traditional football
family.
So we don't talk footy at home.
It's, you know, it's normal.
It's not normally rugby or something different.
So that was, I think, a blessing in itself as well.
And my brother, you know, he was, he still is an Adelaide Crow supporter.
He grew up loving Brett Burton.
He just loved the Birdman.
So his dream was to always see someone take a hang like he did on my shoulders.
And yeah, he never went for West Coast.
He supported me, but he didn't go for us.
And, um, yeah.
And all my mates, like we've got a range.
I don't expect people just to be mates to me because they're, you know, an Eagle supporter.
My best mates are, you know, Frio supporters or, you know, Bombers, whatever it is.
And I think that's been a good part too, because sometimes, as you know, in this world,
in this game, your ego can get struck, um, you know, a lot of the time and you can think
you're bigger than what you are.
And it's always good to have those people sort of pull you back, back down to your place
and realize that, you know, you're just a person out there entertaining and sometimes
you do it well, sometimes you do it not so well.
There's a beautiful humility to all of that.
And, you know, you, people wouldn't understand from almost the first or second game you play,
there was this intensity of fascination.
With you and WA being a footy mad town and the amount of attention and scrutiny that
came your way, you got to hand over the jumper to a young man called Harley Reid, number
one draft pick, who's probably captivated WA in the same way you did all those years
ago.
What, what advice would you give him?
Yeah, I catch up with Harley every, every sort of fortnight at the club.
Uh, and I speak to him.
I took him down to the beach for a coffee actually the other week to just talk about
the highs and lows of footy.
I was lucky enough that I caught up with Juddy when I was 17, 18 years old.
And he spoke a bit about the roller coaster and, and WA, you know, him and him and Cuzz,
who were the nine before me sort of, you know, we're in that same sort of spotlight and,
um, spoke about, you know, when you're up and you, you know, you're riding these highs,
you'll, and then you go down and you're losing and, or, you know, the articles are bad about
you, um, you can really affect yourself mentally.
So, um, he always talked about the roller coaster and I've always spoken to other guys
about it, but Harley in particular, you know, I was in the paper every second day in WA.
Harley's in the paper every day, like the back page every single day.
Yeah.
And it's become, uh, an obsession and cra- and a craze, which he's pretty level-headed.
He's a good kid and he understands sort of how it works, but I always just go in and
check in on him, but make sure that he understands how, you know, the footy media work and especially
in a fishbowl town like WA, uh, where there's only two teams and you know, all the other
sports are sort of dampened, um, so AFL takes priority.
Yeah.
It must be hard for a kid because when you're 18, 19, all you want to do is play footy,
hang out with your mates and all of a sudden this pressure's thrusted upon you.
Yeah.
So I feel for him, but I'm also happy because it means that I'm not on there, so I, um,
but he, he, he'll handle it really well.
He's, he's mature beyond his years, so no, I think he'll be, he's perfectly suited for
it.
Chris Judd said something that always resonated with me that he, you know, and I won't quite
get it right, but he said, why would I give away my sense of wellbeing by reading an article,
good or bad?
He said, the good sometimes is just as you read this stuff about you being superhuman
and then, and when you have a bad game, you read about yourself in a way.
So you know, he just ignored that.
You go, you're the trusted people in your world, your coaches and the handful of people,
but try and leave that outside, outside noise out of your life.
Is that, sounds harder to do than perhaps it is?
No, it's big.
And I feel bad sometimes saying it cause I, you know, I, I've always worked with closely
with people like channel seven and things like that, but I never watched the news.
I don't read the paper.
Like it's just, and not because I hate it or don't agree with it.
Like you said, it just, it's good for your mental health, especially when you're in it
in the spotlight.
A lot of the time, if you keep up to, you know, the date with what people are writing about,
saying about you every single day, you can really, you know, lose your way.
And I'm guessing someone that's in Hollywood or something like that, they're not reading
the tabloid media or watching the news or things like that, because if they did that,
um, either be full of themselves or they'd be really depressed.
So Jody's probably the man to, to thank for that.
He will never take credit for it, or maybe it will now, but, um, nah, he was pretty good.
And, and I've spent a lot of time with Kazi as well, um, you know, over his sort of roller
coaster of the journey, post football as well, and, and learn the right and the wrong things.
And we happily speak about it.
The right and wrong things to do, uh, especially in our town, how much bigger it is if you
do those things.
So that's, I've been lucky to have those guys, um, from the young age teach me and navigate
through, you know, the world of footy.
Your twin brother's right.
He said you're in the real world now, post the AFL and, and life changes, uh, immediately.
I know you've got a range of different interests, uh, a non-alcoholic seltzer called Alter is,
uh, is getting great traction around Australia.
Tell us about what you're up to post footy.
Yeah.
So, um, I've got a friend, uh, former teammate of mine that played at Brisbane as well as
involved and, and his mate Darcy, um, he's sort of the brains behind it.
Um, he's, uh, worked for a big company and, and understand the sort of beverage game.
I, I don't know.
I was reluctant at the start.
I know a lot of football is getting the fashion or drinks or beers or things like that, or,
and, um, don't really work well, but once I got into it, I started really looking, um,
into the nuts and bolts of it and understanding it.
And yeah, we're doing a healthy sort of seltzer and having all natural ingredients is, you
know, a big thing.
Um, the zero sugar and low calories is sort of the in thing at the moment.
Um, you know, everyone went through the kombucha phase and drinking that and, you know, we
thought, how can we replicate that and do it in a, a sparkling version that actually
tastes, you know, not like a health drink.
And I think we've nailed it.
Um, yeah, we've teamed up, you know, with some of your mates and, you know, the shiny
venues car with pubs and, you know, all the groceries and that are getting on board and
convenient.
So it's, uh, it's been, it's been a good challenge.
It's been a, a real, uh, learning curve because, um, like I said to you earlier, you don't
get handed anything.
Um.
You know, you played so many games of footy or did what you did.
They still make you earn it.
They might look after you a little bit, but, um, that's been the best thing I've been looking
for a challenge since finishing.
And this is that, you know, that little drive and challenge and sort of a test for me that,
that, um, that keeps me, keeps me going and keeps me sane.
And you're starting to use your brain in a different way to grow a dream, a really competitive
market.
As you said, Nicknado is going to open the door a few times, but your product's got to
be good.
And then your business model's got to be good.
And so you're finding that that's something you're enjoying, trying to pull those pieces
of the jigsaw together.
Yeah, for sure.
And, and I look at it, you're competing with, you can compete with the smaller brands, but,
um, I don't know, being footballers, you want to compete with the best.
So I look at Coke, I look at Pepsi, I look at, um, Red Bull V all of those and I think,
you know, how can we, you know, we don't have to do the same numbers as them, but let's
try and see their formula and what they do and try and, um, you know, get close to them.
So, uh, we'll see where it takes us.
I'd love to look back in, jump back on a podcast with you in a couple of years time and see
it doing well.
But, um, nah, I'll give it every, every shot I have.
And the fact you've got.
The, the supply chain.
I love, you know, where you've got to already and, uh, having tasted it, it, it is a great
product.
And, and I think that's where the market for the next generation don't drink like our generation
drank.
And so it feels like you guys have got a plan that makes sense.
We've been really privileged, Nick, to cross over with you in something we're really passionate
about, uh, a thing called Alita and Alita Connect, where we bring together people from
diverse backgrounds and different thinking in groups of five or six.
Can you tell us a bit about how that's been for you?
Alita's been good.
Been, been amazing.
You know, as, at a football club, I think only if you're a part of Alita, you know,
leadership group, you actually get to sit down and, you know, make decisions and talk
about some of the problems around the footy or around your footy club.
So to be able to do that away from the footy club, I wish I did it a little bit earlier
because it would have been very helpful with my day to day, you know, as a player as well,
just to get my mind away from it.
But I just have been able to connect my, my group in particular is got a range of people,
you know, we've got people that used to work for AstraZeneca who now moved to a new role.
Um, we've got a guy that runs, you know, some groceries, um, over here in Victoria and,
you know, we've got.
Producers, um, and there's just such a, a wide range of people, um, there's a lady that
runs like a, a charity, um, for, for women and empowerment with women or young women
and just to pick their brains and, you know, everyone has the same sort of issues and problems
and that, but everyone's got a different perspective on things.
So it's just been refreshing to bring out some topics or, or talk about things and then
someone either has an answer or they look at it differently.
So yeah, sometimes I reckon I get tunnel vision and just get real focused on the, you know,
on one thing.
Um, which, you know, is to my detriment, but to have the range of voices around you
is, is awesome.
And I wish everyone had a group like this or had a, you know, an, a leader group in
their life.
Uh, because it just, whether you, I don't know, I went in a bit skeptical at the start
thinking, I've done all these leadership things, I don't know whether it's for me and, um,
you know, and then actually getting into it, I don't, I don't want it to end.
So I'm looking at ways to keep it going forever.
And, um, you know, Don Pike, our CEO at the club at West Coast and John Worsfold and a
few others.
Justin Langer, there's been so many guys that are, um, have been a part of it and still
to this day, um, speak highly of it and still catch up as a group.
So it means it works.
It's a proven product and it's something that, that I've been so happy that I've been involved
with.
Very grateful to have you, have you part of it.
Um, what's Nick Nannanui like as a dad?
You've got two young kids.
Tell us about your leadership on the home front.
Family's been big for me.
Like it's always been a part of my, my makeup.
Like I don't know, I think it's probably just a cultural thing where looking after kids
is just a mark.
But given you don't get a choice, really, I've always had cousins and everything running
through my house and, you know, changing nappies from a young age.
So I'm not one of those dads that were grossed out by it even, you know, like, um, but it's
funny cause I, I've actually, retirement has been, you know, it was a difficult decision,
but it's also been one of the best things cause I get to spend time a lot more at home
and see my little ones sort of grow up and developmental changes over the course of months,
um, is, is, is amazing.
So to be able to see them go from crawling or saying their first word or talking as,
as being good, I've got Ezekiel and I've got Zuri.
So I always laugh because they both got the Zs or Zs in their name, but they don't catch
any Zs at night.
They're wide awake all night, they don't sleep and, um, they drive you mad, but then they
get up and smile at 5am and they just give you a big cuddle or a kiss and all is forgotten
for what happened the night before.
So, um, they're smart.
They know what they're doing, but two under two, there's no TV in my house, I think.
Um, yeah, we're, we're mad.
We, um, yeah, they'll be good.
Everyone always says they'll be great and close when they get older.
But, um, yeah.
Yeah.
I mean, at this point in time, we're in the trenches.
They're not older, they're young, they're full of energy and they want to want to do
things themselves.
And, but it's been the best thing like, and it's been a good learning curve and a lead
has been a big one for it.
Um, I've always had, I always am curious and wanting to know what to do.
And I always ask most of the time, people, you know, probably expect me to talk footy
or talk about, you know, business or things in my life that I've done.
But I asked a lot of parenting advice.
I'm like, oh, so, you know, some of the people in my group, we've got four or five kids.
You're like, how do you deal with this?
Or what did you do to do this?
when this was happening and everyone's got their own little hacks
and tricks to do it and you find your groove through that.
And there's not a lot of places you can go for parenting advice.
A lot of us have done it, but they're not really readily available.
I'm a bit like you, you're curious about.
It's probably the thing you want to do best in your life.
And I love what you said before, that Buller Fijian way with kids.
And anyone who's ever been to Fiji with their kids, it's magical over there.
The connection that the Fijian people have, even with kids that aren't their own,
it's hard to describe, but it's part of the culture.
It's amazing.
It's funny, obviously being wintery time now, this is going to sound gross,
but my family, any kid is their kid.
So my sister's kid, my sister and brother-in-law and uncles and aunties
will treat my kids like their own.
So I was away the other day and I get this video of my brother-in-law.
My little boy is clogged up, so he's so snotty.
And my brother-in-law just gets his mouth over his nose and sucks all the snot out.
It's the only way.
Because my little fella.
He can't blow his nose, so he's like, it's the only way to decongest him.
And everyone laughs.
And I said, that's the Fijian way, but I claim to be Australian when that stuff's happening.
I struggle to do it.
And I explain, you forget sometimes.
You've got things like snot suckers and that in the Western world now,
so you don't need to be doing it.
But everyone's just sort of, like you said, just dialed in to do those sort of things
because family is the number one most important thing.
And I find it as well.
There's no retirement villages back home in Fiji.
Your family get old.
They kind of live in the almost back room.
It's almost a granny flat.
They look after you.
You look after them when they're no longer able to look after themselves.
So that's always been the way.
So adjusting to community and family life here where it's all sort of set in stone,
where everyone sort of looks after their own is hard at times
because I've always been pretty big on just welcoming anyone and everyone.
And my mum was a social worker, so we had so many people who were homeless
and that come stay at our house.
Even if we didn't have anything, our door was always open.
I wasn't the biggest fan because I had a twin brother
and we always shared everything.
So then to share with others was always tough.
But no, I've always had that in my life.
So kids have just  they make you have to be selfless
and have to sacrifice a fair bit.
But I think I was well-equipped leading into it.
So life lessons and you go to a place like Fiji
or I love the Balinese in the same way.
It's all family.
It's all connected.
As you said, there's no retirement villages in any of those parts of the world.
Nick, I love sitting down with people like you.
You've got
Yeah.
There's a lot of incredible patterns of success
and we see these dimensions of leadership we love talking about.
Starting with this idea, it's hard to lead anyone else
unless you understand your own self and self-leadership.
What does that mean to you, Nick?
Yeah, I think just knowing who I am as a person,
I think it's taken a lot of time over the years
just living in a place where your Fijian heritage,
whether it's accepted and it wasn't accepted in certain parts as a youngster,
but then embracing it as I got older and today,
that sort of diversity is accepted more than ever.
So I understand.
Understanding who I was and what I wanted to be about, having strong morals and values was big for me and sticking to it.
I think the unique thing with football is you deal with the CEOs and big corporates and the millionaires and billionaires of the country,
but you also deal with just the everyday person that is a consumer or buying a ticket or a membership, and you have such a big impact.
So I think finding who I am and not trying to lead like other leaders do, but finding my own niche and leading the way Nick Natanui leads has been the biggest learning for me,
and I'm still doing it, still learning and still developing, and having that at the forefront has helped me be who I am today.
And I can see that authentically, you being yourself, Nick comes out in everything you do.
We see leaders really conscious of having a positive impact on others every day in their environment, everywhere they turn up, and I can see that in you.
Is that something that you've thought about?
Massive.
Yeah, that's big.
I always want to have an impression on someone.
When they walk in the room, I've got a big thing on saying hello to every single person, whether you're the cleaner, whether you're a producer, whatever you are.
If you're in the room, I want to make everyone feel sort of special or part of things, and that's just the way I am, and it's something that gives me a lot of joy.
And yeah, it's weird because football is a place where you're a role model and you have a lot of responsibility, and some people shy away from it, but I think it's such a privilege.
I went to the children's hospital with Harley Reid and a few other guys at West Coast the other week.
And there's a sick kid with cancer who won't eat their food or their veggies and stuff to help with their treatment.
The nurses and the mom and dad are telling them to do it, but as soon as a couple of footballers walk in and say, hey, you'll get big muscles and being as strong to do it, and they eat it, I said, that's the biggest power you have in the world.
It's superhuman in my eyes because you have so much influence and so much power, both positively and negatively, but to be able to do things like that and impact people's lives is amazing.
I had a guy last week come up.
Two weeks ago, sorry.
Come up.
He came up to me and speak to me about how grateful he was for me playing football, and I didn't understand why.
I thought he enjoyed the spectacle, but he spoke about he and his dad never had a really good relationship, and he said, oh, what I was able to do was buy a membership for us both.
And he goes, I got to sit next to my dad for two hours.
We used to fight for so long, but two hours every second week, I got to sit in the stands with him.
We didn't talk, but at least I knew that I was getting some quality time with my dad.
So he's like, thank you, because there was no other forum where we'd be able to sit in the same room together.
So there's different ways you get to impact people's lives in a positive way, and I'm so grateful that my job has allowed me to do that.
And I can see that, Nick.
We just walked down, you and I, to the local coffee shop before this started, and you stand out in the crowd.
There's no mistaking it, but you've got this sort of happy presence, and even the way you interact with the guy we bought a coffee from before.
You can see he had a smile on his face.
You probably don't even see it walking out.
It's brilliant.
See, leaders are really conscious of the visions that they have and how they go about creating.
And sharing it, you've obviously had some great success.
Have you thought about that and maybe going to this next part of your life, creating and sharing the vision that you want for yourself?
Yeah, I think so.
I've always been a big one on having a vision or having a goal, and that probably is derived from my mentors as a kid.
My local youth worker, Tony Maracci, was a big one.
He used to take us out and teach us the right way.
He used to show us what's going on.
There's guys doing drugs or doing bad things in the corner just down the road, but there's a pathway to go and do what you want to do.
And myself, Chris, and Michael Walters, we all sat down and wanted to buy our mom's houses.
That was our goal.
So having that vision, I thought it was unattainable.
I thought this is a bit far-fetched, man.
I just want to be able to help mom pay this week's rent and rent, not buy a house firstly, but having that end goal.
And there's no straight line.
You're always diverting and there's ups and downs, but as long as you have that foresight to go, I want to get to that, it gave me a bit of drive.
And that's sort of what I do now.
I have a vision of what I want to get to.
And I think the biggest thing is understanding that you will fail at times.
And if I'm not going to get there, at least I've given it my all and I knew I was doing the right things to put myself there.
I think I'd be more upset with myself if I didn't do that and I fell short because I'd just be floating through.
So having that vision has been big and sharing it as well and letting people know what I'm about and what I want to do helps open doors
and helps you get to where you want to do because people are out there.
They are willing to help.
So did you, Sonny Walters and Chris Yaron, as kids talk about wanting to be successful enough to buy your mom's houses to give them that security.
That's an amazing thing for kids to talk about.
Oh, it was awesome.
And it was our, you know, Frank Caviccio, who was our junior coach and his wife, Sharon, um, and, and, uh, Antonio Mirachi, those guys, they were, they put that in their heads.
They said, guys, you know, you can do what your cousins or your mates and they're doing down the road and have an okay job.
Or you can, you can be the first people.
And it was not only, it was bigger than just.
Yeah.
Buying a house for our family.
It was more being the first person in your family to buy a house.
That was a big thing.
No one, you know, no one in my whole family had been to university.
No one had, has been bought a house ever.
Um, so to be able to do that and I got to do it, you know, in my early twenties was, that was bigger than any footballing moment, anything.
I still get into those boys cause I got to do it first.
Um, you know, I said, you just, you boys say, but you didn't say it properly or your clubs weren't paying you right.
So I, um, no, it was always something proud and, you know, once we'd all ticked it off, it was awesome.
It was amazing.
So for me, I get the most pleasure from that.
And I'm so thankful that I was given a goal or a purpose to do it.
And now in life, I've got the same thing, you know, like I said, it just gives me purpose to do what I do every day.
And I think footballers in particular should have that, you know, whether they want to buy a house for their family or buy a new car, there's always a reason why you play.
Finding your why has been a big thing for me for so many years.
And I heard you in your retirement speech, you referenced that, didn't you?
You know, like, Oh, you can't take this house away from me.
The footy's given me this and I'll be great.
Grateful, regardless of the ups and downs.
It's incredibly powerful.
Curiosity is a word we hear and use a lot.
And we see people like you often really curious about life.
And through that, they try and get better all the time.
Does that resonate with you?
Oh, all the time.
I like to know people's stories, where they're from.
With the leader, we had a guy, Michael Hewitt, um, call in from, from Rome of all places.
And, you know, such a, an intellect, such a smart man.
And he spoke about how many books he's read over his lifetime and how many he's written.
And it really humbled me because I was like, okay, I need to step my game up here if I want to get.
You know, even scratch the surface of where he's got to.
And, um, he spoke a lot about curiosity, which is a big thing.
And I, um, yeah, the software of the brain and understanding.
Sometimes we, we think we know it all and we just, you know, we get, um, really fixated on just doing it the way we do it.
But, you know, speaking to other people and seeing, Oh, he sees it from that perspective or she, she sees it from that perspective.
Then you, you know, that curiosity helps you develop a better, um, outcome, I think.
Um, sometimes we just go in with, Oh, no, this is how it's been done for so long.
This is how it should be done.
And, and sometimes it'll work, but it's so much more powerful and better and allowing people to have input as well as is a big one.
I think being, you know, collaboration and letting people, you know, have an input and be curious about different things just makes a better working environment, better life environment.
And I've always been curious.
I've always wanted to know how to, you know, I'm one of those people that will go on YouTube and watch, um, how to do things, not just get it done.
Um, then I'll, then I'll end up paying someone to do it anyway, but cause I know I'm bad at it.
Yeah.
I always, I always wonder how things work and I always ask questions on, you know, you know, how does a microphone work?
How does a helicopter spin or what, what, what kind of fuel does it run off?
Things like that.
So, um, sometimes it's a bit annoying, but I tell you, because I want to know people better and I've got a real genuine interest in, in, in humans and people.
Um, you know, I did a bit of anthropology, um, at uni for my first year and a bit.
Um, and it was something that I just really loved doing.
I've, I've had work with world vision and, um, United nations and, you know, being a.
Places like East Africa and, you know, I've been to Israel and to the border and Gaza, those type of places and just meeting with people and hearing their stories and hearing how they got to where they got, because I think that's a powerful way to learn a lot more about the world and, you know, broaden my perspective on the world as well, uh, not be so insular.
So now I've always been curious and I think it's, uh, it's the best trait that I, um, that I have.
I love it, Nick.
And I can hear it come out.
Michael, you're glancing, you referenced, um, lucky enough.
To record a podcast.
He's founded the school of thinking with Edward de Bono and lateral thinking.
I curious always about, uh, your ability to change the way you think through other people.
And you explained that really well.
You, you, you communicate, uh, really beautifully in your own way.
And if you thought about that, the way that you've been able to get your message out and how you communicate it.
Yeah.
I think the biggest thing is, um, you know, doing things like this, doing podcasts, like I've got a million things in my mind sometimes, you know, um, it's, it's a bad thing cause it keeps me awake at night.
But, um, you know, doing.
Podcasts or just having conversations with people is, is a great, is a powerful thing because it actually helps me articulate, um, you know, what's going on inside my head.
Cause there's no use having all these great thoughts in your head if you then can't push it out.
So finding different avenues to talk about it and do it is, um, oh, it's been so helpful in my life and the leadership part.
I've always been a big advocate of, um, I dunno, as, as, as you know, you walk out into these big stadiums or football arenas and, you know, you do media and things like that, and you have so much.
Um,
I guess power to do or say whatever you want and people will respect and listen to it, but I was, I've always been a big one on, you've got to lead well at home before you can leave it, lead out in the real world.
And that's something that sometimes gets forgotten at times.
I think a lot of people are great leaders, you know, big CEOs and corporates and whatever, and, and good on them, but sometimes I forget to lead at home.
So that's something that I always reflect on.
If, if I'm going to be this good or people can see me in a good light out in the public and, you know, praise you for this.
How does my family talk?
Talk about me, you know, how did my kids, how did my missus talk about my relationship at home?
So that's always been a big one for me, not forgetting, you know, who I am or where I come from and, you know, still give that same energy out to the people that I don't know.
So, um, it's a constant battle and I, and I still, you know, I still struggle and learn along the way, but that's something that, you know, is always in the back of my mind.
It's such a, it's a brilliant, powerful thing you've just said, Nick, and I often have this discussion, you know, I turned 49, uh, in a couple of months time.
And, you know, like you, you see people that.
Excel in the outside world and have great business success, but maybe at the detriment of their home life and their family life.
And I think, you know, that's why I love the city across from this incredible Fijian champion who gets family values more than maybe anyone else does.
And you think at the end of it, when it's all over, they talk about the regrets of the dying, isn't it?
What would you regret more that I excelled and strive more to be a better CEO or gave more time on the home front?
It sounds like you've understood that at a young age.
Yeah.
Oh, from a young age for sure.
I think, you know, being present is a big part, you know, especially as a father, the, the issues a lot of people can have, um, later on in life is because of the neglect or things they haven't had as a youngster.
And, um, I've been very present and, you know, making sure that that's a big thing for me, but I don't know.
I I'd love, like I said, I'd love for my partner to talk about me, you know, as, as well as, you know, someone who's in a commentary box does, um, you know, so I always feel that people have such big connection and big, um, you know, life.
Um, things that happen in their world, but I have it with, um, people at their workplace and they forget to have those moments with their own family.
So that's a big, that's a big thing, especially in the football world.
You know, you come home full of happiness because you're like, oh man, my mates, we, you know, we trained hard today.
Then we, we beat the Bulldogs on the weekend by a hundred points.
And, um, you know, you come back one point and, um, and you have, you know, you have all this elation and all this happiness and that.
And then, you know, you can go home to your partner who's, you know, been rocking the kids for, you know, seven.
Seven hours, you know, no TV, no stimulation, no adult conversations.
And I think that's a big part on, on myself and understanding that, you know, lead at home first and be the best role model you can be there.
And then go and translate that out in the, in the business world.
So, um, yeah, if you ever see me making a hundred million dollars, um, or 200, whatever it is, um, make sure you come and remind me about that.
Because I, I always am a person that seeks feedback and want people to remind.
Me of, Hey, don't just say what you say, actually practice what you preach.
So yeah, I think that's wishful thinking a hundred million, but you know what, I'll be happy with 1 million.
If my family's happy.
Yeah.
Beautifully said, uh, Nick, um, how important has collaboration been for you?
You mentioned it earlier.
What's it meant to you?
Big.
And I think, um, through any sort of aspect football and out there in the public, um, just letting people be involved or working with others just broadens your mindset and broadens your ideas.
Like, like I said earlier, you think, you know.
Everything, or especially as a young teenage boy, um, or an adolescent, you think, you know, how the world works and it's only until you sit down with a, you know, a 70, 80 year old person that had lived it, lived their life.
And, you know, has a wealth of wisdom that you realize that you don't know everything.
Um, and you know, I had this conversation with, uh, probably don't, um, digress a little bit, but I, um, have this conversation with a company that builds, you know, indigenous housing, for instance, up north where I just was, um, a WA and, you know, some of those houses get
trashed because some of the communities are, you know, skinning kangaroos inside the house and 20, 30 people living in the house.
And I, I challenged them and I said, Hey, do you ever think about building a model that is, um, suitable for an indigenous community?
Because, you know, what works in the Western society down here in Perth or in Melbourne or Adelaide, wherever it is, doesn't translate to a, you know, a rural place that's off the grid, um, where these guys are, you know, traditionally nomadic people who live off the land.
They don't have a husband, wife, and kids that live in a house.
They traditionally have cousins.
Uncles, everyone passing by and staying in the house and, you know, they want a central meeting place where they can light a fire inside, inside.
So do you ever think about changing the model?
And I think, you know, people love hearing that because they, they don't actually sit down, you know, you can sit in a boardroom and throw a million ideas, but until you get amongst the people and, and see what their ideas are and, you know, collaborating with different groups, then you go, oh, I didn't think of that.
Like this, this actually might work.
So, and I've been a victim and been a, you know, a, a culprit of doing that myself, you know, thinking this is how it should work.
This is, this is the way you do it.
But until you work with others and see how, you know, you always have strength in numbers.
Um, and that's probably what becomes from football as well, where, you know, you're only as good as, as your worst player.
Like you need everyone to be giving their best on game day.
You, you know, you can have two superstars in your team, but, um, you know, if you don't have other guys playing their role and, and, and being a part of it or not buying into the culture, then it can easily be found out.
Yeah.
I love what you said.
There isn't, we're ignoring tens of thousands of years of history in remote indigenous communities with an arrogance.
It suggests that we can potentially do it better.
And that's the opposite of, of collaboration is an ignoring all the wisdom that's there.
Nick, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Um, I, it's funny.
I thought about this question.
I, um, you know, I think of all these people, um, you know, I've had great coaches and, you know, John Worsfold and Adam Simpson and a few others.
And, um, you know, Robbie Wiley's, but you know, the footy world, but I think it's my mom.
I think it is.
I look at, I do love to say these guys who have, you know, helped me teach me things, but I don't think mom, anyone's taught me anything better than what mom has.
And the sacrifice, the, you know, reconciliation and also the, the understanding, like the forgiveness, I think is a big thing.
Like mom's been a one that could be salty.
A lot of people, cause you know, growing up, we lived in about 60 to 70 houses.
You know what I mean?
Like I got drafted to West coast and I was still living in about four or five different houses over that time trying to just, you know, pay rent.
I think the hardest.
And I think mom's been the biggest leader.
Like we never had, um, uh, Medicare or didn't have access to Centrelink or things like that.
Cause we weren't Australian citizens.
So I think mom struggled, but she made it, like I said, made life so seamless and, you know, like every other kid.
So, uh, I'd be, it'd be remiss of me to say that, you know, she wasn't the greatest influence and greatest leader in my life.
And it's funny.
Sometimes you, you think about that cause I, uh, I saw a question the other day and it was about little kids getting interviewed.
And it was like, and their parents get interviewed and they pulled them apart and they said, oh, to the mom and dad, who would you be your, you know, your two biggest dinner guests that you'd invite.
And yeah, so the parents would be like, oh, LeBron James and who else, uh, Steph Curry.
And they'd think of all these big superstars and their kids, you know, answer the same questions on the microphone.
They go, oh, mom and dad.
And you just like, sometimes you forget those who are just right next to you, the closest to you.
And they're the most powerful, most influential people in the world yet.
Sometimes we get fascinated.
And in awe of, I guess, the stardom and the glamor of those who are out in the, in the public eye.
So, mum, mum by far.
What a hero, your mum.
And I, you know, to come to Australia for a better life for her to, to go through detention center, to then not leave until she felt comfortable with you and your twin brother were, you know, that's the age 20.
Like it's, it's one of the great stories you could imagine, as you said, and to have that in your world.
And I can't imagine, as you said, moving from house to house and growing up in, in neighborhoods with the challenges.
It's, uh.
I'm not surprised at all that they, they, your values, we are a bit obsessed with collaboration, you know, leader, and you've described it as well as anyone I ever have.
Is there been anyone that you've thought you've got a range of different things?
I know your community work's really important and back in Fiji and now your commercial and entrepreneurial path.
There's been something you thought, God, that's, you know, Nick Nannan who gets access to a lot of people.
Is there been one person you thought you liked to collaborate?
Um, yeah, I, I go to the stardom again.
Nah, there's been some like, NBA people and that, that I'd love to, you know, work alongside or speak to and, and pick their brains.
Um, I don't want to be dropping names, but there's been some big ones, um.
That you've been able to get access to?
I've had access to, yeah, yes.
You've got to drop one for us here, Nick.
No.
I saw you give Mike Tyson a jumper the other day from the West Coast point of view and.
Yeah, we get some, yeah, I know Mike's manager, so he, um, yeah, Mike wants to come, come out to Perth and come out to Australia and, um, you know, he's a big boxing fight coming up.
I, I just think you get to meet so many, you know, good people, you know, and especially, you know, the Kelly Slaters of the world.
Those type of guys.
Who are just, you know, just the best of the best of what they do.
Um, and I've got a real interest in those guys, but I'm trying to think the UN, I've got a real, like I said, I've got a real passion for people.
So every year I try to go away to a place that's off the beaten track.
So I'll go to, um, refugee camps where there's like a million people in a, you know, the size of the Melbourne CBD.
Like just, I go to places like that and it's, you know, through the UN, like we were lucky enough to have Julie Bishop on our board at West Coast.
So she's opened up a few doors and allowed me to do some trips and through World Vision.
So I think collaborating.
With someone at that level where you're able to go into countries, but see sort of everything, not just see the tourist sites, but see how, you know, some of the hardships and that, um, you know, I went to a place where there was famine and no water and things like that in, in Africa and seeing, you know, how, how people were impacting their lives and doing things.
So my dream collaborator would be, yeah, someone of that sort of realm.
Um, and then on the flip side, yeah, I think just great leaders.
Like you see how powerful it is when someone like a Tom Brady comes to town.
Yeah.
Or, you know, Michael Jordan, if he ever came and did something, you know, how much you'd want to pick his brain.
So, um, yeah, I don't know.
I sort of go through a mixture of people dealing with, um, real life stuff, but then those who are actually, you know, living, I guess, a similar life to me where they're under, you know, the, the public eye in a, in a town, um, so small and every move is watch, you know, you fill up my car, you get a photo of someone, you, you go to get your shopping in the same sort of thing, you get stopped a couple of times.
So I like.
I like picking those people's brains who are in the same position, because then I can go and say, oh, I can implement this in my life, or this is how they did it.
It's not the worst thing, but this is how to do it.
But no, in terms of a specific person, I don't think I can give you, give you one.
I love what you said, Nick.
And there's, that's to me, sums up sitting across from this incredible athlete we all admired.
But I think understanding there's a humanitarian, there's a person who wants to be the best dad and the best partner and influence people, but also, you know, live the best possible life.
It's a, it's a great.
It's a great story, Nick, full of admiration for you.
Appreciate you taking the time.
And I, as you said, I'd love to do this again, because I feel like the next chapter of your life might be even more exciting and you can impact so many people in a positive way.
So thanks again.
Thanks for having me.
Cheers, guys.
Thanks for listening to another episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Huge thanks, as always, to our great friends at Temper, and we encourage you to check out our Leader Connect program.
New episodes are out every Wednesday morning at 6 a.m.