A Listener Production.
G'day, it's Luke Darson.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership both on and off the field
has been a lifelong passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective
and have had the privilege of working with thousands of leaders
in education, sport, industry and the arts
that have helped shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership
where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
Nicole Gibson is a multi-award winning social entrepreneur
that prefers to be known as an unstoppable messenger
of love and human potential.
At 18 years of age, Nicole established a not-for-profit
and grew it to sustainability.
At 20 years of age, she was a finalist for the Young Australian of the Year,
listed as one of Australia's top 100 most influential women at 21.
She is a fierce ambassador for mental health innovation and connection
after recovering from her own terrifying lived experience
with anorexia nervosa through her teenage years.
Nicole is the CEO of the Rogan Roos Foundation
and recently completed three terms
as the youngest Commonwealth Commissioner for Mental Health.
Nicole, it's a great honour and privilege to spend some time with you
and to catch up in person.
Thanks for joining me.
Thank you, Luke.
That's an old bio, but it's nice to reminisce on where I was at at that time.
Well, please update it because I want to be fact-checked.
I found myself, Nicole, your own words so articulate,
which I really do, but I just feel like the best way to...
That was beautiful.
...try and bring people back to you is to hear your own words.
And I have got a slab here, if you can bear with me,
and I want to ask you a question on the back of it.
But these are some of the words I found in research for you.
Growing up, I had the world at my fingertips.
Attending an excellent school for the arts,
I majored in theatre whilst pursuing modelling and fashion styling.
An insufferable perfectionist, I was always trapped inside my own rigidity
and ideas of wrong and right.
Excelling at a young age and finding myself in elitist groups,
I could never quite grasp my own opportunities or potential.
I always felt like a slave to the voice inside my mind,
that would tell me you are not good enough,
spiralling me invisibly into an internal war
and engaging in self-destructive behaviours
that were not known by anyone on the outside.
At 16, and on the fringes of an emotional, mental,
spiritual and physical breakdown,
I was diagnosed with anorexia nervosa,
extreme amount of anxiety and dissociative tendencies.
I was falling deeper and deeper into the dark.
My extremely low body weight made me feel like
I was walking through life in a haze.
Nothing was ever clear.
I never felt fully there.
Amazing opportunities were centimetres in front of me.
Yet I could never quite grasp them
because of my own inability to love myself.
It's a powerful statement.
I want to jump to your school principal sits you down.
What happens then?
Yeah, so I, obviously this story is so dear to my heart.
And at that point in my life, I think, you know,
setting the context of how difficult it was
for people to approach me makes this story
so much more significant because you look at that situation.
He was a school principal.
Principal, really alpha dude, you know,
the least likely person actually that I probably
would have thought, you know, to lean in to that conversation.
But he approaches me at school and he was visibly nervous,
you know, visibly vulnerable and said to me,
please, can you come and have a conversation with me?
And I just remember feeling terrified
because no one had really confronted me
about what I was going through.
And I just had the sense that that's what he wanted to talk to me about.
And on one hand, I wanted so much for someone to see my pain,
you know, as we all do, I think, when we're in pain.
But as soon as there was someone right there in front of me seeing that pain,
I wanted to run a million miles in the other direction.
But I followed him to his office and the tension was so intense
that I couldn't even sit across from him as you normally would,
you know, in the principal's office like you and I are sitting right now.
So instead, just to manage my anxiety,
I went and sat in the corner of his office.
It was quite a big office.
So I could just get some physical distance from the tension.
And I put my head in my hands like I was bracing myself
because I thought or I felt that I was going to get yelled at or told off,
you know, because I think the shame I was in,
that was like my assumption.
And I sat there in that position, very defensive position,
and he said to me,
the first words that came out of his mouth when he called him,
I'm not here to say that there's anything wrong with what you're going through.
I just want you to know that you're not alone.
And it's such a simple statement, right?
But it was so powerful for me in that moment.
It was a genuine feeling of like relief
because I always felt so responsible for other people's discomfort,
which was quite a common thing going through,
I guess,
a mental illness that was so physically confronting.
Unlike, I guess,
other mental health challenges,
which is somewhat a lot of the time invisible.
They can't be seen avertedly,
but anorexia is different.
And I felt like it was a genuine invitation for me to just come as I was.
And so I just cried,
cried and cried and cried.
And he just let me cry.
He didn't sort of come and tap me on the back and say,
it's all right, mate,
you know, stop crying.
He just let me be.
Which was very healing.
And then he asked me a question,
maybe 10 minutes,
20 minutes into that.
You know what my favorite thing to do after school is?
And I shook my head through my tears.
And he said,
it always has been since I've been an educator,
is to have a beer when I get home.
And I was thinking in my mind,
like, why are you telling me this?
Are you going to say that that's the answer to my problems here?
Or, you know,
where are you going with this?
And,
and then he said,
I want to make you a deal,
Nicole.
And he got out a piece of paper from his desk drawer
and he wrote on the piece of paper,
like it was a contract.
I'm not going to have a beer until you hit your weight target.
And he signed it.
And then he got out some sticky tape
and he put it on the side of his desk.
And I just looked at it in complete shock,
thinking like,
why would someone sacrifice something they loved,
you know,
something they enjoyed for me?
And there was so many nuances as to why that was,
was such a beautiful approach.
You know,
he didn't directly say evidently is struggling with an eating disorder.
Clearly there's something wrong with you.
He just,
he gave me this commitment that I can see you're struggling and I don't want
you to do it alone.
And this is,
this is what I think I can do to help you feel less alone.
So naturally I just said,
why,
why would you do that for me?
And he said,
I'm not going to know what it's like to be a teenage girl going through this,
but I know what it's like to be a human who's struggling and who's struggling
alone.
And I just want you to not feel that way.
And that was a conversation that really in,
in every way changed the trajectory of my life,
potentially saved my life.
Um,
and it wasn't that it was a magical,
you know,
three,
two,
one,
now you cured.
It's that through what was a very difficult journey of recovery and
rehabilitation,
I had this light of someone who saw something in me that was very human,
that was very real.
And was a constant presence of doesn't matter how clinical this gets,
how many doctors you interact with.
I see you and I believe in you.
What a legend.
Legend.
What a,
what a story of incredible leadership,
as you said,
from an unlikely source,
you know,
we don't celebrate it.
There are educators enough.
I think when you find someone like that,
seriously to have,
you know,
I can imagine him being nervous,
but to,
to step up and do that for you and to get it so right,
I mean,
God,
you,
you know,
it's,
it's incredible.
Have you spent time with him?
Is he aware?
I mean,
clearly your stories is a really well-known story now.
Is he,
is he understanding of how important that was?
Yeah.
Well,
I,
he's very,
very humble,
really struggles,
I think,
to maybe receive fully the impact that had on me.
And throughout the years,
we definitely saw each other multiple times,
even after I graduated and I would reinforce that.
And,
you know,
he would always say,
no,
that was,
it was all you,
you know,
I didn't,
I didn't do anything,
you know,
and I,
I think that is just a,
another testament to the leadership,
you know,
when you,
when you give,
make sure you're doing it from a place of really wanting to empower the other person.
I've taken so much from that in,
in my own leadership.
We find that the best leaders are,
humility is such a common trait is that they,
you know,
really don't want credit for any of their great examples.
And it doesn't surprise,
as you said,
you don't click your fingers in that conversation and you're healthy again.
It's,
can't,
imagine stepping into those shoes,
but I'm sure recovery from that had enormous amount of pain and ups and downs.
But I read with interest,
you spoke about a defining moment where you flipped your mindset from,
this is happening to me and I'm concentrating solely on myself to what can I give to others?
Can you,
can you tell me how you got to,
to changing your mindset in that way?
Yeah.
I can try and summarize that.
I think,
you know,
suffering,
well,
there's a distinction that,
that I've now learned to create in my life.
And that's pain really is inevitable,
but suffering is optional.
And I was in a lot of suffering,
a lot of suffering that was driven by,
yeah,
I think fundamentally this,
this self orientation.
And I don't think that's directly addressed enough with people that are struggling the way I was because can obviously seem like a very sensitive or controversial thing to say to someone who's in so much suffering.
You really thinking about yourself a lot,
you know,
but actually do think that that is the source of,
of much suffering,
you know,
in,
in people's experience,
because when you start to extend yourself,
all of those insecurities and those challenges of,
am I enough?
And what am I worth?
And you know,
what value do I have in the world?
It starts to dissipate because your focus is actually on,
on giving.
I think in my instance,
I was forced into this position where my condition was very critical.
So I could have,
I could have lost my life.
And I think there's a confrontation there that that's very difficult to explain unless someone's been in a similar situation.
But basically I had to ask myself the question,
am I actually prepared to potentially die for my idea of identity,
my ego and what else am I meant to do in this life?
You know,
and I'm so blessed that I did have this deep sense that I was destined for more than,
than anorexia.
And I was simultaneously so terrified to know who I was going to be on the other side of that,
because it was such a defining part of who I was at that time.
But I think getting to that place where I had to ask that question,
it was a,
it was in a way,
I guess,
like an awakening,
a realization that I didn't want to take that illness all the way through to the nth degree and potentially lose my life.
I wanted to do more with my life.
And my way of really understanding how to get out of myself,
I was so fed up,
you know,
so fed up with the way those insecurities just controlled me,
and giving was,
you know,
when I started to ask those questions to myself into life,
there was a fire that really started to burn very,
very deeply in me to want to be a value,
you know,
to others.
My,
you know,
I think it's amazing where you've taken that.
Just going back a step,
it's,
you know,
I've heard it said before,
isn't it?
It's hard to be depressed or in a challenging situation.
I know this,
as you said,
it's a,
it's a hard thing to say,
isn't it?
Effectively you're saying to someone,
you know,
you're being selfish,
and that's,
and far be it from me to do that.
But I think you articulate,
well,
as soon as you start having to think about giving to someone else,
your mind's completely changed immediately,
isn't it?
As you said,
it dissipates you.
You,
you go from that extraordinary,
challenging situation to founding a not-for-profit,
um,
18 years of age.
You,
you,
you buy a yellow van from what I read,
and you decide to grab a couple of friends and take off around Australia.
You visit 300 communities,
um,
you know,
75,000 people with the idea that you're going to talk about emotional and mental health.
It's a,
it's a big call.
Um,
to,
what,
what did you discover on that trip?
It strangely seems like such a logical,
you know,
next move.
And I think that that's,
that's been quite,
um,
characteristic,
most of my pursuits is,
yeah,
I guess in hindsight,
it was very bold kind of proposition for me to have at that time.
But I,
I just,
I saw,
I saw it overcoming it myself.
I saw how many people were in that pain,
you know,
that,
that suffering and that there were these cultural reasons why that was the case.
And,
you know,
Luke going back,
10,
15 years,
there really was a very common opinion of what mental health challenges actually meant.
And it was very,
very clinically driven.
You know,
the,
the leading thought slash attitude was if you have a mental health challenge,
you know,
the best you're going to do is manage it.
You're probably never going to fully overcome it.
And it's most likely a biological predisposition.
Now,
because of the influence I had,
you know,
an amazing principal who's,
who acted as that leader in my life,
breaking free of some of those prisons in myself,
um,
which I'm so thankful for.
It gave me this,
this perspective that actually,
no,
this is for the most part,
cultural and environmental,
but that was not a common way of thinking,
you know,
back then.
And so that was a big part of my inspiration was to,
I didn't think I knew it all.
I wanted to validate that perspective.
And I thought the best way to do that would be to listen to people.
And a big part of how we facilitated those workshops during that,
what became almost a two year tour was to invite people,
into a safe space to share their story.
And,
um,
I did a lot more listening than I did,
did speaking and that deeply transformed me because I realized,
you know,
and interestingly,
like the tour went from having,
you know,
three,
three or four people,
you know,
maybe show up and kind of through gritted teeth,
start to share some of that vulnerabilities to watching this evolution eventually of like 30 people in a workshop,
50 people in a workshop getting invited into businesses.
And universities and watching this expansion,
eventually,
you know,
government seeing that we're not so different,
even,
even when the details of our life are technically different,
we come from different places,
different social class,
gender,
age,
whatever.
When you really give people the space to get down to the core of what's been affecting them.
It's this theme of I don't feel heard.
I don't feel seen.
I don't know how to,
give love.
And I don't know how to receive love.
And it was uniform through every single story.
And once you see that,
I think anyone would come to the same conclusion.
If they had that exposure,
you realize,
well,
we have a world that's so focused on difference when actually fundamentally,
we all want the same thing.
Yeah,
it's an amazing,
you know,
the way that you've summed it up.
You don't have to give love.
I don't have to receive love.
I'll get to love out loud.
And you're in movement.
You're creating the incredible book,
but I think it's what you pointed out,
was reminding people of the stigma of mental health.
Wasn't it?
It was just,
I won't employ someone who's got a mental health issue.
I won't,
you know,
that's bad luck that's happened to them.
They're not really quite right.
And we can hope to support them.
What you've been a huge part of is breaking down that stereotype.
And actually,
you know,
when you think about mental health,
it's,
it's a,
I suppose,
a paradigm or a,
some level,
we've all got a level.
We're all on that spectrum.
That spectrum is,
you know,
we wake up some days and we feel terrible.
And whether that becomes a clinical issue,
I think we're united by,
as you pointed out beautifully,
that desire for the same thing.
You move to,
as I said in the intro,
appointed as the youngest ever commissioner for mental health,
youngest commissioner ever by the Commonwealth,
21 years of age.
You serve three terms.
Tell me about that experience of going into the,
you know,
big government industry.
Yeah.
I mean,
that was a crazy juxtaposition,
right?
I went from living in my van.
And,
and working,
you know,
and living actually in,
in these remote communities,
which was so grassroots,
like I couldn't have got closer to the core,
you know,
of the essence of the,
the challenge on the,
on the subject of mental health through to advising a $30 billion budget,
you know,
and writing recommendations with my fellow commissioners on what that would look like.
It could not have been,
you know,
a polar side of that,
that spectrum,
which was incredible,
because having the background I had,
and I continued to do that work,
even,
even as a commissioner,
I was growing my foundation and visiting communities.
So I'd spend,
you know,
a week in a community and then be in Parliament House.
And so I really got to see how the decisions that were being made on the highest level were disconnected from the realities.
And there's a lot I could say about that experience.
Some things were absolutely incredible.
Some of the things that I really walked away with though,
was this deep understanding that policy can change,
you know,
we can rewrite policy.
We can,
we can make it illegal to violate human rights or stigmatize people who are dealing with mental health challenges in the workplace.
But fundamentally,
these things don't actually change culture.
They really don't.
And I saw that in a very real way,
just like there are things that are illegal,
but it doesn't necessarily stop someone committing a crime.
And so there's,
there's a deep fabric there of what is inspiring or motivating human behavior.
And I really felt that that was not being addressed.
You know,
I realized that these issues like mental illness are not actually political issues.
Yes,
the government have a responsibility to build infrastructure and build support,
of course,
but a government cannot,
you know,
inspire a human being to treat someone else with kindness.
And that's where I really actually saw the true need.
That,
that to me is the true need,
but it's one of the most complex problems that you can set out to solve because why people do what they do.
Yeah.
There's so many variables to that.
It's a great conversation,
isn't it?
I mean,
you,
you sum it up beautifully.
Again,
you can't inspire people to be kind.
We can't force people to be kind,
but you can lead the way.
Yeah.
Can have the example.
I think perhaps the,
uh,
the,
the great step was,
was actually getting you at 21 years of age onto a commission,
for 60 year olds and saying,
Hey,
we're least acknowledging it's some small step that we need to understand more about how it affects.
And I love that opportunity for us to learn from such different backgrounds and at least start there and have conversations,
hopefully like this,
where you're open-minded to,
to learn from people with a whole diverse range of backgrounds.
One of the stories that I,
I love reading about was you sat down with your commissioners early day and you said,
take your shoes off,
uh,
you know,
come and sit in a acknowledgement circle,
I think,
is your term.
How was that received by that group?
You know what?
By the end,
it was amazing again,
because it doesn't matter what level you're working on.
There was so much resistance in the beginning,
but,
um,
when,
when you move past that,
you know,
um,
and I think as a facilitator,
what I've learned is you just have to have that much conviction in,
in what you're asking and what you're inviting people into.
And if you're relentless in that conviction,
people will,
you know,
even through,
um,
their resistance,
they'll come to the party most of the time,
you know,
like really most of the time.
And in that,
you know,
how,
how beautiful to see people that otherwise maybe see each other as,
as against one another or competition to each other to actually still see the humanness,
you know,
and the appreciation and what each party saw in the other,
that,
that is the most transformative thing.
You know,
it changes the way people make decisions.
It changes the way,
people work together.
And,
um,
I think fundamentally challenges is imperative.
We need systems that have enough polarity and enough difference of opinion that there's no group think,
and we need to be brave enough to challenge each other.
But to be against each other is,
uh,
I think a very destructive path.
And,
um,
these activities is my,
you know,
one of my ways of trying to help people overcome that idea that I have to win,
at the expense of you.
Or I have to be against you in some way.
Yeah.
So again,
another,
um,
you know,
amazing thing that you're doing,
your community is about all of that,
isn't it?
Building a community based on love.
And I,
I'm working my way towards that,
that specific conversation.
But there's another point that I think you sum up really well.
You talk about two choices in life.
You can either live in,
I think you describe it as judgment,
which equals fear or acceptance,
which equals love.
Can you expand on,
on that a bit?
It feels a bit like the essence of what you're talking about.
Yeah,
totally.
I mean,
so looking at that,
that model,
um,
which is,
you know,
it's,
they,
they're,
they're big concepts.
It's my attempt to sort of simplify it.
Judgment,
we,
we need to ask ourselves where it comes from because judgment,
our judgmental mind has actually served us really well through our evolution as animals.
When we were in a state of fear,
we needed to hunt,
you know,
we were in danger.
We move away from the prefrontal cortex and into the most primitive part of our brain so that we can make quick judgments.
You're not,
wanting to stand there for lines,
chasing you and contemplate the meaning of life.
You know,
you want to make a very fast judgment.
The challenge is,
um,
as we've evolved into a modern day society,
we don't have those physical threats,
you know,
as much,
but we have a lot of overstimulation and I think a lot of people are feeling consistently unsafe emotionally and psychologically.
You could,
you know,
that's a whole podcast in and of itself,
but what that has created is the same kind of response where people are not,
um,
then that they don't have access to the part of them that can accept,
you know,
because,
um,
yeah,
they're under so much stress all the time,
which is the path to more expansion and more unity and,
and more,
more compassion.
And so judgment,
ultimately it's a,
it's a protection and it's a sign that someone's actually in a state of defense and it's a sign that,
you know,
they're,
they're needing to protect themselves from something.
But then when you look at how that plays out in society,
it,
it really is quite shocking how many people are in a judgment of themselves,
of one another.
And actually there's,
there's nothing to be against,
you know,
when you really were to break it down.
Yeah,
there's,
there's nothing,
there's nothing.
That's right.
And you,
and you,
and you catch yourself.
Sometimes you sort of walk into a crowd and just,
you know,
your brains,
summing people up that,
sizing them up in a second.
And,
and,
you know,
you stop and you pause and,
often they're the most interesting people as it turns out.
And,
and it's,
yeah,
there's a reflex part there that is,
totally,
you know,
there at the time,
at times that doesn't feel that helpful.
I suppose,
you know,
I will go there because,
it's a,
it's a common question.
And I,
and I want to ask you about,
with all the algorithms and social media,
it seems to have turbo charged that,
you know,
I speak about my teenage daughter a lot,
particularly when I come across someone like Unicole,
because you see,
and the boys too,
you know,
teenage boys and that constant,
judgment is there.
Every second of your day.
And so comparing to unrealistic imagery,
that feels as though it's a quantum shift in what,
you know,
the next generation are dealing.
What's your answer to that?
It's a world that we can't put the genie back in the bottle.
What do you make of that?
I think we really need to truly evaluate.
It's almost like we need to,
how would I say,
we need to extend this conversation because I think this conversation in,
in some ways has kind of been capped at,
well,
we know social media is damaging and then that's the extent of the conversation.
So I just see,
we need to expand that conversation and increase.
See,
I think it's brilliant at one level.
I don't operate on it,
but I love watching how they connect with their friends.
I love how,
you know,
from the year I grew up,
how hard it was to organize two people together.
They're amazing communities they form and,
and when it works well and everyone's accepted and included,
it's brilliant.
Yeah.
It's just the,
the one that I look at,
you know,
is Snapchat.
I see it through my kids.
It is a drug.
It's amazing.
And they all know where each other are.
Yeah.
And,
and then you sort of think,
what if you're the one person that's being excluded in real time?
You can sit there on your phone and watch everyone else getting together.
Like that,
that has got a touch of evil in it that it's hard enough.
And even when you're my age,
Nicole,
and you miss out on an invite,
everyone likes to be included,
you know,
it's,
it's a,
but when you're 15 or 16 and it's,
it's brutal,
isn't it?
Yeah.
But I,
we've got to actually ask,
like,
what is the,
what is the true longterm effects,
you know,
of these algorithms that essentially reinforcing.
So there's a social component.
And then I think there's,
there's a component of this conversation,
which is really shaping the psychology,
you know,
and the mindset of,
of an entire generation,
which is this mindset of having all of what you currently think reinforced consistently.
And I think that's the true danger.
Yes.
There's,
there's challenges with how young people are affected by exclusion,
you know,
online bullying,
that that's an important conversation,
but I almost think that raising a generation that are going to find it increasingly difficult to be present with a difference of opinion.
That to me is,
is a very dangerous kind of path that,
that algorithms and the way social media works is,
is reinforcing.
It basically knows what you like,
and it will only feed you what it thinks you like.
And so that's not an accurate depiction of reality.
You know,
growing up,
surely you remember having to listen to people you didn't agree with needing to have those conversations.
It's a,
it's an important part of development.
I think the world at large is actually struggling with this a lot.
You know,
the,
the willingness to actually listen to people you don't agree with and the push towards convenience,
you know,
is,
and the echo chambers that that creates,
I think,
is costing us way more than what it's,
what it's saving us.
Yeah,
it's a,
it's another big discussion.
We've got four podcasts to do with Nicole because all of them,
and I agree,
it feels as though they're out of debate.
And having a friend that you have a totally different view on a,
on a matter with used to be the great thing you did together,
catching up,
and then you learn from each other and you're now,
we hate that person.
We want to cancel that person.
Totally.
We,
you know,
had a federal election recently and people put up their billboards and,
and support and then you're going to,
you know,
graffiti on them,
like you don't have this opportunity now to sort of meet somewhere in the middle.
What's,
it's,
uh,
how can we evolve as a species?
If that's,
um,
if the push is always towards having a right opinion and trying to force everyone to,
to think the same,
I think that's,
it's,
uh,
one of,
one of the most primitive ways actually of,
of,
of operating,
you know,
and I'm going to,
um,
I promise you,
I'm getting there to you.
I love this conversation.
We've got a community that you're building,
which is incredible.
And some tech that I want to talk to you about in a moment as well,
which is an incredible,
um,
creative,
you know,
part of the puzzle,
I think that's missing that,
uh,
I know you're in town,
um,
you know,
working on at the moment here in Melbourne.
I did just want to ask you a question.
We lived through,
uh,
in Melbourne,
the city,
um,
I think the longest lockdown in the world.
So that's a stat that's,
that's,
that's there.
And at the end of that,
Nicole,
there was some alarming numbers of eating,
eating disorders in teenage girl explosion.
I think in the last 12 weeks of lockdown,
the numbers,
and I,
you know,
I won't get this quite right,
but it was a six or 700 a week being diagnosed.
And I saw lots of people in my community,
particularly young girls that were healthy before that,
that weren't to,
to,
to young people listening to this or to parents who've had that on the back of,
um,
of what they've been through you having found your path through,
what would you,
what would you say to them?
I've,
my heart,
you know,
is,
is obviously so connected to this,
to this challenge.
And the first thing I'd say is I just,
I,
I really acknowledge and feel every family that's going through that.
And,
um,
it can feel impossible at times,
but just don't,
don't lose connection to seeing that that loved one is healthy and well,
that's the first thing I would say.
The second thing I suppose on a more societal level is we really need to start
asking the question,
why,
um,
why?
Because these things are symptoms,
you know,
these things are symptoms of something that's going wrong culturally,
societally.
Like it's really no wonder you look at the DNA of an eating disorder.
Characteristically,
it's because,
uh,
someone's feeling out of control.
And when you,
when you look around at the world,
it's no wonder we have a generation of girls and boys that are probably feeling
so uncertain about what's ahead,
you know,
or what to expect.
And that's a,
a manifestation of,
of that.
Um,
we got to address that.
Otherwise we're just constantly putting out spot fires,
you know,
where we're trying to just apply band-aids to something so much deeper.
Uh,
and how bad is it going to get?
You know,
like,
uh,
I was reading these,
statistics recently around youth mental health in Australia during,
during COVID and the effects of the lockdowns.
And it was eating disorders.
It was suicide attempts.
It was calls to kids helpline,
you know,
and I think we've got,
we've also got to evaluate the,
the broader impact of,
um,
increased drug abuse and alcohol abuse in,
in the family dynamics because people were out of work and no,
it's,
it's such a myriad of challenges.
Domestic violence increased.
Um,
at what point do we start to critically evaluate the effect of these,
of these decisions in a balanced way?
And I don't think enough people have been brave enough to have that
conversation at all.
And in fact,
that conversation is in a,
in a convenient conversation.
So no one wants to have it because,
you know,
it doesn't suit the narrative that those decisions were there to keep us safe.
And you know what?
I'm sure some of them were,
you know,
but as a consequence,
these things happen and they're not being spoken about out loud.
They happen in our community.
And if it,
you're lucky enough that it wasn't your family,
it was probably luck in some ways,
you know,
eight or nine suicides a day,
Lou that's,
that's,
and it's,
I think that was pre COVID.
So that's the number one killer,
22 to 54 year olds.
In Australia,
when you think about more than anything else,
it's been get to the point to take their own life.
The people that attempt to do that,
the numbers are catastrophic as well.
Your solutions,
maybe too big a word,
but your contribution to this love is the solution.
It is just for everyone listening.
There you go.
Exactly.
Love out loud.
And again,
I'm going to use your words because I,
I couldn't go anywhere near doing the job that you do.
Love out loud is a cutting edge,
global movement that's shifting humanity's paradigm of fear and painting
a possibility with a vision to facilitate the world's largest love based
movement in human history.
Love is an actionable skill set that can be taught,
applied and cultivated in each moment.
No exceptions.
It's time.
We stopped seeing love as a romanticized cliche and begin to harness its
power to transform,
heal and create.
It's a,
it's,
it's a incredible vision.
Tell me about it.
Thank you.
Yeah.
I mean,
having the background that we just spoke through,
it really wasn't this utopian.
It sounds like a very utopian vision and I suppose it is in essence,
but it really was through deep observation and evaluating this,
um,
the,
the condition we've found ourselves in societally and listening to enough
people,
hundreds of thousands of people over,
over the years.
This is the answer.
It really,
really is because we can have sophisticated systems,
you know,
as mentioned,
we can change policy.
We can have all of the funding shifts,
you know,
uh,
we can have more billions of dollars invested into,
into these challenges.
But fundamentally,
if,
uh,
if we have a world that's void of love and compassion,
this won't heal.
And so we need to see these things as,
as a skill,
just like we learn to feed ourselves and,
you know,
we learn to read and write.
And this is a,
this is a skill just like any of those things.
And anyone that has people in their life that they love,
you would know that it's not always easy,
easy to love the people you love.
You don't always like the people you love.
Um,
but if you really love them and there's a commitment there to work through
difficulty,
you're going to find a way to meet them,
you know,
in,
in the middle.
And this is a very important skill that,
uh,
that I fear we're at risk of,
of losing for a myriad of different reasons.
It takes an extension of yourself.
I think it takes a level of self security to actually love,
you know,
because it's vulnerable.
Um,
and I don't think this,
this should be dismissed at all in,
in the global context of what we really need to start looking at,
because we can discuss these other major,
you know,
global challenges,
um,
in different areas,
whether that's governmental or environmental or,
but really if you were to strip even,
even all of that back,
um,
if someone's really in a,
in a true state of,
uh,
awakening,
you know,
and,
and love these cease to be significant,
challenges.
Um,
and yet if you try and address those challenges with fear,
if you try and wrong people or punish people again,
you know,
because it's void of love,
we don't respond to it.
And one of the things that I've seen doing this work now for,
for many years is a lot of us,
I think have been conditioned to have this core belief that humans are innately selfish.
And if we were left to our own devices,
we would destroy ourselves.
And I've experienced the opposite.
Truly when,
when I've seen people held,
um,
beyond restriction and given full safety and love,
people become more of themselves.
They come out of themselves more that the best parts of themselves,
you know,
come online and it's in that place that they have more energy to,
to be a selfless and to be generous and to,
to do the right thing.
But if they're being held constantly in a frame of contempt or fear,
or judgment,
there's no space in that,
you know,
to,
to become more and to become better.
And I love your thoughts about treating it as an actionable skill or something that needs to be,
uh,
practiced.
And,
uh,
I can align with that.
I,
if you don't mind,
I share my own version of,
of this.
And I,
um,
a father of four,
Nicole,
and I think that the emotion around your own kids is always perhaps the,
you know,
the,
the point that the guest,
you know,
I remember we had,
a health issue with one of our kids and I was at home and I was,
uh,
you know,
not known as a great crier,
Nicole,
not a badge of honor,
but my wife always says boarding school took a fair bit of the emotion out of,
uh,
out of you.
I grew up in a,
in a beautiful,
incredible relationship.
My dad,
my mom turned 70,
couldn't have had a more brilliant upbringing.
So beautiful parents.
But,
um,
and I just remember thinking,
God,
my commitment to my own kids,
but I don't use the word love.
It wasn't something that had been part of my,
now I never feel unloved,
by anyone.
In fact,
quite the opposite.
I,
I felt like I had a really loving upbringing,
but I made this sort of commitment to myself.
I'm going to use that word because I don't.
And so,
how long ago was that?
Uh,
this would be 14 years ago,
13 or 14 years ago.
So you've been on the journey.
I have.
And it just became this thing.
I just kept saying to myself and the three boys,
I love you,
mate.
You know,
my daughter,
Sienna,
I say,
you know,
my beautiful daughter,
I love you.
You know,
the most,
you know,
uh,
and they sort of roll their hearts cause I,
you know,
say it so often.
They'll look back on it.
So often at the time,
but this is how funny it got in the car.
Cause I can remember I was practicing,
you know,
I was practicing saying,
and even to bet,
you know,
my wife and an old mate rang and I've been saying,
yeah,
I love you,
mate.
mate,
to the boys.
And so we had this conversation at the end of it.
I said,
unbeknownst to me,
I love you.
I didn't know that I'd said it.
Hang up.
I get this call back three minutes later,
it rings back and he says,
mate,
I just want to say I really love you too,
mate.
And I was like,
this is what changes the world.
I was like,
that was a really weird experience.
You know,
that was not the language that we would use,
but,
uh,
it's,
it's powerful.
Our youngest,
uh,
little Maxie's 12 cause he's been born.
He just expresses that so freely.
And to the point where it's almost,
you know,
on the way to school,
you get six hugs and six,
I love you,
dad.
It's like,
Maxie,
you know,
can you say it too often?
Maybe Nicole,
I don't know,
but it was a practice,
you know,
sort of forcibly try,
but there's your result right there.
Your youngest,
your youngest is the,
you're probably right.
Yeah.
You know,
you're practicing probably on the first ones.
You're working your way out of it and might,
you know,
fake it to your mate,
not your fight,
the love for your kids,
but being the discomfort.
That's right.
The discomfort.
Yeah.
There is a,
an uncomfortable people with my year and probably people have any really,
isn't it?
It's always vulnerable.
Yeah.
And you can practice it.
And is that part of the community you're saying is we got to teach people again that this is,
you know,
yeah,
it's like,
uh,
that,
that's a really nice way of simplifying,
you know,
the,
the core message.
Um,
I think like the way that I've learned to familiarize myself with love is it's,
it's actually visceral.
You know,
I,
I think about it now is in my body and then,
you know,
that's a whole other conversation and how many people don't actually have a connection to what they feel.
And that's seriously problematic for a lot of reasons.
But when you're in a,
when you're choosing love,
you feel expansive.
You feel,
yeah,
there's a discomfort,
but you feel there's a,
there's a way for you to actually become expanded.
There's a,
there's a person.
And that's,
that's the ultimately the feeling.
If you can bring that feeling into more of your choices,
it's not just a better parent or,
you know,
brother or sister,
you're a better boss.
You're a better coworker.
You're a better stranger on the street.
You're a better customer to barista.
Like just being in that expansive state,
moving out of a state of defense,
moving out of a state of attack,
which is fear,
you know,
that contracted state,
the need to judge others really often for no reason,
just because you don't feel,
you know,
good or safe,
moving away from that way of being which,
you know,
when you look at our world,
that way of being has infiltrated so much of our systems,
how our,
how our world's actually been built.
It's control regulation,
order punishment.
If you do the wrong thing,
there's a whole nother way to live,
you know,
and it doesn't,
it doesn't equal chaos.
Actually,
like love is,
is very good at holding boundaries and being fair and being,
you know,
righteous when it needs to be.
It's not,
I think people have this concept that love is kind of airy fairy.
It's pie in the sky.
Like when,
when it comes down to it,
it's never going to work,
but actually think about the love you have for your children.
You would do anything to make sure that they were safe,
you know,
and that's the,
that is the power of love.
It's actually very strong and it can be soft when it,
when it needs to be,
can also be really firm when it needs to be.
I think we have culturally so many misconceptions around what love is,
and that dilutes people's connection to its,
to its power.
Yeah.
Beautifully said.
Um,
I hate to take this to where I'm about to now,
but my mind is,
is we're in a week and,
you know,
hopefully this conversation will be timeless,
but we had another horrific mass shooting in America.
An 18 year old lunatic goes into a classroom and murders 18,
you know,
less than 10 year olds in the most horrific way.
And I think it is juxtap,
supposing what you're talking about.
You're talking the,
what happens when you,
you spread love,
but what do you think when you,
when you see it in the crazy and,
and then what happens on the back of it,
it becomes,
you know,
the NRA come and,
and,
and hold rallies for more guns.
And it's just more anger and more divide.
And surely,
surely everyone could unite around school kids getting murdered with assault
rifles.
And it's the craziest thing in the world and most horrific.
I mean,
when you're building a community based on,
on love,
what do you think when you say that?
I mean,
the first thing that I,
that I always feel present to is how have we found ourselves at a,
at a point where it doesn't really seem to matter how tragic or yeah,
just,
unfair the circumstance is the response can still lack so much humanity and,
and sensitivity is just what my question is.
What will it take,
you know,
for people to actually just,
step away from force and actually just to acknowledge and,
and truly be present with,
with that circumstance,
because if you're truly present with that circumstance and you connect to just how tragic that is,
I think that is the transformation that we need to go through as a,
as a humanity,
not to get,
you know,
straight away,
at least on our high horses,
but to actually face.
That situation to feel that situation.
Otherwise we risk just always being in this place where we're not humanizing these,
these experiences.
We're seeing it as a,
I don't know,
just like another statistic.
You see it in mental health all the time too.
It's just another statistic and no,
it's not,
it's,
it's stories,
you know,
that there's 18 families.
That's a community.
That would extend to thousands,
if not tens of thousands of people that would have been directly impacted and affected by that tragedy.
We need to learn to actually open our hearts to that because this is what will,
I believe,
or what I've seen through my work,
create real change,
not seeing it as an opportunity,
you know,
to,
to have our opinion heard or it happens too much,
I think.
And yeah,
I think there's,
there's a lot of complaints,
a lot of complexity as to why.
I think people are,
I think deep down,
probably afraid to feel,
you know,
the realities of that.
There are realities in our world that are really hard to feel,
but we won't evolve beyond these things.
We won't evolve beyond violence,
you know,
war,
corruption,
until this happens.
Yeah,
well said.
It's,
yeah,
it's just a extraordinary thing to even get your head around,
isn't it?
When you stop and pause and,
and you're right.
It's sort of,
it can be,
you can dissociate from it,
you know,
until it's someone connected to you or until it's your family or until it's your daughter with a mental health issue or your kid in a school that's practicing drills so they don't,
get shot by a mass shooter.
It's,
it's crazy.
I love,
love out loud.
I love the word flow.
The word flows when you're around you,
Nicole.
And I think what you explained to me when we spoke a few weeks ago,
using tech,
to actually measure this,
it's,
it's a brilliant creative thing that you're undertaking.
Can you explain to us what you're,
what you're trying to do using technology for love?
Yeah.
So,
I mean,
definitely people,
I think had,
some people had question marks when they,
they heard that I and the company wanted to move into,
into tech because it can seem,
I think the stereotype is that it's so,
so opposite to,
to work of humanity.
But I definitely got to a place where I recognize,
you know,
this message,
this way of being is,
it has infinite scale,
but we need a,
a pathway of distribution that can facilitate that infinite scale.
And so naturally tech comes into the,
comes into the equation.
Our vision is that we have 4%,
which is in physics,
they say critical mass.
When you have 4% of a population,
the rest of the population shift.
So it's sort of hundreds monkey theory style,
collective consciousness research,
which is amazing.
Say 300 to 300,
350 million people.
If we had that many people engaged and truly living this way,
we will change the world and it will shift the paradigm of how we,
how we operate.
The biggest pain point in our previous model,
purely just focusing on community building and events was scale.
And so the question became,
how do we,
how do we take the essence of what we're really trying to awaken in people
and put that into a technology that people can replicate and have whenever
they need it in real time,
which was another pain point.
We had,
you know,
we can't hold people in a retreat 24 seven,
all day,
every day,
365 days a year.
And that,
that challenge became a challenge that I was obsessed by,
you know,
what if we could give people that power to test the alignment that they have to,
to the decisions that they're making to actually measure integrity.
One thing that my work had historically taught me,
which I'm so grateful for,
is concepts like love and truth and integrity can be physiologically measured.
When you are telling the truth,
there's a physical response.
You know,
there's a somatic response that we can measure when you're in deceit.
There's a physical response that we can measure.
And so this is taking things that have historically been very elusive and,
and making them tangible.
And so our tech is basically seeking to measure those things.
So imagine,
as a user,
you can type in a statement.
So maybe the statement is I'm in perfect health.
And then to actually be able to get a score that will help you understand how in alignment to that statement,
are you,
because from a conscious mind perspective,
the conscious mind is only 10% of our experience.
The other 90% is our nervous system,
somatic response and our subconscious mind.
And so a lot of the time,
what the resistance,
that people experience,
you know,
my passion is obviously the connection to love and fear or,
acceptance and judgment,
but it could be anything,
you know,
like I'm trying to lose weight and I'm going to get up every morning at 6am and go for a run.
Your snows alarm goes off.
So your alarm goes off and you press snows.
And then you wonder like,
why can't I,
you know,
do the thing that I want to do to get the result I want to get.
And it's not only because you know,
you're lazy or you know,
whatever you tell yourself.
Actually,
there's,
there's a conflict in your system.
There's something that your conscious mind is telling you you want,
but in us on a subconscious level,
there could be a series of beliefs.
Like I'm not worthy of feeling great,
for example,
or I don't know.
It could be anything.
The subconscious is is a bit of a labyrinth of what you study it.
And so it's always been very,
I think difficult for human beings to harness the true power of their own consciousness to have a system that's working.
In alignment with itself to get this the conscious subconscious and the body all on the same page.
That's a space where you don't experience resistance where things actually become easier.
And so our tech is is basically giving people the ability to facilitate that and to to inspire choice,
you know in in a in a greater way.
I think a lot of people would have noticed in my work is they feel life's happening to them.
They don't feel like they're in the driver's seat.
Of their their life and their destiny.
And I I know that if people have a tool that helped them actually successfully achieve,
you know,
the outcomes that they want in their life and they can identify what's blocking them and they can move into a state of flow and alignment with that very quickly.
People are going to understand I'm really powerful and we need a civilization that understands,
you know,
you're not you're not disempowered as disempowered as you think you are.
You're powerful and you can make change.
And so,
that's that's the the mission of the tech is to just be that I guess bridge or training wheels to give people the an insight into their true power.
Yeah,
it's amazing isn't it?
The idea,
you know,
we're all holding these smart devices in our hands and I think anyone who's felt,
the love for a partner or for a child or you can tangibly feel that,
you know,
you're floating,
and to be able to make good decisions based on knowing that feeling because I think your point is a good one when you've lost that feeling.
Yeah,
you've got to relearn that feeling again.
And if you can make decisions in your life based from being close to that feeling,
I think it's a brilliant extraordinary initiative that you're undertaking and I look forward to seeing it.
Yeah,
Nicole so much to talk to you about and I could go on for so many different areas,
but we've been asking range of different lessons.
This is one of our great passions and the way we're doing it.
A leader Nicole is connecting with just like you did with the,
the Mental Health Commission to have voices that have got a very different and diverse background.
And so we're sort of seeing dimensions of leadership that we think are common traits of great leadership.
Your leadership story to me is as powerful as I've heard from 16 years of age to what you are currently doing.
So please expand as much as you like on any of these answers or as little as you like,
but we think all leaders are really got a sense of self-leadership and your journey is full of self-leadership.
What do you think when I talk to you about self-leadership?
What does it mean?
Yeah,
self-leadership.
I mean,
yeah,
you're so right that I feel like there's so many ways that you can answer that question.
The first thing that arises for me,
I guess that I've had to learn is true.
Integrity is what you choose when no one's watching,
you know,
like what will you choose to still live?
You know what?
What your message is even when you know externally,
there's no reason to and the deeper.
I've gone into that process and that practice and really devoted myself to what I believe I'm here to do.
These other these other things that I think are important in the subject of self-leadership,
like like discipline like,
you know,
effective decision-making and values alignment.
I think all of that starts to sort itself out when you really committed devoted to that message
and it's not it's not always easy.
I fail all the time,
you know,
I fail to be loving.
I failed to be honest when I when I felt really scared at times,
but the mark I think of that responsibility is are you willing to write those wrongs?
Are you willing to have the humility to come back onto the path?
And the more I've done that,
you know,
the the greater I feel I've been trusted with bigger and bigger responsibilities,
I suppose because I'm proving,
you know,
my character in those moments.
No doubt about that.
What an incredible answer.
I love that thought,
isn't it?
It's when no one's looking at you living those same values as a as a sense of self-leadership is incredible.
We see leaders are really conscious of how they positively impact others in their environment
and really focus on that.
You're creating a movement to change global consciousness.
That's a fair,
you know thought about positively impacting others.
So is that really where the essence is for you?
You consciously feel like you're four percent of the population.
Get these concepts.
You can really,
you know,
shift the world in a in a pretty powerful way.
Yeah,
I believe that like that's that's so real inside of me.
And it I think definitely makes me on probably,
you know from the outside sometimes delusional because it's it's already done,
you know inside of me.
Yeah,
I think the biggest reminder actually is is to really just love every step and not not always see it.
As I think it as a visionary,
you know,
maybe you can relate or someone listening can relate.
Sometimes you see things as you know,
the puzzle pieces required to get to your vision and I've had to really actively practice not seeing things as that,
you know,
and being in my experience and enjoying where I'm at now and not living,
you know in the in the future of where I want things to be that remains,
you know,
a very difficult challenge daily.
Yeah,
incredible thought that you've got.
And you know,
the next dimension of leadership.
We talk about Nicole is leaders.
You're thinking about how they go about creating and sharing your their vision.
And you know,
you've done that through a love out loud through your book and through the community.
You're building it.
How have you gone about sharing that vision?
Speaking is like by far.
I think my joy like when I when I can be with people and I can just like this share what's on my heart.
That's when I feel most in flow.
When I talk about my vision.
Um,
yeah,
I mean,
I think as a leader,
you've got to be cross-disciplinary as well.
You've got it.
You've got to share it across the board.
You've got to consistently be there for your team and remind them what the vision is and,
you know,
write it effectively and I also make music,
that's another outlet.
Yeah,
but I definitely think is as a leader know your sweet spot because the impact I can make speaking to an audience.
I know is,
is,
far greater than,
you know,
other maybe modes of communicating that vision.
And so I'm always striving to spend more time in that sweet spot where I can where I feel I can affect the biggest transformation.
And we know you read the research,
which you do a lot Nicole,
and you know,
when you know in your organization or any organization or any community that when you create a space with people generally connected and feel like you care about them or love to use your terminology,
that not only makes them more productive and happier and more connected,
but it goes straight back to their home life and to their family.
And the research will just say that that improves the next generations.
And so when you're in a position where you can impact people regularly,
it's a massive opportunity and a responsibility and the opposite goes to doesn't when people feel detached from what they do day to day,
it has an incredibly negative effect.
So I love the way answer that we see.
Curiosity as a common word that leaders are using and through curiosity,
that's how they approach their their learning and development.
Does that resonate with you?
Yeah, to me,
that's like acceptance of a judgment,
you know,
when you're when you're away from judgment,
I definitely I'm so curious like I've actually had to learn that my curiosity is maybe a bit atypical because I'll become so interested in in things and it's very innocent,
you know,
and people I think who haven't learned how to,
to approach life.
Curiously can find it intense because we don't have a,
you know,
I think a population of people generally that have that curiosity,
but it's so important like a child is so curious and that's that's the sweet spot.
That's when you're learning.
That's when you're absorbing the most insight and information.
So what do you mean when people find it intense your curiosity?
What's an example of of that?
I think people if they're not used to it,
maybe think that it's,
um,
like there's something behind it,
you know,
like why are you so interested or but I really do take interest,
if I'm spending time with people,
it doesn't matter,
you know,
who you are,
what walk of life you're from.
I'm genuinely fascinated.
I want to know.
I want to know your story and I actually think that's been one of the greatest assets because it's allowed me to learn so much.
Curiosity really has been that the bridge there to learn when you're not curious.
You're not inquiring,
you know,
you're not reflecting and not,
you're not really present.
Yeah,
I think that it's so important as a leader and anyone everyone should practice more curiosity.
I think well,
I can say that from experience even just the communication we've had in setting up today and and having the great pleasure to talk to you a couple times.
You can feel that in you.
You can generally feel that you're listening and and you're interested in everything and it's it is rare.
That's it's it's you're right.
There's a presence about that.
That is pretty special.
That clearly is a huge part of you.
We see leaders are very conscious of communicating with clarity.
You need to go and check out Nicole's Ted talk and and that's why I use your language today because it's incredibly clear.
Is that something that you know,
you've developed in terms of the way you communicate not actively?
No,
I really it was never something I tried to to have honestly,
I probably would say that it's because I spent so many years listening.
Before I started talking and that's there's something in that,
you know,
I think a lot of the people I look up to have said similar things learn to listen more than you you speak.
And if you do that,
there's there's a natural clarity,
you know that you didn't you're not trying to prove anything,
you know,
like I think that's a big big part of having people receive you as clear when you're clear in your energy,
you know when you're speaking because you genuinely have something to say,
you genuinely feel like you you can add value to a conversation.
It then it's it's less convoluted than if you're you know,
trying or forcing or having something to prove and I don't I don't actually think that that clarity is about level of articulation
or having the right words,
you know,
the perfect words.
I think it's a it's an energy that everyone you know,
so if you because I've been asked that question before and I feel sometimes,
when I've been asked that people have been afraid to step into leadership
or lead a conversation because they don't feel like they're articulate enough
or intelligent enough or clear enough,
but just know that when you are really connected to what you're saying,
you know,
and you really believe in what you're saying people will hear you.
Yeah,
and you mentioned it twice here the capacity to listen and you know going on tour to listen to people
and and it's a lost skill really isn't it?
Totally.
We spend most of our time,
so much,
waiting for the last word to finish so we can get our next word in if we're not interrupting someone in the first place
and you can see organizations now,
smart ones are actually teaching their people going back to listen and understand.
I think that's part of being heard isn't it?
If you work in a space where that is a skill,
it's you know,
I'm not surprised to hear that's been a really important thing for you
and you can you can feel it and being your presence again.
Thank you.
Collaboration is something we see,
these range of great leaders are really focused on these days.
Collaboration is super important.
How do you go about collaboration?
Collaboration,
so hard to do effectively isn't it?
It is definitely a buzzword.
What could I contribute to that conversation?
I would say listening.
Why do you say it's so hard to do effectively is it?
I mean I've worked with a lot of communities right and a part of my job has been to help people collaborate and humans,
each have a perspective,
you know,
bringing those perspectives into some kind of unity and Harmony.
There's always going to be a challenge in that,
you know,
I experienced it in my team too.
I think collaboration is so powerful when you can get it right,
you know,
of course because the alternative is I guess more of an orthocratic style of being and operating as a company or a community,
which is one person's mind versus many people's.
Minds I've learned to do it effectively intentionality is really important.
So having specific times where you where you discuss ideas and then specific times with where you've delegated,
you know,
and there's actually things that need to be executed.
Otherwise collaborative leadership models.
I guess what I've noticed is the risk is decisions become really hard.
So having clarity,
you know,
so that decisions can be made and things can actually be moved forward.
And people I think as a as a leader,
maybe that wants to be collaborative in your approach.
You got to remember that the people you're leading also need directiveness,
you know,
sometimes and assertiveness and then there's a balance there that I can't claim to have mastered that,
but I'm very aware that that's something I would like to to master through my leadership journey.
Yeah,
it's it's it's again a great insight into you're right,
isn't it?
At some point,
you know,
if you're running an organization that's got the vision that you've got,
you've got to make the calls at some point in time,
but that sense that the people who are working with you have a voice and feel like they're being heard.
That's that feels like the skill to me.
Yeah,
where the best idea can come from anywhere.
and if you're not open to hearing that then people don't feel as though and I,
you know,
we've all worked in places.
I've been around places where it feels like there's only three people that have got all the ideas and everyone else misses out.
So I think,
yeah,
that's pretty limiting.
I've been asking these two questions Nicole to everyone and I'm fascinated with this with you.
Who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Definitely my principal.
That would be yeah,
that would be one.
Um,
who would I say?
I mean on a personal level,
he's he definitely there's no other leader that's impacted me as much.
Yeah,
pretty hard to go past that,
isn't it?
Yeah,
it's a very defining for me.
you still teaching?
No.
Yeah.
Yeah,
retired or is he on a farm?
Really?
Yeah,
living life.
Yeah.
One of the things we really want to do through this format actually is celebrate great educators and you know,
the we think it's under sold a lot.
Um,
my,
uh,
my great friend Matt Waterwood.
So we started a leader leadership is a great educator and don't feel like we in Australia quite do that well enough and other parts of the world.
Um,
there's a lot more respect for,
yeah,
people who change people's lives like your principal did.
It's it's it's undersold.
Sometimes in this part of the world,
teachers are expected to be so much,
you know?
Yeah,
I think that that's a big conversation to um,
huh?
And I think so much needs to change and I do think it will change.
I think we were going to most likely see a huge transformation of a lot of our systems and I hope education is is one of them because what worked,
you know,
200 years ago training kids,
uh,
um,
go into different sort of batches of this factory style education.
It's just not going to work for how the world is.
And so teachers are naturally not going to be inspired.
I think working in an environment that actually isn't contextually relevant.
Yeah,
it's disruption for sure.
Does that if you could collaborate in the in the spirit of collaboration going with anyone in the world on anything,
Nicole,
clearly,
you've got great passion.
Is there is there someone that,
that jumps out at you that you would like to collaborate with?
That's a huge,
that's a huge question.
Um,
and depending on,
you know,
the the space you've got,
um,
you know,
I think some of Elon's ideas,
um,
in,
you know,
technological advancement and what it's going to take to evolve the human race.
I think he is such a genius and I feel that the message of love out loud and our tech,
um,
which is called in truth.
I feel like if some of that thinking was to merge with with some of his thinking,
there'd be this amazing kind of hybrid that came out of needing,
you know,
to merge human consciousness with artificial intelligence.
I don't think that that has to be the way I don't think we need to lose what's fundamentally true about the human spirit to to evolve.
So I'd love to start,
you know,
working in that space more and this is my next big challenge,
as a leader is to be young female tech founder wanting to take on really like some of the most powerful people in the world.
And I've got a book coming out in a couple of months,
um,
titled legacy disorder and it's written for some of these characters in the world that I just feel maybe need to rethink what legacy means and to really start asking deeper questions about how their ideas of legacy,
uh,
influencing the direction of our evolution.
Yeah,
I can't wait to read that.
I mean,
Elon comes up as semi regularly.
Really?
You know,
I think,
uh,
you know,
there's not,
he's on the leading edge.
That's why.
Yeah.
And he's transformed things that other people thought was way too hard to go.
I mean,
you know,
all the car manufacturers had the electric car available to them and everyone sort of laughed at him with Tesla and launching,
uh,
SpaceX and taking on NASA and,
you know,
there's clearly some genius there,
isn't there?
Yeah.
Huge.
It's,
um,
and so committed,
you know,
you can,
you can see in everything.
One of his interviews,
he's given,
he has given so much to his,
his vision and his mission.
Yeah.
Your nice partner,
uh,
for,
for the love out loud world and,
uh,
and what you're doing in the tech space.
Um,
you know,
I feel like when you have the great pleasure to spend some time with you,
we all need more love.
We all need more connection and yeah,
who doesn't want to be part of a community that's,
that's spreading that message.
So I really appreciate you,
you know,
catching up today,
spreading that,
incredible message that you've got.
And,
uh,
please check out all of Nicole's work.
Go to,
um,
Nicole Gibson's website,
nicolegibson.com.au,
I think.
And,
um,
dot com.
Uh,
Nicole's Ted talk as well is,
is as you would imagine having listened to her today,
really worth,
uh,
worth your time.
Thanks again.
It's been,
uh,
been awesome spending time with you.
Thank you so much,
Luke.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me,
Luke Darcy,
produced by Matt Dwyer with audio production by Darcy Thompson.
Start your leadership journey.
I encourage you to go to a leader collective.com.
Take our empowering leaders,
indicate a tool and understand the impact you have on your environment.
Join us at a leader to learn,
lead and collaborate.
Listener.