Hello and welcome to a very special episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
We are constantly inspired in the work we do at Alita by the great people in our community,
many of whom have appeared on this podcast and the common threads that appear when you
speak to people who've had successful lives.
We are really passionate about growing this Alita community.
We bring together groups of five to six people from diverse backgrounds to come together
to learn and to connect and to share.
We'd love to collaborate with you if you're interested in joining our Alita Connect community
have a look at our website head to alitacollective.com book a discovery call today love to chat to
you and one of those common threads is the idea that great sleep is really important
for a successful life.
Couldn't believe in recording this sleep special that if you're lucky enough to live to 90
years of age 30 of those years will be asleep so understanding sleep, sleep routines and
sleep health might be the most important thing you listen to this year.
Way back many thousands of years ago in my studies sleep being one of the three
pillars of health and well-being a lot has been uncovered about the role of sleep in not only
optimizing brain health but health in all aspects of the body it's just as important as daily
exercise there is nothing more necessary to a human than sleep that's it sleep is the most
underutilized natural performance enhancer that we have we're going to hear from dr elise face
a child's phd who works with elite athletes
including the melbourne storm the oracle green edge cycling team secure to football club and
also business leaders through her work at monash university as the founder of peak sleep to elite
with a focus on optimizing sleep and body clocks for better health mindset and performance it was
great to have elise join us dr troy flanagan phd has an aerospace engineering background and also
is the head of high performance for the nba's milwaukee bucks had the privilege of interviewing
troy on the podcast earlier this year.
and it was excellent to get him back as part of this special to enlighten us on the sleep regime
of some of the best athletes and astronauts in the world dr shanta raja atnam professor of sleep
and circadian medicine is one of the world's globally renowned sleep experts and researchers
whose focus on designing treatment approaches for sleep disorders caused by biological clock
disruption is a world-leading voice on this topic and you're going to enjoy the conversation
with shanta dr daniel.
dr troy flanagan phd has an aerospace engineering background and also is the founder of peak sleep
better known as dr golly pediatrician and former chief resident medical officer of the royal
children's hospital dr golly has worked with thousands of babies and parents over more than
a decade of practice guiding whole families towards a full night's sleep and he is a very
important voice on this topic mark bunn joins us as well former afl player and now ayurvedic health
leader who has written one of the world's leading novels on ancient wisdom for modern health
he gives us a great insight into combining those worlds of eastern health and modern health
and western science bringing forward the understanding lessons learned from thousands
of years of humankind trying to get the best possible night's sleep and you think of evolution
it's not as though people need less sleep a thousand years on it's something that we all
require and mark's a great voice on this topic i always thought traditionally that i was a really
good sleeper but i have to say these conversations have fundamentally changed the way i think about
sleep and now talking to my kids about how they can approach sleep in an even better way than
i have in the past i'm hoping that by listening you'll also gain a lot of insight on how you can
optimize your own sleep in order to improve your life in a profound way this sleep special is
proudly brought to you by temper mattresses adjustable bases and pillows the difference
is temper huge thanks to jason nicholas and the team from temper for their ongoing support
and it is a mattress like no other we began by discussing the importance of sleep and what it
means to us humans and shanta got straight to the point
we devote about a third of our lives to sleep if we live to the age of 90 we will spend about 30
years asleep throughout the course of evolution this function has been preserved it must play a
critical function to preserving our health otherwise it would have become redundant
but it hasn't and so that suggested to me that we have a long way to go
in our discovery about the importance of sleep health over the past three decades or so
a lot has been uncovered about the role of sleep in not only optimizing brain health
but health in all aspects of of the body and so we know now that sleep plays a critical role
in maintaining our cognitive functions our mental health but also
every system in the body is affected by sleep disturbance and sleep plays therefore
an important role in preserving you know from everything from cardiovascular health
to metabolic health and so on mark barn as someone that has studied health in depth
how important a role does sleep play oh absolutely fundamental does way back many
thousands of years ago in my studies um ayurvedic medicine they actually had texts that
went into great detail about sleep being one of the three pillars of health and well-being obviously
things like diet and is very important but you know we can all appreciate in our modern world
we have a very strong focus on activity and performance and high level performance and
when we take a step back and consider sleep from that level we um can look at mother nature and
mother nature has these two core pillars and that is rest and activity you know we need winter to
balance summer we need night to balance day and night to balance day and night to balance day and
so from many traditional cultures and long-living cultures they have just as much respect and
honor and acknowledgement of the importance of deep rest as they do for dynamic sort of
outward activity so um really important someone once described sleep deprivation to me as
being almost worse than smoking or alcoholism that the continual lack of sleep is incredibly
detrimental to your health is that something you subscribe to absolutely yeah and even if you're
on a diet and um research over the last decade or two they now have an understanding what's known as
functional holes in the brain so we think of the brain we think of a sort of solid mass but in terms
of neuron neuronal connections and how the brain functions you can actually have or develop holes
in that you know long-term cigarette smoking drug abuse and sleep deprivation is right up there with
that so we still have a brain the neurons are still there but they just don't communicate with
each other so um
yeah no i'd definitely uh back that up and dr golly let me turn to you people have always said
in the past you've just got to grind your way through everyone goes through it and you've
effectively got to suck it up but we know sleep deprivation is incredibly bad for your health and
your overall well-being is that how you view it there is nothing more necessary to a human
than sleep that's it you know i do a lot of talks at um football clubs uh basketball clubs netball
we i've given talks about sleep deprivation and sleep deprivation and i've given talks about sleep
and sleep deprivation and sleep deprivation at orica and l'oreal and you know publicist these
companies are understanding more and more and sporting clubs when we're talking about high
performance are understanding more and more that sleep is paramount you know for a corporate to
turn around and say we are going to bring you in to talk to our new families and expectant families
about the importance of sleep you know they're onto something so if you can improve your sleep
it's a no-brainer it improves performance
statistics that come out of the research into how much businesses lose because of their staff
having poor sleep in terms of sick days, in terms of mistakes being made, and poor retention as
well. It's absolutely undeniable that sleep is paramount. Anyone who's a parent, anyone who's
gone through poor sleep for whatever reason will tell you that their performance suffers.
There's no question. It's equivocal, you know, the effect of sleep deprivation with being drunk
or having really, really uncontrolled ADHD. Performance absolutely drops, cognition drops,
recall drops, everything drops when we're not sleeping well, not to mention the fact that
we're more likely to get sick and then have days when we're not working. So the answer to your
question is a definitive yes. At least it used to be considered somewhat a badge of honor to say
that I don't need sleep or I can get away with little or no sleep. People used to boast about
it, didn't they, in a way? It was, as you said, like a badge of honor. I think the tide has turned
a little bit on that one. And I think in elite sport, that is a real area where, you know,
it's good for individual athletes for their own performance and health, but athletes, elite
athletes can act as role models for the community and for other people around them. And if we look
at, you know, how LeBron James talks about his sleep and how he prioritizes
it and how much time he spends on it, think how many people that gets disseminated to and then
that think more about their sleep. So I think there's a lot that us scientists and researchers
and consultants can do, but it's important as well to acknowledge that the reach that some
elite athletes have can have a real impact, similar with, you know, mental health in sports
and how Simone Biles has, you know, openly and a lot of other athletes have openly spoken about,
about their troubles and how that is helping to kind of normalize and allow other people to share
their story as well. I don't know if you know this one, how many hours does LeBron James sleep a night?
I know he invests enormous amounts of money in his own, you know, routines and habits. So let
me have a guess. I don't know, but nine hours? More.
10? More.
He's sleeping more than 10 hours a night. 11 hours, LeBron?
Kind of.
Sleeps about 10 hours a night. Obviously, I'm not studying him. I'm not going to try and claim that
this is, this is just what I've heard, but around 10 hours and then has a nap during the day as
well. So total around 12 hours, maybe over a 24 hour period.
So he's going to spend 45 years asleep, LeBron, the way he's tracking as a professional athlete.
Well, we look at the success he's had.
At his 40 years of age and still playing at the top of his game. And when you're working with
elite athletes to improve their sleep.
What are the common things that you're often sharing with them to improve sleep?
I feel like the sleep field, well, for one, sleep in sport has become huge over the last
five to 10 years. You know, everyone has seen this really big increase in the
interest in sleep and a push towards integrating sleep into high performance and considering it.
What I think is still missing is there's been quite a generalized approach. And we see this
with sleep health.
In the general population, but also in, in elite sport is that there's very kind of generic
advice and recommendations that are given, you know, sure sleep a certain amount of time and
at these times. And I really think that what most, I think all sleep, sleep researchers would,
would agree. There's no one size fits all. As we move towards more of individualized medicine,
sleep needs to go with that as well. And it really,
really depends on the individual in terms of what their sleep presentations are or their
difficulties with sleep and then how you manage it.
Elise, how big a benefit can you get as a high performing athlete or in life in general by
achieving really good sleep? How, how, how big a factor is it in your mind?
I think this is said quite a lot and I do use it quite a bit, but I think sleep is
the most underutilized natural performance enhancer that we have.
The funny thing is, I think sleep is the most underutilized natural performance enhancer that we have.
It's free. You know, it's not on the anti-doping. It's not illicit substance. It's not,
you know, any of those, those things it's free and we're not using it enough, I think. And
especially in elite sport, most athletes, you know, are going to be in that range of
pretty good, healthy sleep. Probably, you know, you will, you'll have a small percentage that
have a clinical sleep issue that needs to be managed, diagnosed and managed.
But a lot of athletes are in that kind of good sleep range. What we want to look at is
how we can optimize that. Like, can we increase that a little bit to then try and improve recovery
and performance? And if we think of it just in terms of proportion of time that you spend sleeping
versus other activities, you know, 33% of our time we should spend sleeping. So to put that
in proportion across...
If you live until you're 90, 30 years of those, you'll be sleeping or expected to be asleep.
And if we look at that in proportion to other activities, like time you actually spend
exercising, training, competing as an athlete, that's probably a couple of percent. If we look
at the number of minutes that you're in the gym or out on the ground or on the court compared to
the time that you're spending sleeping, that is a huge difference. So I think we haven't tapped
into that enough.
And again, in your role as the head of high performance at the Milwaukee Bucks in the NBA,
your bedtime with the team can be any time between 1am and 5am, depending on the schedule
and the roster and the travel. You've got elite athletes that mightn't get to bed until 3, 4,
5am after a game. So what do you do the next day with elite athletes so that they can function
on that sort of schedule?
The short answer is they have what we call an NBA nap. And it really depends on
what they need. Do they need physical recovery? Well, that determines what type of nap they have.
Or if they need cognitive or brain recovery, that determines what type of nap they need.
And so the shorter naps, under 30 minutes, are more about the physical side. The 30 to 60 is
more of your deep sleep type of nap. And that's where you start to get a little bit more physical.
But then...
And the 90 minute, like a full sleep cycle, that's where you get the whole physical and mental and
brain function recovery. So it really depends on what you're looking for as to what type of nap
that you have the next day. But even a 15 minute nap, where you just go into the first phase of
sleep cycle, that we call it the light or the non-REM light phase, that can just totally change
your energy levels. And so...
So there are different types of naps that you can take. And it's okay to do that. But one of the
things I find as a busy executive is sometimes it's the middle of the day. And there's no other
place to put it. And we're on the road with the team. And you just kind of feel guilty that you're
taking a 15 minute nap when you perhaps should be working. And so you really have to have a plan
is kind of the number one thing. And you have to periodize.
What is my schedule coming up? And where am I going to catch up knowing that I'm going to be in
deficit on day two and day three away? And then you can start to schedule it and feel okay about it.
And do you think, Troy, we need to actually have a better conversation around sleep? If you're an
exec that's had to work overnight or be at a late function or work on a schedule like you,
you're seriously going to be more effective with that 15 minute power nap the next day.
Do we need people to understand actually what you're doing
or productive by having that nap than trying to push through? Is that a conversation we need to
have? Yeah, I think it's just as important as daily exercise and periodizing when you're in
sleep deficit or sleep debt. It's okay to structure that during a lunch break or when we go into the
morning. As soon as we get back and have lunch, we send all the players to bed and they try and
get through a full.
Sleep cycle. And then they come back, get back on court, play a game that night. And they're
highly structured in the way that they do that and super effective at doing it. And when they
don't get it, they actually get quite concerned. And so I think that we empower people, particularly
an NBA team, to go and get rest because we need you at your best tonight at 9 p.m.
So Troy, to break that down a little bit, I think we've all been in that scenario where you've lost
some sleep. You might jump into bed during the night. You might get up in the morning and you're
like, okay, I'm going to sleep for the rest of the day. Is sleep maybe what feels like a bit too
long? And you wake up and you never can get back on the right foot for the rest of the day. Are you
really detailed in, right, this is a 60-minute sleep or a 90-minute sleep? And do you put alarms
around making sure that you don't sleep too long? Yeah. So I think I have to just quickly describe
the different types of sleep. So just to go into it really simply, there's light, moderate, and
deep sleep, right? So light is between moderate and deep sleep. And then there's light, moderate,
you know, one to five minutes or up to 15 minutes of sleep. That's that quick nap that you might
take as your plane's taking off. You just fall asleep for 15 minutes and wake up when you take
off, right? The moderate is kind of like the 10 to 25 minutes. So that's the nap that most people
will take. And then the deep sleep is between, you know, 20 to 40 minutes. And that's where you
can actually wake up and feel a little groggy. And so that's the nap that we usually try and
avoid. And then there's a full sleep cycle, which is going from light to moderate to deep,
and then REM sleep, which is like the super deep, where you get all your brain recovery.
That's a 90-minute nap. And so most of the recommendations around napping is under 30
minutes or a full sleep cycle, which is 90 minutes. And so if you want physical recovery,
it's under 30 minutes. If you want the full physical and cognitive recovery, it's 90 minutes.
And Dr. Golley, for me,
the other type of elite athlete that we should discuss definitely here is the parent and
especially parents with new babies. It is the most important thing. You know,
we talk about sleep. It's almost become a bit of a throwaway term. You know, oh, yeah,
you got to get good sleep. You got to get good exercise. You got to eat well. Everyone means
to do it, but people don't give it the amount of attention that it really deserves. And I think
individuals as well as organizations are coming to the party. They're realizing more and more
just how important it is. And I think that's a really important thing. And I think that's a really
important thing. And I think that's a really important thing. And when you throw the curveball
of a new mother into the conversation, what people and especially mothers don't appreciate enough
is that when you arrive at the stage of welcoming a newborn, you know, for us dads, it's a hell of
a lot easier. We just get a newborn placed into our arms. But what women have to understand
is that they are coming to that point in their life on the back of nine months of pregnancy,
most commonly, which is extremely,
exhausting and depleting physically and emotionally. And in many cases, you're talking
about a conception journey as well for those who go through IVF and other forms of, you know,
if they're having fertility issues. So there is a huge amount of sleep debt and exhaustion that
people come to a newborn with. And then they're dealing with all of these issues, potentially of
breastfeeding problems, lack of sleep with an unsettled baby, so many different pieces of the
puzzle. And so, yes, sleep is important, but it's also a lot of work. And so, yes, sleep is
important, but it is a hundred times more important for a new parent, especially a new
mother. I'm going back 21 years, taking home our first born. It was two days after the birth.
You're literally, the system seems to want to get you out of the hospital as quickly as possible,
which I understand at one level. But I remember just that terror of like, what do we do? Like,
no understanding, no education, exhausted, you know, Beck, my beautiful wife, and then,
yes, sleep immediately. First 12 weeks, I remember thinking, this is crazy. And there
isn't that village of support around. Is that something that you see a lot of and
why it's such a tough path these days in the West for young mums in particular?
Yeah, you're a hundred percent right. It's not something I see a lot of. It's all that I see.
You know, we do, we live in a completely different world to where we lived a hundred years ago in
terms of the lack of village and the lack of support. We live in silos. We're all independent.
We've all got our own kitchen. We've all got our own bathroom, our own bedroom,
whereas it used to be much more communal. And so we're doing this by ourselves. But it's even
harder now because there are so many more dual income families. So we've got mums working.
We've got mums with careers who are trying to juggle two things. So many times people are
often starting a new business. They're at the depths of their mortgage stress. It all seems
to happen at once. And it's almost like a perfect storm. We are seeing an enormous amount of pressure
on young families. And the thing that I see,
most commonly, is that the couple who have prepared for weeks, potentially months on a
birth plan, they know all of the options in terms of pain relief, in terms of vaginal birth, Caesar,
all of the things, they've got their plan, the way they want things to work, their contingencies.
And this is wonderful, but they haven't made a baby plan. As you said, you get home two days
later, three days later, and it's like, okay, what do I do now? I haven't thought about this
part. I haven't planned that. And that is where,
my work begins. That's where I've devoted all of my attention into those first few weeks
so that you can really thrive and not just survive that period.
So Elise, let me ask you, what should we be doing at night? And how do we go about making
sure that we get better sleep, particularly in regard to light exposure?
Yeah. And light exposure is the biggest factor that influences our body clocks.
And that's why getting light exposure,
a bright light in the mornings, resets our body clock every day. And that's what's really good
for us. The other end of the day in the evening, limiting that light exposure, essentially what's
happening is we have evolved to be diurnal, which means day active. We're awake when it's light,
and we're normally asleep when it's dark. And what we did when we invented artificial light
is essentially the sun goes down, we used to go to sleep then, and then we turn on the
light switch and we extend our days into the night. And what you're doing there is telling
your body to be awake. You're essentially signaling to the body to still be awake. It's
still daytime, it's active time. And that's why switching the light switch off and then going to
bed, your body is saying, I'm still awake. I've been told, I've got the signals that it's daytime.
And so it's quite hard to then fall asleep. So I think preparing your body for sleep in that few
hours, that's a big part of it. And I think that's a big part of it. And I think that's a big part of
hours before you want to go to sleep and limiting your light exposure as much as you can. There's
some really simple things, you know, do you need to have the overhead lights on? You know, do you
need all this glaring light in your house in those evening hours? If not, can you just use a side
light? On your phones, most phones now have a function to be able to modify the color of the
screen. So on an iPhone, it's called night mode or night shift. And you can actually modify,
you can turn it on so that at a certain time in the evening, the color of your screen changes to
more of an orange color and that our eyes are the least sensitive to that kind of light. And so that
can help as well. Shanda, it seems to me that we're surrounded by more and more bright light on
our phones and we're stimulated by our screens more than ever before in human history. Are you seeing
from the research you're doing that that bright light exposure is having a negative effect on
people's sleep patterns? Look, I'm glad you asked about light. Light is a critical time cue for the
circadian system and the circadian process that I referred to earlier. Now, light, we have evolved
as organisms to be responding to a natural light-dark cycle before the advent of electricity.
And artificial light, we had a light-dark cycle where we had exposure to light from pretty much
from sunrise to sunset and then darkness thereafter. Now, we're able to control our own
light and dark exposure and electronic devices have compounded this because now we hold a device
very close to our eyes that is emitting light.
And so we're now regulating our own light-dark cycle in a very different way to two or three
hundred years ago, what we have been exposed to. We know that the light that is emitted by those
devices, the circadian system is responsive to. And how it responds is that it boosts your
alertness, your arousal level. It reduces your sleepiness and therefore it disrupts your sleep.
It delays your sleep. And so we're now regulating our own light-dark cycle in a very different way to
two or three hundred years ago, what we have been exposed to. We know that the light that is emitted by those devices, the circadian system is responsive to. And how it responds is that it boosts your sleep.
It delays the timing of your sleep and it disrupts your sleep.
Now we know that there are big inter-individual differences in the sensitivity to light. Some
people are much, much more sensitive to the effects of light than others. So we need to
keep that in mind. There is a spectrum of sensitivity. However, in general, as a part
of that sleep hygiene I referred to, I would certainly recommend the avoidance of light-emitting devices,
electronic devices, close to bedtime and particularly in the hour or so before bedtime.
And Troy, you're the head of high performance at the Milwaukee Bucks, but also have a background
in aerospace engineering, a PhD on that subject. Tell us a bit more about what you're seeing
in the sleep world from that perspective.
Yeah, it's one of the areas where we've done a lot of investigation. So, and if you look
in the space industry, astronauts who are out of space, it's kind of like the same all
day, right?
So how does an astronaut go to sleep out there? And one of the things they use on the International
Space Station in the past has been blue light filters. That's where all that technology
kind of came from. If you get a big blast of blue light right before you're trying to
go to sleep, your brain actually thinking it's the middle of the day. And so if you
want to delay your bedtime or your natural bedtime, blast it with that blue light. And
so a lot of people these days are filtering out blue light in their bedrooms and the bedside
tables and lamps.
And so they use blue light, and they use blue light on their screens in order to allow that
natural process that happens about one to two hours before they go to sleep where it
gets dark, one of the glands in the body starts to produce a hormone called melatonin, and
that starts to reduce your body temperature, which also reduces blood pressure, reduces
cognitive function, and makes you sleepy so that you go to sleep at that right time. And
but blue light is actually something that really interferes with that. And it's something
that I always encourage people to start to play with. On the flip side, you know, when
it's cold and wet in Milwaukee, and you want players to come into the training facility
like this, you actually want a lot of blue light. So we actually put a lot of blue light
into our training facility behind us in order to wake the players up and make them feel
alert in the middle of winter.
So if you're wanting to go to sleep, you jump on your phone for half an hour as you're sitting
in bed and you fire off those last six emails that you couldn't wait to not get to. And then
you wonder why it's very hard then to switch off and go to sleep. Is that a problem you think a lot
of people haven't worked out yet? Yeah, I think so. It's definitely,
you can get like little filters that go onto your screen. You can get glasses. There are
technologies that do that. And Mark, tell us about the
understanding of light and the A of 80 perspective of understanding that's relevance to sleep.
I'll come at it from two angles. One is the more traditional understanding. And that is that
my training, Ayurvedic medicine, which is a six, 7,000 year old sort of tradition of knowledge.
It talks about the body going through six, four hour cycles each day when our body's designed to
do different functions. And I like the analogy of a surfer. If you've got a wave on the ocean,
if as a surfer, you can time it. So you catch the wave at its peak. The wave does all the work
for you as a surfer.
It's fun. It's enjoyable. You're cutting back, hanging 10. It's like, well, it's fantastic.
If you're getting the wave at the wrong time, like I do when I usually go surfing,
the wave's crashing down on top of your head. And so bad timing equates to stress,
mouthful of water, never going to surf again, not good. And so if we can understand these six,
four hour cycles and understand particularly that at 10 PM till 2 AM is when the body goes
into its natural rejuvenation cycle to deep sleep.
To do everything we want a good night's sleep to do. But back ended on that is that the early
morning cycle, when the sun's just coming up in the sky is when we're designed to wake. And if we
get that natural light, that particularly sunlight, but even natural light when it's winter, that is
what regulates and stimulates the appropriate neurochemistry to send us to sleep at night.
From a modern perspective, the circadian rhythm is similar, but just understanding the different
sort of hormonal patterns.
And the cortisols that cycle during the day. And a fascinating study that's just come out in the
last 18 months ago, Stanford University, many of your listeners will know Andrew Huberman,
great podcaster. So we need between two and 10 minutes of that natural light early hours of the
day to stimulate the appropriate cortisol response, to increase our focus and attention during the
day. It starts the melatonin response that we need. And it also syncs our circadian rhythm so
that by the end of the day, we're going to be able to sleep at night.
By the end of the day, we actually can go into our natural sleep cycle. So circadian rhythm is just
like that wave on the ocean. There's an inbuilt timer, if you like. And if we can sync our body
clock with that timer, then not only sleep, but proper digestion of food, proper elimination of
wastes, the whole thing just comes into sync and balance.
Well, for mine, we have just started to scratch the surface of sleep health, better sleep,
and what it means to live.
A successful, healthy, and happy life. Brilliant news is that the elite panel we've assembled will
be back next week. Make sure you join us for part two of our sleep special series. We're going to
come back with the same panel of experts and some expert advice, practical tips on how you can
improve your sleep health and go on to live a healthier and happier life. As always, if you've
enjoyed this episode or any of our episodes previously, please, we would love you to help us
and leave a rating or a review and grow the community.
With your support, a big thank you to the team at Tempur for their incredible support
over a long period of time. This sleep special is proudly brought to you by Tempur mattresses,
adjustable bases and pillows. The difference is Tempur. They are world leaders themselves
in sleep health. Investing in a mattress like Tempur will change your life.