There is nothing more necessary to a human than sleep.
That's it.
If we live to the age of 90, we will spend about 30 years asleep.
Way back many thousands of years ago in my studies,
sleep being one of the three pillars of health and well-being.
Sleep is the most underutilized natural performance enhancer that we have.
It's just as important as daily exercise.
Hello and welcome to another special episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Over the past year, we've featured conversations
with a diverse range of incredibly talented creatives,
academics, athletes, philanthropists, and business leaders.
And as always, some common threads have appeared.
One of which is the idea that great sleep is maybe more important
than we ever realized for a successful life.
Many of these guests we've had on the podcast are members of our leader community
and we are constantly inspired by the work we do working alongside these people
in our city.
This is our signature Elita Connect program,
where we bring together groups of five to six people from diverse backgrounds
to come together to learn, to connect, and to share.
And we would love to collaborate with you.
So if you're interested in joining our leader community,
have a look at our website, head to elitacollective.com,
book a discovery call today.
We would love to chat to you.
There is a brilliant study that I've had a look at recently
of Division One Stanford basketball players
who by simply adding two hours sleep a night
saw tangible improvements in sleep.
Free throw, three point percentage, reaction time, VO2 max,
and general mood among other markers.
Same study has been repeated in tennis players and swimmers
with similar results.
And it's now been shown that even just 45 minutes extra sleep per night
for just three days can have a significant impact
on an athlete's performance, including a 20% reduction in cortisol
and losses of body fat.
If it can have that big an effect on elite athletes,
imagine what it can do for you.
And your life.
And with amazing data like that out there
and that common clue that sleep leads to success,
I wanted to dive in more.
So we assembled a panel of world-leading experts
who have genuinely helped me understand
that probably the greatest opportunity to improve your life
is through improving your sleep.
In our first sleep episode last week,
The Sharpest Minds in Sleep highlighted
how important sleep is to your personal wellbeing,
your career, and what a huge predictor of success
it is in any given field.
In this episode,
we focus on the practical advice we all need
to help us create the best sleep habits
that we possibly can.
We'll cover light exposure,
body and bed temperature,
hygiene practices,
schedules and consistency,
stress prevention,
and some advice for parents and expecting parents,
perhaps the most sleep-deprived people of all.
Our experts over these two specials are
Dr. Elise Facer-Childs, PhD,
who works with elite athletes,
including from the Melbourne Storm, the NRL,
the Orica GreenEdge cycling team,
and also business leaders through her focus
on optimising sleep for better health,
mindset and performance.
Dr. Troy Flanagan, PhD,
is an aerospace engineering graduate
and the high-performance manager at the NBA,
Milwaukee Bucks,
and has had great success in all of his work.
Dr. Shanta Rajaratnam,
Professor of Sleep and Circadian Medicine,
who is a globally renowned sleep expert and researcher
whose work focuses on designing treatment approaches
for sleep disorders,
caused by biological clock disruption,
a global expert in every sense.
Dr. Daniel Golszewski,
better known as Dr. Golley,
a paediatrician who has worked with thousands of babies
and parents over more than a decade of practice.
And Mark Bunn, former AFL player
and now Ayurvedic health leader
who combines thousands of years of Eastern wisdom
with modern Western science
to help us all get the best night's sleep possible.
Big thanks to Jason Nicholas
and his team at Tempered Bedding.
This sleep special is proudly brought to you
by Tempered mattresses,
adjustable bases and pillows.
The difference is temper.
The conversations I had with this panel
have fundamentally changed the way I think about sleep.
And I'm hoping that by listening in,
you'll also gain a lot of insight
into how you can optimize your own sleep
in order to live the best life you can.
The final part of our panel's discussion
is here for you today.
And I began by asking Dr. Elise Faceford Childs,
who specialize in taking people from good sleep
to high-performing sleep,
what are some of the things we can all do to optimize sleep?
To optimize our sleep in a more powerful way.
I mean, a lot of people,
like looking at basic sleep habits and behaviors
kind of at the simple level.
And this is things that people are probably all aware of,
you know, managing,
making sure that you're getting enough sleep opportunity.
So the time that you're actually in bed,
for some people, you know,
I'll say I went to bed at 10 and I got up at six.
So I slept eight hours, but that's not quite true.
That's how long you were in bed.
So you're already in bed.
You're already shortening the time
that you're probably spending asleep.
So making sure that you have enough sleep opportunity,
and that should be based on how much sleep your body needs.
And that varies between individuals.
So that's, what's really important.
And where the generalization I think comes from
is some people like, oh, I need to sleep eight hours.
And then when they don't, that can start,
you know, having an impact.
Some people and athletes,
we see tend to need a bit more sleep.
Some people need a bit more sleep than the general population,
maybe just because of the mental and physical load
that they're going through.
Other things in terms of your maintaining kind of good habits
and behaviors around your sleep environment,
the temperature, things like light exposure
is a huge factor that I think is not talked about enough yet.
So managing your light exposure in the morning
compared to limiting it in the evening.
Lots of little things like that,
but it can be significant in isolation.
If you add all of those together,
you can often see this improvement in sleep.
For the average person listening
that wants to have better sleep,
what are some key things they should look at
to achieve better sleep?
One of the things that's recently come out
in the research that is quite interesting
and getting a lot of attention at the moment
is your consistency in your sleep.
So that is going to bed and waking up at a similar time
and keeping regular with you,
with that day to day.
That's something that lots of people we chop and change
because of our social schedules, you know,
and at the weekend we have social activities that we go out
and then our sleep timings change
and then maybe we sleep in.
But sleep regularity or sleep consistency
has started emerging as a really important factor
that is linked to health and performance outcomes.
If that was just one thing that I would say is trying to keep,
a regular sleep schedule, maybe not to the minute,
you know, we're doing some research around
what's the optimal window that you can vary
with your sleep regularity,
but trying to keep as consistent as you can
and not chopping and changing between the days.
That would be, that would be my number one.
Dr. Troy Flanagan, we often say you spend a third
of your life asleep if you add it all up.
So I wanna ask you about how important the right bedding is
given you've worked extensively with Olympic athletes.
And this year we saw a number of athletes,
a number of Olympians in Paris,
literally turning up with their own beds
to make sure they could get the best night's sleep possible
and replicate their home set up.
So how important to you is having the right bedding?
I think it's really important for,
you know, firstly for comfort and also for hygiene.
It's one of the things that, you know,
sleep is also related to your immune system.
So making sure that you get the right amount of sleep,
but also you're sleeping in a hygienic environment.
It's the one thing that we have to continually remind
young athletes.
This is, you know, have a very strict routine
on changing over bed sheeting and things like that
so that they stay in a hygienic environment.
Another intervention that we're doing at the moment,
particularly to enhance deep sleep and REM sleep
is to cool the bedding.
And so there's some really smart beds these days
that I actually have this on my bed at home.
And what it will do, it will start to learn about your sleep
and it measures sleep as you go,
and it manipulates the temperature of your bed.
So we know that when you go into deep sleep,
your body temperature drops.
And so it starts to cool you and to get you into that deep sleep.
And it will manipulate and start to play with the up and down.
Oh, he's going to deeper sleep that work.
And the smart bed actually starts to enhance
the amount of deep sleep you get and REM sleep that you get.
And so there's so much technology coming out in this area.
The bedding and it's really exciting and quite interesting
to start to look at and see how your bed's getting smarter
and affecting you over time.
Exposure to sunlight during the day
is another one that is really important.
I think exercise in the morning or early afternoon
is really good.
I wouldn't exercise too close to bedtime
just because of the processes, the waking up processes
that happen with exercise.
But I think it's really important.
I think there's lots of interventions to stay up
with what the latest is.
But really try and think like a physiologist
in how we plan and periodize training.
You should be planning and periodizing your sleep.
So even things like caffeine, Troy,
understanding when the last time that you have that before sleep
are all those factors you said diet, exercise, sleep, sunlight.
It's the whole gamut.
Yeah, I think caffeine is definitely a stimulant.
If you habituate it, it's less of a stimulant.
But I think having strict rules around caffeine.
And caffeine does actually take 48 hours
to clear out of the body when you have a cup of coffee.
The half-life of caffeine is two days before it's completely zero.
And so don't think that, oh, I had one at 3 o'clock.
All the caffeine's gone.
It's still there.
So if you're getting into deficit,
maybe that's when you go off caffeine for a couple of days
until you catch up and then go back on it.
But golly, for parents, and in particular expecting parents out there,
can you give us a snapshot of what a healthy plan looks like
when you bring a newborn baby home
and you're wanting to get the best sleep possible?
What are some tips that you can give us?
For me, the number one thing is prevention.
So prevent stress.
And one example of that is know what is to be expected.
One of many examples is knowing what a newborn rash is,
knowing that all babies get these little red dots
all over their bodies in the first few days of life,
and it's completely harmless.
But if you've never heard of or read about
or seen a photo of a newborn rash,
you could automatically think that your child's got
some sort of bacterial infection, and then you panic,
and then you lose hours of sleep.
And you lose the ability to enjoy that period
because a three-day-old,
you should just be wanting to eat them.
They're just so gorgeous and adorable and angelic,
and you don't need to be spending your time and energy
worrying about things that are completely normal.
So that's the first thing is being prepared,
knowing what's normal,
and knowing when you need to call for help.
And I think also in terms of setting up for success,
it's all about trying to get into a good rhythm.
I don't talk about sleep routines under six weeks of age.
I talk about a good rhythm,
and that is something you can achieve
in the first few days and weeks of life,
which is discrete feeding time,
discrete sleeping time,
and then other, which is play, bath, changing, et cetera.
And I see a lot of moms, dads, and dads, and they say,
okay, now you've come up with a pretty good routine,
and they call it a day.
It's where you have to be prepared
to get there sooner rather than later.
That's the basic thing,
and I think that if there are any concerns
aboutuvoirts fighters or dads, or couples,
getting into problems where they are cluster feeding
their snack feeding,
and there's often a very simple reason
as to why that's happening,
and they're in a bit of a snack cycle,
it's not a difficult thing to break.
And, as I said, that's where I put all of my attention,
six weeks, five kilograms sleeping through the night. So if you can get through that period
with sleep deprivation and all the stress just for six weeks, you can then, you know, there's
a light at the end of the tunnel. There are lots of people I see who come to me in my rooms
four months, even four years later, and they've just said, well, I haven't slept since my child
was born. And that kind of thing, I just, I hate when people write off that period. It doesn't
need to be like that. You can sleep, you can expect to sleep. And there is always a reason,
and there's always something we can do to help that baby and then help the parents and all
members of the household. Mark Barn, you've written books and are a world-leading expert
on Ayurveda. It's a whole body system of medicine that began in India thousands of years ago.
What are some of the traditional methods of improving sleep quality that you bring forward
from Ayurveda? What are some of the traditional methods of improving sleep that we can learn
from this?
From an Ayurvedic perspective, we always ask the question, what's causing the lack of sleep? So
there's not one size fits all, but there's a number of really key and common sort of
considerations with most people today. One is the understanding that lack of sleep generally
is due to an overexcitation of the nervous system. And it's an accumulated effect of many things.
It can be, you know, caffeine, obviously, stress at work. And one of the big things that's coming
out in the last five, 10 years is a disconnection from our natural cycles or natural rhythm. So
when I speak about people getting better sleep, I actually try and rephrase it,
that we have to get back in tune with what's called circadian health. All the great traditions
of knowledge, the long-living cultures have understood that, you know, the cycle of the sun,
particularly, which emits a certain frequency of light through the eyes and stimulates the
pineal gland that then stimulates our neurotransmitters.
And the melatonins that we all hear about is absolutely fundamental to good sleep. So getting
in tune with a circadian rhythm, you know, waking up at the right times, getting early morning
sunlight. So it sort of sequences our neurotransmitters so that we can fall asleep
effectively at night. And then this sort of second sort of understanding of just reducing that
often excessive mental stimulation, what's sort of aggravating the nervous system. So when it's
time to sleep, the mind's not sort of racing at 100%.
Miles an hour and we toss and turn and can't get a good night.
So Bunny, if someone's listening to this, they are struggling with sleep. I know it's not one
size fits all, but could you give maybe two or three or four things that would make sense to
help someone achieve better sleep? Yeah. So basically start first minute
of the day. We can go through a daily clock if you like. So if they're not getting outside in
the early hours of the day, and that's within usually 30 to 60 minutes of sunrise, they
want to readjust their bedtime. And a lot of research now on good sleep is getting to bed
and waking up at roughly the same time a day, because that's what resets that circadian rhythm.
So getting outside, most of us today live in artificially lit homes. Many people go to
workplaces that are artificially lit, and then they come home at the end of the day, artificially lit
homes. So we're what's called mal-illuminated. We need that natural light, particularly sunlight,
if it's out. So 5, 10, 15,
minutes, early morning, outside, walk the dog, do some stretching, whatever it is, make some phone
calls, be productive, all good. But that's really going to set up the whole hormonal sequence for
the day. At the end of a workday, which is often when we get that overexcitation, we need to sort
of switch off from the day. One thing I'd really recommend is some form of earthing or grounding.
Again, many of your listeners will be familiar with this term, but we now know that connecting
to nature,
particularly directly, so taking the shoes and socks off at the end of the day and just
walking down the beach, if you're near a body of water or the ocean, even at home, just sitting
outside having your glass of red wine or your de-stressed beer at the end of the day, having
lunch in a park, anything we can do to connect to the earth itself. We know douses the inflammatory
fires that line our tissues, but it also profoundly earths the body. When we think of not being our
sleep, we often use terms like, I'm spacey, I feel airy, and I'm away with the fairies.
What's the exact operatives of space and air? It's earth or ground. So looking to that,
there's even indoor earthing products now that people can buy where they have bed sheets or
earthing pillowcases where you're basically earthed, even when you're indoors. And a lot
of people find them really helpful for insomnia. And then probably the last one would be around
6 p.m. is when the ancient understanding is that we transition from the day cycle to the night
cycle. And that's when the body's really trying to slow down in readiness to deep sleep. So
anything we can do to reduce the overstimulation of that time is really, really helpful. We've
all heard about blue light from our laptops and our iPhones. So where we can is trying to jump
on a desktop at night if we have to do some work.
Because it gives us a bit more distance. Screen protectors, blue light filtering glasses,
all those things, even looking into dimming the lights in people's homes, or even looking at what
they now call circadian lighting or smart lighting, where you can actually get different color hues
that come on in the evening to actually reduce that blue light exposure and promote good sleep.
And probably the final one is just using aromatherapy in the bedroom. I'm really
trying to be practical when I talk about sleep. People are so busy that I don't often have time
to do foot massages and meditate for an hour and all that sort of stuff. But getting a really good
quality diffuser, put it in the bedroom at seven o'clock at night, you go and put some really
relaxing, calming essential oils. And then once you're in the bedroom, you get seven or eight
hours of benefit of this powerful effects of aromatherapy, reducing that mental stimulation
and just relaxation.
And obviously in the lounge room as well at night, if the other people in your house are okay with
the smells you're putting out there, but that'd be a few key ones I think can really help.
And finally, Shanta, you're one of the world's leading experts and researchers in sleep. Over
many decades, you've been on research panels around the globe. For people listening, can you
share a few tips that are maybe universal to achieving better sleep? And what would you
suggest to people they can do right now to help them sleep better?
So Luke, I would refer to three...
We now refer to three dimensions of sleep health to maintain optimal health and performance.
The first is duration. That's what we were talking about first. Everyone's aware that
you need to get a good, adequate amount of sleep to be able to recover, to be able to,
for sleep to play those critical functions that they play. So the best way to know how
much sleep you need is the extent to which you sleep.
Okay.
The extent to which you're relying on stimulants and other things to keep you awake during
the day. The extent to which you're falling asleep involuntarily. The extent to which
you're relying on an alarm clock to wake up in the morning. How much do you oversleep
when you take away the alarm clock? All of those are indicators of, are you getting an
adequate amount of sleep? So the majority of the population would need somewhere between
seven and nine. And certainly the epidemiological evidence, the evidence at a population level,
suggests that less than six is associated with adverse effects on your health, your
mortality, risk of various medical conditions. It's usually the less than six and the shorter
sleep that is associated with the risk of those conditions.
So the first is duration. The second we were talking about is timing and regularity of
your sleep.
So what we're talking about here is trying to optimize the time that you go to sleep
so that it is as close as possible to your circadian drive for sleep, your circadian
timing, and also keeping it regular. We now know that the circadian clock is programmed
to be able to do something that is predictable, is synchronized to the external environment,
that you're in. And shifting it around every day gives you kind of like this permanent
state of jet lag. And so regularity and timing are a critical dimension as well.
The third one is quality of sleep. So if you can get the duration right, you can get the
regularity and timing right, can you get the quality, an optimal quality of sleep? And
there are several things that affect the quality of sleep.
The first is that many people have sleep disorders that they're unaware of. There
are over 90 types of sleep disorders, and many remain undiagnosed because there is an
inadequate awareness of them.
So the first is to look out for the symptoms of sleep disorders. The Sleep Health Foundation
has several fact sheets that help the public to understand what are the common symptoms
of sleep disorders.
So sleep disorders really compromise your quality of sleep.
The second thing is your own behavior and the environment you sleep in can also compromise
the quality of your sleep. If you have had meals too late in the day, caffeine late in
the day, alcohol disrupts the quality of your sleep, the temperature in which you're sleeping,
the bedroom environment, all of these factors, you know, collectively are referred to as
sleep hygiene.
Okay.
What can impact your quality of sleep?
So paying attention to all of these factors, some of them are internally driven, biologically
driven like sleep disorders.
Some of these are environmentally driven and behaviorally driven, but they all impact upon
your quality of sleep.
So my message to your listeners, focus on duration, focus on regularity and focus on
quality of sleep.
I really hope that you've enjoyed the two sleep episodes with our brilliant panel of
experts.
A big thank you to all of them.
And if you missed last week's episode, be sure to go back and check it out.
There's some incredible information there about the power of sleep that helps us understand
why making these changes in our lives can so dramatically impact us and the people around
us.
As always, if you've enjoyed this episode or any of the episodes previously, please
help us reach more listeners by leaving a rating and review or subscribe today.
And a big thank you again to the team at Tempur, the sleep special proudly brought to you by
Tempur mattresses, adjustable bases and pillows.
The difference is Tempur.
We'll see you next time.
Bye.