How do you start a new leadership journey when the way you've been taught is embedded
in everything you do?
And how does this affect the way you bond with your team or your colleagues?
G'day, it's Luke Darcy.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership both on and off the field has been a lifelong
passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective and have had the privilege
of working with thousands of leaders in education, sport, industry and the arts that have helped
shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
I sat down with Australian fast bowler and vice captain Pat Cummins to discuss the young
leaders he works with to improve their leadership, finding balance in your life when you're constantly
touring and how he thinks about career longevity.
Well, our guest today grew up in beautiful Mount Riverview at the base of the Blue Mountains
in New South Wales, an incredible part of the world.
He's 28 years of age.
He's the vice captain of the Australian cricket team in all formats and currently the ICC number
one ranked test bowler in the world.
It's an extraordinary achievement in the world of sport.
He joins us on the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Pat, thanks for your time today.
No worries.
G'day, Darcy.
How are you going?
I'm well, mate.
I've been looking forward to catching up with you and excited to chat to you about all things
leadership.
Can I start by asking, was leadership something that you always had aspirations to be?
No, never really aspirations to be captain.
I think I've always loved...
Sport and being part of a team, trying to achieve a common goal.
And I think now in my, I guess, professional career, I think it's my 11th or 12th season
playing for Australia.
So with that and with age, I think it comes a bit more responsibility.
So yeah, naturally assume a bit more of a role.
Well, maybe it's interesting.
I was actually looking up ahead of this chat around why hasn't there been a fast bowler's
captain of Australia?
I think there's this...
My statsman told me that Ray Linwell back in 1952...
1956 filled in for a short period of time.
But why can't fast bowlers be captain of the Australian cricket team?
I don't know.
I mean, we're always the smartest ones.
So I don't know.
That's certainly not a reason why.
It's just one of those things.
It's, I guess, you know, the reasons most commonly, I guess, said are, you know, batters
aren't injured as much.
They've got more time in the field.
A lot of them say they're, you know, they're smarter.
They think about the game more deeply than bowlers.
They're probably the most common.
I've played with a lot of batters who weren't very smart.
And I've played a lot of bowlers who weren't very smart or, you know, vice versa, really
smart guys.
And you don't play professional sport unless you know the game really, really well.
So, yeah, I don't think there's any reason why a fast bowler can't be.
I think it brings with it some more challenges, you know, probably physical when you're out
there on the field.
But, you know, lots of different opportunities as well as a fast bowler.
In my old sport, the world of AFL, Ruckman Coppert as well.
But we are the smartest bracket in our game as well.
So, no, the big men are much unfairly maligned.
I'm with you.
The smartest people are fast bowlers and big men from the world of footy.
Coach Justin Lay will be lucky enough to speak on this podcast as well.
And when he talks about leadership, it's all self-improvement and collaboration.
And his respect for your leadership is through the roof.
Can I ask you, what sort of influence has the coach had on you?
He's been great.
Yeah, I came into the role as vice captain since he's been coach.
And exactly as you said, self-improvement, you know, he's a big reader.
So, he's always got books he's suggesting and handing out, trying to find different ways
to do, you know, different things.
So, I've really enjoyed, well, you know, hearing his experience.
He's been a coach for quite a long time now.
Obviously, he played at the highest level, works, you know, with West Coast Eagles as
well, a few other different sports.
So, I've learned a lot from him.
And I think just being closer to someone in a high-pressure role who has quite a lot of
responsibility.
I just probably never fully appreciated, you know, that role until, yeah, you become
a senior player, I guess, and are a bit more involved.
The dynamics of cricket fascinate me, Pat.
You work in pretty small teams when you think about 11 take the field and travelling parties
comparatively are pretty small.
You spend a lot of time together, hotel rooms and on planes travelling around the globe.
It comes with it, I suppose, some interesting challenges.
How do you go about trying to...
How do you get the best out of teammates around you in what is a pretty unique environment?
Oh, it is.
And, you know, I've chatted to a few other, you know, guys from different sports and the
common thread that, yeah, we've had to adjust to in cricket is it's not just a tour.
It's really our life.
You know, we spend more time on the road than at home.
So, trying to find...
If you're doing things that aren't, I guess, sustainable, you know, if you're pushing someone
too hard, if you're asking too much for, you know, too many hours of them or anything,
you're going to be found out eventually.
So, yeah, trying to find that balance to what makes everyone tick, create an environment
where even on a cricket tour, we get totally away from cricket.
And a lot of the guys raise their children for the first, you know, five, six, seven
years of the children's lives in hotel rooms.
So, trying to strike that balance is probably the biggest challenge.
And the personality is not unique to cricket.
Like every environment, there's different types of characters.
But I suppose that gets magnified.
Or here in Australia, the other codes having to hub together and their families travel
together.
And, you know, some of the stories are positive, some of them not so positive, Pat, around
suddenly you're dealing with, you know, other people's families as well.
That's something you guys have to do.
What sort of mechanisms do you put in place?
Do you need time apart?
Do you just bond more?
Or are there groups of guys that...
Does it form more cliques in cricket?
Is there any explanation for that?
Oh, there's definitely cliques within, you know, any team.
But, I mean, we spend, you know...
The fast bowler...
Bowlers, we're tight, not only because we're the same age and from the same state, but
for most of the year, we're living basically together.
And every night, you're in the physio room together eating dinner.
So, there's different cliques that form.
But, yeah, I think everyone manages differently.
Some players love having their partners there all the time.
Others like, you know, partners and family coming in for a couple of weeks and then maybe
having a couple of weeks just to concentrate on cricket.
But I think the big thing is we're open to everything.
You've everyone...
Need something different, then we can try and cater to that to make sure, you know,
not only that they perform well, but they're happy.
And, Pat, we got connected in recent times through the passion for work we've been doing
with a business called Alita and one of my oldest friends, Matt Waterwitz.
And you've been part of a really interesting collaboration I was keen to talk to you about
if you're open to.
But, you know, you formed a group that reflect together and catch up.
And it's a really fascinating group for me.
Marcus Bondapeli is the...
25-year-old superstar AFL player, captain of the Bulldogs and one of the great players
in the game and a young captain, Andy Lee, who's one of the most successful entertainers.
And I know an old friend of yours, Hamish and Andy Fame, and just an extraordinary person
and leader in his own right.
And Rob Sitch is a slightly different generation, Rob.
But what he's achieved with the Working Dog team and some of the greatest entertainment
pieces ever produced have come out of Working Dog.
And Rob's just a fascinating guy.
Can you tell us about your...
Your interest in that and what that group's done for you?
I've loved it.
Yeah, we've caught up every fortnight for the last few months.
I didn't know Marcus or Rob beforehand.
You know, I know Andy, you know, quite well for quite a few years.
But I love hearing, you know, shared experiences with someone like Marcus, who's in the middle
of his career.
He's leading a, you know, a whole side and a club, which is quite different to, you know,
cricket in a lot of ways.
And of course, Rob and Andy, total different industries.
Going into it, I thought them as more, I guess, creative, laid back types.
And then you quickly realise there's a method behind, you know, the longevity and the success
and, yeah, so many different, I guess, problems or challenges that come up, you know, no matter
the industry, they're the same kind of problems and challenges and, yeah, speak to those two
experienced guys, especially how they've overcome them and how they see, you know, what they
see is important.
Things that get them rolled up, which they've learned over time, aren't that important.
I've just really enjoyed, yeah, a lot of shared experiences with those guys.
And Pat, we've sort of got this passion, Matt and I were the leader around, you know, connecting
groups of people because, you know, traditionally you do, you know, work in silos and someone
like you travelling the world, you've got an incredibly busy schedule and the idea that
you, you know, take time out and, you know, it might necessarily look like a direct fit
perhaps with another sporting captain.
Like the Bond, but, you know, I suppose if you found that there's things that you've
applied directly into your daily life, has there been examples where you're like, oh,
that's something that I can really take away and it helps me on a day-to-day basis?
Yeah, I think, I hope, I'm sure he won't mind me mentioning this, but Andy, when we
first said, okay, we're going to do this, I asked him and he's like, yeah, I'll come
on.
I think he was just trying to help me out really and he, yeah, Matt sent through, oh,
we're going to do eight classes or eight, sorry, lessons.
We're going to do eight lessons together and Andy said, oh, I'll see how I go after
the first two.
I'm pretty busy after that, which was kind of, he leaving the door open so he could exit
and then he, a couple of weeks ago, he's like, geez, I'm so sorry I said that.
I want more.
So, it's, yeah, there's been lots of things.
I guess, you know, different almost like hacks that people do to Rob or Andy or Mark as a
founder to get the best out of, I guess, co-workers.
Yeah.
Around managing.
Around managing time and expectations and, you know, one for me is how to, you know,
busy people create their own space and time to make sure they stay creative and engaged
and think of new ideas and so there's heaps of things I'm butchering in a bit but I've
got a notepad full of about a hundred of them that I, yeah, I go back to.
Yeah, and I understand that you're an incredible contributor and clearly there's a, you know,
private conversation.
And a lot of that is not for air but, you know, Matt has told me, you know, who's facilitating
it on behalf of a leader.
What a great contributor you are that you're an avid reader yourself.
Can I ask what sort of books are you into?
I understand you read a lot about leadership.
What sort of books can you share with us?
Basically anything really.
I chop and change, you know, depending on my mood.
I guess, to be honest, a lot of the time it's just what I'm doing at that stage.
So, for example, if I'm on tour.
And I'm all cricket, I'll try and normally get non-fiction in a total different subject
and I find getting away from cricket and, you know, learning something new, that kind
of energises me.
And then there's other times where I'm, I don't know, flat out, things are going on
and I'll read a novel or something where it's, you know, a bit of an escapism of something
totally different.
But anything, at the moment I'm reading a Bill Bryson book.
It's One Summer in 1927, I think it's called.
It's, yeah.
Quite a fun read about America in 1927.
But, yeah, leadership, you know, science, quite like that, you know, self-improvement,
psychology, all those types of books I find quite good.
I'm going to put it on you then, Pat.
If you could recommend one book and you want to share that with a whole group of people,
what's the one you're going to give to all your mates?
The one I've probably given away the most, it's a little bit different.
It's called Awareness by Anthony DeMello.
And he was a, I think he was a Jesuit priest or something.
But he was based in India and he, you know, puts a lot of, yeah, I guess, ownership of
yourself.
The awareness is around trying to know where your prejudices are and your things that affect
you that you might not perhaps think about.
And, yeah, I find reading that just gives me good clarity on, I guess, how I think and
things that, yeah, you get right up about never seem as bad as they are.
Awareness by Anthony DeMello.
Writing that down.
We'll put that in the notes.
But I hope you won't mind.
But Matt was telling me of a hack recently that I hope you don't mind us sharing around
you talking about decision-making in recent times and perhaps it leads to trusting your
gut instinct.
In your mind, it's that you either have that moment where someone asks you to do something
and it's, hell yes, I want to do it or hell no.
Is that something you use in your decision-making?
Yeah, it is.
You know, really lucky in the last few years, so many different opportunities come forward
and I'm a lot of them.
I'm pretty easily excited.
So, I can find myself saying yes to basically anything pretty quickly.
Before that, the trade-offs normally, you know, Becky or partners say, I haven't seen
you in a week or I'm, you know, doing something in the middle of a test match.
So, more as a way to control time.
Yeah, I heard this kind of, you know, someone talk about this tool where it's a, hell yes,
you know, I want to jump out of bed and do this.
If it's only a, yeah, I can do that, then, you know what, it's probably a no and think
about it down the track.
But, yeah, I've got a bit of a framework, I think, of things I think about.
Normally, it comes down to, yeah, is it a hell yes?
Is it going to be fun?
Is it going to be worth my time?
Because if it is, I'm all in.
Yeah, Pat, we're passionate about the self-reflection part of it and part of, I think, what you
did initially is take on a bit of self-reflection and talking to you before this, you went to
your coach, Justin Langer, and we're building an indicator tool so that people, you know,
are listening in.
And, you know, to me, you don't have to be.
You don't have to be the captain of the Australian career team or the vice captain or CEO of
an organisation to want to be a great leader.
You can impact people, you know, in your office without a title and you can start that journey.
And we're passionate about people taking on some reflection around those around us.
And you were saying before, maybe you had your time again, you'd survey a bit more deeply
around the team or even the captain of the team that you're in at the moment.
Is that something you're passionate about, actually, firstly, starting with some data
on what you're like as a leader?
For sure.
Yeah, I'm quite...
Yeah, data-driven in a lot of things I do.
You know, cricket, I love looking at stats and building my intuition and can't feel that
way.
I don't know, it's just the way I'm wired.
But objective feedback, like the 360-degree, you know, review or the, you know, the leadership
tool, it's so good to work out where do I think of myself?
And then that kind of starts the conversation.
I think if you do it in the reverse, you're kind of anchored to the point of most people
as a rule are pretty, you know, good people.
They're gentle and don't want to hurt you.
So, you're kind of anchored at a different point as opposed to you've got the hard data
there.
I really like that.
So, I find that really helpful.
I guess a lot of the space is not being captain.
I don't work as directly with, you know, management or some things around as opposed
to, you know, specifically, say, teammates or painting.
That was just a couple of the areas where I'd probably go and get further feedback from
others.
But the more you can do that and create a bit of a feedback system...
Yeah, we'll send out some links.
We encourage you to have a think about that.
If you're listening to Pat Cummings, you want to start your own self-reflective leadership
journey, the Leader Indicator Tool, send a link out how you can get involved in that.
And we're sort of seeing this shift, Pat.
I'm not sure you're a younger generation than me, but the old 20th century I talk about
a lot is hierarchy.
And, you know, I certainly worked into a professional sporting environment at the age of 17.
You didn't say a word.
You didn't have any chance you'd have access to the senior coach.
And you were terrified.
You were terrified, really, to put your hand up.
Whereas, you know, in sporting organizations, we're seeing now that, you know, young people
have got more of a voice and their voice is respected.
Are you seeing that?
Are you seeing that in your environments now that you really have to collaborate from day
one and it doesn't matter of your status or how high up the pecking order you are?
Absolutely.
Yeah.
It's, I'll be the same, Darcy.
I think when I started, I was 17 or 18 and I was looking around the change room and, you
know, it's probably half a dozen guys have played a hundred tests.
So, I didn't say boo, but earlier now you see a lot of young guys who are confident in
their own game to make the international side.
They've done well domestically.
And to be honest, I love seeing those new guys and learning of them because they've
got no inhibitions.
Now, that little bit of naivety is great.
I love seeing that because you can lose that by being in the system for, you know, 10 years.
So, you know, I almost have to protect against the, every now and then I think, you know,
this guy's played a hundred tests.
This guy's...
Played one.
He's definitely got an opinion and it's definitely worthwhile, but you probably give more weight
to the guy who's seen it and been around a lot longer, but it's great.
You get so many different ideas and I think that's changed even in the last kind of five
years.
You walked in as a 17-year-old and you went straight out of the Wanderers Stadium in South
Africa.
You took six wickets, Pat, in your first test.
That's a way to make an impact and get a voice.
Can you take us back to there?
Did you feel instantly that, hang on, there was a level of respect that maybe 17-year-olds,
17-year-olds aren't afforded after your first up effort?
Yeah, perhaps.
So, I think I was glad that I felt like I at least belonged and I guess probably more reasons
why I shouldn't have been picked than I was, but I was kind of backed in.
So, I was really glad to, I guess, repay that faith, but by no means.
I remember, well, as soon as I played that first test, I was injured and out of, you
know, action for about nine months and I just remember desperate to play a second test and
prove myself again because so many people were, you know, I guess saying, oh, how good
was that debut?
You know, you belong, whatever it is.
And I felt the opposite.
I was looking around at Ricky Ponting and Mitchell Johnson, these guys, and thought,
you know, I'm so far away from those guys and what they've achieved.
So, I didn't really believe the hype or try not to let myself believe the hype.
You had a six-year break between that and getting back in the test arena.
So, you had a bit of time, went through a huge amount of injuries, as we know.
What did you learn about yourself in that?
Quite a lot.
It was an age between, yeah, I guess, 18 years old and 23, which is, you know, a big stage
in anyone's life.
You know, I moved out of home.
You're kind of turning from a school student into an adult.
So, I think you have a lot of lessons and you learn a lot about yourself along the way.
But by the end of that stage, the one big thing I learned was, you know, patience and,
you know, you want everything now as a kid.
And unfortunately, that just isn't the best way or the most sustainable way.
So, you've just got a level of acceptance by the time you're a little bit older.
So, again, you get, you know, you meet a lot of good people along the way.
So, I think becoming, you know, a better judge of character of different people.
And, yeah, I think through that time, I got a bit more life experience.
As I said, I moved out of home.
I did a university degree.
I still got to travel the world and play some cricket all around the world.
So, you know, having a full-time job, all these things, yeah, I guess, culminated into,
you know, who I am now.
And do you feel like experiencing that, you know, the position you are now at 28 years
of age, is that potentially going through a pretty tough time, you know, being injured
for that amount of time?
Do you think that's going to give you more longevity or would you, you know, that's
maybe the wrong question.
Would you change it?
If you look back now, do you think it's actually stood you in good stead?
Yeah.
I mean, I guess you can lament the years lost where I wasn't playing and, you know,
look up now and I've played 30 on tests.
I wish that was 60 or 70, but it was a waste of time for sure.
Physically, I got a lot stronger.
Yeah, I grew up and I guess that's the other thing I learned was, yeah, there's not a huge
rush.
You know, a 12-year career is just fine.
It doesn't have to be a 14-year career.
So, a lot of the things that happened, I was glad when I look back at it.
When Australia is successful in cricket, the whole pulse of the nation, you know, feels
better about themselves and, you know, hearing JL talk in recent times about wanting to make
Australians proud and there was some controversy in South Africa coming back and trying to
reboot the team after Sampo Brigade issues.
Do you feel that, you know, that pressure, I suppose, as a leader in the Australian cricket
team that there's the whole country riding behind your success?
Yeah.
I think there's a real ownership that's felt by, you know, fans.
As a kid, I felt that.
I felt like that's our team.
We're taking on the world.
Yeah.
Live and die by the results sometimes.
You know, we kind of, it's a weird thing about, you know, Australian culture.
We want us to be the underdogs, but we also want us to be the best in the world at the
same time.
So you're not going to please everyone.
I think you've got to make sure you're really strong on what you stand for and how you want
to go about it.
But, I mean, the upside of it is huge.
You know, my favourite moment of my career so far was World Cup in 2015 where we won
the World Cup in Melbourne.
Yeah.
You could do no wrong.
I mean, every single person in Australia was right behind you.
So, yeah, it's great.
I love that about our culture and we're really lucky in cricket to have that.
You've grown up with the world of social media.
It's escaped me, maybe for good or bad.
I'm getting some pressure to get into it, this later stage of my life.
How would you describe that?
I see a lot of professional athletes that I know that see an amazing opportunity but
an amazing challenge at the same time.
And, you know, the public can get access to you.
And see you in ways that other sports people haven't had to put up with in the past.
How do you deal with that?
I think it's easy to lose control of.
And that's the most important thing going into, you know, social media and putting yourself
out there is you've just got to know what you're signing up for.
So, you know, if you're entering the public space, there's going to be good, there's going
to be bad.
And, you know, honestly, I think for a lot of people, if you're not going to cope well
with that, you know, it'll be upside down.
It's not going to be the upside or the downside.
Well, maybe it isn't a arena you should spend too much time in.
You know, for times I've felt on tour, I've just deleted Instagram or Twitter.
You know, I think Asher's last year was just a really busy time.
I just deleted it just because there's so much conversation and noise going on.
And as much as anything, it's a time-wasting tool, which I kind of feel like I need to
reset every now and then.
So every now and then I'll just delete it for a couple of weeks or a month.
And I always find I just use it slightly differently when I come back onto it.
But, I mean, it's great.
It's, you know, 20 years ago, 10 years ago, we couldn't speak to fans and, you know, kids
that, you know, so directly.
So with it brings so much opportunity, but no doubt you have to be careful.
So you literally, you delete it on your phone.
So it's not there and have a spell for a while.
That's a genuine thing that works for you to have a little just a break.
I suppose if your phone's pinging, you naturally go to it, don't you?
And that's not a bad way to handle it.
Yeah.
Or you're sitting in a hotel waiting.
You're waiting for the bus or you're sitting on the bus or whatever it is.
You find yourself 15 minutes has gone to scrolling something pointless.
So I just use it as a way to reset.
Yeah.
The amount of times you pull your phone out of your pocket and realise you don't have
the app, you go, oh, I would have just wasted 10 minutes, you know, traditionally.
Or, you know, people that seem so famous and so everywhere on Instagram, as soon as you
delete it, you go, oh, actually, they're not a part of my life.
And it's.
It's just funny.
You kind of, you know, each time I do it, I'm like, oh, actually, I haven't thought
about them for a month.
It's interesting.
Now, Pat, a lot of people listening will say, you know, it's the dream life.
You had your challenges, but 28 to travel the world and play at the level that you do.
I'm always interested to maybe ask the question around a mistake or a poor decision you can
share.
I think it humanises people a little bit.
You look back and have not so much a regret, but think, God, if I.
Had my time again, I'd make a better decision.
Is there an example you can share on that front?
No specific example.
I think there was definitely some time where I thought I was pretty good.
You know, like early 20s, 19, where I look back and I, you know, achieved nothing really,
you know, played a few games here and there, but thought I was a bit of a hotshot.
I knew everything.
And, you know, so I wish I maybe did that a little bit differently.
Yeah, maybe some injuries kind of racing back thinking.
That next to it was the most important thing in the world as opposed to biding my time
and, you know, just waiting it out.
But, yeah, nothing drastic that I can think of other than, yeah, like any young kid, you
go through a phase where you think you're pretty good.
And I always try to remember that when I see some young guys come through that they are
young and you do change.
Like, there are years where you do really change.
Now, I'm interested as well in, you know, people like you live.
You know, busy lives and successful lives.
Are there things that you do every day that in your mind set you up to be successful?
Have you got any habits or routines that you might share with us?
I'm not great in this space.
I try different little things at different stages.
So, you know, that's one thing I do struggle with is routine because we might be in England
on a test tour and then suddenly we're in India on a one-day tour where we're playing
finishing games at midnight.
So, like a sleeping and a daily routine.
Always seems different.
You know, some of the things I try to do here at home, switch my phone off at night.
So, I leave it upstairs or I leave it in a different room just to take away a temptation.
I try and create space every day for just, I don't know, just being.
So, whether it's reading or just pottering around the garden, I just like a little half
an hour breather where I'm just, yeah, left to my own devices.
And yeah.
I'll say that that's probably the most simple things.
Now, I understand that you're not far away from being a father in October with your
beautiful partner.
Becky, have you thought about leadership through the eyes of being a dad?
Have you given that some thought?
I have a little bit.
Not as much as probably Becky wishes I had.
Yeah.
Naturally, I think you go back to your own childhood and I was like, yeah, I had a great
childhood.
I've got two brothers, two sisters.
Parents were great.
So, yeah.
You try and take the best things, I guess, out of that.
And then, yeah, just how do I want to, kind of what life do I want to, yeah, give the
child.
So, yeah.
I've thought a little bit.
I'm sure I'll think of more ideas, but at the moment, my head goes to playing sport,
getting up to mischief as opposed to probably reality, which would be nappies and no sleep
for a little while.
Yeah.
I was having a look.
I've never been to the Blue Mountains.
But it just looks like a magic place.
Yeah.
It's a magic place that you grew up.
And I see, as you said, you've got two brothers, two sisters, and it looks like an incredibly
close-knit family, the Cummins family.
And what was it like?
I mean, clearly, the person you are, we're all a product of our upbringing.
How would you describe it?
How has that influenced the person that you are?
Yeah.
Well, we had a big family.
It's a family of seven, five kids, and I was the youngest of three boys.
So, in terms of, I guess, a cricketing and sporting sense.
We were so sporty.
I remember we went on a big holiday, went on this one big holiday in my childhood, over
to Europe, and we took a football.
So every single photo in front of the Eiffel Tower or wherever we are, we're passing a
football.
Louvre Museum, we're passing a footy down the halls.
So just always active, always competitive.
We had a big backyard space.
Just fun.
We were always up to plenty of different things, us kids and mum and dad, and there's always
adventure.
Mum and dad are really positive, happy, curious people.
So yeah, just had a great childhood.
Really lucky.
I've just got an image of my learning to take kids on the Spanish Steps, kicking footies
off the top of that amongst the crowd and trying to take speckies.
It sounds like a similar upbringing, mate.
The footy goes everywhere.
It's like an appendage in a house.
My daughter is 16, so it's either in the DNA or it's not, isn't it, mate?
It comes with us everywhere.
I know.
We were in Paris, and my brother tried to drop kick over this huge tree and got stuck
up there.
So we spent a whole day in Paris, going to all the sports stores, trying to see if we
got a share in it.
Well, you know, Phil, man, I've seen you kick the footy pretty well, mate, as a big, classy
left footer.
I mean, you grew up in rugby league heartland, really, in the west of Sydney.
Did you see both codes?
Yeah, both codes.
It's actually one of my regrets.
I wish I played AFL as a kid.
Both my brothers played a little bit, but not till probably kind of mid-teens.
We had a school across the road with a big field, and we'd go there literally every afternoon
in winter, and we'd just try and slot goals with, you know, contests.
You had to kick right and left foot, and we'd be out there for hours till dark.
So I love the AFL.
The Swannies used to go into, you know, SCG and A&Z Stadium to watch the Swannies.
Yeah.
The Swannies.
And, yeah, still follow along.
Ah, brilliant.
Now, Pat, we've been trying to ask a series of questions, and I know you've been brilliant
to be part of what we're calling a Leader Connect and these little, you know, connection
pods we spoke about with Rob and Andy and Marcus Bontempele, and trying to identify
all the dimensions that we think make great leadership and asking, you know, incredible
leaders like yourself.
So I'm keen to get your thoughts on the dimensions of leadership as we see it.
I want to ask you firstly about self-leadership.
What does that mean to you?
You know, I'm a big believer that, you know, you control your own space and you take ownership
of that, and, you know, you'd be unwavering, you know, nothing can affect that.
You're in total control of that, but knowing that everyone else is different and appreciating
that and trying to be open-minded and curious and try and learn yourself.
But I think, you know, owning your own space and leading by example, know who you are and
who you want to be.
It's the easiest job in the world.
Just be yourself.
So, yeah, I guess that's what it means to me.
Yeah.
The idea of trying to be many things to many people is pretty tiring, isn't it?
And that's a fascinating answer because I've heard a lot of people exactly identify the
way you are, isn't it?
When you understand yourself, you don't have to try too hard.
You just do what you do.
How about the environment?
I suppose you give this some thought as the Vice-Captain of the Australian Career Team,
but how do you go about positively trying to impact others in your environment?
Yeah.
So, I try and be really consistent, you know, naturally, you know, I'm lucky, I feel like
I'm quite a happy, positive person.
So, you know, I try and bring that to the table as much as I can, try to stay curious
and open-minded and create a safe space for people to be themselves and talk to.
And I think, you know, cricket side or any, you know, sporting side or office, you have
this kind of critical mass of where most of the people are.
And what makes them tick?
And even if that's different to me or someone else, trying to make sure we kind of encourage
that as much as we can and facilitate that.
In terms of vision, how do you go about creating your own vision and how do you go about sharing
that with others?
So, yeah, we've just gone through a bit of a process with the team and try and get everyone's
understanding of what's important, what's the next three, five years look like, where
do we want to put emphasis on and kind of go from there.
But I think everyone's understanding of what's important, what's the next three, five years
look like.
Where do we want to put emphasis on and kind of go from there.
I think everyone's got different things that makes them tick, but the end goal is normally
pretty similar.
So if you talk about, you know, a cricket side, we want to win, but we want to have
good fun along the way, have great relationships and impact kind of as many people as we can.
So yeah, still kind of, that's a working process for sure.
What sort of feedback did you get from the guys in the Elita Connect group today around
vision?
Yeah, I've got to go back to my notes here.
But yeah, again, they all systemize it, which, you know, I find great.
So someone like, you know, Andy, I hope I'm not speaking out of school, but he, for a
podcast and a really fun kind of duo, they still reach out to their employees of, okay,
where do you see us going?
This is what we're thinking about.
And they, you know, really do think ahead and of course, within that framework, there's
lots of fun along the way that changes, but making time, whether it's once a year or once,
every few months, just to allocate that, you know, time and preface it with, you know,
us cricketers, we hate talking about all the kind of business meetings types of stuff.
So it's, even if you preface it with, all right, the next hour, that's all we need.
Give us one good hour of concentration for the next six months and we'll forget about
it.
So yeah, that a few good tools.
I heard you mentioned curiosity a lot, and that is a dimension of leadership we talk
about a lot.
I think for us, it leads into learning and improvement.
Yeah.
And what do you think about curiosity and how do you, how do you approach learning?
I find it has a lot of benefits for me.
You know, first of all, I just find there's so much out there that interests me that I
don't know, or there's people out there that are interesting and I want to learn.
I find that, you know, just like watching a movie or a TV show for me, I sometimes prefer
reading or podcasts or just hearing different experiences outside sport, outside cricket.
So, you know, why I tap into that, I find it energising me sometimes when I'm feeling
like I'm not as stimulated as I, you know, want to be, you know, whether it's just, I've
been all out cricket and I just need something else.
I'll tell you the big one, which has been a benefit for me in this space is I find it
really takes pressure off performance.
The more things I'm interested in, and I feel like, you know, opportunities to, I don't
know.
Yeah.
I feel like all of it takes pressure away from performance.
I know that you have a bad day on the field.
Well, I'm going to be okay because I've got all these other things that interest me, all
these other people I've met and they really don't care whether I took five wickets or
went none for a hundred.
So as much as a pressure relieving tool as anything I find learning, you know, things
outside of cricket.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's a brilliant insight, Pat. I'm fascinated by it. I've never thought of it that way around being curious actually helps you relieve pressure. And it's a smart way to think about it, isn't it? Because we do get into our narrow zones in your world, isn't it? People want to ask you directly about that all the time. But the diversity of interests, that's a fascinating way to think about it. Makes a lot of sense.
Communication is something that I think every leadership environment thinks about. What's your take on communicating with clarity?
There's a few things. For me, I think relationships is everything. So if you've got a good relationship with someone that's been built up over time and shared experiences, it's pretty easy to communicate on it clearly. They know it's coming from a good place. It's not coming out of the blue.
So I guess the groundwork along the way makes the messaging really easy. And then I guess a few little tools inside of that. I hate fluff. I hate jargon. If it's not needed, keep it clear and concise. We're cricketers, so we don't need big speeches.
It's just a couple of key points. There's a saying that gets said all the time before a long-winded point. It's always, oh, it goes without saying.
But then I'll say it anyway, and it takes five minutes. So those little things that annoy me, I just try and keep short and sharp.
I like that. Final one. How about collaboration? How important is that to you, and how do you go about it?
Of course, you don't know everything. So just try to get different points of views. Everyone sees the world slightly differently, specifically to, say, skills in cricket.
I know what I'm feeling and what I'm trying to achieve. Someone's from the outside's got a different...
Point of view. So I love listening to what they've got to say. And of course, you're your own filter. So yeah, don't take in everything. But everyone's been through and goes through so much more than yourself. So just collective, the powers in the collective.
Thanks so much for sharing. Bonus question, mate. I'll finish on. I've been asking this across the series and questioning with that.
Who's the greatest leader in your team?
That's a good one. I mean, I'd say my parents. Mum and dad equally. Just both. We've raised five kids, but just in control of their life. Incredibly proactive, I guess, in everything they do. I'll say that. I think you can't get two better examples.
Nice place to start and a nice place to finish as well, Pat. It's been really great to catch up with you. I'm fascinated by the way your life has...
You've turned out with plenty more to come, mate, as a dad-to-be. Congratulations on that. And I know from talking to Matt and the guys, you've been incredible. And the life experiences that you've shared and collaborated with. So thanks so much for your time today on the Empowering Leaders podcast. It's been a great pleasure to speak with you.
No worries. Thanks, though, Darcy. Loved it.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me, Luke Darcy, produced by Matt Dwyer, with audio production by Darcy Thompson.
To start your leadership journey, I encourage you to go to elitercollective.com.
Take our Empowering Leaders indicator tool and understand the impact you have on your environment. Join us at Elita to learn, lead and collaborate.