A Listener Production.
G'day, it's Luke Darson.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership both on and off the field
has been a lifelong passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective
and have had the privilege of working with thousands of leaders
in education, sport, industry and the arts
that have helped shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership
where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
Paul Little is one of Australia's most successful businessmen.
In 1985, Paul negotiated a management buyout
of the transport and logistics business Toll Holdings.
He went on to serve as managing director of the Toll Group from 1986 to 2011.
In that time, Toll grew from an 18-truck operation worth $1.5 million
into an organisation with 45,000-plus employees in 50 countries,
eventually being sold to Japan Post for $6.5 billion.
Paul's creativity and success has expanded through the Little Group investment
in the property, technology, marine transport and lifestyle sectors.
Paul and his wife, Jane Hanson, are very active philanthropists.
The Hanson Little Foundation has a singular objective
to create a legacy of significant and positive change
that enables and inspires Australians.
Paul is the chairman of the Australian Grand Prix Corporation
and is the past chair of the Essendon Football Clubs and Visit Victoria.
Paul, extraordinary life of success and leadership that you've lived.
Did you have big ambition and big vision as a kid?
No, not really, Luke.
Thanks for the invitation to be here and it's great to chat to you.
No, I think as going through the education process,
you're not quite sure.
You don't have a vision about where it's all headed,
but, you know, it sort of evolves, I think,
over time.
My ambition and my course, yeah.
You left school, you went to work as a trainee executive at Main Nicholas
and then you were studying at night at RMIT.
Was there a desire within you at that early age to run your own business?
No, I'd like to be able to say it was,
but no, I really wanted to cut out a role in the corporate sector.
That, to me, was the pathway that...
that I felt had the most upside.
But at that point in time, running and owning my own business wasn't part of it, no.
You diverted for a while,
and we'll talk about your incredible success in the transport industry,
but you ran a guest house and a motel business for three years.
What was that chapter like and what did you learn from that?
Yeah, look, I think you have done your research.
Well done there.
I think at that point in time,
the corporate sector was...
was pretty cutthroat and I was a young man,
probably in a hurry to achieve things.
And I just felt after eight or nine years working with my original employer,
it was time for me to do something myself.
And so I bought and ran a guest house down at Point Lonsdale.
You love history and I want to talk to you about your love of that
and restoring brilliant buildings and bringing them back to life is...
it seems a great passion.
I want to go back to 1985.
And you do a deal that is a management buyout of Toll Holdings.
Now, assuming you look back on that as a life-changing moment,
how hard was it to do a deal like that at the time?
Yeah, well, it was hard because I'd never borrowed significant amount of funding from anyone,
never had any debt of significance once again.
So I had to borrow, as I recall, something like $20 million
and then cut a deal with a group called...
Pico Walls End, who were a very large mining, a global mining group.
And for me, to say I felt somewhat out of my depth is not an exaggeration.
But as it turned out, we acquired the business, yeah.
And you went into the transport industry, highly competitive,
and a lot of people, you know, try and fail in that area.
You take over as managing director.
And when you look back, what was your point of difference?
Why did you have such extraordinary success?
Well, we ran it as a private company up until 93.
And then in 93, we decided that for the business to grow significantly,
which was a key requirement of success moving forward,
scale is terribly important in transport and logistics.
So we IPO'd or floated the business
and it turned out to be a success.
And it turned out to be a success.
And I think that then gave us not only the funding we needed to grow,
but gave us the belief that we really could grow,
compete against the multinationals here in Australia,
but more importantly, compete against globally
and certainly within the Asia-Pacific region.
I read that you, over the course of the 28 years or so,
that you were invested significantly in Toll,
that you had 120...
I mean, clearly doing a deal that is a strength of you.
What is the secret to doing a good deal?
I think knowing what the industry that you're dealing.
I mean, I'm not being critical of bankers there
because clearly they have a different outlook.
But we became very good at identifying an opportunity,
transacting that opportunity,
and then importantly, integrating that back into,
into our business.
We became good at doing that.
And I think the secret, if there is one,
is really understanding and knowing the business
that you're acquiring.
I've been told by people around you
and doing some homework, Paul,
that you've also been prepared to walk away
from plenty of deals.
And is that the discipline?
If it doesn't fit your criteria,
you've walked away from as many as you've made.
Yeah, I think that was one of them.
I have a number of favourite sayings.
That's one of them.
And you've got to be prepared to walk away.
And if you're not,
then you'll compromise your negotiation
and probably not end up with a good deal.
So before you enter a deal,
you've got to be prepared not to do it.
Paul, there's probably one deal in your history
that had the most amount of publicity.
I want to ask you about it.
It was Toll acquiring the Steve Adoring giant, Patrick.
And Toll and Patrick were compared a lot
throughout your time.
You and Chris Corrigan,
they compared a lot, the CEO of Patrick at the time.
And there was a sense, you know,
reading a bit of the history and remembering at the time too
that the freight industry in Australia
maybe wasn't big enough for both of yours
and Chris's ambitions.
It got pretty personal, that one, didn't it?
He was attacking you regularly in the media.
I think he took out a full paid ad at one stage to attack.
And those who don't know the history,
I mean, Chris Corrigan was famous for him staring down
the unions in the waterfront dispute of 1998.
So you knew you were taking on a fairly combative person.
When you look back at that, what are your reflections
and would you change anything?
477 days is how long it took to complete.
So I'd certainly change that.
We, you know, if you knew it was going to be that ugly
and that personal and that length of time,
you may have had a second sort of thought about
whether or not you wanted to do it.
But no, look, I think it was absolutely
the right strategic move for Toll at that time.
However, ultimately succeeding and acquiring Patrick,
the competition regulator or the ACCC
then decided that we, Toll,
were becoming too significant.
In the Australian market.
So they forced sales on us of some of the assets
that we had acquired from Patrick,
which took the icing off the cake.
I mean, post the acquisition of Patrick,
we had revenues in excess of eight billion
and we had, more importantly,
an ability to influence in a positive way
the movement of goods.
Into and out of Australia,
which was the key sieve adoring asset that Patrick had.
And so from my point of view,
it was very successful.
And had we not been successful,
there's a reasonable argument that Patrick
could have ultimately acquired Toll.
Given that we were smaller than Patrick
and not as profitable as Patrick,
it was a very ambitious,
ambitious move.
At the end of the day,
we were successful and I think that really put Toll,
launched Toll into more of a,
I guess, a business that had global recognition,
not just within Australia.
I like, Paul, how you're able to say 477 days.
I mean, clearly, it takes some skin off you,
I'm assuming, when you go into that sort of negotiation.
And was it, is that as stressful a time as,
as you've had or?
Yeah, look, there've been a few.
I know we'll talk about Essendon shortly
and some of the stress that that job entailed.
But no, look, from a corporate point of view,
it was three to four years of distraction,
three to four years of knowing that if we succeeded,
it would be amazing.
If we didn't succeed, it would be a pretty painful exit.
So, yeah, it doesn't come without, though.
There's, I guess, realizations, but we did get there and it was an amazing acquisition
and the right one for Toll.
Well, we might segue, Paul, because you've done it for me into your chapter as Essendon
president.
And for those that aren't familiar with the story, in 2013, Paul steps up as president
at the Essendon Football Club, a club that you've loved all your life.
But it's in the middle of arguably the biggest sporting challenge that a club's faced in
Australian history.
It wouldn't be two.
It's a bigger call, I don't think, to make.
ASADA, the Australian Doping Authority, and the World Anti-Doping Authority, WADA, were
conducting an investigation into what was known as the Supplements Saga.
It took four years investigations, legal proceedings.
In the end, 34 players were banned for a two year period.
And it devastated individuals.
It was a horrible time in the industry.
What are your reflections?
I mean, for you to put your hand up at that time, it must have been incredible.
It must have been a wonderful time.
tough time but when you look back on it what do you feel about it yeah um not a lot has changed
for me uh on how i sort of um felt about it then and now um i think i think it was fair to say it
wasn't in the middle of of this investigation it was right at the outset and um not that that
would have changed a lot either i mean the the then chair and i was deputy chair
um for health reasons couldn't uh or didn't wish to continue and so without a lot of
notice um i was found myself in the role had i'd known it was going to take so long
and being once again quite um uh quite ugly from a personal point of view um you know maybe it
would have made me feel better but i think it would have made me feel better and i think it
would have made me feel better and i think it would have made me feel better and i think it would
more determined to continue rather than less so but um uh it was a a particularly difficult time
we started off uh we the club we the board started off uh having uh not a lot of knowledge about what
was about to unfold um and i i think um being on the back foot then um meant that uh it was difficult
to get ready and prepare and and and uh probably fight as hard as we could have or should have
at that point in time um so being on the back foot and being um attacked uh not only by those
organizations that you mentioned but by by the press and and a couple of um journalists in
particular uh just meant that i spent most of my time um trying to explain the the the
what really happened and and um rather than um trying to find reasons for um uh the a lot of the
accusations being um uh unfounded and paul i think i always go to the personal stories because i look
it's a pretty small community the afl community and i've been lucky enough to be part of it all
all of my working life and you see you know legendary people like james heard and and you
know david evans was the chairman you spoke about whose families had an enormous history in the
game as as you're aware um leave alone the 34 players who were devastated have you got a sense
that what happened to to those individuals was was unfair oh there's no question and and um uh you
know no player was ever charged uh with uh an offense of taking performance enhancing drugs or
i should say none no one was ever found guilty um of taking performance enhancing drugs and um
i knew that i had not the slightest doubt about that being the case but as i said before there
was a wall of criticism there that was very difficult for us to get over um and so was it
unfair terribly unfair um and impacted so many lives i mean um the the players their families
and one of the jobs i had on a regular basis was to talk to the families
um of the players because these young men probably didn't have the the the knowledge or the um i guess
courage to sit down with their um mother and father and girlfriend and whoever else and try
and explain that you know they hadn't hadn't done what they were being accused of doing i mean it's
a pretty difficult situation all around so um yeah it was a um
uh it was a tough time and unfortunately for me you rightly uh pointed out that uh eston is a club
that i've loved and enjoyed for many many years um i never really got the opportunity to uh to
enjoy it as a chairman or president of a footy club uh i just felt that uh i was just fighting a
a fight the whole time i was in that role if you look back i mean what what should have and could
have been done differently to avoid a fight and to avoid a fight and to avoid a fight and to avoid a fight
the enormous pain that the individuals faced and the industry faced and i suppose everyone around it
there was there was shrapnel going everywhere for anyone that was anywhere near eston at the time
yeah well having a couple of the other um clubs giving me advice along the way i didn't appreciate
so they you can you can put those individuals and those clubs to one side what should have
happened i i don't think anyone should be treated as being guilty and until they've been found to be
guilty
and and um um sure do i hate drugs in sport absolutely and there's no question about that
but we we were um and and some of the individuals you mentioned james in particular who's a close
personal friend um was being treated as a as a guilty person in this process and and they weren't
and and they they never were um in my um
my estimation um um nor should they have been um put through what they were put through so
uh it was um not only was it uh could it have been avoided um look i i think the afl in hindsight and
the people running the afl at the time probably needed to be a bit stronger in in the role that
they played um and um
once again um we spent a lot of our time just trying to refute some of the um um
the the pretty wild accusations that were out there about what the club had been doing
we'll change uh tact uh paul and people listening to this we'll see your life and how it's unfolded
and it's littered with with success everywhere if uh if you're giving advice to someone who's
thinking about being an entrepreneur or a leader in whatever environment you're in i'm not going to
do that i'm not going to do that i'm not going to do that i'm not going to do that i'm not going to do that i'm not going to do that
they're in i mean what lessons have you learned along the way that you would pass on
yeah well i think um and and thank you for saying i've been successful in everything i've known i'm
not quite sure that uh that's exactly uh right but um look i i think uh you you really do need to
have a clear knowledge around what it is you're trying to achieve and and sure people can learn
and and um um can improve their their own knowledge and understanding of a particular area but people
look at me and say you've made some uh wonderful decisions in the um the building and construction
industry for example and i i would say to them i've spent my whole life in that industry this
isn't something that the the taxi driver told me i should do this is something that i fully believe
in and and then i'm not going to do that i'm not going to do that i'm not going to do that i'm not
i surround myself with people who um are capable of working with me to achieve outcomes and um
so i i i think building the team around you really understanding the industry and and not
sort of over overstepping the mark when it comes to what you're investing in or what you're trying
to achieve have some um have a plan and uh don't sort of
try and go outside that plan that would be my advice yeah and you've had a clear plan as well
in in terms of giving back and the handsome little uh foundation in combination with uh
with your wife is doing some extraordinary things and and i mentioned your love of history one of
the projects that that springs to mind is that the little hall at melbourne university can you
give people an insight into your thinking because that's a really fascinating way that you've gone
about giving back you you've built a building at melbourne university can you explain that project
and why that means so much to you yeah it really started with i suppose uh jane my wife and and
myself being uh keen to bring more to the table and simply just funding um a program and uh jane's
involvement at melbourne university gave her an insight into what um as she felt was an an
opportunity to identify and then um uh create opportunity
and roadways for for some scholars that were were brilliant scholars that that perhaps had
family issues that didn't allow them to realize their dreams so we created a pathway for those
scholars to be identified and then put in a very nurturing uh helpful environment and then i guess
my uh part of the um uh the overall outcome there was to um to build
design and build a student accommodation that um uh was better than the normal student accommodation
and and um um the location the design of the building uh the um uh all of the other um uh
abilities for a a building like little hall to be um with uh theater space and and libraries and
and meeting rooms so
we put it all together got the blessing of melbourne uni and um out of the 699 or 669 i should say
beds in little hall um there's there's a quite a high percentage now probably around 50 to 60 of
them are occupied by these um scholars who um are outstanding young uh australians and uh so
we're nurturing them through the pro through their um
time at melbourne uni but also um creating a need with the um with the um student accommodation that
in our view needed to be upgraded in terms of quality to some extent yeah it's a it's a
brilliant story and legacy project of giving back and opportunity for those that wouldn't have had
it previously there's a lot of diversity in your life i didn't realize that you were
passionate uh into doing my research uh motorsport enthusiasts you you drove
at a high level and and now the chairman of the grand prix corporation you had um successful v8
supercar team for a period of time where did that passion come from um that's a good question i i
think as a young man um i and this might explain my involvement in logistics too but i loved
anything that effectively was on wheels and moved and to some extent i love the challenge of uh a
competition and so i think it's a great question and i think it's a great question and i think it's a
great question and i think it's a great question and i think it's a great question and i think it's a
so motor racing was a logical extension of all of that um from my point of view uh once again did
i start off with a long-term plan of owning a team and and competing in a in a team no not
necessarily but but one thing leads to another and uh we we've had uh quite a successful time
in in motorsport and of course now the um australian grand prix corporation has just uh
been uh blessed with the um the the uh largest um occupancy uh of of fans through the gate
um for this year's um grand prix an amazing um success story and one that i think will see the
grand prix corporation go on to bigger and better things uh moving forward i'm fascinated by uh that
jumping off on that for a moment and it's been such a huge piece of melbourne obviously the
grand prix started in in adelaide initially but the resurgence of fans back to the sport and and
i can't help but link it to the netflix series drive to survive and the impact that's had i mean
i have got to confess to not being a sport that i am a great follower of but that series has brought
it to life for me understanding the characters sitting down with my wife who's the least
motorsport but she's interested in the spot are you linking the success of that show look i i think
um um there's
no question it's had an impact uh globally not just within australia and interesting we
we monitor um all sorts of things at the grand prix corp and and the numbers of females that
are now following the sport um and and let's say through the gate for the grand prix meeting
itself uh has moved up to 60 it was 40 so men and women have have really um both enjoyed that
drive to survive show but also the uh the knock-on effect of that and um i i think um i really do
believe that the australian grand prix corporation has run such a successful event not just this
year but in previous years that we're capable of um uh helping formula one uh grow its business
and and um in the within the region so that's we're quite ambitious
about being able to do that well on this podcast i've been speaking to a range of different leaders
from from successful business people like you to to young musicians in the arts who are trained
changing their uh space and we see leadership now as being this uh doesn't necessarily require a
title we we see people being able to bring leadership from all walks of life so i've been
asking a series of questions because we see some synergy in what leadership looks like so please
to all the leaders please be expansive as as you like um or as or as
short as you like as well but we see one of the first traits balls of people who are um consistently
successful in leadership have an idea of what self-leadership means to them what does that
term mean to you when i say self-leadership well success doesn't just happen it's caused
and and uh i you know i i have um uh very strong ideas around um bringing together um
the people needed the skills the people needed the skills the people needed the skills the people
needed um and the timing needs to be right to to achieve an outcome that it and it may be
philanthropy it may be in sport and it may be in business so i i think the model that i use if i
can call it a model is something that i believe in and and something that's worked well for me
yeah and they tell me that your own self-discipline is pretty strong or even through the the full-on
years that your your fitness and your training and your and your
healthy approach to to food and along the way is that has that been part of part of you uh look it
it's not something that i've found difficult it's something i enjoy doing uh i enjoy having energy i
enjoy feeling fit and strong and um i enjoy the satisfaction having had um a good workout for
example so i i think from my point of view that's um that's an easy one leaders we see now a
dimension of their leadership pool is they're really conscious of their leadership and they're
they're really conscious of how they positively impact others and i and i picked up the phone i
rang a few people in preparation and then they were very adamant that the total success was very
much that people love working in that environment with you and for you and under you and that you
create an environment that people love going and they felt engaged in it has that been something
you've been conscious of how you impact those in your environment yeah i i think in empowering
people around you um is something that i get the most satisfaction
out of um um and and you know at toll that certainly there's one very quick quick example
of uh you made mention of the the corrigan um incident let's call it uh the acquisition and
and um i called my 20 key guys together at crown one day and said look um we're in this fight um
it's the right fight to be in um but what i want from you
is to
go away and run the business for me uh for as long as it takes now
to allow me to focus on trying to win this other uh fight that or um acquisition that we're in
um and i'd have to say the response from empowering those key people um was amazing
we we made for uh six or twelve month periods we made record profits um and to me it didn't come
as a surprise at all it was
something i knew that uh we'd probably been getting ready for even if uh it hadn't been
obvious at the time yeah and you do that uh now from from what i can see as well paul you know
the the portfolio stuff you're interested in is diverse there's technology uh startups you've got
the property business which you say a long history clearly with toll was a big property owner and
business as well but you you run a ferry service between uh geelong and and and melbourne and which
was creative uh idea the long-term and the long-term and the long-term and the long-term
lifestyle assets and you've just renovated historic hotel in in port arlington so is that
the same when you talk about empowering someone for those listening how do you practically go
about it is it this is your team this is your division i'm going to set you up for success
can you give us some more detail on that uh well i think um there's no point in uh telling
someone you're going to empower them unless you really do so you you become almost um
an advisor to the person who's doing the role that you want them to do they have a clear
understanding they have full control um they have the power to whether it's higher or fire or or
fund or not fund or whatever so you you really need to hand over the business to them um and you
become as i said before someone that they can speak to if they have an issue or a problem or
hopefully an opportunity
so i i think uh yeah whether it's the ferries um or the um any of the lifestyle assets that we've
got but but i think with the ferries it was a bit different because uh governments uh were involved
they're really keen to see this part of melbourne's transport grow and build and we needed some help
to do that and um i i also have uh um i i believe good relationships with state and federal government
which have
helped us in in that that sort of situation there paul we see leaders are really clear
on how they create and share their vision the vision for toll you can still read it it was
about being the preeminent uh logistics uh provider in in asia and you you went on to to to
achieve that how did you go about you know not only that vision but the vision you've got for
all the other things that you're trying to achieve um well you don't just wake up one morning and all
of a sudden you have a vision for what it is that you're trying to achieve and you're trying to
do whatever it is you want to do i i think it it um um it happens over a period of time but
you you you see the opportunity you assess whether these are commercial um observations i suppose you
you you assess whether or not you can make money out of it because whilst i love doing philanthropy
and and working with groups like the footy club and different ones i also enjoy having successful
commercial uh activities and i think it's it's it's it's it's it's it's it's it's it's it's it's it's it's
um and assuming you can make money and assuming you've got the right people to help you do it
then um you you you push the button and off you go um uh i i continually say to my family i'm going
to try and declutter my life um but at this point in time i haven't been successful in doing that
um i do enjoy being um busy i do enjoy being
running successful entities and and they're not all successful some some are quite challenging
but uh from my point of view um i'd i'd hate to become boring i don't wish to become boring
because i enjoy so much what i do yeah just picking up on that paul though you know clearly
your commercial success has been uh you know incredible path that you followed and and and
the tale story speaks for itself but you you don't you know do the things that you've done
without purpose and you don't do the things that you've done without purpose and you don't do the
passion involved in our machine you don't take on a a challenge like acquiring you know patrick's
without that sense of what was that sense of purpose in you was it about creating a successful
business or was there a love of the transport industry was it a i think it's not so much the
love of the industry but the the belief that i you know to to to put it uh i can't put any other
way i was quite good at it and so we're our team we were good at it and we knew that and and uh
we were good at it not just um locally here but comparing ourselves against other global players
we firmly believed we could achieve it if we had the courage the funding the you know all the
ingredients needed to be there um but it you know it it um i guess the greater the reward the greater
the risk quite often too and um i guess taking on the the the the the the the the the the the the
the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the
taking risks and managing those risks is a big part of uh how at toll in particular we were so
successful paul we see leaders are really curious that word comes up all the time a real dimension of
of leadership is is curiosity and then a lot of leaders through their curiosity
approach how they continually learn and develop that does that resonate with you
um i'm not sure i understand what you mean by curiosity in that sense well we see leaders
constantly
wondering what is around them that they can learn from how they can you know whether they digest
information through reading or through other people and they they have this innate sense of
of wanting to understand things is that yeah i i often i mean i i look at you and wonder um
i suppose whether i could do that job you know and and i'm always looking i see a building and
i think i wonder if i could build that building or you know i wonder if i could build that building
if i'd be good at running that team or not and and i'm quite realistic with myself i don't sort of
it's not a love affair with myself but but so i think in that sense yeah the curiosity
um is probably a good word because um um i um i love one thing i do love is seeing
um the the um the a visible result of what it is i've been doing
is important to me and i think it's important to me and i think it's important to me and i think
it's important to me as whether it's building a building or creating a premiership team or
building a ferry or a renovating an old hotel or whatever um i i do like to be able to um
uh i know i know one of the the people who um murray rants who you know i say to murray all
the time take photos of it send me the photos i want to see the photos of it so every time he
goes to one of these businesses um you know he's got he's he's out there taking photos
and sending them to me so i i just think having um uh a real time um way of determining our
progress and how we're going um is uh has always and still is important to me yeah great afl
footballer murray rants from the west coast eagles and my old club the bulldogs and his son alex end
up becoming one of the legendary players in recent times as well i know he's heavily involved in in
in running your your projects and uh have
crossed paths with with uh murray before and he he clearly speaks highly of the way you guys
work together we see great leaders uh paula uh very much aware of their communication and how
they communicate i mean you end up with a business that's got 40 plus thousand employees in 50
countries how have you gone about communicating when you've had that sort of scale yeah it's a
real challenge um but but terribly important that they want to know there's a real person
sitting there behind the desk and not not a cardboard cutout so one of the things that
i did um probably to the detriment of you know your family um life and the whole thing is that
i would constantly be traveling and um i would um uh back in the tall time in particular um
every second week we'd be off somewhere around the world so so that's a um i mean i love the
technology is kicking the tires i mean i love doing that um and i love talking to the people
that are running the uh the the particular um job that we're we're um we're looking at but
um it it's a balance and finding that balance um has become easier for me with um uh doing more
things from a family point of view now particularly the the philanthropy um is very much uh something
that um the family my wife in particular is uh heavily involved in and um uh so i i think you've
you've got to be um you've got to be conscious of the need to balance things up you can't just
embark on this amazing uh sort of vision or dream that you have it's got to be done in a reasonable
way yeah i'm passionate about the family balance question paul and i was was planning to get there
at some point i mean you're the father of uh of three you tragically lost your first child and
first wife uh to cancer back in 1991 and um you know i'm assuming the the challenges around that
did you have i mean you sound like a really system and an organized person did you you're trying to
grow this extraordinary business did you have the the sort of systems to make sure that you got
the family time as well how did you go about that well i've always um and it's fairly simplistic i
guess but i've always said that i don't take work home with me and i
just won't do that uh do i thrash around at night no i don't um do i work weekends uh if it's at all
possible i don't and so i think if you there's got to be that sort of interaction with the with
the family um but uh you'd be better off asking my wife that she would probably say that i haven't
really succeeded in that area but i am very conscious of it yeah we see poor leaders uh
very uh aware of collaboration
as a dimension of their leadership uh was that important to you along the way and how did you go
about it um oh everyone needs to collaborate i mean you you just don't have all the answers you
don't have quite often you need reassurance yourself um so whether you're collaborating
with your family which is the the way that i love to do it um um or whether you have one or two
people that you you use as a way to collaborate with your family or whether you have one or two
sounding board um whether it's the bank manager and probably doesn't matter much but you really
get well it does matter but you really do need um to uh i think reassure yourself occasionally
that you're heading down the right path i mean people think that it comes naturally but but it
doesn't you get better at it but but you still need to make sure that what you're doing is
balanced and you get the right sort of input from from others and
um i find that speaking to jane about what i'm doing um helps in that way a lot yeah
paul been asking these two questions to to all the range of leaders and and uh take as much time with
these final two questions but we're obsessed with leadership and and what it looks like and i love
hearing your story uh as much as any that have been told but in your my who's been the greatest
leader in your life
oh dear uh the greatest leader um i'd probably need to think about that one um are you talking
about in in every area of endeavor or are you talking about i mean um i guess uh i i love getting
advice from my father when he was around and and um as a young man who probably never thought that
he would succeed i mean you have a lot of people who are who are who are who are who are who are
self-doubt when you're younger and quite often that's what drives you i think um but uh my father
would uh always um sort of point me in the right direction i think yeah so he wasn't a leader but
he was my leader yeah and that is a common answer for you'd be people scan and they uh some people
go to to great historical you know mandela type leaders who they've read about and have had an
influence on them but those that had a an influential parent often that's where they
start what what sort of
dad was he like what sort of influence did he have yeah he was very similar um i mean he um
played a few games with melvin i think um he uh was a great tennis player um he was um um a fairly
um you know what didn't have a a crazy social life he was a good family man he was always around
um yeah he he was
um
sensible balanced and um he told me what he was thinking which is probably what i needed as a
young man we uh we see collaboration as we said before of being something that uh is really uh
been uh beneficial to the way people thinking about leadership now in that spirit if you could
collaborate with anyone on anything paul and you've got a diverse range of interests in any
part of your life is there is there someone that jumps out at you that you'd like to collaborate
with
yeah if i if i had a problem or an opportunity of significance i'd probably want to talk to jade
about it i think yeah and the two of you together i mean and she's had an extraordinary you know
successful life as an investment banker and you know she's an order of australia alongside you
for the work you do together so it's a real partnership and a real collaboration on on
and on all those things or do you have things that you that you sort of separated
oh
Oh, no, we don't always agree if that's what you mean.
No, but it's probably interesting for you and your listeners to know that Jane was the
banker who floated toll for us back in 93.
Is that how you met?
Yeah.
I didn't know that.
And that's an interesting relationship to them.
Yeah.
And was it an, it was, you know, they're an attraction straight away or?
Oh, you mean to the business or to me?
Look, I think when Jane was asked by her sort of a quite a large, well-known global bank
to go out to a place called Brooklyn here in Victoria or in Melbourne, I mean, she knew
where Brooklyn was in the US.
Slightly different than Brooklyn here in the western suburbs of Melbourne.
So I think she thought she'd probably made the wrong decision to consider coming back
to Melbourne and working here.
Yeah, for a while.
But no, we talk about a lot of things, obviously, and I respect her view, which comes probably
from a different angle in my view with a lot of these things.
So it works well.
Paul, I've been looking forward to this conversation and fascinated by the way you've approached
your life.
It's such a unique path that you've taken.
And there's so much to learn from your life experience and the way you've gone about approaching
everything.
So we really appreciate you joining me today.
It's been great to catch up.
Pleasure.
No, I've loved it.
Thanks, Paul.
Thank you.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me, Luke Darcy, produced by Matt Dwyer, with audio
production by Darcy Thompson.
To start your leadership journey, I encourage you to go to elitacollective.com, take our
Empowering Leaders Indicator Tool and understand the impact you have on your environment.
Join us at Elita to learn, lead and collaborate.