Paul Watterson's life story from intensive care nurse to building and running a number of massive scale businesses in healthcare and now hospitality is a remarkable story to me on every level.
His crystal clear thinking and understanding of where opportunities exist is worth listening to and it all started with what was a genuine sliding door moment.
One of my mates still takes responsibility for the career trajectory from that moment.
I think we'd had one beer at a pub in Kighton and we're heading up to Moama and young Toddy sort of you know straight off the road into a tree.
At that time there was just no way you could go back and work along the bedside.
Paul shares the great influence his two mentors Bruce Dixon and Vita Pepe had on him and the lessons he still applies today.
The combination of two people makes one outstanding leader and Bruce was sort of the master at seeing strategy, execution.
Kitting on that strategy, delivering organic growth and Vita has just an incredible eye for detail, she's very methodical, she's very driven.
If you're interested in scaling your business or how to grow your world then Paul Watterson's story of buying a single pub for fun to now running a pub group that turns over $1.4 billion in sales a year is worth a listen.
It's always focus on organic growth because clearly that's the most prized growth that you can get in any business.
So if you can deliver organically.
Organic growth through that mix of either price or volume depending on the type of business that you're in then you have really built an incredible sort of box or unit in which you can grow value from.
It's been a great privilege for us to have Paul Watterson as part of our Alita Connect community.
We are really passionate about this idea of bringing people together from diverse backgrounds and groups of five or six from around the globe to learn, to connect and to share.
Head to alitacollective.com, book a discovery call, we'd love to chat to you and connect with you.
Thanks as always to Jason Nicholas and the team from Temper Bedding Australia and their great support of conversations like this one with Paul Watterson.
Temper is a mattress like no other, NASA approved and the world's best in bedding.
Paul Watterson is the founder, chief executive officer of Australian Venue Co.
A venture that started in 2014 with Paul and a few mates bought the station hotel in Footscray because they wanted to have somewhere to drink.
Ten years later they've purchased 160 venues, renovated four of them and built eight new greenfield pubs.
The business generates $1.4 billion in sales and earnings of $250 million.
Paul started his working life as an intensive care nurse before a car accident on a golf trip ended with him breaking his hand.
Not able to work in the ICU, he spent a year in the Department of Health and in 2001 Paul joined a business called Healthscope that at the time owned 16 hospitals.
His role was to move around the country and run a hospital in the year after they bought a new one, taking him from Sydney to Canberra to Adelaide and back to Sydney again.
Healthscope was valued at $20 million when he started and ten years later was sold to private equity for $2.7 billion.
Paul then joined his two mentors from Healthscope, Bruce Dixon and Vita Pepe, as they partnered with private equity to purchase Spotless Catering in 2012 for $720 million.
After a major restructure two years later, Spotless was listed for $1.9 billion.
Success stories everywhere, Paul. It's great to catch up with you. Thanks for joining me.
Yeah, thanks Luke. Thanks for having me. I'd love to take responsibility for them, but it's always nice to be here.
I get the feeling your humility is going to limit you from taking too much credit on anything, but for a boy who grew up in Swan Hill, son of parents who were both secondary school teachers, it's an incredible working life. Does it surprise you how it's ended up?
I think with this stuff, you never plan it. You take the opportunities as they come up, and I think having the ability to move around as opportunities came up really helped.
So yeah, certainly not something you plan as you take your first step as an 18-year-old nurse.
In Melbourne, a genuine sliding door moment, it must have been when you break your hand, you're with your mates on a golf trip, and a car hits a tree, you end up with a broken hand, can't do your job in intensive care, you go into management or in the Department of Health.
Were you surprised that your skills translated so well? Suddenly you're running hospitals, pretty complex businesses. What were the skills that helped you do that?
We were genuinely surprised, and one of my mates still takes responsibility for the career trajectory from that moment.
I think we'd had one beer at a pub in Kighton, and we're heading up to Moama, and this young toddy sort of, you know, straight off the road into a tree.
At that time, there was just no way you could go back and work along the bedside.
And if that hadn't happened, to be honest, I'd probably still be there today, because I really loved working with a great group of friends at the Royal Melbourne ICU, and it was a genuinely sliding door moment.
I think from there, it had really come to take that opportunity.
to work within the Department of Health, but more broadly, go and work for Healthscope.
And I think nursing's a funny career whereby, in a lot of ways back then, and even now, to run a hospital, you had to have a director of nursing.
So it meant a lot of people with nursing qualifications could go in and essentially run a small business for the first time, and that's probably where I got my opportunity.
So you think if that hadn't happened, you would have been quite happily a career intensive care nurse?
You loved it.
I absolutely, yeah, genuinely loved it.
It was one of those places you see a lot of tragedy, you see a lot of hope, you deal with a lot of families, but it was a great group of people.
And I probably genuinely do think I'd probably be there today if it hadn't have been for that moment.
Amazing, amazing story.
Bruce Dixon, Vita Pepe, if I'm saying that correctly, you worked with at Healthscope and Spotless, and they became great mentors in your words.
What did you learn from them?
Yeah, it's a great example where the conversation.
The combination of two people makes one outstanding leader.
And Bruce just had this, and still does, had the foresight to identify an opportunity like private health care was at the moment.
At that time, it was private health cover had just rolled in, that lifetime health cover.
And all of a sudden, the penetration of private health care went through the roof.
Bruce was sort of the master seeing strategy, executing on that strategy.
Delivering organic growth.
But he will tell you that, you know, his attention to detail is not that great.
And that's where someone like Vita came in.
Now, Vita has been the chief operating officer of those businesses, Healthscope and Spotless.
And Vita has just an incredible eye for detail.
She's very methodical.
She's very driven.
She's very unforgiving of poor performance.
And, you know, her philosophy, you know, we used to say it's the equivalent to Yoda in Star Wars.
You know?
And you don't, you do or you don't do.
There's no try with Vita.
And that really held you accountable as a leader and a young manager.
And that's sort of really defined who I've tried to become today.
I love that idea.
You're a visionary person like Bruce who can see things that others can't ahead of time.
There's a gift in that, isn't there?
But understanding that I can't succeed on the detail stuff.
Very few people have both, do they?
That they can walk the vision and the detail.
But they must have been harmonious together, that skill set.
Oh, yeah.
Incredibly harmonious.
And I think it's also about identification of what your skill set is and what your weaknesses is
and find someone who complements you because very few people are everything to everyone.
Yeah, brilliant.
And you found those learnings really were something you're able to take and absorb,
the way that they're able to combine seeing an opportunity and then executing it with detail?
Well, in the early stages of my career, I spent most of my time alongside Vita
and just her approach and attention.
Her detail, her reviews of things like profit and loss statements, reviews of cash flow,
reviews of general ledgers, reviews of balance sheet.
It was just such a methodical, detail-orientated approach.
It really became very much built within my DNA.
And then over the journey as I've moved into more CEO-style roles,
that's when you can leverage and learn from some of Bruce's history and just some key lessons
like continually maintaining forward.
Momentum in business, even when things go your way or mistakes get made,
just continually just drive along that pathway to get that more strategic outcome.
It's been so much scale in the organizations that you've worked with all the way through.
You've been out and it looks like scale really quickly.
For people listening, most people want to expand their space, whatever it is.
Have you got a message on how to grow your business?
Yeah, I think it's always focused on organic growth because clearly that's the most prized
growth that you can get in.
Any business.
So if you can deliver organic growth through that mix of either price or volume,
depending on the type of business that you're in,
then you have really built an incredible sort of box or unit in which you can grow value from.
Now, moreover to organic growth, that then allows you to do what we would call inorganic growth,
which are things like acquisitions or things like adding capacity to an existing venue,
something we would call a brownfield or things like building a new venue from scratch.
Yeah.
So it's really focusing on what drivers you have within your individual business to really
drive that organic growth.
And then the ability to bolt on other inorganic growth levers really gives you that growth
multiplier.
You know, the organic, it just literally generate more sales by being better at your own existing
business and, or, you know, but now to get more margin out of your prices.
And so that's the sort of, that's where you start before you go to the expansion part.
Yeah, very much so.
And I think if you look at a business like hospitals or pubs, they're very much got a,
a fixed cost base.
So any incremental volume, new customers you can add or price you can take, and obviously
that third lever is mixed, how you get say premiumization within your product comes through
at a relatively high gross margin when you've got a big fixed cost base.
So focusing on that then enables you to go to people like investors and say, you've got
this ability to grow within a platform and hopefully they'll fund you to then bolt on
additional platforms so you can get those benefits.
Yeah.
That's in perpetuity.
Australian Venue Co is such an amazing story.
The local pubs and institution, but you saw a gap that maybe others, you know, didn't.
Can you explain why you saw, you just described them being able to add different platforms
to it, but what, what was the gap that you saw?
I think with the pub business, initially, as you said, we went in thinking it'd be nice
to own a pub or two.
And originally it was, uh, we bought some pubs for Bruce's son, Mike, to go in and run.
But once we got in there, we could see.
It was an incredibly fragmented industry within Australia.
So there's about 9,500 pubs in Australia and only 11% of them are owned by corporate groups.
And I know you and your family have a strong history in, in a number of venues.
One of ours, Angler's Tavern is a, everyone still thinks it's owned by the Darcy's, which
is good for us.
But, but ultimately what we saw in the model was the ability to sort of professionalize
and scale.
That model.
And I think it was part opportunistic, but it was also partially timing because the technology
had evolved so much in the previous 10 years that you could really run a business like
that at scale.
And I would imagine 10, 15, 20 years ago, running a pub, running 200 pubs just would
have been a nightmare because cash would have been walking out the door.
You know, the chef would have walked out with a leg of lamb at the end of the night, you
would have lost so much stock.
Now there's controls and systems.
Yeah.
In place that enable you to do that in scale that just weren't there 20 years ago.
That is an interesting point I hadn't thought of in your model, isn't it?
That there was a huge amount of leakage out of, uh, the local pub and it was almost accepted
that, you know, your mate behind the bar gave free drinks.
Like my dad would roll in his grave, you know, you don't have a friend at the supermarket
that gives you free groceries, but when we, you know, I can picture dad calling people
out, it's going, that's actually called theft.
We buy that beer, you give it away for free.
That kills us.
We, we go out of business.
But it was just.
It was sort of hospitality jovial thing that went on or you're right, like the chefs had
their side deals with the steaks going to their house and out the back, but in the end
it, it sent a lot of businesses broke.
Yeah, very much so.
And it wasn't scalable.
So you've now got systems, for example, that decrement stock.
So you know what your theoretical stock take should be at any time based on the products
that you're selling.
And if the stock level is different, you know, pretty much on a daily basis, if you've got
an issue.
I think the other thing is cash.
Like we're over 95%.
Is carded or through order at table now says it's just not cash in the business like there
was previously.
And that's really helped the ability to scale the model.
And I think the other thing that, that you've seen is just the, the new customer based systems
that, that you can introduce and things like order at table.
You know, we were the first business to introduce order at table QR code.
And some people in the history absolutely hate us for that.
But you go back to 2018, it just didn't exist.
And there's space for that sort of technology that you can then use to run your businesses
in slightly different ways.
And then finally, the other big enabler that we have now is customer data and using that
customer data to tweak your model and tweak your offering is just something that just
wasn't there 20 years ago.
Can you give us an idea of how many people go through, you know, on a weekly or an annual
basis when you've got scale like you have, there must be a big volume of people, a lot
of people.
Eyeballs that comes through your venues.
We have 6 million users in our customer database.
And so when we talk about users, they're customers who transact with them on an annual basis,
maybe multiple times.
And that looks at things like what their spend is within venues, what cross sell there is,
i.e. what venues they, multiple venues they go to us.
We can see what their preferences are.
So we can see if you've ordered a kid's meal and we can show you other ones of our pubs
that have kids based.
So there's different ways you can segment that customer base, but it's about 6 million
users that we have in the business at the moment.
And is the buying power scale a profound thing?
Does that help the model as well?
Oh, very much so.
I think it's one of those ones where once again, you, you can go to a supplier base
and you can say, you've got this enormously powerful customer group.
And when you want to introduce say new products, we can tell you what, uh, venues will suit
those new products.
And a good example is sort of hard solo or hard rated that came out last year.
That, that was a product that didn't exist two years ago.
It's come in and pretty quickly become probably in the top three or four products sold within
most pubs.
So we could really quickly identify who was the likely drinker of hard rated.
And then we can mobilize a product like that almost immediately to sort of match that customer
base.
Yeah.
That's fascinating to me that the data that you're able to collect now that wasn't available
in the pub.
I always felt growing up in a family of publicans that the pub was just great part of the local
community and you actually serve people.
And when it was done well, it was a really big part of forming communities.
I think it's been misunderstood and lost a little bit in translation.
Have you enjoyed that part of it?
Bringing life back to some of these old venues?
Oh yeah.
It's incredible.
And I think it's a big part of what we try and do.
I think there's this misconception that a larger group couldn't run pubs.
And we were very careful about our model.
And so much as what we wanted to do is systematize the back of house, but keep the front of house
experience very unique, which is why we've got a range of things like small, uh, what
would have been previously family owned pubs all the way through to nightclubs with totally
different demographics.
So, you know, we sort of in, in house refer to it as that sort of reverse mullet style
where you've got, you know, all, all business out the back and party up the front.
So you, you've got to have a unique offering for the customer base.
And then it's about building something that those local customers want.
And Angler's Tavern is a good example of that.
So we obviously rebuilt that post the flood two years ago, but you can do a lot of work
and say, okay, there's a very young family led demographic out there now, which means
you want to install big kids play areas.
You want to look at making sure you've got a very broad kids based menu.
You want family based activations.
You need a great sports bar because there's a great sports bar customer out there and
you need a big, big.
Out and outdoor style area.
And then in the evenings, it transitions almost to a nightclub on a Saturday night where you've
got young, uh, 18 to sort of 30 year olds from that part of Melbourne wanting to come
in and have a big night out.
So having to build a venue that meets that whole consumer is, is quite a challenge.
Yeah.
And obviously a place I know really well.
And I think, you know, when that's up and running really successfully, a lot of the
kids from the inner West, when there wasn't a venue like that had to pour into the city
and there's all the risk.
Of cost.
And then there was a lot of trouble going on in the overcrowding city venue.
So to have a local venue closer to home that serves all those purposes, you can go there
with your family and have a meal on the 18 to 30 hours.
They need a place to go and socialize and meet and catch up.
So it's brilliant that you are able to do that.
I want to get back to the spotless example.
You come in that business needed serious restructuring.
800 people get sacked pretty quickly as that, the business got bloated.
How have you found those sort of tough leadership calls to, to make them?
Oh, there.
They're the hardest calls that you ever have to make in is downsizing an organization.
And it's something that you only want to do if it's absolutely necessary.
You want to really focus on growing your business and maintaining your cost base equivalent
to what your revenue size and scale is.
But occasionally there's businesses that get out of whack and that's either because they
don't grow as quickly as you think they're going to grow or they shrink.
And spotless was one of those businesses.
That had lost revenue over the journey, but had maintained its cost base.
And then you come in and you look at what are areas within the business that are not
a hundred percent required for the revenue base you have at the moment.
And, and at that example, spotless had a very bloated head office cost base.
And so you really look at what changes you can make that don't impact the end customer
and end consumer.
And unfortunately.
That meant we had to make a huge amount of reductions at the, at the head office level.
And we tried to be very honest, very transparent with teams.
You try to be very fair on the affected people, uh, be very generous with payouts, but that
probably would have been, and, and do it very quickly.
And that probably would have been the toughest sort of eight weeks professionally that, that
I've ever been involved in.
I, uh, I've got to ask you about a story.
You mentioned mom and dad, uh, fair, but tough country folk described as.
Can you share the story?
Can you share the story of why you no longer eat chicken?
Chicken?
Well, back growing up in Swan Hill and country, as you know, Luke, you often, uh, eat what
you grow in, in some of those locations.
So we'd have the potty cars, we'd have the goats, we'd have the, the chickens.
And, you know, one day, and mom still denies this to this day, I should say, but my brothers
have backed me up on this is that we had a beautiful, uh, chicken meal at the end of
it.
I went out to feed my pet chicken who was named Peter Moore at the time after the Collingwood
legend, the great Peter Moore, the great Peter Moore, but Peter Moore wasn't in the
coop anymore.
Peter Moore had just been served up for dinner.
And, uh, and so that was sort of put me off chicken for life.
So I'm very firmly a steak man that stayed off chicken forever.
I love the patterns of, of great stories like yours.
And there's the idea that very hard to do what you do without the sense of self-leadership.
How do you go about feeling your best to run a team?
And the size that you do, what do you, what do you do to fill your cup up?
Yeah, it's a hard subject to talk about self-leadership, isn't it?
Cause it's very, um, subjective.
I think having the self-awareness and a model that works for you personally is probably
what's most critical.
And I think it's very different for each people.
And I think from a home and work life perspective, you're kidding yourself if there's not compromises
both sides.
And I think that's sort of inevitable, but I think it comes.
It comes back to principles about how you run your business and how you run your life.
And that's about capital allocation.
You have a defined amount of money to invest, or you have a defined amount of hours in the
day.
And you've just got to be very methodical about how you allocate that.
Personally, for me, I like to get into work very early, i.e.
6am, but then I like to leave at about 4.30 and spend some time at home in the evenings.
It's a very, it's always a challenge and it's going to have to be something that people
find individually work for.
And I think in the modern workforce, there's no better time to be flexible in terms of
finding a solution that works best for an individual.
And you can get through the door at 4.30 and switch off.
Do you find you got that distance?
So you've got it all nailed during the day most of the time?
Oh, not really in so much as my son will say I'm on the phone the whole time, but I'm very
much switch on and switch off.
So I take a call, put the phone down and I've switched off again, or pick the phone up,
do an email, put it down.
Everything becomes a bit integrated and melded, but it works for me.
It may not work for everyone else, but I think that's where you've just got to find whatever
model works best for you.
Has there been one piece of leadership advice that you pass on most?
From a leadership perspective, there's heaps of them, right?
I don't think there's ever one principle.
There is always lots of little learnings that you take along the journey that you try to
apply to your own learning.
I look at it.
And when you first.
As a sort of young manager, start appearing in places like board meetings.
So there's no more intimidating environment than a public company board meeting.
And I look early at the health scope days and we had Ron Evans, a great AFL commissioner
who was our deputy chairman at health scope and going in to present to Ron and the board
on the performance of the business you're responsible for is an incredibly intimidating
environment.
And.
And Bruce said to me a number of times that when you go into a board meeting, you can
never make your career in a boardroom, but you can certainly stuff it up.
So I think you go in and just be very methodical about approach, very, um, consistent, very
measured and very factual.
So I think that is probably what's sort of guided my approach, certainly to board meetings.
So not trying to oversell or undersell, just stick to this is the.
The facts and be clear and consistent.
Is that.
Exactly.
You don't want to go, it's not the sort of environment you want to go in there and try
and shoot the lights out because you're likely to spray it, spray it out of bounds on the
full.
I love, um, the idea of vision and Australian venue is an amazing vision.
That's really been yours.
And then you go in and run it and then you've got, you know, I'm not sure what the headcount
would be.
You'd employ a lot of people now, maybe you can share that with us, but how do you go
about sharing that vision?
That's really clear to you with that bigger scope of people.
Yeah.
We have.
8,500 people across the 230 venues, which is spread all across Australia and New Zealand.
So it really is that mix between spending time on the road.
It sounds ridiculous, but you know, I'm very focused on getting to every venue.
Every year and just spending time inside venues, talking to the teams on the ground,
understanding what their challenges are, and then learning from those and applying those
learnings.
I think the other strategy that you use is similar, obviously, listen to your podcast
with the CR Bunnings and spoke about their approach with workplace, which we also use
to try and have that top down approach and that interactive approach with the team where
you try and impart where you see vision.
And I think it's in modeling behavior.
I mean, one thing that's very important to myself as a business is how much the customers
enjoy the pubs when they're in them.
And, and you have very.
Very rich information that once again, you probably didn't have 20 years ago.
You look at customer reviews, we get about 120,000 customer reviews across our business
every year.
And inevitably some are negative, about 3% of our reviews are negative.
So we look at those as a incredible learning opportunity whereby any one or two star review,
we get instantly to our email for myself and the chief operating officer and the chief
marketing officer.
And then.
It's incredible how much little nuggets of gold you get in those that you can use to
sort of drive decision-making, understand if a venue is going off and, but just, and
directly engaging with the teams on the ground to sort of really impart one of those
visions is that customer experience is really critical in our sorts of venues.
So it's really a mix of being able to spend time in venues, talking to people and having
that sort of top down approach and trying to just be visible and share.
You're a very humble location.
Be way about you, Paul.
And I've, I've had the pleasure of having a beer with you in one of your venues and
I just watch you sit at the bar, you go up and order.
You often know the person's name, but have you found that valuable?
And it sounds like you like meeting in your venues and, and do they always recognize you
or can you fly under the radar?
I can very, I can very easily fly under the radar, but, but I do love spending time with
the team in venue.
They're just, as you said, they're just great places.
And I don't think people outside Australia really.
Understand the psyche of the Australian culture and how important pubs are to that
Australian culture and just what a critical infrastructure that we have and how lucky
are we that we have 9,500 incredible venues, incredible meeting places, places that we
can share with family, share with mates, watch sport.
It's just quite a unique model.
Yeah.
Long may it continue.
It feels like we're losing a few more to apartments a bit more quickly than we would like.
The idea of curiosity, we see something really consistent with successful people and leaders
like you.
Do you go down different rabbit holes of curiosity?
Can you share one with us?
Oh yeah.
All the time.
I think, um, once again, coming from outside the pub industry enables you to come in and
sort of ask those stupid questions that you would, wouldn't otherwise normally ask.
And you can ask them with a straight face.
And so you look at things like, you know, why are certain things done a certain way?
And you can challenge that sort of status quo and you can introduce new technology.
I spoke about things like order at table.
When we looked at investing in Mr.
Yum, the order at table tool at the time, everyone thought we were ridiculous.
No one would ever order through their phone to get a beer from a bar that was a hundred
meters away.
But now like 25% of our revenue comes through order at table tool.
We're playing with things like AI at the moment where we're looking at things like what do
customers want?
Within venues, what learnings can we take and then apply them over multiple venues?
We're looking at things like AI for things like labor forecasting, where we can say,
okay, we've Collingwood plays Carlton on a Friday night.
There's 90,000 people and the temperature is 13 degrees and it's raining.
How many people do we need to staff the Duke of Wellington before the game?
So it's trying to leverage that technology and using new technology to continually help
improve the business.
I keep thinking of my dad listening to you, Paul, where he would just be a smile from
ear to ear because growing up listening to him, you know, walk into the pub and too
many people on and he was, you know, he was a pretty calm, cool collector, but he hated
it when there was someone had not got the roster to write.
It's both sides too, right?
Like you got too many on, but there's nothing worse than when you got a full bar and they're
six deep and you're leaving revenue on the table.
So it goes both ways.
Just as bad.
That's right.
Or the new person behind the bar that was spilling the beer and he was just, you know,
that's going down the drain.
I can't believe it, but I love where you're going with AI and collaboration is a huge
part of the world that we're in.
And we've loved having you part of our leader group, Paul.
And I know so many people have enjoyed the wisdom that you've brought to the table, but
this idea that the cost of leadership is time.
And you mentioned a bit of how you struck for your day to still be across eight and
a half thousand staff, have your own family life.
How do you find that balance?
I think it really comes down to how you allocate your time and allocate your day and just staying
really focused on.
What adds value, what doesn't add value and try and avoid things that don't add value
to your business.
I think very much, um, as a sort of business to consumer business, you've got to be very
focused on the customer and very focused on the team who's delivering that service to
the customer.
And if you're forever pulling back on what are your key levers and is what you're doing
in your business consistent with driving those key levers in our case, organic growth within
a business.
Then you can still go down rabbit holes, but pull yourself back out pretty quickly because
you can say, okay, I've spent two hours on this.
Is this improving the customer experience in the pubs?
Is it helping the team?
If it's neither of those, you're better off sort of moving on and, and picking something
out.
So you end up kissing a lot of frogs and trying different things, but you just got to stay
disciplined to those principles.
Do you have a mantra with communication?
I suppose you have to be sophisticated with it.
The scale that you've got now, have you got a system around that?
I think it is.
It is really about having sort of clear, concise messaging.
And I think being conscious of all types of communication, I think people sort of typecast
talking as communication, but it's just as important to be really actively listening.
So that's where I do have to really pull myself in and say, just put the phone down and concentrate
on the person in front of you.
Look at their body language.
Look at what they're saying to you.
Look at where the challenges are and try and work through and sort of solve those.
And I think the other thing is being very clear and decisive on your messaging.
We've done, there's a lot of studies out there that show when you meet someone new, what
you do within that first sort of, you know, 30 seconds to a minute is really important
about getting your message across.
So that's the other thing I really try and focus on when I'm in a meeting or meeting
someone new for a half an hour or an hour, just go in and really understand what are
the key messages that you've got.
Want to get across and do it within the first minute or so, because if you can do that and
you still got their attention, then hopefully something comes from it.
Oh, it's a great, um, why you've described that point.
You're right.
Is it, you almost instantaneously can feel someone's listening to your game and it's
happened to the first 30 seconds.
And if they're glancing at their phone or looking over your shoulder, it's almost like
it's done, isn't it?
In that time.
I haven't thought of it that way, but you're right, isn't it?
If you're not paying attention, it's, it's a waste of everyone's time.
It is.
And I think it's one thing, you, you know,
how bad it is when you're talking to someone and they're not concentrating and focusing
on you.
I have to pull myself up and say, this, this is how you're being perceived by other people.
So put the phone down.
Don't glance at the phone while someone's trying to tell you something.
It's something I've got to work on and stay really focused on.
Yeah.
Brilliant.
Who has been the greatest leader in your life?
Oh, well, other than those sort of two mentors, Bruce and Vita, I think family and, and mum
and dad have always been incredibly supportive of myself.
And, and then you look at.
You know, who's out there globally, big titans of industries to see who you can learn from
as well.
But I think really trying to take the best out of Bruce and Vita has probably influenced
me most of all.
What do mum and dad think when they, you know, you sit back, you go back to the farm and
you catch up and you're in the old family house you grew up in and do they smile or
do they, are they surprised?
What do they think?
Oh yeah.
I think, um, you know, our mums and dads are like, they're surprised with whatever you
do and pleased with whatever.
I'm proud of whatever you do.
You know, I was over overseas last week and there was an article in the age about what
was going on in the St. Kilda market and mum rang and said, oh, I saw you in the paper.
You know, I think anything that you do is, is a surprise, but you know, they're always
parents always proud, aren't they?
Of whatever you're doing.
And they're proud of, uh, my other two brothers and sisters equally.
We're a bit obsessed with collaboration.
As we said, it's been great to have you in our leader connect world and curating those
groups around the globe.
Have you thought of a, you know, you've had reach with a number of different people.
Has there been someone you thought, God, I'd love to connect or collaborate with them in
any of your passions?
I think if you look at who are some of the global leaders out there in our industry,
you can, and part of what we do is go around and see what is trending globally.
What's new food and beverage concepts coming.
So going and looking internationally, there's, I was in the States recently looking at businesses
like there's a guy called Danny Meyer who runs a business site, union square.
Hospitality and, and that's an incredible food and beverage led business in New York.
He he's an incredible collaborator.
And I think what sort of scales he got out of, well, he, he's got only about 10 venues,
but just the attention to detail in those 10 venues and they're far more restaurant
led venues.
It's just great to go in there as a customer and pick up on those interaction points they
have with, with each customer and just really try and learn off those models and apply those
learnings.
Yeah.
And I think more broadly.
You can look at great investors of, uh, over the journey, people like Charlie Munger, those
sort of guys, you can just learn a lot from listening to people who take what is a relatively
complex situation and can just distill it in a very simple way.
And Paul, you seem to be a great sharer.
You're an open book, even with other people in the industry, you don't get concerned about,
Hey, this is what we're doing.
This is how we purchase.
And can we help you?
It's a great trade of yours.
Is that something?
You've been focused on as well?
Was it?
I think Australian hospitality is very unique in its collaboration and cooperation.
It's a double-edged sword in that it's not the sort of industry where there's a lot of
publicly available data.
So I will often ring mentors and helpers within the industry that says, Oh, our trade is doing
this in Victoria.
How's your going?
Because ultimately it's one of those industries where the rising tide floats all boats.
And if we have a stronger hospitality industry, generally.
I think that's what makes Australian hospitality so unique in that you've got space for that
incredible 120 seats, small bar, large restaurants, bigger corporate players like us.
It's a very unique industry that all those groups can coexist and do well and learn from
each other.
The intensity.
The intensity of CareNurse from Swan Hill turned into one of the great business success
stories is an incredible story to share.
I've followed with great interest, Paul, and I love how clear you are and you're thinking.
Awesome to catch up with you today.
Thanks for joining me.
Thanks so much, guys.
Thanks for listening to another episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Huge thanks, as always, to our great friends at Temper, and we encourage you to check out
our Leader Connect program.
New episodes are out every Wednesday morning at 6 a.m.