For me, vulnerability is really close to honesty.
What am I prepared to share with the world about who I am?
And Renee talks about this a lot.
It doesn't mean full exposure because, you know,
you need to also feel safe enough to be vulnerable.
But if you can be honest about where you're at, you can adapt.
And when we're not vulnerable, it's because we're unwilling to do that.
And that means that we have a boundary up somewhere.
We're afraid of something and that results in conformity.
Yes, people, everything being a little bit less diverse,
a little bit more homogenous.
And to me, that means you won't go quite as far
as you possibly could to your own edge.
Hello and welcome to another episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
At Alita, we are passionate about inspiring connections
and creating a world of collaboration.
Our signature program, Alita Connect, curates groups of five to six leaders
from diverse backgrounds in sport, industry, social venture,
and the arts who come together to learn, to connect, and to collaborate.
Kirsten King, founder of Fluidform Pilates.
It's been amazing.
Here you are on this Zoom call, feeling within the first session
like you intimately know these people and care for them.
And then all of a sudden realising that even though you're
in totally different industries, we're all going through the same thing
or we've been through it and we can help each other
or there's just this hurdle that you can't,
you can't see past and then you share it with the group
and there's five answers in 40 minutes and you think,
I have not slept for two weeks thinking about that.
Like, how is this possible?
Craig McRae, senior coach of the Collingwood Football Club.
You're listening to stories and the breadcrumbs of what makes success
and I constantly get something out of these Zoom calls and catch-ups
because we're all living the same stuff, aren't we?
Extraordinary people with extraordinary experience.
What happens there is magical.
The Empowering Leaders podcast is proudly brought to you
by Victoria University, where cutting-edge sports
and exercise science facilities like heat chambers, performance labs
and altitude environments mean VU is ranked seventh in the world
for sports science.
VU, uniquely you.
As always, a big thank you to Jason Nicholas and his team
at Temper Bedding, a mattress like no other.
If you enjoy listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast,
be sure to subscribe and please,
if you have a moment, we would love you to leave a review
so we can reach more listeners and empower more leaders.
Today we have an incredible guest,
someone who has transformed the way elite athletes, leaders
and organisations think about performance, fear and human connection.
Dr Pippa Grange is a psychologist, author and culture coach
best known for her groundbreaking work with England's national football team,
helping them to shift their mindset from fear-driven performance
to true psychological freedom.
Pippa's career began in Australia, where she worked extensively
in sports psychology, advising many AFL teams
and other elite sporting organisations before taking on the role
of head of people and team development at England's football association,
the oldest football association in the world.
It was there that she played a pivotal role in transforming
England's national football team, shifting their focus
from external pressures to a more connected, fearless mindset,
one that helped drive the historic success at the 2018 World Cup.
Pippa's impact on the sport has been a key part of her career.
She's been a part of the sport since she was a kid.
Pippa's impact on the English team was so great,
it's now being portrayed across the UK in the critically acclaimed
Dear England, an award-winning play about the journey
to reshape English football.
Beyond sport, Pippa's influence extends into leadership
and culture building.
She's often been compared to thought leader, Brené Brown,
someone she personally admires and has collaborated with
in conversations around vulnerability, belonging
and courageous leadership.
Pippa's book, Fearless, How to Win at Life Without Losing Yourself,
challenges traditional ideas of success and offers
a more human-centred approach to high-performance football.
Pippa Grange is helping us all to understand the impact
of fear on performance and the pitfalls of operating
with clenched fists rather than an open heart.
Pippa, it was a big introduction, but it's been a big life.
Nice to see you again.
It was nice to see you too, Luke.
Thank you.
I need to get that bio off you.
That was pretty impressive.
Thank you.
It's an impressive CV and a body of work that you've done
and you've had a huge influence on so many people.
How do you reflect on what you've been able to achieve?
You know, it's really interesting hearing somebody,
describe it like that.
For me, to be a psychologist, to be even an author
and a culture coach is to be in the background
and being in the background and really enabling other people
is where I feel best and where I really value the work
that gets done, not just me doing it,
but all the work that gets done in this way.
So I listen to it and I reflect on it and I'm humbled
and privileged.
But, you know, I always have a slight sort of unease
about being centred rather than being on the side
because I like being on the side.
Well, it's nice to put you right front and centre
for this conversation.
You're a brilliant author amongst all the other achievements
and your book, Fearless, has shown a whole generation
of people how to start living their life with less fear
and you find, you know, the real passions are deep
and fulfilment you talk about a lot in the book.
Can you share about some of the challenges that you share,
in the book, about growing up in a council estate in Yorkshire
and you tragically lost a brother to suicide?
Has it been a really personal thing for you trying
to teach the world about living with less fear?
You know, I think when you're a psychologist or when you're
a leader of any kind, actually, and you are trying
to help others, you're always working through yourself
and I think anybody who imagines that they can do this kind
of work without really understanding
where they're at and what happened for them
and how that becomes part of it.
So, yeah, absolutely it influenced the way I see
and the things I care about in a number of ways,
not just in terms of method and context and what I think works,
but also because it's personal.
So, you know, when I write about fear, it's personal.
When I write about trauma, it's personal.
When I write about performing from a more whole place,
which I'm writing about now, it's personal.
And it's sort of the job is to kind of,
like, get rid of the things that might get in the way
that have come from your own life and use them as context
so that you can help other people.
And I think that's the journey, but there's no way you have
any kind of life that's got any kind of adventure in it,
so to speak, that means that you can put that to the side
and compartmentalise and be some kind of separate expert.
You have to integrate both.
Pippa, I want to talk about your work
with the England National Soccer Team,
and it seems to me, as an outsider,
that almost the whole UK take their own sense of self-worth
based on the success or otherwise of the England National Team.
And then you come in as the culture coach
and solve that issue for a nation, if you like.
You can't get a bigger job in your world.
Can you share some of the practical ways
that you work with players under that extreme pressure
that they're under in that environment?
What are some practical things you do?
Mostly, Luke, it is actually not working directly with the players.
Yeah.
I think one of the things that you can do
when you're working with players, or not first,
is working with the leaders, the coaches,
the leaders that are surrounding the players.
Because especially in an international context,
the time that you have one-on-one with players is very minimal.
They're at their clubs and they come into camp,
and you might have them for a fifth of the year
if you're really lucky, depending on the tournament cycle.
That's really not long to start learning stuff.
So mostly you're editing and helping them adapt,
for the players directly.
And the deeper work is with coaches.
So that starts with real conversations with coaches,
especially around fear.
It starts with assessing what am I seeing in the culture?
What's not being talked about?
Where are the cringes and the points of avoidance
and what I call the ghosts in the walls?
If people were listening,
what would the ghosts be whispering about that nobody's saying?
And that's exactly what I want to go for when I come
into an organisation to say, what is it that we're doing?
What is it that we really need to be able to be more real
and more whole and more able to be free when you're putting
on a tournament or you have a big event?
And a lot of time that's emotional stuff
or psychological stuff like fear.
And then the work with players is secondary to that.
I think some of the most important work in England
or New Zealand Rugby League and different organisations
that I've worked with was helping the frontline leaders be really good
at seeing what they needed to do to help the psychology of the team.
And I'm not a big fan of the sort of wheeling guru
because I think it's really temporary.
Great information gets passed.
Maybe some things stick.
But if you don't actually have the deep time with the players,
you have to have a different method.
And for me, I call that working through,
which is I'm going to identify who is in authority in that organisation.
And that doesn't necessarily mean top dog, boss.
It means where's the power?
So sometimes that's a particular player.
Sometimes that's a particular coach or a physio or somebody else.
And if I'm working in a non-sport organisation,
it's the same thing.
In a group there's always a couple of people who are very influential
and I'm going to work with them and on them around helping them be amazing
and creating the sort of culture that lets people come alive
and really go to their own edge.
And on that note, Pippa, your influence suggests that if you get
to the key influences,
they can have that trickle-down effect on the rest of the organisation
or the rest of the team.
Absolutely.
Absolutely, yeah.
Culture is something that's made by what you resist and what you reward.
And that has to come in all sorts of different forms and different methods.
So the way that things get done like feedback gets given or a meeting gets run
or processes and practices come into play, they're all absolute culture builders
and that's not stuff that the players do or the workforce do generally.
That generally comes cascade, trickle-down and that's why I think it's really,
really important to build culture from the start with the top
and then come ground up.
Start with the top in terms of what practices, processes,
systems are in place and how things get done.
You've worked with elite leaders and CEOs and elite organisations around the globe.
Are there some common traits that you see that see people live the happiest
and most fulfilled lives?
That you talk about in your book?
Is there some patterns that you can see?
Most definitely.
I think the number one thing for me is seeing, understanding
and addressing not good enough fear.
So it doesn't matter how accomplished you are in your career,
how far you've got, almost all of us have some not good enough fear kicking
around in the back, you know, and being able to really address that
and unravel that I think is essential for leaders.
The Fearless book is one of them.
It's all about that.
How do you get at that?
But I think connected to that is we talk a lot in leadership terms
about authenticity, right, like show up authentically.
But sometimes I think that that is just another role people play, you know,
and unless they really go there, unless they're really willing
and safe enough to go there themselves as leaders and start to understand
what's in their way, what do they want to avoid, what's the thing that they dread,
or fear most, or the relationship that's most tense for them
that they don't want to face into?
Because sometimes they are the things that unlock the freedom.
And so, you know, really, really mapping out where are the things
that you identify, if I were working with you, you know,
what are the things that you really think are your own blocks?
Because as soon as you see them and admit them or face them,
then we can get to work.
And that's so often there.
Small things are massive unlocks for psychological freedom.
I love that term you used, that not good enough fear that we've all got
within ourselves, and it plays out in you.
And then you moved into that idea that we're playing this role all the time
and how draining that is to show up at the school pick-up and want
to look a certain way so the other parents view you the way you want
or it's pretending all the time to be something so that we're so concerned
about what other people think.
And that's the fear you're talking about.
Not the fear of a burglar bursting into your house.
Yeah, exactly.
The moment fear versus the not good enough fear.
That's right.
And you're saying getting a handle on that and not the fake pretending
authentic but really being close as you can to who you really are.
Is that where you see freedom?
Is that how you describe it?
Yeah, that's exactly it.
And I don't think that most people fake on purpose.
You know, we need an in-between word between sort of honest and fake
because it's not sort of an intentional pretext.
But we just all are so acculturated into presenting ourselves
in particular ways and so acculturated into sort of this idea of needing
to look successful, whether that's as a parent or a professional
in any sort of way.
And really looking at where you think the gaps are.
Sometimes what you might need to let go of is as important as what you might
need to grow or build or change.
Yeah.
But unless you can see it yourself and identify it yourself,
it's really hard to show up real.
The show up real might be, you know, okay, I'm not going to look perfect today.
I'm not going to sound perfect today.
I don't know all the answers.
I'm running late.
I'm frazzled.
I'm in a caffeinated haze.
Whatever it is for you on that day, you know, you're allowed to be you.
And I think when we can really do that, we unravel some of that perfectionism
that is so prevalent.
And I think that's just something that we need to do
in people and especially in leaders.
Sometimes we think the further up the pecking order you get,
the easier that is, it's not true.
Actually, sometimes it amplifies as you're more visible to people,
you have more accountability, more responsibility.
So I just think it's something that we actually need
to intentionally cultivate.
We're living in this hyper-competitive world,
and we compete often, sometimes, unknownly against people
shallow versus winning deep. Can you share what that means to you? Yeah. So when I talk about
winning shallow is the kind of winning that may look great on the scoreboard, so to speak,
whatever that is for you. But it's driven by a scarcity mindset. It's winning so that you don't
fail. It's running towards success because you're afraid of what's chasing you rather than winning
deep, which is much more about what's possible here. Where's my potential? What might happen?
It's much more open. It's got a lot more freedom in it. And winning deep is associated with really,
really sort of deep-rooted meaning for the person. And I think sometimes we talk about purpose,
and obviously that's really important, but it's so much more subtle and nuanced than that. It's
like, you know, when you've had a deep win and you know, when you've had a shallow win,
I can't tell you how many athletes I've worked with that have had the big win.
And really what they feel immediately afterwards is relief, which is understandable. But then a
day or two later, they're thinking about the next win. They actually can't leave any space to
celebrate themselves or the achievement. Nothing's ever quite enough. And that's shallow winning.
It never compounds. You're just always chasing. And that is really,
really unfulfilling, actually. It's not nearly as, whether you've got the medal around your neck
or not, it's not really nearly as good as people think it is. And winning deep is where there's
been all the same blood, sweat, and tears in it, but there was something more that you were doing
it for and something that you trusted in yourself, in others, something you let go to, something you
took risks on that felt real. And it's not driven by scarcity. It's driven by possibility.
ISKRA When I was reading,
in your book, I thought of the Michael Jordan documentary, The Last Dance. And I'm conflicted
over it because it looks, I'm assuming you've seen it, most of the world has. There appears
to be a body count of people that won championships that seem incredibly unfulfilled and don't look
back with any joy at all at that. And then you've got the six-time champion, maybe the greatest
athlete that's ever lived. And it was part of me to think, God, I'd love to have been on that team.
Regardless of how brutal it was, get me on that team. So I don't know, do you see that as winning
shallow or winning deep? I'm also conflicted about that. And I think they're not necessarily
one and done concepts. You might have periods where you're winning shallow and periods where
you're winning deep. But what I noticed in that documentary, I couldn't help focusing on it,
is watching Michael Jordan sitting in that big chair, tapping his whiskey glass, tapping his
glass.
There was a level of not enoughness about it that I think is probably quite unfulfilling.
And you see so many athletes achieve extraordinary things and unravel afterwards or express
dissatisfaction. And for me, what is the point of competition? It's chasing something for
fulfillment.
To find out what humans are capable of, to find out what you're capable of. And there's got to be
a point where it compounds, where you start to feel good about yourself, about your endeavor,
about the trust you put in this pursuit and your own ability. And if you're in that winning shallow
piece, as I think maybe Michael Jordan was for quite a lot of his career, you maybe don't feel
that. And you've interviewed some of his teammates. It'd be interesting to sort of see
how others feel about that. And I think that's a really good point.
And I think that's a really good point. And I think that's a really good point.
A lot of people felt about that body count too, because what is it to be in a team? What is it to
compete? What is it to win? Maybe it's more than your own glory. And he's extraordinary. He's
probably the best athlete, but what did it cost? Yeah, as I'm listening to you speak, I think
the sadness to think that there isn't deep relationships with any of those teammates.
And I think he was quite open about that, that there was not a connection at all, even with
the ones that played six championships.
As you're talking, could you win five or four or three or two and have great relationships? Is
that bigger success? And I probably think the answer is yes, isn't it? In my mind, as I play
that out, that to me, the greatest thing about playing team sport was the relationships that
you had for life afterwards. It's a big cost. If in winning, you've given up all of that for life,
that's a big price to pay, isn't it?
Yeah. I think about that word competition and the origin of the word has got sort of two different
roots.
It's an old French and an old Latin. Conquerere is the old Latin. And conquerere means to compete
against. And it's kind of like dominate over. It became dominate over to beast somebody, to be on
top, to be unquestionable, unassailable in your dominance. And the other origin of the word
was more like to run alongside.
So you can't find your very best unless you've got an amazing athlete running alongside you
to compete with. And that was more like testing your mettle, finding what you as a human being
are really capable of. I think of people like Kipchoge when I say that, and like extraordinary
athletes that really are testing the bounds of possibility rather than trying to dominate.
And there's something really interesting in our culture, especially our sports culture,
where we say, oh, I'm going to win. I'm going to win. I'm going to win. I'm going to win. I'm going to
win. And we seem to have picked up a lot of the time the rivalry. And our language is about the
rivalry and about smashing and dominating and conquering. And I think that sets a cultural
tone that is scarcity, that's glory and individual glory or individual team glory
against all else. And for me, the stronger possibilities are in the respect of competing
and the human potential in competing. And I think you've got,
all the same effort, all the same grit, all the same blood, sweat and tears, as I said,
to get you there. But the feeling is very, very different. And I think that's really sort of an
essential part of that. Are you winning shallow or deep? What and who was it for? And how do you feel?
We all are born different.
As we grow, the experiences we have develop into outlooks uniquely our own.
Charting our life's course. No one sees an idea, opinion or opportunity like you.
And no one sees you like VU. Victoria University. Uniquely you.
My name's Gabrielle. I'm studying law. What made me want to get into law is,
I guess, the reward you get after the feelings that you get for helping other people.
I'm really passionate about making sure that people have that voice,
people that don't feel like they can be heard. And that's something that's really important to me.
I have quite deep personal values. So it was really important to me to find a university
that aligns with those values. And VU's that for me.
At Alita, our signature program, Alita Connect, is something we're really passionate and proud of.
We bring together groups of five to six people around the globe from diverse backgrounds,
sport, industry, social venture and the arts, and come together to learn, to connect and to
collaborate.
The thing that I've loved about it is not just the meetings that we have with our group. It's
the thinking that you do for days and days afterwards. Someone says something and it
sparks a thought. And within my sport and within women's sport, I'm just someone who
I try to lead by keeping people talking about the issues. There's times when I think the person I'm
trying to convince is not listening to me. It actually got me thinking about this is how I
need to address my communication with them. So it was, I can't tell you how much I enjoyed it.
Yeah, I was thinking as you were talking about James Tompkins, I was lucky enough to interview
on this podcast. He's a six-time Olympian, one of the greatest Australian athletes, a triple gold
medal winner. And he referenced a couple of times, and I won't get this quite right, but the original
ode of the Olympics, the original creed, which was talking about the wholeness of a person and that
you needed great academics for the mind and you needed spirituality for the soul. And the physical
part was just part of that. And I think that's what I've learned. And I think that's what I've
learned. And I think that's what I've learned. And I think that's what I've learned. And I think
of the all-round performer and you celebrated the great all-round human being, not just
the athlete who could run the fastest or the longest. And maybe it feels as though our world's
gone the other way, isn't it? That we don't value the whole rounded part that you're talking about,
that maybe is sort of fearing less and living a more wholesome life.
Yeah, I totally agree with that. Two words you use there, whole and soul,
that I think are really central in this. Human performance, human endeavour,
whether it's sort of scientific breakthrough or Olympic gold, has always been about understanding
ourselves. How far can we go? What are we? Who are we? What's possible? And I think as we've got
more excellent at the technical, we've lost something in there. We've kind of mechanised
ourselves a little bit, become a little bit maybe more robotic than we ought to be, a bit more
narrow, a bit more expert. And then in the deepening of expertise, potentially we've lost
some wholeness. And that for me is really a dreadful shame and something that we need to get
back to, especially for young people, young athletes. Renee Brown's a huge fan of your work,
Pippa, and references it regularly. And you've collaborated with her and the champion of the
word vulnerability is how I think of her. How big a role does that play for you in success in life,
being able to show up and be vulnerable?
Well, for me, vulnerability is really close to honesty. What am I prepared to share
with the world about who I am? And that doesn't mean you have to expose yourself.
And Renee talks about this a lot. It doesn't mean full exposure because you need to also feel safe
enough to be vulnerable. But if you can be honest about where you're at, you can adapt,
you can edit, you can show commitment, you can show love,
you can go deeper. And those things for me are massive performance factors. So vulnerability
is smack bang in the middle. And when we're not vulnerable, it's because we're unwilling to do
that. And that means that we have a boundary up somewhere. We're afraid of something and we're
going to do it our way. And that for me results in conformity. Yes, people, everything being a
little bit less diverse, a little bit more homogenous. And to me, that means you won't go
quite as far.
As you possibly could to your own edge.
Pippa, I mentioned in the intro that your work with the England football team has now been part
of a major theatre production. And Here England explores that psychology of the winning and the
culture shift in England football. What's that been like for you to see some of your work on the
stage?
I mean, it's an extraordinary privilege. And I'm really thrilled for what it's done for
sports psychology and the culture of sport. It's very weird to watch somebody play,
you on stage. The first time I went, I guess I'd met James Graham, the playwright and the first cast.
And I went and watched a play and I was cringing all the way through. But that's because I like
being on the sideline as well. But the second time I saw it, I could see the fun in it. And I just
thought, wow, that's really extraordinary that some of that work can result in other people even
thinking about whether they're winning.
Deep or shallow, whether they're living and performing with fear or if there's a better
option.
Pippa, you're writing again at the moment. You shared a little earlier about chronic
overperformance and how we can be more regenerative and whole in the way we approach
performance. Can you give us a little insight into what's struck a chord with you at the moment?
I've noticed over sort of, you know, 25 year career working with high performers that
there's a lot of patterns. And some of those patterns are what we've spoke about before,
that people don't feel.
As good as they could. And part of that is fear. But I also think that one of the behavioural
patterns that comes out of that is the sort of never quit mentality, but applied large
into all things in life. And I just see a lot of people really overperforming rather than performing
in a whole and excellent way. So I've been writing about and thinking about the sort of
narratives that underpin what it is that we do and sort of narratives of,
things like optimisation. It's never okay not to improve in the stories that we have about who we
are. And I think that that is really leaves us very thirsty, spiritually and otherwise. And I
really genuinely don't believe that that takes us to best performance. So there are moments to push,
but we're not diverse in it. We live push rush all the time. So optimisation is one example.
Another example is how,
sort of caught up we are in the sort of what I call the market narrative of like everything needs to be
visibly seen to be bigger, more, have more, do more, be more. And we see that in all sorts of ways
with performers and all of, I'm talking about all of us as performers. So I'm exploring that.
I'm exploring how that leads to feelings of less and sadness and burnout. And then what are the
tipping points that turn us into,
living from a more whole place? I describe it as whole being. And then, you know, what would we
need to do if we were regenerative in our performances? How, what would we shift? Because
we still want to perform. Performing feels great, right? But to do it the same way all the time with
no off button, I think we've got a little bit caught up in a cultural narrative that doesn't
serve us as human beings. And the whole point is life.
Yeah. And we sometimes miss the point of life in pursuit of all these things, as you write
that beautifully.
In the race to have more and be more and be seen to do more. And people find it hard to talk about
soul or talk about love or even love in sport, you know, is how would you even introduce that? But
you're saying that they're the missing ingredients, that we're not actually
getting to that sort of deeper sense of what living is all about. Is that a question you're
asking?
Yeah, absolutely. For me, the pursuit of sport, this is why I think that those sort of root
origins of the word competition,
are so interesting, because it's all love. Everything I've ever seen in sport from working
with like six year olds through to vets, you know, it's about love. It's, it's, you know,
joy and potential and expression. And, you know, there are moments of in any sport, there's
aggression, and there's, there is dominance over and all of those things, but they've just become
so big. And they've been marketed, basically, to be,
too central. And actually, when you ask anybody, any athlete, or any coach, what is it that you got
from this? And they're going to that really, when you get down to the bottom of the ladder,
they're going to say love. You know, I felt something I didn't know was possible to feel.
I connected to people, to audiences, to fans, to teammates, and self love as well, if we get it
right. I think it's all about love. And then this, this question of soul, you know, which,
it's pretty terrifying, turning up and talking to a bunch of blokes with their arms folded,
usually blokes, in my case, in my career, talking about soul, and you know, that people are
imagining, oh, what is this? Where is this going? But actually, the sort of pursuit of something
else, something bigger, that, that is where that sits. You know, when we reduce it all to mechanics,
and the technical, and the expert, and the,
the mental part of it, and the, the piece that we have to say, why we can't fail,
and the this window only, you miss soul. And you miss love. And the whole thing has got a high risk
of not being worth it.
The saddest thing for me is, we all do things initially, because we love them when we're kids,
or we kick a ball because we're fascinated and we love it. And then you've witnessed it many
times over. And we've all seen this high profile athlete, who are all suffering performance anxiety,
or you can see the love of the sports completely drained out of them. And,
Yeah.
that that love of playing the game essentially goes with trying to be a professional.
Yeah. And sometimes with a coach or a leadership group in an organisation, I might ask,
what is it that you can't give up as a starting question, you know, and see where they're at in
terms of this idea of scoreboard winning versus what is this as a human endeavour? And of course,
there's the commerciality and all the other things that you have to roll into that,
but then they don't have to be exclusive. You know, if you work and play with love and soul,
it doesn't mean that everything else is going to go horribly wrong. It means that you actually are
motivated differently. Your sense of why is different and deeper. And then all the things
that we were talking about before around ability to accept change or to go through volatile periods
or vulnerable periods or to deepen commitment.
They're much deeper and much stronger, but you can't force that. You have to do it through love
and soul. And so, but it's scary for people if they feel it's got to be now, it's got to be this way.
There'll be old school coaches listening to that going, what do you mean, let go of
the competitive element and that can't possibly work. But you're saying even in the most elite
environments, if you simplify it back down to that and you regain your love and your connection
for what you're doing and your connection to your team,
find something deeper, performance is going to go up. That's what the research is saying.
That's the guts of it. And it's actually not about lowering competition. Competition's
brilliant. Competition's very natural to us as a human mammal. But it's, what does that mean to
you? Can you compete to find what you've got, find what the team's got and take the threat
and the scarcity out of it, take the urgency out of it and think about human,
potential. That's where it's at. That's the gold in it. So it's method, it's all method,
especially for the old school coaches who have really got, a lot of those people have got wins
on the board and experience doing it a particular way. But what we also have to remember is how much
the world changes and how the younger generation of people who are listening have so many different
influences than they did even 15, 20 years ago.
And we've got to adapt with it. And so understanding what it is to help them
find the very essence of sport that that old school coach felt when they were first pulling
their boots on, why did they love it? And where is that essence now in it? And the mentorship
and the care and the adult figures and the guidance, all the things that we don't talk
about in sport that are so critical and why coaches matter so much, especially now at this
moment.
For young people, that's, you know, we need, we need that is just what is the essence and
is it still vibrant for you? Is it still vibrant or has that culture of scarcity and that little
bit of not good enough fear and a little bit of push and rush taken over? And where does fear sit
and how can you let go of it? Because they've got everything they need, but fear gets in the way.
The brilliant way you articulate it. And I think it just makes sense when you boil it down,
but we get lost.
In the race of life, as you described, a bit obsessed with this idea that there's patterns
of what makes people successful and someone as thought out as you, I'm curious in these answers
and where idea of sort of self-leadership, but that it's hard to lead anyone else without this
idea of what you do to feel your best so you can lead others effectively. Can you share with us
what fills your bucket up so that you can be the best for others?
You know, I think one of the most important things that I have learned,
and that I do myself, I strive to do myself, but I also have seen in great leaders is letting go.
So I think, you know, when you fail or you stuff something up, or even when you really had
something that you thought was all promise and you loved it, sometimes you've got to let it go.
And that's really hard. There's like a living grief that goes with those things. And being
able to metabolize and compost that and move is really important. There's plenty of times where
we've all taken a wrong turn or maybe a wrong role or, you know, a wrong partnership, or it shows
up in all sorts of ways in life. But how can you let go and ground yourself and go again, move again,
not just from the perspective of resilience and bounce back, but in terms of genuinely composting
and growing again? You know, I think that's so important and very, very underrated as a sort of
a factor for whole being and a factor for performance.
You've got a specific example.
On that, Pippa, that you've been able to just, right, that turn didn't work out. Have you got
one that springs to mind?
Yeah. One that was quite hard for me, but after I was at England and I went to work with an
organization called Right to Dream, who I really loved. Right to Dream, they had a football club
in Denmark, in Copenhagen, and they had academies in Ghana. And I went as a chief of culture,
loved it. And then they actually got,
acquired by an organization which enabled them to really fund what was going to happen next and
scale. But in that scaling and that changing, and especially because they ended up in North America
rather than back in the UK, I wasn't going to be able to do my work there. And I didn't want to be
on a plane all the time. And I really cared about the organization. So I had to let go. You know,
I really found some grief in that because I cared deeply, but it wasn't the right fit.
So it wasn't going to be the right fit in a way that let me stay whole. So sometimes you get one
of those, you know, and I still really care about them, but I had to let it go because it wasn't
going to be right. And every time you do that and you let it settle, something else grows out of it.
Is there one piece of leadership advice that you pass on the most?
You know, I'm not a fan of the one piece or the silver bullet, but because it's always so nuanced
for me. But I suppose it's always so nuanced for me, but I suppose it's always so nuanced for me,
the thing I would say is to get to know yourself, genuinely, actually get to know yourself and
especially what you prefer to avoid. Because you as a leader, however good you are at the thing
that you do, you're the instrument of the work. So unless you're well-tuned, unless you actually
understand you, you're not going to be able to play it as well. And, you know, I think that's
really critical. So there's a lot of times we get really good at stuff, but we still don't
know who we are. Yeah, beautifully said. You've had a unique vision for the way that culture
should operate and you've evolved it over time and shown up in these organisations that have
some challenge. How have you been able to get others on board with the vision that you've been
pretty clear on for yourself? That's not always easy. I think things are changing. But one thing
that I would say is that, and again, it's another strange word sometimes in sport, but intimacy.
So to be able to talk honestly and frankly and sincerely and in a real way with the people who
are the decision makers and the culture makers and to say what I mean, to walk in the door and
say what I mean rather than hedge, win favour, you know, find the lay of the land. You've got to run
a parallel process with doing that and make sure that you're credible and trusted, but you actually
have to speak straight. You've got to speak straight. You've got to speak straight. You've
got to speak straight too about what you see and what you mean and build partnership. So I think
that that's where it starts of actually saying really what you mean when you go in and you're
building culture or working on human potential, human performance. So people that I have the
privilege of sitting down with this situation is normally inherently curious, Pippa, and that
curiosity can take them down different rabbit holes. Have you got an example of a curiosity
you've been down of late? I'm always here. I'm in a warren of curiosity, not just one rabbit hole.
I live in that. I think probably the one that stands out for me is I'm always curious about
why people resist things. Where does resistance come from? Is it actually fear? Is it genuinely
informed by experience? And what does it get in the way of? So often when I work with leaders,
I do something called slow coaching.
Where a coach or a leader will come and I'll spend, say, three days with them. And the first
day and a half is just regrounding, recentering. You might be out hiking. They might be in the
sauna in the ice bath. They might be just getting back in their body, basically, so they can
think spaciously. And one of the things quite often that I speak about with coaches or leaders
when I do that is, what is it that you'd rather avoid?
Where are your points of resistance? And I always get really curious about what comes up there. It
informs the rest of the work for the slow coaching. And I think it just lets you go
layers and layers and layers deeper.
We love this quote that the cost of leadership is time. How have you been able to manage that and
still live the balanced life that allows you to live the way you want to without fear and showing
up authentically yourself? Can you share that path for you?
I don't.
I don't always get that right. I haven't always got that right. Because I'm very curious, I can
easily be too busy. But I've really, I had to have a think about what I cared most about a few years
back, you know, as I was getting too tired and a bit burnt out. And just let things go. So now I
do work that I care most about, which means some sacrifices and a lot more saying no when I would
like to help. But I have to say no a lot more. And, you know, I think it's really important to
be curious. And I think that's a really important part and really really important for me. I absolutely
need the time on learning and curiosity. And I absolutely need time outside. I could actually live in a
rabbit warren, I think. And where I live in the world as well, it allows me to be sort of outside and I
find vibrancy there. And so I've got really attuned to how I'm actually feeling. You know, where am I at in myenn
space have i created for myself and if i'm going to work with somebody if i'm going to
coach somebody um and they've given me the privilege of having their time and their
vulnerability then i need to show up in good shape so that becomes like a central reason for me to
do less actually um and i do so much less than i used to now but i just really like the things
that i do people the idea of understanding how you communicate you get that precious time in
organizations and you've already described how nuanced it is to to be able to come in with your
message you have a mantra when it comes to how you communicate in your work i don't know that
i've described it as a mantra but most certainly i would go for you know my my response to that
would be to to do your very best to show up honestly you know and again
isn't about avoiding pretending or or deceit in any way but to just show more of what you
are about and what you care about and then trust that if it's right for that organization or that
leader or that set of leaders then that then naturally a trust and a partnership will develop
but you know that is where you find influence rather than selling or promoting that is where
you find genuine connection rather than pushing and that's
that's always better always better for me who's been the greatest leader in your life
i think my husband actually you know who's a um it's easy to just sort of go to a professional
setting for thinking about leadership but he leads so differently to me he's he's um he's really
um people oriented in a sort of community sense he's much more social than i am
and his way of leading is to really stick with a problem and stick with a purpose
and until it's resolved and he showed me so much more about walking with
people in different ways um more subtle ways you know because the work i'd done had been sort of
a formal helper and he helps in really different ways and he's so in service so i think he's
probably been the best leader in my life yeah what a great answer we're a bit obsessed with
this idea of collaboration if you're on what it's like when you put inspiring people together and
how great things happen and yeah you've collaborated
around the world with extraordinary people has there been one person that you thought
wow i'd love to you know when in one of your passions in life is there a name that springs to
mind you know um more recently in the last sort of five years i know it's mad to do more doctoral
work but i did and i went down the path of ecology and eat what's called eco psychology or ecological
psychology which is about understanding how the way things work in the natural world is the same
way that things
work in the human mind and the human world so this sort of idea of culture and nature coming
together it's a bit of biomimicry it's a bit of um sort of systems thinking so there's a couple of
like amazing people in that world um that i would really love to to spend time with and collaborate
with there's a guy merlin sheldrake who's done all the stuff on mycelial networks and how things
collaborate underground and how how we know so little about it but it's so
informative it's such a different form of intelligence so i think i would go that way
actually to to find more people who think about nature and culture together and see if i can bring
that i don't think i've ever spoken to anyone who's done two doctoral degrees people it's a
great effort and you know the wealth of knowledge that you've brought to the world and and really
changed the way people think and continue to think in such a profound way is a great message for all
of us around the race of life and slowing down and that fear that's in all of us is a great message for
us if we stop and think about it we're all playing sometimes a role that we you know creeps into our
life and yeah it certainly have made me stop and think tonight about what's important and and you
know slowing down and uh it's a short life and i think you've got a great perspective on how to
live the best version of it it's great to see you again and really appreciate you taking the time
yeah thank you so much luke and thank you for the work that you do too the conversations are
excellent and um yeah i'm really happy to spend the time with you great to see you