This week's conversation is with a truly remarkable Australian in my mind, Professor Scott O'Neill,
an Australian scientist who is on the path to eliminate dengue fever around the world.
You hear him talk about collaborating with some of the most influential leaders around the world.
His perseverance and dedication to impact so many lives is one of the great stories of leadership and success.
The challenge doesn't end. You have to keep going out there and showing people the benefit and how it's working and how it could benefit other communities.
And so, yeah, the work continues. If our goal is really not about the discovery, our goal is about having the impact.
It always feels like a real privilege to learn from incredible leaders like Professor Scott O'Neill.
It's the basis for the work we do in our leadership business, Alita.
And if you're interested in leading, learning and collaborating, check out our signature Alita Connect program.
Head to alitacollective.com.
Professor Scott O'Neill is an extraordinary Australian scientist, internationally recognised as the founder of the World Mosquito Program.
His breakthrough innovation of infecting mosquito communities with Wolbachia virus is proving to eliminate dengue fever,
which affects 400 million people annually, and other mosquito-borne viruses like yellow fever and Zika.
It is a truly remarkable scientific achievement.
Professor O'Neill's academic career has increased.
He's been a member of the Australian Academy of Science, the American Association for the Advancement of Science,
and the American Academy of Microbiology.
Professor Scott O'Neill, it's a great honour to spend some time with you.
Thanks for joining me today on the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Hi, Luke. Nice to be here.
Scott, it's an incredible story.
I think, how does an obscure bacteria like Wolbachia effectively become the centre of your life?
The potential to impact hundreds of millions of people around the world in a positive way.
Can you tell us how it all came about?
Well, it actually started a long time ago when I was a student studying for my PhD,
and I was introduced to this thing called Wolbachia, this bacteria, by my professor of the time at the University of Queensland.
And I got really just absorbed and fascinated with just the unusual things that this bacteria could do to insects.
But not just that, I was interested in how we might be able to utilise the power of this bacteria
to help in the battle against mosquito-transmitted diseases.
And so, you know, it's something that caught my eye many years ago.
I was directed to it, and I've been working with it my whole life, academic life now.
Can we go back a little step to dengue fever?
It's probably the most known mosquito-borne virus that you work with,
and I'm not sure how accurate the numbers are.
Yeah.
There's 400 million people around the globe.
But how bad is dengue fever, and how important is it to find a solution?
The numbers are estimates, but we estimate that around 400 million people get sick each year.
But even more scary than that number is that half of the world's population is at risk of getting the disease any given year,
virtually anywhere in the tropics of the world.
If you live anywhere in the tropics of the world, you're at risk.
And the terrible thing about it is there's really no...
There's no effective treatment for it.
And so, you just have to weather the sickness when you get it and hope that it's not so severe that you die from it.
And so, to understand, you know, without getting overly technical, Scott,
but it's amazing that you've been able to, you know, I understand fruit flies are affected with Wolbachia,
but effectively what happens is the mosquitoes get that and then it shortens their lifespan and their chance of passing on those diseases.
Is that a simple way to explain?
Yeah.
So, you know, the way I would say it is that we found this naturally occurring bacteria.
It only infects insects.
It doesn't infect people.
It's called Wolbachia.
And we found that about 50% of insects carry this bacteria naturally,
but not the mosquitoes that do all this disease transmission to people.
And the big technical breakthrough for us was that we were able to put this bacteria into the mosquito
that transmits diseases like dengue.
And when we did, we found that the viruses couldn't grow in the mosquito body.
And if they can't grow in the body, then they can't be transmitted between people.
And so we had a way to naturally block the transmission of these viruses in human communities
by introducing the bacteria to the mosquito population,
essentially almost like vaccinating all the mosquitoes naturally
so that they can no longer transmit the viruses between people.
And so it didn't require anything to be done to the human population.
No medicine or drugs for the humans,
just focusing on the mosquito and being able to eliminate transmission that way.
And part of the brilliance of what I love about what you've done
is that it doesn't involve insecticides.
It doesn't involve genetic modification.
And I'm assuming mosquitoes play a really important role in the ecosystem.
So for it to be safe, it's cost effective.
I understand it's incredibly effective at the same time.
Feels like the perfect solution in lots of ways.
Yeah, in many ways.
You know, it's got a lot of very desirable,
As you said, it doesn't kill the mosquitoes.
It just makes them harmless to people.
So they stay within the role.
If there is such a role that they might play in the ecosystem,
we're not spreading toxins around like insecticides that aren't that effective anyway,
but have a lot of knock-on effects into the environment.
So it's a really targeted green intervention.
But what I like most about it is that it self-sustains
so that once we deploy it,
we don't have to re-deploy it.
We don't have to re-deploy it.
Like with a vaccine,
you have to keep giving vaccines to newborn children or whatever.
With this, we put it out once and we're done.
And then it just keeps giving protection to communities
because the Wolbachia maintains itself in the mosquito population
and people get protected year after year.
So it's both sustainable and highly cost-effective.
And in the public, global public health area,
those are really key attributes that are needed
with a public health intervention
so that it's cheap and it sustains itself.
So many layers to this story.
And I also love, first of all, your genius to discover it,
to persevere because it wasn't an overnight success.
I mean, you've been toiling away for more than 20 years
to firstly get it to be proven in communities.
But the second part then is to scale this globally.
And that takes a whole different set of leadership skills.
Scott, I'm assuming a different part of your brain.
Can I ask you about part two?
What sort of leadership have you found within yourself?
You know, to firstly get this to work
and then the scaling part globally,
that must have been a second challenge.
Yeah, so I think, you know, firstly,
when you're doing anything that's very unusual or innovative,
there's always a lot of resistance to change.
And so, as you mentioned,
we've been sort of fighting uphill a little bit,
not just to show that we can do this technically,
but to gain acceptance of it
because it's different from what's been done in the past.
And so, you know, that's created a set of obstacles
that we've had to face.
It's required me and others in our team
to become effective communicators,
to be convincing people and doing advocacy
for the intervention that we've developed
so that people can understand it
and appreciate the value that it could bring.
And now, as you say, we're into the next phase now
of now that we've shown that it works.
We've currently protected around 10 million people
in 11 countries around the world so far in our journey so far.
But our goal is to get to 500 million,
and that's going to require, as you say,
a different set of skills
to be able to undertake that scale-up journey.
And so, again, you know, we're actively doing it
and it requires active advocacy for what we're doing
to drive the demand in communities
to make people aware of what we're doing
and to make it available to communities.
And so, yeah, there's different sets of skills
that have been needed across the whole journey.
That we've been travelling on and we do that.
I think we obtain those skills by mixing our team around
and we bring in new team members with different skill sets
as the challenges change.
And if anything, I think the contribution,
the leadership contribution,
the large one that I'm fortunate to be able to make
is that I think I naturally have a flair
for being able to help pick those teams
and to pick the individuals that we need at the right time
and to create an environment
where they want to collaborate with the rest of our scientists
and other people that work for us as well
to achieve the results we want.
So I think I'm a bit lucky in that I'm able to get together
and coalesce groups of quite different people
that are needed to execute on a really complex task.
And that is a brilliant skill
that clearly you've uncovered within yourself
and it's a real passion in the leaders that we talk to,
Professor O'Neill, around that idea of being able to collaborate
and to collaborate.
And get people on board.
You don't scale something like you have done
and the ambition to take it to 500 million people.
So was that just a natural thing you found
that you feel like you've got an ability
to get people on board with your vision?
Is that something that you discovered in this process
or was that evident for you at a younger age?
Yeah, I think, to tell you the truth,
I haven't really had a focus that much on it
and I don't just sort of do the introspection of what it is.
But I think, you know,
I think it's sort of,
it's something that has been natural
and I think, you know, in some ways
we're easy to work on a topic
that is relatively easy to motivate people around
because, you know, it's a good story we work on.
We're bringing hope to communities in the tropics,
poor people that wouldn't otherwise have it.
And so it's, I think, having passion about what we do
is a big assist in helping us to be effective
in being able to build the teams we require.
But, you know, I guess that what we're talking about,
I think, has just always been part of my personality.
And you started the initial pilot North Queensland up in Cairns
and there's an element of trust required, isn't it,
for a community to say,
hey, we're going to release mosquitoes
that are carrying a bacteria.
It's got, you know, an element you need to build into people
to say, hey, this is going to work.
And I suppose those North Queensland communities
are very familiar with cane toads
that were introduced back in the 90s.
I mean, it's a devastation that cane toads have caused
in that part of the world.
So that must have been an interesting sell
to get them to trust you.
Yeah, it was a very interesting time period then.
I think, you know, I was holding so many community meetings
in North Queensland and I was flying up there regularly
to talk to people.
And, yeah, think about what the ask was
that we had in front of people.
We were a bunch of scientists from down south
who had cooked up this idea that had never been tested.
And we were going to come to these communities
and these people had been listening
to health education programs for the last 30 years
saying you've got to kill mosquitoes to stay healthy
so you don't get sick.
You have a bunch of scientists who are going to release mosquitoes
into your backyard that are going to bite you
and your six-month-old baby and your 97-year-old grandmother.
And the scientists are not sure if it's even going to work or not.
And so, yeah.
It was a pretty big ask of the community.
But I have to say, you know, the people in North Queensland
appreciated our transparency
and they appreciated our authenticity of what we knew
and what we didn't know and being prepared to talk to them
and people about why we were going to do it.
And the good people, people who live in North Queensland,
and they ended up welcoming us in,
not just for their own benefit, interestingly,
but for there was a serious interest in being involved
in something that could help.
Other countries and other people.
So I was quite surprised by that.
It wasn't total self-motivation around the people in North Queensland
where we started.
Amazing story that needs to be shared and told
and done on the back of your skill
and reading about just the technical difficulty
of what you tried to do.
And it was described, I read someone describe it
as effectively getting a needle that's hair thin.
You're injecting this bacteria into a mosquito egg
that's the size of a poppy seed.
I mean, you were toiling away at that
for a long time.
I mean, you were toiling away at that for a long time.
You must have had to find some resilience
to get that to work.
Can you tell us a bit about why and how you did that?
Yeah, I don't know if you've been travelling
around the world in Asia.
You can see people on the street making money
by engraving your name on a grain of rice or whatever.
I've always marvelled at the skill of those people.
And what we were doing was somewhat similar
but even more frustrating than trying to do that
was to, as you described,
I sort of liken it, if you could imagine,
taking a knitting needle and being able to put it
into a balloon full of water
and then pull the needle back out of the balloon
without breaking the balloon.
That's sort of a sense of what we had to do technically
under a microscope to make this thing work.
And it took many years to get that to happen.
Lots and lots of failure.
My story's full of failure and perseverance,
I think, as you said originally.
So, yeah, we just had this grind.
This grinding obsession that this was going to work.
And so, yeah, we spent, we kept persisting
and wouldn't accept the failure
until eventually we were successful.
What I love about so many of these incredible stories
of leadership is that we read out the headlines at the start
and we talk about you creating this technology,
but we always, that's the bio, we overlook the 20 years of,
as you said, frustration and could this work?
Is it going to work when I release these mosquitoes
in Queensland?
There must have been some nervous moments around that.
I mean, I think pivoting to the next part,
which I think is equally brilliant,
to get funding at the level you had, you know,
the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation,
the Gillespie Foundation, who are the founders
of Baker's Delight, they're incredibly sophisticated
and smart people.
They're big on impact and you need to prove
that what you are doing is worthwhile.
Collaborating with leaders on that level,
can you tell us, you know, how you achieved that success?
Yeah.
So, I think what really, I was like many scientists
living off government grants, one grant at a time,
which, you know, it's highly competitive to get
and the money is not very large.
And I sort of liken my job to being a professional beggar.
And so, you know, I really spend a lot of my time
with my handout asking people for money to keep
the whole thing going and a lot of my time.
And so, we're always scanning for opportunities.
And when the Gates Foundation,
came around with a competition they announced globally,
which was they had 14 big questions
that they wanted to get addressed
and they were looking for solutions for them.
And one of them was mosquito transmitted diseases.
And we thought, you know, okay, this fits us
and put the application in or a letter of intent in.
And we ended up in a competition
with about 1,700 other scientists around the world.
And we were lucky enough to make it to the top 40.
And that placement in the top 40 got us about
16,000 scientists.
So, that's about 6 million US dollars in funding,
which for me at the time was like winning the lottery.
And, you know, I'd never received that much money in a grant.
My usual grant sizes were maybe 200,000 to 300,000,
if I was lucky.
And so, suddenly in 2004 to receive that money
from the Gates Foundation was a huge boost to our program.
But also, you know, opened up doors for me as well,
being, you know, some of the big brands, if you like,
in the global health,
like the Bill and Linda Gates Foundation, you know,
very well known and very connected.
And so, it connects you to other people and other opportunities,
if you like.
And so, yeah, it's been a very fortunate ride
from that point of view to be able to interact
with people from those foundations.
And for us, you know, we're incredibly grateful
for what that funding that we've received has allowed us
to achieve, not just the Gates Foundation,
but Wellcome Trust, Gillespie family,
as you mentioned, Macquarie Bank, McKenzie Scott.
Various other donors have really, really helped us get
to where we needed to get to.
And so, we're hugely grateful for them.
I love hearing that in the not-for-profit space as well,
Professor O'Neill.
We often hear of, you know,
people get a massive business breakthrough
with one particular high-level, you know, client effectively,
and then the knock-on effect.
And clearly, that's happened for you
with the Gillespie Foundation.
Yeah.
And the support of the Gates Foundation
and Open Doors that were bigger than the initial $6 million,
which was obviously huge.
Reading some of your history in research for this,
and again, correct me if I'm wrong,
but in your own words, I've heard you describe yourself
as a naughty kid who wasn't academically focused,
who scrapped through year 12.
I mean, for people listening and think a scientist
is potentially going to have as big an impact
as anyone in a global sense for a long period of time.
I mean, is that accurate?
And why did you start?
Why did you struggle so much at school?
I don't know if I struggled at school,
but, you know, I wasn't, certainly,
wasn't the most brilliant student in that school.
And I was interested, as I think many young teenagers are,
about life and learning about life, not just about chemistry.
You know, I was, I had wide interests, I think, at the time,
and maybe didn't put as much attention into my schoolwork
as I probably would have if I had been a bit more mature
at the time.
And, you know, I went to university initially
and enjoyed the freedom that I had and the ability
to go out and party and, you know, failed out or dropped
out of my first stint at university
within the first six months of going.
And then sort of went and worked fruit picking
and doing different things and got, sort of got a little bit
more together and went back to university a bit more serious.
And, yeah, and then it got, I got to, found success,
and got more interested in it, if you like,
as a result of that, and paid more and more attention to it.
And then, you know, went all the way through university,
did a PhD, and then ended up going to the US
and got into some very good labs and to interact
with some very good people.
And, you know, it all went from there.
Gives hope to everyone, Professor O'Neill,
that you can end up achieving what you have
without necessarily, because as we know,
and we've talked to great educators on this podcast as well,
that, you know, perhaps the school system is,
needs some disruption as well.
It's not one size fits all.
I mean, you've found a way through,
but a lot of brilliant people don't.
Yeah, I think what was more important for me
than what I learned at school was, you know,
having a good sense of curiosity and perseverance and drive
and being willing to chase your dream.
And I think that in the end, you know,
kept me in good stead,
maybe more than what I learned in physics.
What a great life lesson.
It's a great lesson to share, isn't it?
And I want to come back and ask you about curiosity
in a moment.
I've also read that you've got a belief
that we need more scientists in key leadership positions
in government, CEO roles,
and a sense that if we're going to solve the big issues
that the planet faces, Professor O'Neill,
global warming and energy, et cetera,
that, you know, we need more science-based leaders.
Is that, is that real for you?
Yeah, yeah, it is for me.
You know, as a scientist,
I can appreciate some of the things
that are coming across the news every night
with regards to climate change
and what the future is looking for the planet.
You know, we've got large numbers,
very large numbers of people that need to be fed.
We've got an unstable climate that's changing.
It's going to disrupt agricultural production systems.
We're running out of energy.
We need clean energy drastically.
There's a huge, big issues to solve.
And then I look at the quality
of our global political leadership,
and, and it just, you know, it's, you know,
it just seems to me the problem
and the people that we have at the moment tasked
to help resolve those problems don't match up very well.
And I think we've, my sense would be
that we need a little bit more, you know,
a little bit louder voice for the people
that really understand what the problems are
that we're facing and where the solutions will be found.
And so I'm a strong advocate
for seeing more science-trained people in jobs
as like political leadership jobs or running countries.
than they currently are at the moment.
I think when you see examples of them, they do quite well.
And the problem is they're just not drawn in that direction.
But I think there's a job for universities
to be training scientists,
to go out and to have very broad roles,
not to be scientists sitting in the back room of labs,
toiling away, but to be running companies,
to be running government departments,
to really bring their training
to where it can have a broader societal impact.
So yeah, I feel fairly strongly about that.
We've got big problems in front of us.
Yeah, it's a brilliant thought.
And in a slightly different way, you know,
the essence of this podcast, Professor O'Neill,
is about capturing what great leadership looks like
in different contexts and seeing that really,
there's a big shift in leisure,
away from some of the challenging leaders on a global sense,
towards more collaborative, towards more self-reflective,
towards, you know, more inclusive.
And, you know, loving the fact, you know,
that if you are more inclusive as a scientist,
you want to collaborate and get the best outcomes.
You know, it's not my area,
but I suppose that was the essence
of what good science to me used to be, wasn't it?
Was you come up with an idea, you test that idea,
you debate that idea, and then out of that,
you get great breakthroughs.
It seems even in recent times,
I'm getting off track here, Scott,
that, you know, you hear this term, I trust the science.
The science is like, as though there's only one answer
in science in recent times,
that it's not really a panel of experts getting together,
getting together to formulate that.
Is that a reasonable question to ask?
Yeah, you know, it's hard for people,
often people equate science to being something written
in a book that is equals truth.
And, but science is like a living process
and it's a contest, you know,
it's a competition between ideas and thoughts
that's played out through experiments over time
and people bringing data and convincing arguments
that get, you know, tested backwards and forwards
until you get a dominant view.
And that's the process and the beauty of science
and why science leads to such great breakthroughs.
But for the general public, it can be frustrating
if we're in an emergency like COVID
and you're hearing these different viewpoints emerging
and you're like, well, what's real?
And what is science really telling us?
So the scientists know what's going on.
And all it is, is you're seeing the scientific process
at work up close in real time, if you like,
which you don't usually do.
You just see the end of it,
which is the final result.
But it's a very interesting, you know,
enterprise science and how it leads to outcomes, you know.
Before I ask you a range of questions on leadership,
I just got this fascination and, you know,
talking to one of the most prominent scientists in the world,
what are you reading?
What are you listening to?
What piques your interest outside of, I suppose,
the day-to-day of solving mosquito-borne viruses?
Well, you know, I've recently moved to France
and my free time, you know, I've been working
and my free time's being spent trying to learn French
at the moment, not very successfully.
So I need to get smarter at that.
And so I'm actually not spending a lot of time, you know,
in front of reading the news.
I scan through the major news outlets
and have a look what's going on,
but I'm really quite busy in doing what I'm doing.
And for me, downtime is getting some downtime mentally.
And that might be spending time in my garden
or spending time with my honeybees.
Or doing things like that rather than actually getting depressed
watching the news.
Fair enough, too.
You know, I think, as you said before, learning French,
if you're married to a French woman,
it makes a fair bit of sense as a priority, too,
I'm assuming, in the part of the world
where we're talking to you today.
We've identified in our mind these traits
of what great leadership looks like in different contexts.
And I'm fascinated to hear it from your scientific point of view.
But we think all great leadership,
at the moment, Professor O'Neill,
starts with self-leadership and this idea
that you need a sense of self-leadership.
Does that resonate with you?
Yeah, I think to a point that you need to be together yourself
in order to have other people with you.
I don't think if you're not together yourself,
then people are naturally suspicious, I think,
and less willing to go with you on a big adventure.
But yeah, I'm okay with that.
I agree with you.
Yeah.
So when you say be together, you mean if you're not...
That you're coherent, that you're organized,
that you have a clear direction and that you're able to express clarity
around an ambition and a goal that it looks achievable
and exciting to be part of.
I think that's all part of what's required.
Yeah.
Yeah, brilliant.
Makes perfect sense.
We see leaders are really conscious about how they go
about positively impacting others in their environment.
And your program is about world impact on a global scale.
But day-to-day, when you're in the lab,
and are you conscious about how you impact others
that you work with on a day-to-day basis?
Yeah, sure.
I think you've always got a thousand sets of eyeballs on you,
or it feels that way.
And everything you do, people are noting one way or another.
So you sort of have to...
You're living the example of what you want.
And so you have to be fully committed to it,
and living and breathing it yourself in order for people
to sense the authenticity of that and to buy into it, I agree.
We heard a bit of your vision before about scaling the ability
to 500 million people in tropical areas around the globe,
around eliminating mosquito-borne viruses and dengue fever.
I mean, how have you gone about creating a vision like that
and then sharing your vision?
Have you been systematic about that?
Yeah.
Well, we've been talking, you know, with colleagues.
We've had clear points, like the one of 500 million people protected
for a number of years now, and we, you know, we have a clear...
Our vision, if you like, is packaged down into key points,
which we are communicating regularly, internally, externally,
to different audiences.
And, you know, we need to get to that point.
We have to really bring governments along with us,
and some governments in countries that have a lot
of difficulties and challenges in poor areas of the world.
And there's a whole range of challenges associated with being able
to communicate effectively as foreigners into countries to be able
to bring technology that could help solve problems in countries
that have many, many problems and many issues to deal with.
This is just one of many.
And so, you know, there's a whole lot of challenges around the community,
the communication of what's required to get the buy-in and to build the demand.
You'd think that just having a great solution, you know, well, that's it, isn't it?
Don't you just, you know, dust off your hands, go to your honeybee, sit back,
kick back, and open a beer, and wash your cricket or something.
But no, it doesn't roll by itself.
And so, you've got to be in there actively pushing and working in order
to build the demand that will see it's finally successful and being able
to help the maximum number of people.
Yeah, it's a fascinating point.
You would think you would have the case study in Australia or North Queensland
and say, here is irrefutable evidence of dengue fever effectively being eliminated.
Yeah, you would imagine that that would be not a hard thing to sell, would you?
But clearly...
Yeah, not a hard thing to sell or the endpoint of your journey.
You know, for many scientists, that's the endpoint.
But for us, it was never going to be enough because, you know,
because there are so many other things that are having to be dealt with,
problems around the world and worthy issues grabbing people's attention.
It's, you know, the challenge doesn't end.
You have to keep going out there and showing people the benefit and how it's working
and how it could benefit other communities.
And so, yeah, the work continues.
If our goal is really not about the discovery, our goal is about having the impact.
And I think that's probably what separates us from...
You know, the goal is great, you know, getting to the point, getting to the summit is great,
but it's not enough.
You know, it doesn't get the impact.
And so, we're all about getting the impact.
We heard you mention curiosity before, Scott.
It's something that probably got you through, you know, schooling and that was the gift
that kept your mind, I suppose, open when, you know, you were, as you said, had a range
of things you're interested in.
We see leaders are really conscious of curiosity as a dimension.
And then through that, they approach their own learning and development.
Does that statement resonate with you around curiosity?
Yeah.
Yeah, sure.
I'm naturally a curious person and, you know, I'm always hungry to be learning things.
And if I'm not learning something, I'm feeling, you know, it's like I need to get up and exercise
or something.
I need to exercise my brain, if you like, by learning things.
So, luckily now, I've just shifted countries.
I've got a whole lot of learning opportunities in front of me to keep me sane and a little
bit more focused.
Yeah.
I'm a little bit occupied learning new language and culture, but yeah, I have to be, I'm very
curious driven.
I want to know about everything and then I, yeah, I can't help myself really about it.
It's part of my, you know, workings.
I just have to scratch that itch, you know, and so I'm out there learning about stuff.
Yeah.
Curious about everything.
It's brilliant.
I love hearing the way you articulate.
Communicating with clarity for leaders is a dimension that's pretty common and you mentioned
it.
I know the end point you would think might have been making this work, but to keep communicating
the importance to have the impact you're talking about, have you gone about communicating
with clarity?
You know, I think that's something that we all see, I think, is of huge importance and
something that we practice, you know, continuously practicing to try and get better at and take
advice from professionals in the area.
But I think for me, you know.
Yeah.
I think that the key for good communication is authenticity and, you know, people can
smell it, you know.
People can smell when you're bullshitting and, you know, I think we've all got a bullshit
detector in us and I think when you don't make that needle move and people can see that
what you're saying is you're delivering with authenticity and it's transparent and I think
it's much easier to build trust with people.
And trust is the key element that then allows things to happen.
And so for me, communication is about the elegance of simplicity wherever possible and
the importance of authenticity and being able to communicate with clarity in a simple way
that's truthful.
Yeah.
Brilliantly said.
I love the way you said that the elegance of simplicity with authenticity, it resonates
so strongly.
And the way you're communicating today, collaboration more important we think for leaders than ever
before and really seek it out.
How important has collaboration been for you?
Oh, critically important.
You know, I've always, you know, we've only gotten to where we have because we've been
a group of people.
It's not one individual.
Often I stand out the front, you know, because I'm the spokesperson, the leader or whatever.
But, you know, it's a group effort, has always been a team and a group effort from all the
way.
The team changes and the expertise in the team changes depending on what are the huge
problems we have at the time.
But it's always that notion of it's a collective effort and it has to be.
And so getting and attracting and retaining and getting the input of highly skilled professionals
in all sorts of different areas, not just scientists, but all sorts of different areas,
people that know how to engage communities, communication specialists.
People that understand government financing, you know, we've got a whole lot of specialists
in our group and each contributes very importantly.
And so, yeah, this thing was never going to fly if it was just going to be a single effort
of a single individual.
It was going nowhere from the beginning.
And so, yeah, that's self-evident, the need for that, for a team and having that diverse
set of skills because they're not held by any one individual.
The challenge then becomes managing that.
And making that happen smoothly with all of the interpersonal dynamics, the ego, and
you get a lot of good people working together, they often have strongly held views.
So navigating through the differences of opinions, et cetera, can become a bit challenging.
But that's all critically, in part, part of the success.
It is a brilliant story in every sense and maybe the ultimate story of collaboration
as you said.
To have seen this in the different communities in Brazil and through Asia.
And, you know, all parts of the world, incredible achievement in every sense of the word.
But asking these final two questions, Professor Scott O'Neill, to a range of different leaders
and I'm keen to do that right now with you.
Who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Oh, wow.
Probably this is sort of a question like, what's my favorite movie I'd like to sort
of reflect on to make sure I gave a really smart answer rather than the first one that
comes into my head.
But, oh, I don't know.
I don't know.
Who's, who's, you know, I'm going to avoid it a little bit in saying that I think it's
not a single individual.
I think I've learned different things off many, many people and, and rather than pin
it on a single individual, I think it's all those experiences that I've gained through
working and collaborating with so many different gifted people through my training, through
my university journey.
Through time, through my management at a university, a large Australian university
in an executive role there, you know, all of those experiences have helped shape me
in different ways.
And, and in each sort of phase, I've had different mentors and people that I looked up to, and
I'm not sure that I would label one more important than the others.
And, and so I'm going to skirt it in a way and say, I think it's been, you know, all
of these different individuals that have inputted into my thinking and my own evolution that
have been critical for me.
Which is a brilliant answer in, in itself, and it, most of that, and I'm, I'm, I'm having
a second round here in five minutes in time, but is it, is it most of that come in the
scientific community for you in terms of leadership or have you found, you know, from family to
outside influences have, have had as big an impact in?
Yeah, you know, I've, you know, I think our parents are always a huge influence very early
on.
They set our values.
They set our, you know, what's important to us as individuals.
And then I, you know, I can think as I've gone through in my life, there've been technical
mentors.
There've been people that have picked me up when I've, you know, failed so many times
in a row.
I didn't think I could keep going.
And people that would keep encouraging you and, um, people that would show you things
and people that would help you learn from failure.
Um, cause sometimes the failures can be rather harsh.
And so when you feel like you've lost the skin off your hands and your knees and your
feet altogether.
So at one time, like you've had an accident, you know, an accident off your, your bike
or something, your push bike, um, those people that can steer you away from the pain to think
about, okay, well, what's actually important here for you getting up and for the next step.
Um, but those moments are many, I think, and many individuals have contributed to that
through my journey.
And I'm, you know, extremely grateful to all those people.
The idea of collaboration for us is, uh, where we see, and it's happening in your world.
And this again, may be hard for you to.
Yeah.
And you're already collaborating with, you know, extraordinary people.
We mentioned, uh, you know, some of the financial support you get from the Gates foundation,
the Gillespie foundation, but in your mind, is there, if you could collaborate with anyone
in the world and it may be learning French, maybe it's another part of your brain that
you're thinking of.
Is there anyone that springs to mind in terms of collaboration that, uh, you'd like to connect
with?
That I haven't connected with that I would like to connect with.
Um, yeah.
Yeah.
I'm really fascinated by people.
And part of the reason that I do do well in picking teams and getting people together
is I'm inherently interested in people and, um, and I'm, I'm always fascinated, um, um,
in successful people, um, in whatever domain you would way that you would define success.
I, because I, I mentioned to you earlier, I'm a professional beggar in my job.
And so, you know, if you're begging, you usually go to people that have money in order to beg.
And often people that have money have, have an interesting story, uh, associated with
them.
And, uh, and I'm, I get really interested in the people I interact with, um, that way.
And, um, and, um, and learn from, I hope I learn from my interactions with those people
as well.
Not just learn about how better to ask for money, but, uh, learn some things that are
important for life and about how we take our program forward as well.
And so in a way, um, my begging became, um, you know, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my,
my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my,
my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my begging
becomes like, uh, a large collection of mentors that I I'm getting around to me.
Um, and, uh, are there people that, that I haven't interacted with that I would like
to?
Yeah, absolutely.
There's many people in the world I would love to interact.
Um, uh.
That might be interested in helping us as well and what we're wanting to do.
But, um, um, is there an individual, you know, I've, I've met some incredibly interesting
people.
Bill Gates is a very interesting individual.
You know, I marvel at both his, the strength of his intellect
and the broad interest and the passion and drive he brings to it
and amazed at the criticism he takes.
And so much of it, I think, is so unfounded.
And he gets up and continues doing it day after day.
I find that fascinating.
People like that fascinate me.
And so, yeah, they're sure there are plenty, would I name them.
You know, I'm interested in political leaders.
I'm interested in leaders who are able to span beyond countries,
people that have impact, you know, people that work in organisations
like the World Health Organisation.
I have huge respect for them to see what they do
and are able to achieve very complex geopolitical context there.
And so, yeah, there are many people.
So, look, I feel like I'm letting you down here
on these last two questions being a slippery eel.
But I'm thinking about it as I'm speaking to you.
And, yeah, I could give you a list, but I don't have it in my back pocket.
And I'm not sure.
You know, often to me as well, it's not planned to the point
that I go out and seek out individuals.
They just seem to come to me.
It's through my other, what I do.
And so, you know, I'm always looking forward to the opportunity
of meeting people and learning from people.
Well, I've loved seeing you shift in your chair
just slightly a little bit there, Professor O'Neill, at the end.
And, you know, someone did ask me these same questions back
and I was equally uncomfortable and I feel the same way.
It has been a great privilege to me to, you know,
as someone who hasn't got any scientific DNA at all or background,
I'm fascinated by the way your brain works
and equally your language.
You learn so much, don't you, from diversity and other people
in different areas.
And today it has been an incredibly enlightening discussion.
And you zoom out to me again and you're thinking, you know,
an Australian scientist is going to, you know,
already is on a global scale, solve a problem that causes
so much hardship, dengue fever.
And we mentioned yellow fever and Zika.
And there was another virus I'm not mentioning
because I can't say their names.
Quite a name, chikungunya, Zika, dengue, yellow fever,
my aura, the list goes on.
Yeah, we're lucky to be able to control it.
We're lucky to be able to control many diseases
with the one intervention, yeah.
It is an amazing story of ingenuity and resilience
and leadership in every sense.
And I'm really honoured that you were prepared
to take some time out to share the story with me today.
Thanks so much.
And I look forward to seeing it scale up to 500 million people
over the next decade.
Thanks again for your time.
Thanks, Luke.
I appreciate it.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me, Luke Darcy,
produced by Matt Dwyer, with audio production
by Darcy Thompson.
To start your leadership journey,
I encourage you to go to www.empoweringleaders.com.
I encourage you to go to www.elitacollective.com,
take our Empowering Leaders Indicator tool
and understand the impact you have on your environment.
Join us at Elida to learn, lead and collaborate.
Listener.