How do you break the status quo?
Pursue what you think is right and lead in a fight for the voiceless.
G'day, it's Luke Darson.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership both on and off the field has been a lifelong passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective.
I've had the privilege of working with thousands of leaders in education, sport, industry and the arts
that have helped shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
Today, I caught up with Professor Pat McGorry, a psychiatrist known worldwide for his development and advocacy for youth mental health services.
In an environment which wasn't necessarily accepting of his passion, I talked to Pat about fighting for what's right
and how he has led the way in saving millions of young Australian lives.
Professor Patrick McGorry is a leading international researcher, clinician and advocate for youth mental health reform.
He is the executive director of Origin Youth Health, a world-renowned mental health organisation for young people
that has put Australia at the forefront of innovation in the prevention and treatment of mental illness.
Origin targets the needs of young people with emerging serious mental illness
and has become the model with which many youth mental health services use around the world.
Pat McGorry is also a founding board member of Headspace, the National Youth Mental Health Foundation.
He believes that early intervention offers the greatest hope for recovery
and therefore takes every opportunity to educate the community to recognise the early signs of mental illness
without stigmatising or discriminating.
His extraordinary 30-plus years of contribution to the improvement of youth mental health in this sector
has transformed literally the lives of tens of thousands of young people all over the world
and in 2010, his recognition for Pat's extraordinary life work, he was named.
As the Australian of the Year, Pat, congratulations on a lifetime of contribution and achievement.
I wanted to just start by saying thank you for your time in this important time, it seems, in the world.
But firstly, where did the passion for youth mental health come from?
Well, I remember when I was a young medical student, I was looking at the spectrum of medicine, really,
and one of the areas that was, from a human rights point of view, that was so underserved and so neglected was mental illness.
You know, people...
In those days, we were locked away in, you know, mental hospitals, asylums,
and it was like a 19th century approach, really,
and I just felt that there are many areas of medicine you can work in,
and I did actually work for about four years in general medicine, in diabetes and those sorts of areas,
but really, you know, there was more than enough being done in those areas.
All of those areas were improving and, you know, well supported financially and with skill and talent,
but mental health...
You know, it needed something very special to happen,
and I thought maybe I could make a better contribution there.
People tried to talk me out of it.
They said, don't waste your life, you know,
because the prejudice and stigma was even worse in those days,
and it's improved a lot in recent years.
But actually, because it was coming up such a low base,
we can make a huge difference if we improve things in that space.
So that's what attracted me to it,
and I guess I felt an affinity for the suffering of the people, too,
you know, the old school approach to medicine, the vocational sort of feeling about it.
I definitely think I had that,
and I've been very lucky to have a lot of satisfaction and sort of reward
from being able to work in an area where you see so many people benefiting and recovering,
and they wouldn't have otherwise if you hadn't sort of put that effort in.
Yeah, I love the sense of empathy, Pat,
whenever I hear you talk about your genuine care for this space,
and I did want to ask you that because I had read that that was the case,
and your colleagues in the medical fraternity almost tried to talk you out of it
and said, as you just quoted, then don't waste your time.
This is not an area that needs that attention.
So it was literally people said to you, don't worry about this space.
Was that one of the things that came your way?
Yeah, because I actually, without sort of promoting myself too much,
I actually was – I did quite well in my medical course,
and I probably could have done – I would have had the opportunity to do other things.
If I wanted to, and people probably around me sort of probably saw that,
and they said, well, why are you doing that?
That's a waste of time, because they actually didn't see the people
with mental illness as fully human, I don't think.
It was that bad, you know, and it's hard to imagine, in fact, these days, isn't it?
But that was the way they thought, and we still see that structural stigma
in various areas, and the underfunding of mental health until just about now
has been a result of that.
Yeah.
In medical research, even though, you know, we brought the biggest grants
from the US and Europe into medical research in Australia in mental health,
our colleagues in medical research tend to look down on our research
as somehow not being as good as theirs.
So there's still that sort of judgmental and stigma operating.
Yeah, it's remarkable, isn't it?
And we're all thankful, Pat, and so many are, that you used your skills this way.
You did qualify as a surgeon and a doctor, and you went down this path.
But can I ask you, I feel like there is clearly in 2021 and now an understanding
for those that probably generally are well and haven't suffered a medical illness
in the mental health space, that they have an understanding of you need to do things
to protect and better your mental health.
I don't think a lot of people had made that connection until recently.
Is that a fair thing to say, Pat, in your mind?
Yeah, that's a very astute observation, Luke, I reckon.
And that's one of the benefits of the pandemic, even though it's unleashed a shadow pandemic,
on us with another 25% of people needing professional help for mental ill health.
It's sensitized the whole population, whether it's, you know, just watching our kids,
our teenagers and our young adult kids struggle, because they've borne the big burden
of the pandemic, really, or it's ourselves.
I mean, maybe we haven't become, you know, seriously mentally ill as a result of the pandemic,
most of us, thank God, but many of us actually got pretty close to the edge
of the precipice there.
And all of us have suffered a loss of well-being and morale, I think.
We've all lost the sort of access to things that make life worth living during the last
18 months or so, especially in Melbourne.
And so we feel it, you know, we know, we've got a better idea of what it feels
to lose mental health.
And when you turn for help, you can't access it at the moment.
It's very difficult to access, and the quality of it isn't what it could be, I suppose.
So I think it's great to have the public sort of...
What's the word?
They've had awareness for years in a superficial sense, I mean,
but they haven't really felt it.
They haven't, you know, I think in a deeper way, like you're alluding to, yeah.
Yeah, I might jump into that, Pat.
The term shadow pandemic was a really profound use of words that you really brought
to people's attention around what was going on.
And it's hard to ignore you and I both living in Melbourne,
and for those listening around the country or elsewhere in the world,
it is the record for the most locked down city in the world, Melbourne.
And tragically and unfortunately, and it felt to me, Pat,
in some ways as a perfect storm for our youth.
And clearly, you're at the coalface of this and you've seen a 25% increase.
But there is, you know, even watching my own household full of teenagers
and your own kids and their friends just to see the impact, Pat.
There are some numbers that I can't get out of my brain, Pat,
that you'll probably be able to clarify.
But Damon Johnson, the Australian, was reporting several weeks ago
that at the peak of this last lockdown in Melbourne,
there was 830.
Eating disorders diagnosed a week in Melbourne.
In one city, there was 350 of our teenagers presenting at emergency
because their families were so concerned about the fact
they may take their own lives.
There was a couple of hundred a week who were self-harming in regularness.
In that sort of numbers, as you said, a shadow pandemic
that wasn't being spoken about or discussed.
What advice have you got for parents that have been generally concerned
about their kids through this time?
What are some practical things that parents can do, Pat?
On the numbers, before we get into that,
we run five headspace centres across the North West through Origin
and we run the state specialist mental health system at Origin too.
There's a backup system to that.
We've got about 1,000 young people on our waiting list
who can't get into our system because it's just not built to scale yet.
And as you say, a lot of that is young people, young women quite often
with an emerging eating disorder like anorexia nervosa.
Or combinations of that with anxiety, depression and often a lot of self-harm
because they've discovered that that's a way of alleviating
the emotional pain temporarily.
It's kind of a very disturbing thing, isn't it,
when you see people cutting themselves to relieve emotional pain.
Parents really freak out when they see that happening quite rightly.
But it shows how desperate the situation is.
So that's what we're dealing with on a day-to-day basis.
And in terms of what...
And I suppose the first thing is recognition.
And you don't want to kind of, I suppose, panic.
Just because your teenager is having a bad day, you don't want to overreact
because it's an emotionally challenging time growing up
and working out who you are and dealing with bullying
and peer groups and all that sort of stuff.
We all have to do it.
But 50% of the young people as they navigate that transition to adult life
will have a period of poor mental health.
So it's not like we're...
Medicalising it is just a reality.
And what we've got to do is help those kids
because if they're not helped, you know,
it's the biggest cause of death in young people
up to the age of even 40 is suicide.
And it's certainly by far the biggest cause of disability
or not fulfilling your potential as a human being
if you have untreated mental ill health.
Often it's quite obvious that the young person has become more withdrawn,
they're not going so well at school,
they're not so much in contact with their friends
or they're angry and irritable.
Not just on a one-off,
but just a sustained, you know, irritability, anger and distress.
You know, I mean, you can see the distress.
Now, obviously, more obvious things like weight loss in a young woman,
that's a warning sign.
So if parents are worried, they should definitely educate themselves
and also try to access help.
The parents will have been affected badly by the pandemic.
Parents will have suffered.
A loss of reserve, a loss of morale,
a lot of, you know, loss of kind of well-being themselves
and they might be struggling as adults.
And if the parents are struggling,
it has obvious secondary effects on the kids, doesn't it?
Because the parents and the peer group are the support system
and the teachers, they're the support system
for that young adult, emerging adult.
And if the support system is struggling,
then the young person will struggle too.
And Pat, one of the things as parents that, you know,
a lot of us spend a lot of time, as you'd be aware,
trying to manage screen time these days
and make sure that your kids have enough balance.
You've got to live with that world
and there are some benefits clearly to social media.
It's a topic that's talked about regularly,
but particularly in Melbourne,
where you've had two years of training kids to a screen at homeschooling,
you can just see that has become an even bigger issue
for kids then to get them out connecting.
And, you know, I use the word perfect storm,
but for young teenage girls in particular
and young boys seeing these unrealistic images on social media
that, you know, they're not going to be able to get out of school.
And I think that's a big issue.
They're bombarded with,
without the connection of sport that's been taken away
and without all the things that keep them healthy,
those intricate social catch-ups and connections
that have been going, Pat, it's staggering.
And for you to say you've got a thousand kids in your centres alone
that can't access the help they need,
I mean, that's a stunning thing to me in such a developed city
that we're not able to look after them.
Pat, am I reading that the right way?
Yeah, yeah.
And I think, you know, we were lucky we've got a Premier
and a Deputy Premier that recognised this
and we had a health minister
so Martin Foley, we had a Royal Commission
which actually recognised the massive underinvestment
in mental health care, especially in young people.
So that is going to get fixed over the next few years.
But right now, we've got a thousand young people,
many of whom are in life-threatening situations
that we can't help.
Just imagine what that feels like for a mental health professional
to be in that situation.
It's as if, you know, with COVID,
it's as if they had to turn away two out of three COVID cases
who might die.
That's what we have to do every single day.
And Pat, I'm so grateful that you're shining a light on this.
And I know, you know, you've got great, you know, ability
and what you've done to respond, but exactly that choice, isn't it?
For your healthcare professionals that can't literally save lives
in this space, but for families as well
who are watching literally their young children
without the ability, you know, to get help for them
is just a heartbreaking thing.
And I've seen it personally around the people
that we live with that have got children
that literally can't get an appointment for 18 months.
There is no opportunity there.
So how do you, is there any solution, you know,
Pat, to that crisis at all in the short term or not?
Yeah, I think there is because,
and you've got to fight for your family, right?
And whatever the health problem.
And so GPs, thank God for GPs, they are there
and they will actually see people, you know,
and then it's up to them to try to find a pathway
into it.
Into more expert help when it's needed.
And it can be done, but it takes a predetermined, you know,
family and a predetermined GP to do that.
And then the last resort is the emergency department.
That's why you're seeing the blowouts
in emergency department stats for young people especially
because the emergency department can't turn,
well, it has to see people, you know.
It's the only way you can actually get seen.
Now, because the channel is so narrow,
a lot of those people bounce out.
And they don't make it through.
But that is the place, those are the two options
if you can't find a way in anywhere else.
And we're working really hard.
And look, I've got to be grateful to the government here
because they are actually investing now.
We've got the money to actually employ more people,
but we've got to find them.
So we have to find them from other states,
maybe from overseas now the borders are opening up.
So I think we're doing everything we can to sort
of get reinforcements and build the system.
And that's been our problem, Luke.
Yeah.
I mean, you know, we haven't had the public support
that has forced politicians to respond.
And I think the World Health Organization is saying
that by 2030 it will be the biggest issue
that mankind faces, anxiety and mental health related issues.
I have had this thought, Pat,
and in no way is this a political statement at all.
I'm not angling in that in any shape or form.
But I feel so passionate about it, Pat.
You mentioned the word recognition.
To me, the news coverage quite rightly of the concerns
around people and the virus have dominated the cycles.
And as you said,
the attention on this when you actually say the numbers
out loud, you can't ignore them.
And perhaps this is something for me in a city like Melbourne,
I feel like I want to get the other leaders that we know
of the community to come out and assemble en masse under the banner
of we're showing up for our kids.
They've been put through two years of something
that no generation have experienced before.
It feels like this is just going to get passed again
in the news cycle if we don't do something a bit more dramatic.
Yeah, that is a great way to think, Luke.
And in fact, you know, we've got a lot of people out there, you know,
who are going to get back to school.
And I've got to say that, in fact, after 2010, when I had that lucky break
and became the Australian of the Year, I had a chance to have,
I suppose, campaign in a stronger way.
And I tried to sort of set up an organisation modelled on GetUp
so that it mobilised large numbers of people across the country around this issue.
And it was called Australians for Mental Health.
And it took me a couple of goes to get enough money to sort of get it off the ground.
And just in the last year or two, we managed to get more funding support.
So, it's a real...
It's a real campaign now.
It's called Australians for Mental Health.
We have a campaign director called Chris Raine, who set up a thing called Hello Sunday Morning
years ago, which was to help people moderate their drinking.
So he's a bit of a young entrepreneur, a bit like what you were talking about before about
leadership, younger people and the collaborative leadership.
He's amazing.
So he's mobilised this, you know, sort of a platform for a campaign.
And we need probably a few hundred thousand Australians to join this, as you're saying,
like, not to kind of protest in an aggressive way, but just to show the politicians that
this is something that the whole Australian public care about now.
And they expect the right quality of care.
And also the research, like, you know, I'm a researcher as well as a clinician.
And so, I realised that we've got to keep learning and keep discovering new ways of
helping and solving these problems because it's not just, you know, the way mental health
is reported in the news, it sounds like all you need is a few sessions of counselling,
and everything will be okay.
But mental illness is much more complicated than that, and it requires scientific breakthroughs
and knowledge, just like all the other areas of healthcare.
Yeah.
Australians for Mental Health will get all those links, Pat, and make sure that likewise
donating to Headspace.
So if you are commercially minded and you have got a passion, please, we'll give you
the links to donate to Headspace or I love the idea of what you spoke about, Pat, using
a get up style campaign to shine a light on what is unfolding in our communities, particularly,
on the back of these challenging times.
I wanted to maybe just steer back a little bit, Pat, and maybe a more basic question
to me.
What are some of the things people listening to this can do in your mind to practise good
mental health routines, even if they haven't suffered in the past?
What are some examples that really average people can add to their routine if they want
to have a mental, healthier, happier in life?
Yeah.
Well, I think there's a whole range of things that people can do to improve their mental
health.
You know, like things that might work for different people.
For me, I always enjoyed sport and physical activity, so staying physically fit is very
important for me.
I found that very difficult during the pandemic, not being able to go to the gym, for example,
and not being able to go for a surf, things I really depended on being able to do.
So I think that's one thing.
Other people might prefer just reading or just reflecting.
Yeah.
Maybe you can do a little more, more calmer sort of pursuits.
But things that make life worth living, things that you get positive feelings from, really.
I mean, that's, and relationships is another one as well.
I suppose, you know, having friendships, having intimate relationships with people, that those
are things that the scaffolding around someone that keeps them, you know, upright and alive
and enjoying life.
So a lot of it's probably pretty simple.
Connection with nature.
Connection with nature is another thing.
I think that was another thing that we suffered from,
being locked into our homes.
We couldn't actually get out into nature and be exposed,
whether it's the beach or the forest or for a walk along the river
or whatever it is.
And all those things were kind of more difficult.
So a lot of that is common sense.
Now, that will help you with positive mental health.
It doesn't necessarily always protect you against becoming depressed
or unwell.
So there might be two different sort of patterns there.
But the things that cause mental illness, you know,
apart from the genetic or biological basis for it,
the risk factors are things like loss, you know,
if you lose someone in your family, like a death in the family,
especially if there's a traumatic aspect to it,
and other types of abuse or trauma or bullying.
Those are the sort of things that undermine mental health.
And you see that, you know, when people go through those experiences,
those ordeals.
And so trying to obviously protect people against those sort
of negative experiences is another thing.
Yeah, I was having a conversation on this forum, Pat,
with Steve Butoff, the author of, you know, many kids' books,
sorry, books for parents really on adolescence and growing up.
And he referenced just the devastating statistic on how many kids
really experience some form of trauma in their upbringing.
And, you know, close to 70% in one of the studies that was a really
extensive study on what young people are experiencing.
Is that, in your mind, one of the core causes that kids really do have
environments that cause some stress?
Yeah, I would say trauma, like a lot of kids, you know,
like when I work in Origin or Headspace, I see the histories of,
there's about a third of the kids that have been through some kind
of significant trauma, but probably more, another thing which isn't
talked about as much as trauma is attachment problems, you know.
So that, for example, the kids that go in and out of foster care,
they have about 15.
Their parents, by the time they're, you know, 15.
So that rupture of attachments and bonds, relationships is very destructive
to the development of a healthy sort of personality and a strong sort
of person, a strong personality that's not so vulnerable to mental ill health
of various kinds.
But, yeah, I think those two things, loss, attachment and trauma are the kind
of psychological risk factors that impact on people.
And then there's the...
The more biological ones, you know, so that you might have more
of a genetic vulnerability to different types of mental illnesses,
which these environmental risk factors bring out.
So if you think about mental illness, people always argue,
is it the brain, is it biology, or is it psychology or the social
environment that causes it?
Well, it's both, you know.
It's like with any health problem.
It's a mixture of, you know, biological vulnerabilities
and the environmental factors that operate on you as a growing person.
Yeah, Joel.
The debate isn't nurture or nature and what part...
That's it.
...it plays, doesn't it?
It's always a fascinating conversation, isn't it?
What parts or equal parts?
You know, as you're talking again, Pat, I was just thinking about, you know,
obviously the pressures that have come of this time and obviously living
through a period where kids have then been isolated in their homes
for extended periods.
In this podcast, we talk a lot about collaborative leadership
and self-reflective leadership.
Understanding that measures had to be taken through a pandemic, Pat,
and I think that's a big part of it.
Yeah.
And we're not, again, trying to necessarily hold people
to account for their decision-making, but was there enough conversation
because there really, with kids missing school for the amount of time,
kids that were in vulnerable homes, being locked in those homes,
not getting those outlets, had to cause, you know,
more issues than there would have been in the past?
Do you feel like people understood that as a cost of what was going on
in the pandemic, cost of lockdown was always going to be this?
Do you feel like we were collaborated with enough on that?
I accept that until you got to a high level of vaccination,
which probably took a lot longer than it needed to,
we probably had to protect life.
Otherwise, we would have had, you know, instead of hundreds of people dying,
we would have had thousands, maybe tens of thousands of people dying.
So that was a pretty high priority to get right, you know,
which we sort of did, you know, really.
But I suppose at the same time, we didn't actually measure
and count the cost and take enough steps to sort of mitigate
the other impacts.
And obviously, mental health is the main one that I've been aware of.
But again, that's been difficult because governments have neglected
mental health for so long.
That's why we had the Royal Commission even before the pandemic,
that you can't suddenly rebuild from a ruin, you know,
in the middle of a pandemic.
It's been difficult for them.
And so, but you're talking about, I suppose, the preventive measures.
Could they have been a little bit more sort of flexible about some of the sort
of lockdowns?
And those sorts of things?
It's difficult to see exactly how.
But now that we're out of that phase, I think it's fantastic
that they've decided we're not going back.
You know, we're going to do everything except lockdown, you know,
from now on.
And I don't think the public would tolerate it anymore now that we've got
to these high vax levels.
Now that they've done that, they have to really, as you were saying before,
recognise what the legacy of this kind of extreme measures actually is.
You know, in other words, we've done modelling ourselves at Origin.
You know, we're a research institute and we predicted this 30% rise of new cases.
And what we predict is that it's not just going to disappear when lockdown
finishes, it's going to last for months and years.
So you alluded to that yourself, this generational effect.
And so we've got to actually make sure we take care of those people
and help them to recover.
And with the right sort of help, they will.
But if they're just thrown on the scrappy, they won't.
And a lot of your modelling does include economic costs in preparation for this
conversation.
And, you know, reading one of your studies of, you know,
over a $10 billion economic cost annually in Australia with the issues that our
youth face in mental health.
And you can even break that down per person.
I think you had it at $10,500 in loss of productivity effectively out of having
to deal with young children.
So it is a huge cost to the system, isn't it, Pat?
So it does open the door for more investment because those dollars will be
rewarded.
If we look at it as unemotionally as that, keeping people healthy in this space
is a pretty vital thing, isn't it?
Yeah.
It's like a win-win because, you know, we make the argument for treating cancer
because we want to save lives.
But it's not a very cost-effective investment treating cancer because it's
mostly older people, you know, who are not going to contribute an awful lot to
the economy beyond that point on average.
I mean, but no one would think that way, would they?
They would just think we want to save lives and we want to help people live as
long as they can.
Well, we've got that argument in mental health.
And it's even more so because it's in much younger people.
But because it's in younger people, 75% of illnesses appear before the age of 25,
very different from cancer and other medical illnesses.
If we get more people recovered and cured or in remission or even functioning
better, the return on investment is massive.
And that's what the Productivity Commission showed, that we'll not just save
lives and futures, but we'll actually save heaps and heaps of money if we invest
in mental health.
Yeah.
It's different from cancer.
You actually will get a massive return on investment if we actually do this
properly.
I wanted to ask you a question, Pat, or perhaps a bit of a statement.
A passion of mine for my own mental health, Pat, was something I stumbled
across as a 19-year-old in the world of meditation and mindfulness.
And we do some work in education and we've been running programs in the last
couple of years, particularly in a pipe in South Australia, where we've taught
teachers a toolbox of techniques.
In that field, Pat, where we give them an array of meditation, mindfulness
techniques and breathing techniques, and then they've been able to, A, look
after their own health and pass that on to kids.
And we've seen a great reduction in stress and anxiety and behavioral issues
in kids and class.
Are you a believer in those modalities as someone who's a researcher in
preventative mental health?
Do they play a role, Pat, for us to maybe get into better habits at kids in
school before some of these issues arrive?
Yeah.
It's good for normal people who don't have mental illnesses or mental ill
health.
And it can also help people who are diagnosed as well.
But I think, like you say, it's a universal thing that everyone can
benefit from managing stress in a better way and even helping people sleep
better.
You know, if you use those techniques to help you go to sleep, there's lots
of apps that will help you do that now.
So, yeah.
That's all really positive.
Absolutely.
But in terms of preventing, you know, the onset of anorexia or major
depression in teenagers or psychosis, psychotic illnesses, I don't think
it's really powerful enough as a technique for that.
But, look, it's got its place.
Of course, it has.
Yeah.
And can I ask you this question?
If, you know, you could wave a magic wand right now and you've 30 years
of incredible leadership and contribution in this space and cost is not
an issue.
And you wanted to try and I think origin stated goal is that all young
people to enjoy optimal mental health as they grow through to adulthood.
What's the thing you'd do?
What needs to be done to solve this in the best possible way?
Yes, that's a great question.
I think, first of all, because the mental health of young people around the
world was getting worse even before COVID and now COVID has added another,
you know, dollop of, you know, burden as well.
I would like to understand better why the mental health of young people is
getting worse these days.
And the sort of candidates that you mentioned, you know, social media and
stuff like that and the cyberbullying.
But there's more macro forces.
We call them megatrends.
The increasing insecurity of life for young people, you know, the fact they
can't afford to buy a house, that they've got to pay uni fees, you know,
the fact that climate change is hanging over them, the fact that inequality
in society is getting worse, you know.
We know that when you get people getting richer and richer at one time, you know,
one end and poor and poor at the other end and more inequality, that causes a
whole lot of social and health problems for that society.
It's an incredibly dumb thing for a society to do to allow that to happen.
But we're allowing that to happen here in Australia and around the world.
So those sorts of things have to be understood a bit better so we can turn
back the tide or stem the tide.
And then until we can totally, you know, stem the tide, we've got to actually
look after these young people in a much better way.
And so, therefore, we need systems of care.
Like, we've built headspace, Origin designed headspace and rolled it out.
And it's now going to be in 150 places pretty soon around Australia.
So that's great as an entry-level base camp.
So about a third of young people can be helped and will get a lot better with headspace.
The other two-thirds that come in the front door need to go to the next level.
But the next level hasn't been built.
It's like we've built the entrance hall to the house, but we haven't built the second
floor, the second story, you know, haven't built the other rooms in the house.
That's what governments need to do now.
And it needs to be powered by new research, you know.
And you mentioned new techniques.
Well, we're using virtual reality to kind of modernize and make more potent our
psychological therapies.
And then we need drug discoveries.
We need safer and better medications that can be used as maybe the third-line
treatment.
So we need to really invest in new systems of care and basically start flowing
into these systems the products.
of new research.
That's like a great project for Australia for the next 10 years to invest in all that.
Pat, I've been asking a range of leaders a series of questions that we think form
the dimensions of what makes great leaders in this modern world and modern time.
And we certainly see you, Pat, and your life's work in that space.
So please be as expansive as you like.
I'm fascinated to hear your thoughts on it.
But we start with self-leadership as a dimension of what makes great leaders.
When I ask you about self-leadership, what do you think of, Pat?
Yeah.
First of all, I'd say I've been lucky to work with a lot of like-minded people
who also are leaders, you know, people with the same common view and mission.
You know, that's what I've been lucky enough to sort of have around me or with me,
you know, as friends and colleagues and not just here in Australia but around
the world too.
And, you know, people that have got the same sort of, I don't know,
determination, I'd say, as well.
We're lucky because we've got a purpose.
You know, we know what we want to see in the world, you know, and we're very devoted to
sort of following that purpose.
And it took me, you know, just speaking personally, it took me until my late 30s when I'd finished
all my medical and specialist training and also I'd finished my PhD before I got the
chance to do anything as a leader.
You know, I mean, I see these 25-year-olds these days who are starting their own companies,
who are, you know, doing amazing things and they have got the, they've got opportunities
which we didn't have in my day.
You know, we had to sort of get ourselves qualified and in position to do stuff, you know.
And I didn't really ever imagine I would have the opportunity to do the things I've been
lucky enough to have the chance to do.
So, but in a way, you know, I hear about, you know, you probably can relate to this
as a footballer, but you just don't think, you just take care of the basics and you just
think one step ahead at a time.
You don't necessarily think you're going to.
Do X or Y, but you actually just address the things that are right in front of you and
they eventually things start to build and you have, you create something and you have
some success and you just have to keep building on it and reinventing it.
That's what I've found and find people who can share the same idea and you help each
other to do it and you never lose sight of why you're doing it.
So, some people build companies or organizations and they forget why they actually did that
in the first place.
Well, I think we just got to continually.
If you remember what we're actually trying to do, you know, the fundamentals, the real
basics, the grassroots, like seeing the young people like I do, I still, you know, work
on set days in the headspace in Glenroy and it's the best part of the week, you know,
and just being connected to the, what it's really about.
That's what I've found has been absolutely key for me.
I love it, Pat.
I get to hear that sense of purpose still in everything you say.
It's an amazing life's work.
A lot of people are understanding that now, but that has been clearly what you've done
from the.
You know, the various early days in your choices in life and talk about positively impacting
others in your environment.
It's interesting to hear you say about, you know, being fortunate to have those with you
with shared vision and shared determination.
When you turn up in the origin world or the headspace world and you're leading your teams,
how do you think about positively impacting those in your environment?
Yeah, look, I probably not always, you know, I wouldn't, I wouldn't sort of say I'm anywhere
near perfect.
I've probably got, I've got an impatience, you know, especially as I get older, you know,
because I think how much time have I got to solve this problem or to make this progress?
And so I do put pressure on people and that's probably not such a good thing.
You know, I probably, I've got, I expect people to have like energy and that kind of level
of commitment that you can't always expect that of people.
People talk a lot more these days.
These days about work-life balance and, and you know, they're not quite so single-minded
and there is a cost to being like that too, like in your, in your personal life and, and,
and in your, with your relationships, you've got to be careful.
And I probably, you know, I've been, I haven't always had the right balance myself, but so
the people around me, I've got to constantly remind myself that they are, you know, that
they've got lives and they've got choices too.
So just to kind of respect that a bit more than I probably, I do some of the time.
But, you know, I've got to be careful.
But I do, I do sort of feel that, you know, we, we are privileged as well when we get
to these sort of positions.
Like I've got, I've got 12 professors working at Irish and working on different research
things.
And so I think if you're in that position, you know, you've got a responsibility to
use your talents and use your, you know, opportunities for, for good and having really good, what's
the word, trusting relationships with people, trust and, and, and sort of values are really
important as well.
Culture.
You know, I think about football clubs here too, but I think definitely about, about clinical
settings.
If you've got a really good culture in the clinical setting, which shows that like a
real compassion and almost like a love or an affinity for the young people that we're
sort of looking after.
If that comes through that, that's a really precious thing to kind of nurture.
And that probably has to be at all levels of an organization if you can, if you can
pull that off and, and, and yeah, so it depends on all of us having, having that, having that,
having that kind of culture.
So I think that's really important.
Yeah.
That's, that's definitely, it's really important to have that feeling, having that, having that,
that feeling, not just one person is in a leadership role.
Pat, I have to ask you, as a father of three and, and a long-term marriage as well, is
it possible to achieve what you achieve?
And as you said, there's sometimes you felt like everyone's going through that work-life
balance.
I mean, is it, is it something that you look back and think you would have done, you do
differently if you had your time again, or have you felt like, as you've got older, you've
got that, that mix, the right.
It's a hard one, Luke.
I mean, you know, I, I don't know that I've done a good job.
You know, you look back and you can have regrets about your life for sure.
And one of the things I think I probably, in a way I was selfish
because I wanted to pursue what I was trying to do
and I should have spent more time with my kids
and I should have not travelled as much.
And, you know, obviously things happened because I did those things
in a wider way.
But, yeah, there were sacrifices, not just for me,
more for my family, I would say.
That's the thing I should have had a better balance about those things for sure.
But, you know, you sort of don't realise, you mature, you know,
maturation's a slow thing and you look back and you think,
well, yes, I could have done that a bit differently.
And, yeah, I definitely have that feeling.
I want to ask you about creating and sharing your vision.
And it's an extraordinary vision that was rewarded, as we said at the start,
with the Australian of the Year and that platform.
But, as you said,
Headspace will be in 150 different communities.
The work that Origin has done in groundbreaking research
and it's a massive vision for a huge issue.
And your answer before was you've got second and third levels
that you really want to get to.
How do you go about sharing and creating that vision?
I never thought of myself in the way that you were talking about me here.
I just thought it was so obvious, you know, what needed to happen.
Because I saw these young people back in Royal Park Hospital back in the 1980s
coming in.
In the middle of the night, shackled by police, handcuffed by police,
you know, acutely mentally ill, psychotic hearing voices.
And they came into this environment surrounded by 45-year-olds
with chronic mental illnesses.
They were terrified, you know.
And they'd been unwell for maybe a year or two,
sitting in their bedroom quietly psychotic.
And I thought it was just so obvious that what we had to do was find them
much earlier when they first started to become unwell,
like you would do with skin cancer.
You know, chest pain or something.
You find it as soon as it starts to become a problem.
And you treat them in a very careful, nurturing way with skill
and scientific sort of treatments.
And that is not exactly rocket science.
It's so obvious as a logical thing to do.
But trying to make it happen in the real world,
especially when everyone in those days thought those kids were not salvageable,
like they were written off.
You know, they were told, you know, you're going to become disabled
with schizophrenia.
That sort of horror message was given to people.
So to me, I never thought it was a vision.
I thought it was just absolutely bleeding obvious, you know,
what needed to happen.
And fortunately, it's such a simple thing, early intervention,
treating people properly and trying to get the best possible life for them.
Everyone's on board with that now.
But they weren't in those days, and yet it's so obvious.
And now all we've got to do is execute it, really, because, you know,
the evidence is there.
And it's just really a question of getting the money,
the talent enough and skilled, compassionate people to actually work
in those sorts of models.
Yeah, it's important that we don't forget recent history, isn't it?
I'm obviously a generation younger than you,
but where I grew up in South Australia was next to an asylum,
and we were terrified.
We were terrified to walk past and terrified of some of the inmates getting out.
And that was the stigma, wasn't it?
Yeah, that's exactly right, Luke.
And I always thought, even though, you know,
someone that, you know, had never come in contact with serious mental illness
might be frightened by it, when you actually talk to people,
they're just like us, you know.
They're human beings, and they're just the same.
They just happen to have a set of symptoms which can really be quite disturbing
for them, but they're treatable.
I mean, and when they are treated, they're back to normal,
but in the vast majority of cases.
So it's not as mystifying and terrifying as people think,
although to go through it without the right sort of care is terrifying.
But we see curiosity as a great dimension of modern leaders like yourself
and people using almost curiosity as their way to learning
and developing themselves, and clearly your history
of educating yourself is extensive.
How do you approach that now at this stage of your life
through the lens of your own learning and development
and maybe curiosity?
What does that mean to you?
Yeah, that's a great question.
I still am pretty curious.
Like you mentioned eating disorders and anorexia before,
that's something that I'm very curious about now because I've seen so much of it
in the last 18 months just directly and seeing how it develops
and how it's the most misunderstood illness now, I would say.
People have not really got a fundamental understanding
of why it happens or what it is, and there's very few evidence-based
treatments for it, so I'm very curious about that.
But in terms of learning, like I still want to keep learning.
I would like to learn more musical instruments.
I would like to learn more languages.
I'm learning Irish at the moment.
You know, I'm president of a Celtic club, believe it or not,
and I was born in Ireland, and I'm trying to learn the Irish language
here in Melbourne, and I've been doing that for the last 18 months.
So I still want to learn, even though, you know,
probably running out of time, but there's definitely more things
I want to do.
Born in beautiful Dublin in Ireland, and your dad was a doctor,
I believe, Pat, as well, so it's fascinating.
You're full circle now, learning the Celtic languages.
It's quite incredible.
We talk about communicating with clarity as well a lot through this series,
and you've published, you know, I think over 400 peer-reviewed papers
and 50 or more chapters I was reading and edited over six books,
so you know a little bit about communicating with clarity.
How do you think about that in your space?
Yeah, well, that's sort of the thing that you have to do in the research world,
you know, publish papers, and the reason, hopefully, some of them are,
you know, advances in knowledge, and that's kind of the currency
of academic life, you know, but what I learned to do in the last 10
or 15 years is write for the general public, you know,
so I've written heaps of op-ed pieces in the newspapers
and shorter things, you know, trying to actually sort of persuade
and influence people and educate people, I suppose,
not just the scientific community.
I mean, there are battles to be fought there, like the one I mentioned
about trying to prove.
I think that early intervention works and early diagnosis works,
and that's been a big battle because, believe it or not,
people have tried to argue against it in psychiatry.
You know, it's quite, you never see that in cancer, you know,
but you do see it in the mental health field.
But so I've had to do it in the scientific field too,
and you have to be careful so that you don't lose your objectivity
and you don't become a zealot, if I can put it that way,
just like a, just a pure advocate.
You have to still have the, you know, the kind of rational,
objective objectivity about it there.
But I've learned a lot from my great friend, Ian Hickey.
I don't know if you've ever interviewed Ian, but he's got his own podcast.
But he is a fantastic communicator.
Like, he's on the drum all the time, and he's much better out than me.
But we both have the same objective to try to help the public understand
what can be done and what needs to be done.
That's fascinating, Pat, to hear you talk about.
So there's been opposition to early preventative care for mental health issues,
and in your world, have you had to face opposition on that?
I find that quite staggering.
It's like it's hyper-scepticism.
They want roll-gold proof before they do anything, you know,
whereas what you've got to do in the real world is you produce some evidence
about what's the best available evidence for what you should do.
And you see this in, you know, cardiovascular medicine too,
like, you know, the debates about things like aspirin,
whether it's a good thing to do or not.
And so people, you know,
look at the evidence, but in psychiatry I've found there's a small group
of academics that basically just try to undermine any piece of progress
because, well, it's not really clear.
They're just too sceptical or they're – there's other motivating factors perhaps,
but they undermine progress.
And it's been – so we've had these battles within the field as well
to try to get progress.
And, you know, hopefully – as it's turned out,
the evidence has just accumulated and that's washed them away in the end.
But, yeah.
It's been, you know, like a paradigm shift that we've been trying to bring about.
And the best allies in this haven't been colleagues, actually.
It's been the public and the families and the young people that we've worked with.
They're our best supporters and they trust us with the evidence too.
The last dimension we talk about is collaboration.
Great leaders we're seeing are really just passionate about how they collaborate,
who they collaborate with, and clearly to grow Headspace and Origin.
And what you've done is just quite extraordinary.
How have you thought about collaboration?
How have you gone about it?
Well, I suppose I thought about it in two ways.
One is the internal team, you know, like the internal footy team.
And you keep having to find new rookies and new draft picks and, you know,
and you want quite a few hundred gamers in there too.
So I thought about it that way in turn.
It's a team game, what we're doing, you know.
And obviously there's got to be a coach and there's got to be, you know,
a few star players.
So that's probably a simple person.
That's the way I've thought about it.
And then outside, you look around the world and you try to find the other people
that share your kind of, you know, purpose.
And even in other countries, there was a Norwegian psychiatrist in Stavanger
in Norway who was a, you know, very similar personality to me, I think,
you know, and campaigned really in that sort of more political way
for a better deal for the mentally ill.
So finding those sort of people to work with.
And it's very inspiring.
You can learn a lot from these other people.
Which leads in nicely, Pat, to a couple of questions I've been asking all the leaders
that we've had the privilege of speaking to.
And the first one is, who has been the greatest leader in your life, Pat?
Oh, gee.
I have to think about that one.
I think Nelson Mandela has been a pretty inspiring person.
If I think of political leaders.
I was always a big fan of Goff.
I grew up in the 1970s and, you know, I was a medical student
when Goff was the prime minister.
He threatened the status quo so much that they got rid of him, basically.
And, but his legacy continued on for forever, really.
And so he was very inspiring politically.
Within the mental health field, the person that actually got me over the line
to do psychiatry was a woman called Beverly Raphael.
And she was the foundation professor in Newcastle.
I grew up in Newcastle in Australia.
And she was the founder of the University of Newcastle.
I went to uni in Sydney.
She had been an academic in Sydney, Sydney University.
And she became the first professor at the new medical school in Newcastle.
And I was a medical registrar at Royal Newcastle Hospital.
And I went and had a chat with her.
I said, look, I'd really like to do psychiatry, but it looks so terrible
that working the conditions of the patients and everything is, do you think
it's, you know, I needed to be sort of encouraged, I suppose, to take the leap.
And she was a very special person.
She had actually made her career.
She made her career in the study of bereavement and grief, you know, so in other words, helping
people to recover from what we were talking about earlier, the losses and traumas, and
she became a disaster expert later on.
But she was like a warm, compassionate woman who projected that and she was a great communicator
too.
She projected the warmth and compassion.
A lot of psychiatrists that you see, the stereotypes, they're kind of a bit withdrawn and a little
bit aloof, but she was the opposite.
And so I could, I can imagine, you know, that she was the opposite.
You know, being like that and seeing, doing something like what she was doing and what
she had done.
And so I think she was a very good leader.
And then the person that brought me to Melbourne was a professor called Bruce Singh, who's
working for her at the same time.
And he was a different type of character.
He was someone who could build things and he was a tough operator, like politically.
And so I learned a lot from him too.
So those two people were very good leaders within psychiatry and, you know, gave me the
confidence, I suppose, to try to do something in their footsteps.
What a great answer, Pat.
That's from Nelson Mandela, right through to an inspiration very close to home, which
is fascinating to look back and the journey of people that you've been exposed to.
And the final question we've been asking in recent times, if you could collaborate with
anyone in the world, Pat, anyone that we could put you in touch with, who would you collaborate
with?
Well, this might be a bit premature, but I've been reading a lot of books.
I've read a lot of books.
I've been reading some books by a woman called Mariana Mazzucato, who I got exposed to through
my son, Fionn, that I mentioned before.
She's written books about reforming capitalism so that it becomes of value to the community
and the society.
So in other words, not a revolution, but actually modifying it so that you don't get all of
these, what she calls, rent seekers or value extractors out of the economy.
So people have to contribute something positive to the economy, and you do see business people
doing that these days, and I'm just thinking of Andrew Forrest.
He's made a lot of money, but he's actually doing some good things, feeding back in.
But she's talking about something a bit different, I think.
She's talking about value rather than just money as what's produced.
And it's very profound what she's writing about, and I thought trying to sort of build
on that in the terms of like a mentally healthy lifestyle.
Yeah.
A healthy and mentally strong society would be a great thing to just at least probably
support and understand more about that.
But that's going outside of my field, really.
But I'm impressed with her intellect.
If you could get her on the program, she'd be a great one to interview.
Much better than me.
I'd love to.
Pat, you've set a very high bar, and I've always been inspired by listening to you and
have been fortunate enough to chat to you a couple of times in different formats.
And the work you've done is inspirational.
And as I said, I do feel, Pat, like I want to stand on the rooftops and try and bring
as much attention to this.
For whatever reason, I feel passionate about the fact that your term, Shadow Pandemic,
has happened.
And we need to really let people know that there is a massive, massive need for this
and the work that you've done, for whatever reason, hasn't had that attention as the other
illnesses in the past, but it feels as though it's going to be the great issue for our kids'
generation going forward.
So whatever we can do to support, Pat, we'd love to be behind.
And if you feel like donating to Headspace, we'd love to be behind.
Yeah.
Headspace or Origin, we'll send all the links out to the fantastic work that you do.
And Australians for Mental Health, if people more generally beyond young people want to
kind of just raise the kind of temperature of that issue, that would be a great way to
Australians for Mental Health.
You could Google Australians for Mental Health and Chris Raine would be the person to contact.
Yeah, we'll put all those details down.
Pat, it's a great honor to have been able to spend some time with you again.
Congratulations on all your work.
And I'm sure there's plenty more chapters to come.
Plenty more chapters to write.
Thanks so much for your time.
Well, you're way too kind, Luke, but thank you so much for the opportunity.
I really enjoyed talking to you.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me, Luke Darcy, produced by Matt Dwyer, with audio
production by Darcy Thompson.
Start your leadership journey.
I encourage you to go to elitacollective.com, take our Empowering Leaders Indicator tool
and understand the impact you have on your environment.
Join us at Elida to learn, lead, and collaborate.
Transcription by CastingWords