I hope you enjoy this episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast with the one and only Ruddick
Sally, a great Australian, one of our most successful ever businessmen, who as CEO guided
the Swiss Wellness Group to extraordinary success. Ruddick shares his obsession with
creating a workplace that is healthy and happy for everyone. His incredible accountability to
every mistake that he's made or that his team and sharing those mistakes with his team or LGIs,
as he calls them, learning growth, improvement opportunities. He's an incredible leader and a
contributor in every sense. Ruddick epitomizes everything that we're passionate about in the
work we do at Alita. It's a space co-founded with my lifelong friend, Matt Waterwitz,
where we are really passionate about creating a world of collaboration, inspiring connections,
and love you to check out our Alita Connect signature program, where we bring together
diverse range of leaders from industry, from sport, the arts, social venture,
in bespoke leadership forums to learn, to lead,
and collaborate. We'd love to connect with you. Book a call so we can chat. Go to alitacollective.com.
And the Empowering Leaders podcast is proudly presented by the team at Tempa. It is a mattress
like no other. And we know that inspiring leaders like Ruddick Sally understand how important the
health benefits of sleep and sleeping well are, and to sleep on the best NASA-approved bedding
in the world. It is a decision, I guarantee you, that will change your life for the good.
Ruddick Sally is one of Australia's most
successful businessmen, and he's a great leader in the world.
He's a successful business people and a serial entrepreneur in the health and wellness sector.
He revolutionized the Swiss wellness group, pioneering the use of brand ambassadors
before helping to negotiate the sale of Swiss for $1.7 billion. The positive work culture created
at Swiss under Ruddick, the CEO, saw the company recognized in 2015 and 16 as the best place to
work in Australia. Ruddick used some of the proceeds of the sale to set up Light Warrior,
an investment group committed to creating shared value by investing in businesses,
that are socially responsible and environmentally conscious. He's a past GQ entrepreneur of the year,
CEO in residence at Melbourne University, and an honorary alumni at La Trobe University.
Ruddick, it's always great to see you. It's a life full of great joy and success by the sounds of it.
It's only just the beginning. It's a great apprenticeship. So much more to do.
So thanks for having us today.
Well, can I start with the sale of the Swiss Vitamins Group? It was to a Hong Kong-listed
entity.
It's still one of the biggest ever private company transactions
in Australian corporate history. You're the CEO. You're a big part of the ownership group. It is a
great success story. Can you tell us a bit about how you became part of that world?
Yeah, so I was very lucky or fortunate to have been born into a family where I've,
my father's a professor of surgery and my mother's a medical scientist. And dad was one of the first
people to talk about diet causing disease in traditional medicine. So I was very lucky to have
been born in traditional medical circles. And that was back in the 70s. And so he was laughed at back
then. And I was born in the 70s. So I grew up with that as a background. And it took 20 years for his
work to be published in British Medical Journal. And now when we look back on the fact that, you
know, people were laughing at diet causing disease, it's kind of laughable that people were thinking
that way. But he got a seriously hard time. So dad would lecture at home about, you know, his work
and how important it was.
It was. And mum would read the blood of his patients to make sure they had all of the right
nutrition to fight whatever condition that they were preparing to fight. Because, you know, it
makes us so much sense to be as healthy as we possibly can be to deal with whatever medical
condition that we kind of face. And so a lot of these intuitive things that made sense back then
needed science to support it. And, you know, the natural progression would have made to go down the
medical path.
Well, that really turned me off and kind of it was kind of it switched this entrepreneurial side on in
me is how you can beat the system and how you can make the system work in a better way and more
inclusive of all. And Swiss was probably the first incarnation of that, although I did a wonderful
apprenticeship at a place called Village Roadshow where I got to work globally with them, start in
the candy bar and work my way up into senior management roles there.
But.
But by the by the grand old age of 27, I kind of worked out that I wasn't going to be the CEO of
Village Roadshow in the near term future that had just had a 30 year old CEO who didn't work out.
And I thought, oh, gee, now my time's done.
They're not going to appoint me.
So they appointed some some guy that was almost 50 from a toilet paper background.
And so it was time for me to to go and do something else.
And in our network, we had all these interesting, wonderful people that my father knew of.
And one of those was Michael Saba.
He was the managing director of Swiss at the time.
And and dad had had connections with all these people in nutrition because he wanted to make
sure that whatever he recommended his patients was always the best of quality.
He actually never had a financial deal with Swiss until I came on board a little later
and brought him in as a consultant to support us.
He just did it out of the goodness of his heart to make sure that when he was recommending
something for his patients, it had the best quality ingredients.
And and Swiss was one of those groups.
He was working with.
So we had a relationship there and and and timing was right.
They had approached me a couple of times a year or two before that.
And I wanted to stick with what we were doing.
And I came across and joined Swiss and slowly bought into the business and the organization.
And, you know, we had an extraordinary product to start with.
And men's and women's multivitamin were turning about 12, 13 million turnover.
And there was a great culture.
My two business partners are just extraordinary individuals.
Really kind.
And people that really put our people first.
So that gave me a really good basis, a good foundation to build a great business from there.
Your dad, Professor Avani Sully, as you described, the founding father in lots of ways of integrated medicine.
Brilliant man.
I have enjoyed spending some time with with him and ahead of his time in every sense.
As you described, you're a child of the 70s.
And I can imagine those dinner party conversations where your dad was really ahead of his time.
And for those, this integrated medicine is taking the best of Western approach and surgery and but integrating it with things like acupuncture or yoga that has got evidence base around genuinely supporting better health and a better sense of well-being.
And I'm not surprised to hear you say that was a formative part of your world growing up.
Your dad's still in the office at NIM, the National Integrated Medicine.
So you're on the board of NIM.
It has shaped your life.
Hasn't it?
When you look at what you do still and what you did then, it's it's fascinating that's come out in the entrepreneurial space.
But it was probably always going to be there, wasn't it?
Yeah, dad's so unique.
I mean, he works harder than he still works harder than I've ever worked in his 80s.
So I just don't know how he does it.
He's a great inspiration and he just lives and breathes health.
And, you know, that's his passion.
He loves talking about it.
And and that's why he does it every day.
And I love the way you spoke about.
You know, you saw he had to push through.
And I love his patience when you talk to him.
He understands the system and the interest in it.
And he's got this incredible way of acknowledging it, but saying we can still still do good.
I mean, you obviously saw the hardship when people are discrediting you and putting aside stuff that would have helped so many people early.
As you said, the thought that your food doesn't affect your health.
That's what they're arguing against effectively at the time.
But somewhere in your mind, you went, all right, I can.
I can do this without trying to change the system.
I'm going to have an impact in a different way.
Was that a really conscious thing, as you said?
I think so.
I mean, I'm very intuitive and I like to follow where my heart sends me and where my passion is.
And and definitely a lot of roads were leading in that direction.
And to come back to it, it prepared for prepared me for a lot of the inertia we would face as an organisation down the path as we kind of went.
From being as an industry when I kind of started, it was it was it was kind of the hairy hippie hippies or there was kind of product for IBS and UTIs, irritable bowel syndrome or or urinary tract infections and and kind of not barbecue speak.
And I'd come from Village Roadshow where every week we had new movies, great new talent to talk about, you know, what's Brad Pitt's new movie or or what's Angelina Jolie up to?
And and.
And, you know, when's the next premiere?
Can I come along?
And then I suddenly would go to barbecues and tell people I work at Swiss and I'd say, well, the embassy and then I'd say no vitamins and I'd quickly change the subject because I'd be worried I'd be talking about the UTI or IBS and kind of.
And so for me, it became quite, quite obvious that there was a real opportunity to kind of create a lifestyle product.
And there was one product that was doing really, really well, which was called Centrum.
And they had an ambassador.
They're called Rob DeCostella, who is a marathon runner that won some medals in the Commonwealth Games and and and a great talent.
And and and I'd walk into stores and there'd be this wall of Centrum product and I'd ask them about, you know, why do you give so much space to that product?
And they would tell me, oh, because it's because of the I'd say no.
Why? And I'd suggest that they get the best margin out of out of that that brand.
And I'd say, no, it's actually the worst margin in the category.
Why?
And they'd go, I guess, why do you range it so much?
Well, they advertise 52 weeks of the year and they've got this great point of sale with Rob DeCostella.
And interestingly enough, you know, in that barbecue speak, the occasional person would say, yeah, no, no, I take Centrum.
And I'd say, why? Because of Rob DeCostella.
And so we looked at our kind of Swiss world and and I would ask people why they arranged that product in a health food store or pharmacy.
And and they would say, you know, Swiss sells itself.
And I go, maybe we're onto something here.
We've got a premium product.
That's retaining customers.
And we would we research this later on a number of years later on.
And we found we had the highest retention in the category.
Seventy percent of people who would try a brand would retain taking Swiss after after trying it.
So the fundamentals of marketing is that if you've got a great product, which goes back to, again, having people like my father involved in advising on the raw materials, the nutrition and making sure the science was right.
So it would make a noticeable difference.
So if you've got a great product, the fundamentals of marketing.
If you invest in it, you know, you're going to you're going to open up a bigger consumer base.
So I'd look in those pharmacies and you look over to the perfume section and all the cosmetic section that beautifully up.
They had all these great people that were ambassadors or advertising their products.
And as I said, Rob DeCostella was a great sports person.
You know, there was an opportunity to be a bit more dynamic.
And so Ricky Ponting, when you took the.
The product and I reached out to him and said, how would you feel about doing a Swiss campaign?
And we couldn't afford 52 weeks of the TV.
We could only afford sponsoring the cricket.
And that's what we did.
We advertised in the cricket with the personality and off off it went from there.
All the way to Nicole Kidman as a as a brand ambassador, as a pioneer.
And I wasn't I knew the story and we all saw it.
We suddenly saw Swiss everywhere and and it worked.
It became, you know, you know, in the sporting.
World product and you created that sense that, you know, it was aspirational and you wanted to take vitamins and made them, you know, something to behold.
As you said, like every, you know, success story.
That's one thing to have the play.
I mean, can you tell us, you know, you put Nicole Kidman on the whiteboard.
It's one thing to do that.
It's another thing to convince, you know, a Hollywood A grade superstar to to to join the product.
Was that challenging?
Well, I think.
We had a few things work out really well for us.
Whilst all of this was going on and kind of we created this aspirational brand piece in the health category.
What also became quite clear to us is is health became one of the few things you could continue to boast about.
And we all talk about still to this day, the detox program, the marathon we're training for the gym program.
You know, it's one of those few things that we can still keep, you know, say, hey, look at me.
I'm doing this to our friends without people going.
You got to pull your head in there, buddy.
So so we rode that kind of wave of this kind of transformation of wellness being something that everyone wanted to have a part of.
And it would be OK to kind of talk about openly.
So we had all these successful people working with us.
And by the time we got to Nicole, it was around 300 different ambassadors of shapes and sizes and organizations that we'd work with.
So the pitch to Nicole was, you know, it's the first Australian company that she'd ever got behind.
And she'd be very, very careful with her brand.
Timing just felt very right for all parties.
And you have to get timing right.
And there was a sense that we would do the right thing by her.
And this is much as important for us for her to do the right thing for us.
And so, yeah, it was a wildly difficult deal to get done.
And Hollywood managers are excruciatingly challenging at the best of times.
And I used to make the joke of.
While we're doing the deal, I better just check if I've still got my wedding ring on my finger.
But we got there in the end with a lot of patience and not with this kind of positive culture that we had as an organization would always turn negative things into challenges rather than the word problem didn't exist in our business.
So any time something that was a bit of a challenge that came up like with the Nicole contracts that felt insurmountable would say, well, this is a challenge.
And let's turn it into a positive.
And let's work out how we work.
And generally, when you can kind of speak human to human, you can get there.
And thankfully, we got there after about a year of negotiations.
A year, full 12 months.
That's interesting.
It's good to.
I love having the opportunity to do this.
You know, people listen to that story here, the bio and you go straight from Village Road.
So you sell the business for one point seven billion dollars.
You know how what a great path that was.
I'm sure you've got 400 stories of twists and turns and ups and downs.
And as you said, turning problems in into solutions.
I understand, you know, when you took on the US market, that came with a set of challenges as well.
Tell us about your leadership in those situations where, you know, there were moments where, you know, you had some pretty big hurdles to jump.
Yeah.
So, yeah, I was in Swiss for 12 years.
So the journey now we really kind of played around with this formula of growth and then product growth as well that supported that for the sort of first.
Three years.
And then we worked out what we call that flywheel and this flywheel of kind of marketing and personality event.
And then, you know, pre-selling that into a retailer to ensure the cost of the marketing with the sale of the product in and then the product selling through and that creating competitive tension.
Because if we were doing a spring racing carnival promotion with Chemist Warehouse, you know,
the price line would get on the phone and say, we want to do the next promotion because that was extraordinary.
We got great cut through.
So we'd go and work with them on the tennis or the Olympics for Woolworths and then Nicole Kidman for back to Chemist Warehouse or whoever else was kind of in the mix.
So you get the best deal and the best product selling and then the best support from those stores to ensure best sell through.
And so that momentum built and kind of created this kind of flywheel.
But it would go wrong.
And that's when you learn most.
We would actually call it an LGI moment.
We had language in our business that kind of created our framework for our values and our business planning was really, really important.
But our culture planning and the language around our culture would be reviewed as regularly as our business plans.
And we'd had KPIs related to business performance, but also culture performance.
And, you know, you rarely hear me talk about I.
We talk about we as a team.
And, you know, unless I've made an error.
And I would call out my errors quite regularly.
I should have been fired probably three times over.
And I would talk about that with the team so we could all learn from that.
And it was okay to talk about when something went wrong because then you could break it apart and go, okay, what should we have got right and what could we have done better?
And a classic example was launching in the U.S.
We had Ellen DeGeneres and her TV show coming out to Australia, thankfully, and Nicole Kidman featuring on that show to launch.
And we gave away everyone.
We had a seat in the audience to come to Australia to enjoy the Ellen show and spend a week in Australia and in L.A. there.
And it kicked off.
But when I flew in, I was really excited about that.
But we got into our retailers.
We had 30,000 retailers supporting us.
And they all told us that you don't have to worry.
We're going to arrange your products.
You don't need a merchandise.
You don't need a field sales force.
And so I walked into the Walgreens stores and they had these great posters up with Nicole Kidman and Ellen DeGeneres and a Swiss product.
But the product just wasn't.
It was down in the bottom corner, like one product.
There was no merchandising.
I just said to the team, we're gone here.
We're going to have to do something pretty rapidly.
And thankfully, we got on board with our business partners at Swiss.
I mean, sorry, at Swiss.
I'm at Chemist Warehouse.
And we did a deal where we did an exclusive partnership with them for Ellen DeGeneres.
They agreed to buy a certain amount of stock, which was the difference of us going bankrupt or not.
And.
That promotion was absolutely extraordinary and worked for all of us.
And out of that was the kind of basis for what we call Project Gold, which is how we exploded into China.
So you mentioned an LGI moment.
That's a big one, isn't it?
You're literally facing bankruptcy.
You're launching the US and you walked into a store and gone, we're in real trouble here.
This is a moment to find that pathway.
And the Chemist Warehouse story was a great partnership for you in the end.
And it must have been some hairy moments at that.
And what does an LGI moment mean?
Well, it's a learn, grow and improve moment.
So it's something our production manager once said in a production meeting when we were talking about manufacturing.
And he was from Kazakhstan.
And he had a wonderful accent.
And we were running through what had gone right and what had not gone so well.
And he said, yes, yes, this is a learn, grow and improve moment.
And from that moment onward, we call it the LGI.
And so rather than when someone said, you know, you've got something wrong, you know, we've got to talk about it.
You know, immediately then you laughed, as I said, LGI.
And so whenever something went wrong in our business, rather than say, hey, you've got that wrong, we'd say, hey, it's an LGI.
So we'd lighten up the moment and then LA would unpack it and talk about it and have a bit of humour that goes with it to make it a bit easier.
There's a great bit of wisdom in that, isn't it?
Because so many places, you know, the old school of leadership rhetoric is that you don't show weakness or if you've made a mistake,
you're going to let the time.
You're going to let the team down.
And we know how limiting that is when you sort of celebrate the moments to grow.
I mean, it's easier said than done, isn't it, when you put your hand up.
But clearly, you've obviously seen that that's the only way to work.
And is it something that has continued on throughout the life of you that you've been able to just own those moments?
I absolutely have to.
I mean, we're all human.
We make errors.
And I think we've gone away from this period where we survived.
We put on the tie.
And we're doing it, you know, we're doing the work, the business of work for our family.
We've actually got to do it for a bigger cause.
We've got to do it for society.
And that's linked back to our family.
And capitalism plays such a huge part in our society.
And that partnership with democracy is so essential for it to work.
You know, four out of five of us work in businesses and one out of five are in government.
And so, you know, we can't wait for government to.
We can't wait for government to solve issues in society.
And so part of what we can do as business leaders is make our workplaces the best place to be.
And that's what I lose sleep about is how people feel coming to work with me and working on whatever they do and making sure that they have purpose and feel truly engaged and doing what they love.
And also, you know, feel free to be open about where they've fallen over and where they need to improve.
And I just think of the best.
The best relationships in my life, you know, like the one I have currently with my wife, we challenge each other.
We bring out the best with each other.
We're honest with each other.
And that's great.
And, yeah, we irritate each other, but we talk about it and we become better of it.
And I think of the reverse, which, you know, I reckon, you know, 80 to a bit less than I used to say 90 percent.
Now I reckon it's about 80 to 70 percent of people are in that bad relationship we've all had where, you know, I had one of these girlfriends in the past.
When I broke up with her, everyone said, oh, you know, you should have broken up with her years ago and you weren't good for each other and she wasn't good.
It was the same poor thing for her.
I wasn't good for her either and we're both much better people broken up.
But we're all in this kind of, you know, a lot of us are in these workplaces where we feel trepidation about having to go into work and we feel down about it and, you know, that's, you know, really as us business leaders, we're not doing our bit for society and making this kind of form of work.
I think there's a lot of value in that.
But I think it's really important to have that kind of freedom that we have, work to its best and optimum.
So I'm obsessed by sharing that story and hoping others will come along for that journey.
And it is a brilliant thing to share, Radag.
I appreciate you doing that, because you're right, we spend such a significant period of our time at work and when workplaces are unhappy, and often that is the case because someone's in a leadership role, you know, I give people the better of the doubt that, you know, not always malicious but lacking in the language that you just had around leadership.
around being obsessed with making it a place where people can make mistakes, where they are
happy, where they are full of purpose, and when they can grow. I mean, clearly, Swiss was that.
You said you had great partners who I know, but you went after that with that language. And we
know that the research says that you go home, you have a happier home life, you become better
parents, your health, your actual physical health improves when you work. But the bottom line is
the productivity of the group is better too. So it's self-serving at the same time, Ruddick,
but it still seems missed. I've been in so many places where you can walk in and you can tangibly
feel how disconnected and miserable people are in an office. You don't even have to ask a question.
You can actually see it in their face every single day. As you said, it's one of the great
tragedies of life, isn't it? Yeah, it's such a thing just being aware, like you're talking about,
that level of consciousness that we all have.
And have a capability to switch on, which I've had people laugh at or actually say to me,
you can't meditate your way to profit. And we would meditate twice a day. My wife and I bought
it as a gift for each other for our paper anniversary, I think we were fourth or fifth
year in, and said we both need it. And we got this fantastic meditation coach in who trained
us to meditate. And I'd always had meditation in my life. I'd always had meditation in my life.
It was my father and so forth, but I just hadn't found a method that resonated with me. And kind
of where I'm going with the meditation part is kind of meditation to me is like, I ask people
if they shower or they kind of brush their teeth every day. And they kind of, yeah, yeah. And that's
basic hygiene, isn't it? The other part of hygiene that we need to think about is our mind. And our
mind being engaged and ready for what is the present and the now and that person in front of
you. So it's not just the present and the now. It's the present and the now. And that person in
front of you. So it's not just the present and the now and that person in front of you. So it's not
disengaged. You know, we've all sat in meetings where you can clearly see that person is just
caught up in whatever garbage that copped in that last meeting and they're unpacking it in front of
you and it stinks. And kind of meditation makes you, I won't say kind of, meditation makes you
more aware of kind of what that chatter in your mind and whether you are being as present as you
can be and should be for that person. And a classic example of that is before this conversation,
I've had a really busy morning. Funny to think that up here in Brunswick Heads is where we enjoyed
the beach and having a swim. But stuff does go on and it's been back to back meetings and I go,
I just need my 20 minutes. I got up at 5am, the dog barking, wanted to have a drink of water. And
that's, she's got into the pattern of that because we go and meditate and watch the sunrise, which is
fantastic. But then, you know, by just before this, which we're on at two, I was like, oh,
thank goodness, I've got 30 minutes. I took my
breath of meditation and I'm back, you know, I can give you my all and I can be present.
And so, you know, we forget that as leaders that we do need to take time out to bring our best,
to give our all as leaders and to really listen to the people that we're speaking to.
Listening is just a, is something that is a craft that I think that we don't put enough
emphasis on. Yeah, brilliant to hear you talk about that. I knew you were
a passionate meditator.
And, you know, Mark Barney, who wrote a brilliant book, Ancient Wisdom for Modern
Health, and he called it a holiday for his brain, twice a day, the same technique. And I was going
to ask you, you grew up in a house with a forward-thinking mother and father who understood
health in a way that very few did. And you've developed, you know, with your own family,
meditation practice on a daily basis. What other things do you do, Radhik, that, you know, keep
you healthy and happy and successful? What sort of daily habits do you do?
Meditation clearly is the way you start your day. What other things keep you healthy?
Well, I think it's about setting up a routine that works for you, that you really look forward to.
You should love doing all of these things. I love doing the meditation. And if you don't,
you've got to find something that works for you. So something that you're a natural at and that
you kind of, you gravitate to. So it's like, it's no good if you're no good at, if you haven't got
basic ball skills, you're never going to be a great footballer, hey, like, so,
so don't bother trying to do that, even though you like the idea of becoming that. So
work out your wellness program to fit. So for me, and, you know, I can kind of, whenever I have
really stressful times in life, I make sure that I drink a whole lot less and I eat a whole lot
healthier, knowing that I need to be absolutely on my game. I make sure I meditate twice a day.
If I'm a little less stressed, you know, once I'm okay with, and I still crave after that second,
you know, I can, I can deal with once, but if I'm really stressed, I make sure that the twice
is happening. Then I'll do yoga. I do that twice a week. I work out in the gym four times a week.
I'm no good without a personal trainer. I need someone to keep me honest as I turn up.
And then a lot of working, a lot of personal movement and a game of golf, not worrying about
how the golf balls hit, but catching up with friends and, and just talking, talking about
things that you, you normally wouldn't talk about. Us blokes are terrible.
That conversation compared to females, they'll talk about, you know, a lump on their breast
that's formed and be very comfortable about sharing that with a friend, us guys and talking
about a lump somewhere they're uncomfortable about sharing, um, just doesn't come naturally.
So, you know, get a group of friends around you where you can be really open and honest
and they're really open and honest with you and keep you honest in more ways than one,
not only in your personal life, your business life and get to know you intimately. So make
sure that that kind of wellness schedule, um, has a lot of socially,
uh, you know, socially positive things happening. You know, go for a paddleboard down here.
We call it a board meeting because it's with paddleboards and it's usually a bunch of good
friends that we go and paddle. And we just talk as we paddle about things you otherwise
wouldn't talk about. So try and work out a program that allows for all those sorts of
things.
I'm reminded as you're talking of, uh, a line and I will butcher this, but I think it was
a Gandy line saying, I've got the most, uh, uh, busy schedule today. I'm going to meditate
for two hours instead of one to be, uh, to be successful.
And, and it's the start of slowing down to be more productive. Sounds counterintuitive,
doesn't it? But I want to ask you about, about, sorry to cut you off there. I want to ask you
about, uh, you know, the, the commitment to impact investment investing and come back to that before
I do. I, I think this story, and I rarely ask before an interview starts to someone, do you
mind if I ask a question? And your answer was nothing is off limits. You asked me whatever
you like, and you've invested in a range of, uh, of different things with, you know, great,
success and impact as you do in, in lots of areas, including, uh, George Columbaris's
restaurant group made. And shortly after, if I, if I get the sequence right, you do
an audit of the business. It comes to light, the business has underpaid its employees,
$7.8 million or there, there about. You self-report, you go to the Fair Work Commission, you pay
back a hundred percent of the money, but the fallout from it, Radak, is just quite extraordinary.
The cancel culture, George gets canceled out of everything in life. I mean, can you tell us
about that time? For me, it's a great leadership story. In the mainstream world, it was portrayed
as, uh, as something very different. How, how, how did that one play out?
Uh, yeah, it was very challenging at the time. Not, not so challenging for me,
aside from the financial impact. Um, but, but to see over 500 employees,
lose their, their jobs in a, in a sector that, you know, as difficult as it is, you, you're
dealing with, you know, minimum wage, uh, operators. It's, it's really hard for, for people
working in those sorts of organizations. Um, they do shift work, um, and, and, and so, and they
loved working with our organization and, and we, we led from the front and, and something that was
right in the industry and not just in our industry.
It's been an issue for banks, for universities, for government. Every industry has, in some way
or another, that hires casual employees, missed the mark on paying people correctly per hour.
Now, we, we were one of the early ones to say, hey, we're getting this wrong and we want to
fix it and, and we want to be transparent about how we're doing it. How that was interpreted by
the public was, you know, really probably turned into a lobbying campaign.
Which I've seen many times in, in past lives. And, um, and so it was a, it was a lobbying campaign
for the union movement to, and, and they were getting traction, um, by using George's name, um,
as, as, as a wage thief, which is clearly not that because a thief is someone that tries to
steal something without calling out that, hey, they're, they're trying to make it right. Um,
and, and, and that, that got momentum and media momentum was with the story and the facts
suddenly, you know, while, you know, we were, we were, we were, we were, we were, we were, we were
you know, we were, we were, we were, we were, we were, we were, we were, we were, we were, we were,
some of it on, on the face that it wasn't great and, and processes should have been right.
Um, there was a lot that was right. And also go back to, you know, the mess that, uh, all of
these agreements are in. We had 60 ways you would pay, you could pay, different ways you'd pay a,
a restaurant working person. Now, most people in, in the corporate world that I come from,
you pay them a salary and that's it. You don't need to worry about anything above and beyond.
You know, we had, if they'd done this course or that course,
they would be paid this amount and it's five cents difference
and so forth.
You know, where was the impetus on whoever set up those agreements
on making it straightforward for those people being paid
to actually work out what they should be paid?
And I remember if I'm not paid the right amount, you know,
at Village Roadshow, it was really clear what I needed
to be paid each week.
And I'd call out to my employer, hey, you've missed this or that.
But it was near impossible for any employee to actually know
what they're supposed to be paid.
And that's why every industry has been hit by this.
And, you know, you've got businesses that are, and I won't name them
because, you know, they shouldn't be called out for individual
because there's a wider issue in the why and why this has all happened
that needs to be solved for.
And so, you know, there's organisations that were underpaying people
$700 million, almost close to a billion dollars, a number of them,
and there's no individual that was called out.
And I just feel like that George, you know, and I think this is
a fundamental issue with Australia is that we do have casual racism going on.
And if it had been George Smith, it might have been a different story.
It might be controversial, but I'm calling out, as I say,
it was George Kalambaras.
He's a great fella.
And there are sayings that go with that that are negative
and have some negative connotations.
So I think some of that, along with all of the other things,
all just didn't help.
Yeah.
In that situation.
But what I can be very proud of is I can hold my heart on,
hand up my heart and say we did absolutely the right thing
in a very difficult circumstance.
And history will look kindly upon how we've done things.
And that's all you can do.
It will look really kindly on that.
And I know you don't want to mention those,
but it was Woolworths who underpaid three quarters of a billion dollars
only a few months later.
And I'm not pointing fingers there either,
but no one could name the CEO at the time.
He got his bonus.
He got his bonus at the end of the year and moved on.
And, you know, we saw, you know, the perfect storm.
He's an Italian fella.
So maybe my, he's an Italian fella to see.
Maybe my story of casual racism doesn't stack up.
Well, you know, with accounting departments that have got hundreds in,
as opposed to small business and the restaurant game was the other point
that I was trying to make.
And, you know, perfect storm for George.
You're on TV, Australian tall poppy syndrome, as you said,
a touch of casual racism thrown in.
I find a parent, the council culture that has emerged, as you said before,
the LGI, the learn, grow and improve moments to say, yeah,
let's all put our hand up and we can all learn in this together.
I think it's a really worthwhile conversation to have.
I appreciate you sharing it because it leads to my next question.
I asked this young entrepreneur, I sat in a room once about to start
leadership business leader we're really passionate about.
And we had two people sitting there giving us some advice.
And one said,
for my, this is a tough path, you know, it's going to have all sorts of dramas.
And, you know, you've explained there's going to be some hard,
I wouldn't recommend.
And the other guy said, absolutely do it.
It's the greatest thing you can do to create something from nothing.
What advice would you give to an entrepreneur that maybe wants to go down your path?
I think that if you're following your passion and you've done the apprenticeship,
done the schooling, the schooling of life or schooling of university to go with,
to help you be at your best to deliver the outcome, you know,
I do meet a lot of people who just haven't done the hard yards
and understand the fundamentals enough to take that next step.
But, yeah, if you've got that great basis of, you know,
working with a big corporate and got the fundamentals of business
and perhaps done some university training, yeah, you're ready to have a crack
and you'll be fit for the journey.
Otherwise, you may end up, you know,
end up pretty frustrated and a lot of people point to success stories
and whilst there's a lot of those, there's many thousands more of people
where it hasn't worked out.
And so the realities of that need to be talked about.
And if you're up for that, fantastic.
Have a go.
Yeah, and I think that's great context too, Radhik, isn't it?
So if you're betting the house and the whole family future on a startup
without, as you said, a foundation of expertise,
and skill, maybe that's a little touch forward.
If you're having a crack at something you're super passionate about,
you love more than anything in your life, but if it doesn't work out,
you can go back to, you know, Village Roadshow or go and work for Radhik
at Wanderlust, which is where I wanted to head next.
And your passion for socially responsible, you know,
environmentally conscious projects.
Can I ask you about, you know, yoga to music and festivals?
What's the passion at the moment?
So there's kind of two main buckets to our investment organization called Light Warrior,
which is what my wife called me when she fell in love with me.
So we stuck with that name.
So we have Light Warriors, the kind of commercial stuff,
and Light Focus as our charitable foundation work.
And I spend half my time doing community work.
I'm chair of a group called Igniting Change,
which is just the most extraordinary organization that works
with social entrepreneurs making change.
In the community.
And then I'm part of this group called the B Team
and the Climate Leaders Coalition, which I was a founding member of
and helped organize, and I was a founding member
of the B Team of Still Asia, which is plan A is under threat,
and we need to create a plan B, which is, and plan A is profits.
You know, businesses are built just to create profit for shareholders.
Plan B is about creating full stakeholder value.
And, and so, so yeah, so, and then this Climate Leaders Coalition,
which came out of the B Team has all 40 companies now,
over 35% of total carbon emissions represented.
We just want to get on with fixing the carbon issue and, and hit, hit targets
for 50% reduction by 2030 and, and, and the carbon issue by 2050.
But all work together to deliver that, which is just so enlightening and, and enlightening
in part.
And, and so precious to be a part of, and, and see that corporate Australia
is really prepared to make this next step.
We want to get on with it.
And so then whatever we do in business, we want to make sure we create great culture,
but they also are about enhancing our community.
So we, health is, is really, really key.
You know, if we don't love ourself, we're not going to love the world around us.
And so Wanderlust is about that, creating connection through yoga,
creating these amazing events that people want to go to, giving them
Ayurvedic products that, that are herbal products that have been used for thousands
of years.
Yeah.
And now being validated through science, um, posturing that next to meditation,
which you get introduced to through yoga and everyone loves doing a Shavasana after yoga.
Did you know yoga is the number one, um, number one sport in the country has the highest
participation in the country.
Um, so, so it's, it's got a massive, uh, massive appeal and could be even bigger.
Um, and, and so, um, so yeah, so, and then we've got this beautiful business called
commune, which is kind of the Netflix of, of wellness, which plugs in.
It's called social, social, social marketing in Australia, which is really
inspiring because you can find a lot of people who're willing to invest in
what we're talking about and, and, and, and, you know,
to, and to some degree, you know,
to make a difference at the, at the, at the, uh,
at the, uh, at the, at the company level.
So, uh, the, and the information has a lot to do with, with the fact that,
with the fact that we're, we're a nonprofit company, uh,
we're a, we've worked with the United States.
We're the biggest provider of social housing, also solar.
We're a significant provider of that.
We do social bonds, helping people stay in employment
that have been long-term out of work, in work.
So we're kind of, what we're trying to do is fuse purpose
in kind of all of these community needs.
And why we're driven by that is I love what we've got here in Australia,
this balance of capitalism and democracy.
You know, the alternative is a dictatorial capitalist.
That's the next most successful option.
And so we'll end up down that path if we don't nurture what we've got
and make it better.
Yes, there are challenges with it, but we can't blow it up.
We've got to work with it and enhance it.
And how we do that is by leading by example.
I can see why you need your 20 minutes twice a day, Radek.
There's a lot happening for good.
And that's why I love sitting down and having the chance to listen
and learn from you.
And I love hearing from people like you who've got a genuine purpose
and the passion comes out any time you bump into Radek Seller.
You know there's going to be some joy involved.
And as you've heard today, it doesn't mean that there's not some
ripping bumps along the way, is there, that you have to front up
and get the growth out of at the time.
It's brilliant to hear the projects that are underway
and so much going back into the greater good and the community.
We're a bit obsessed in leadership in these conversations
and these sort of different cues.
That are left behind from leaders, common leadership traits.
I want to ask you a few questions along that basis.
And we think very hard to lead, Radek, without a sense of self-leadership first.
What does self-leadership mean to you?
I think it's being in a state that you can be at your best.
So it goes back to the principles we discussed about meditation
and wellness programs.
You've really got to think about how you kind of integrate that
into your lifestyle to be at your best for work
and be at your best for your family.
And your friends.
So then you can truly lead with freedom.
Yeah, well said.
Absolutely, that shows up in the language of your daily routine
and taking care of yourself first.
You've been awarded for the impact you have in your environment.
We see leaders are getting more conscious, Radek,
about how they impact people positively every day.
And I heard you say that.
I'm obsessed with making sure people who work with me are happy.
How do you go about that?
What sort of detail do you do on a daily basis
to make that happen?
Well, I think that this kind of emphasis on thinking about your culture
and living and breathing your culture
and creating a language framework that's relevant to your organisation.
So every business that we work with, we ask for the business plan,
but then we ask for the culture plan and the values plan.
And values is something we're all familiar with.
And I've been in a lot of businesses in the past where I haven't led,
where the values were up on the wall.
But they weren't really lived.
But the values should be a guiding compass in how you make decisions.
And you should be able to remember your values and reel them off.
So whenever someone presents the values, I say,
okay, well, cover your eyes now and tell me your values.
And a lot of the time they forget because they're just doing it
because they're ticking the box.
And they're not really thinking about how those values need to live
and breathe and grow with the organisation.
And everyone needs to own them and be a part of them.
And so that becomes your best culture leader,
your best mechanism for reminding people of how you make decisions,
your best mechanism of when you're not in the room,
knowing that a moral compass is going to come out
and reinforce the way you would make decisions with a group of people
and you not having to worry about being all over every decision made in a business.
So the business then is free to grow without you having to be across everything.
So this kind of value of culture is probably being recognised more
than when we started practising it back in 2005, 2006, when I started at SWIS.
But even later on in the journey, I'd still have people saying,
surely giving people a free lunch for performing doesn't really help.
And I'd have to sort of smile and say, well, that's not the case.
You are human and I'm sure you like getting a free lunch
when it works out pretty well for you too.
And this is that kind of separation.
That of cultures that's kind of starting to dissipate.
But I feel like we're seeing the last pop of it with all of these old blokes
that are holding on to positions in politics,
which is the most public way of kind of seeing this going on.
And you're seeing it with these kind of leaders in China, Russia,
even the US and those personalities that just aren't making way
for this next guard of leadership,
that they are more aware.
And get that, you know, it's not just men on this planet.
There are women and 50% of us came from women
and the other half are women.
So us blokes are pretty damn insecure.
And so we've created this system that kind of protects us
and makes us less feminine and champions male qualities.
But we're seeing change in our time.
We're seeing this great balance of feminine qualities
and males that, you know, we're seeing change in our time.
You know, display these feminine qualities, you know,
it's really inquisitive and it's fantastic and it's a great change.
And I think we'll see much better leaders as that dynamic continues
to perpetuate and that focus on culture and that feeling of how we feel
from, you know, being able to talk about meditation,
talk about being well and how much of a difference that makes
to everyone around us as well as ourselves.
How much better are we going to be if we can all start thinking
a bit more like that, like what's happening in this day and age?
Yeah.
Well said, Radhik, and from the world that I spent a lot of my time
in the sporting world has changed enormously from that old school hierarchy
and verbal, you know, abuse, bit of everything thrown into so much more
empathy and care and with much more sustainable results and success.
It's a big shift and that is, you know, the title of this podcast,
Empowering Leadership, how to empower others to be great.
You know, it's a huge part of your success story from day one
and you can hear it.
And those footy players are just as elite, even more elite than what they were.
I mean, you'd see that today and just go, wow, the stuff they do,
you'd know from their son and the system and what they're producing
in this day and age is better.
So, you know, it's improving.
And they're tougher and they're braver and they, you know,
you don't have to have all the macho pretense that used to be around.
It's, you know, a healthier scenario unfolding.
And when people like you share those conversations, it's really powerful.
The idea of creating and sharing a vision.
We just heard about six or seven projects that have got big vision.
You know, you're talking about government, sorry,
company solving the carbon challenge, which is massive around the world,
around sustainable investing.
There's so many big, how do you go about, you know,
when you're in a position to influence creating and sharing a vision?
Yeah, I think that you've got to start with where you've got your superpowers.
Yes, I, this is not visual,
but I've got this superpower that I've practiced for quite a while where I can
move my hair up and down in my ears.
And that came from a lot of practice as a kid because my granddad could do it.
It's a good party trick, Raddick.
Particularly, can I say, and we are recording this, with a man bun,
that is a, you know, the eye, the head, that is a good party trick.
It's big.
And so, but if we, for the point is that,
we've all got a superpower that we've been working on along this kind of
lifetime journey and something that we're a little bit better than others at
doing.
And we might not be the best in the world,
but we're a little bit better than the average person.
And so we've got to really start there on focusing on what we're kind of a
little bit better at than others.
And then that helps kind of trigger your vision around that,
that passion and where you want to, where you want to step into it.
And it could be as big as building a business.
It's going to solve issues, or it could be as simple as I just want to do.
I want to train,
be a personal trainer and train people to be healthier versions of themselves.
And that's what I get up and be passionate about.
And I love that because I'm better than the average person in exciting someone to
do that.
And so we've all just got to listen to our inner voice and find our purpose.
And we live in this great society where we can, we can pick and choose.
And that's why I kind of say,
we've got to protect it and build on it and,
and have more people following out what they love doing.
So we create more purpose and our system keeps on improving like I believe it is.
So leaders that have great success like you,
Radhik, curiosity is a common word that we hear.
And through curiosity,
that's how people like you tend to approach their learning and development and
self-improvement.
Does that resonate to you, the thought of being curious?
Yeah, I'd hate to,
I always get my back up when my wife,
my wife says I'm not listening to her.
Although I think that this is kind of something we need to all think about is
because, you know,
we've all got a partner or someone that loves us dearly in our lives who says
that we don't listen to them.
And, and what I've worked out,
it's probably about three times it takes before I sometimes I'll register
because you take them for granted.
And so in the workplace,
what I remind leaders of is that,
Hey, you're not,
everyone listens to you.
They don't love you as much as that loved person in your life.
So you're probably going to have to repeat five to 10 times,
um,
what,
what the mission is and how you're going to go about it.
And you've got to simplify it.
So it's easily digestible and people can get on with it.
Um,
and,
and so part of that is kind of the curiosity factor and,
and not killing that by nagging people to,
to actually get outcomes.
So allowing people to sit down and talk about all of their issues and,
and saying,
well,
this,
this is a strategic session where there's permission to talk about
everything and where you sit down and you really hear things and you listen
to stuff that's not working as well as it,
could and could be improved.
You just gain so much insight from that.
And,
you know,
my biggest insights have always come from,
I've listened to customers without an agenda or just caught up and free
wheeled with someone,
um,
to just talk about what,
what,
what's going on in life.
And then all of a sudden you're putting two to two together.
And there's a whole method around that kind of thinking,
which is called design thinking.
Um,
it's beyond research,
which is research driven,
uh,
outcomes where you're asking people questions and they're pointed and you,
you get people,
sense of what they like and they dislike.
Design thinking is about kind of organizing opportunity through a series of
conversations and incidences that happen.
And you can create structures in your workplace that kind of enable that kind
of thinking to grow and thrive.
And,
and,
you know,
this is a large reason that we've seen a lot of innovation that's kind of off
the charts.
You know,
who would have thought our phones would be a personal computer in this day and
age.
And that,
that would never,
as Steve jobs beautifully says,
it's never come from research.
It,
it's essentially come from innovation and design thinking.
And so if you can kind of master that craft and,
and,
and nurture that and nurture curiosity in your business through listening and
engaging with people,
um,
that that's where you'll,
you'll really harness your superpowers and,
and,
and grow something pretty extraordinary.
I think that aligned really,
uh,
with the next dimension I wanted to talk to you about.
Well,
it is really conscious of how they communicate to others and communicating
with,
with clarity.
How have you gone about that in your world?
Yeah.
So it's,
it's difficult because I,
I kind of,
I,
I'm,
I understand that I can be my own worst enemy in,
in kind of making,
being too broad in,
in what we've got to deliver and how we're going to make it happen.
So I also make sure that I'm never the smartest person in the room,
but we've got a whole lot of people that are smarter than me or better than
me at particularly things that I'm not that good at.
So,
um,
or,
you know,
might,
might need support around.
And so having those individuals around you that,
that,
that remind you of that and improve you and help you become better in those
areas and never be as good as what they are,
but definitely helping you get an understanding and empathy,
uh,
for how you go about it just creates this kind of balance and blend that
delivers an outcome.
Just like,
you know,
if we talk about a sporting team,
you've got to get your team right.
And every person has a fit for purpose of what they bring in.
You know,
not everyone can be the full forward and kick a lot of goals like they did
back in the nineties.
Um,
you know,
you've got to create a whole team that everyone is involved in.
And that's why,
you know,
again,
that's a great example of how,
how sports improved.
It's gone beyond one person,
it's team and,
you know,
people on the bench matter as much as the people on the field.
Um,
and every single person on the field and they've all got a role.
That's exactly the same thing in a business.
And,
and they're not thinking about that and not having,
you know,
and I love using sporting analogies in,
in kind of the,
the whole feedback thing.
If you see a team where,
you know,
someone isn't performing and if you see the coach say,
how are you going to do this better?
And the person gives it back to them and says,
I don't want to hear that from you.
You just go,
wow,
that team's dysfunctional.
They're not going to win this game.
That happens in the workplace every day.
You know,
you get,
you get a manager saying,
how are you not doing that?
That well,
the person under their breath walks away and go,
that guy's a,
I can't stand waiting with them and starts poisoning the rest of the team.
And,
and then all of a sudden you get this negative culture because there is,
and this openness and ability to kind of share and improve and,
and permission to get better.
You know,
I liken it to going back to the personal trainer analogy or going to the gym
for the first time and you get a trainer in and,
and you kind of,
if you did your first 10 pushups and that trainer said to you,
you know,
three in that you look really tired,
you're not going to get through this.
That's many workplaces.
And so this is language,
openness,
and,
and everyone having a clear role and a purpose in an organization is,
is,
is something that should be the basics of business.
And we see a feedback loop in sports so quick,
isn't it?
You get outcomes very quickly.
And so you can say,
I had Matt Lafleur on this podcast recently,
Raddick is the head coach of the green Bay pack is brilliant,
outstanding young leader,
but all he was obsessed about talking was his 23 strong coaching staff and
how they are smarter than him.
And the jigsaw puzzle of putting together and how much care and thought he's
got for all the skills I can bring that this is an incredibly capable,
successful individual,
but so,
but so sophisticated and strategic around,
you know,
putting the pieces of,
of the puzzle together,
which was aligned a lot with what you said.
And then we see the leaders more than ever conscious of collaboration,
Raddick and,
and see collaboration is just a real superpower to use one of your terms.
How important has that been for you collaborating?
Well,
you know,
you can only do so much.
And so accepting that what you're,
what you're able to do and then who you need to partner with to enable you,
to go that next step is the key to unlocking extraordinary opportunity.
So for me collaboration partnerships just have to be nurtures.
And so I'm a pretty strange one in this regard.
My closest friends all work in businesses that we operate in and all work with me.
My wife was our director of marketing at Swiss for eight years.
And so,
you know,
I run the gauntlet and we brought her on because she was whinging about her boss
and I couldn't get any decent talent.
And I said,
well,
you're not going to be able to whinge about me,
but we've got a role I need you to fill.
So it'd be fantastic if you came and worked with us.
And,
and it was fantastic.
and,
you know,
it was probably eight years was about right for our marriage.
But,
but,
you know,
my best friends at CEOs or,
or chief revenue officers,
you know,
you name it,
are in our businesses and,
and,
and they're great friends because we spend the majority of time with each other.
But we,
we call each other out.
And I learnt this at,
at,
at Village Roadshow.
When you're working the candy bar as an 18 year old who suddenly realises I'm paying for a university course
and I'm getting paid to learn about business in,
in,
at the cinemas.
I was like,
wow,
what am I doing?
I'm not going to mess around here.
I'm going to get stuck into this and work my guts out because I'm being paid to be it.
Give me every responsibility possible and I'll do it for nothing.
And over and above whatever.
I better be careful because I was paid by an hour.
I don't want to get billed into wage issues.
It was just my passion.
I loved it.
You know,
it was my take home homework to make it better.
And so I'll,
I'll just be calling out for,
you know,
give me the most boring job like a stock take and I'll,
I'll do it.
And then also,
you know,
we've got to inspire my mates to kind of upsell in the candy bar.
So,
you know,
if you,
you bought a Coke,
do you want to,
you want a large popcorn with that,
that,
your friends would be like,
I don't want to say that.
I'll do that.
And you had to learn how to get,
you know,
these are your friends that you'd go for a beer with afterwards and chat about how work went.
And,
and you'd become a shift supervisor and you had to do it in a way that was kind of collegiate and,
and,
and getting them on board and sharing purpose and making it a bit of a bit of fun out of it.
And,
you know,
seeing if we could be,
the best team and,
and,
and be great at what we did and,
and getting people to see that that's going to be a whole lot better way to spend the three hours we worked together while we had a lot of fun doing it.
And,
but it's just became part of the nature of friendship and,
and kind of bonding and,
and not being a dickhead really.
And,
and,
and bringing your best self and your,
and your authentic self,
that same person you are in your social life,
you're in,
in your work life.
So then it's sustainable and it's not exhausting to,
to be someone else at work than,
than who you are at home.
You can just be consistent and,
and that's easier.
Great Australian success story,
Village Roadshow.
And I inadvertently read it,
it was the same,
the same,
when they owned Oz Stereo and I worked at Triple M doing the,
the Breakfast Radio with that team.
And you just,
you got this sense that,
that's,
you know,
when you make movies for a living and you know,
there's a portion,
a portion of them aren't going to work,
there's a risk taking funnel.
You know,
it just,
it was a place that loved good ideas at that stage.
And if you had a good idea,
it was a chance to get up and it could come from anywhere.
And,
you know,
I'm not surprised you took a lot out of your time working under the team from Village Roadshow.
Final two questions,
I've been asking a range of different leaders and I've loved every bit.
There's so much synergy,
you know,
in the world you talk about.
My wife,
Bex,
a meditation teacher and a yoga teacher.
And I have the same practice,
you know,
twice a day.
I don't look as healthy as you,
mate.
So I need to,
I need to talk to you after this,
this finishes to get some balance.
I might need to be in your back shed up there in Brunswick head at some stage.
But I want to ask you who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Look,
to me,
it's,
it's the most inspiring person I work with.
I've got a dog that's going to keep barking if I don't pull her off the couch here.
She's a bit older.
So it's time to pull her off.
I like it.
There's Floella.
Floella.
How old is Floella?
She's 14.
So the greatest leader,
I mean,
the most inspiring leader that I work with is a lady called Joan.
Jane Tooson.
And she's just extraordinary.
She,
she is CEO of Igniting Change.
She's just a gift that we have here in Australia.
She set up Virgin Unite with Richard Branson.
He,
you know,
this was back in the eighties.
And,
and she kind of enabled these kind of philanthropic endeavours back in the day,
inspired them.
And he funded an office for her kind of early days,
which,
that sort of span out into Red Nose Day there,
which is different to the SIDS Red Nose Day that we know here.
It's comic relief there.
And,
and that still raises two to 300 billion pounds per year,
that initiative,
which is just extraordinary.
And she did also a lot of work with the Royal Family,
Lady Di,
and,
and connecting her with community and,
and making things,
you know,
bringing things to life and,
and,
and the frontline.
She moved to Australia 20 odd years ago.
And,
and she just does this inspiring work with,
you know,
hundreds of different individuals in community and just getting beyond,
the unfashionable issues that we,
we deal with.
I'm privileged to be chair of the organisation.
And,
and,
and the unfashionable issues like drug addiction and,
and First Nations people,
homelessness,
and,
and refugees,
and kind of getting into the nitty gritty of people that don't have the
time to fill out forms and aren't part of big organisations.
They're just doing stuff in community and,
and need,
you know,
some support to enable them to do that.
We never help them because they help us just as much back with sharing
their journey of what they do and,
and,
and how they go about it.
And,
and the way Jane garners people's passion and,
and connects people with like-minded organisations,
and creates purpose for family offices,
businesses,
and so forth is,
is,
is just,
it's so inspiring.
And it's,
it's kind of turned into the practice of how we go about doing things at
Light Warrior and trying to weave that net,
that net between community and,
and,
and corporates.
Yeah,
she's a remarkable lady,
Jane,
the privilege of meeting her.
And I walked into the,
the space in St Kilda,
I think,
and it's an eclectic world.
There's always,
you know,
someone's,
refugee who's making a brilliant bit of tapestry or,
you know,
she's doing work in youth prisons to support,
young people who shouldn't be incarcerated.
And the areas that people find very difficult,
my interactions with her,
she seems to navigate better than anyone I've ever met.
And I didn't realise that you were so integrated into that space,
igniting change.
Look it up if you haven't seen the work that Ruddock and,
and Jane do there.
It's remarkable.
It's a remarkable organisation.
One of the many great things Ruddock's doing in the spirit of collaboration.
Final question for you,
Ruddock.
Sorry.
Thank you for your part in what you do with igniting change and,
and visiting jails and,
and,
and introducing meditation to people that otherwise wouldn't have access to it.
It's just,
you know,
that's first class stuff that you don't really talk about and too humble about.
Thank you,
Ruddock.
No,
it's a,
it's a privilege to have that opportunity to,
to,
to sit down and try and do some good.
It's inspiring,
um,
to hear what,
uh,
what you're up to for sure.
If you could collaborate with anyone,
there's such a broad range of interests you've got,
and you're looking at solving,
uh,
you know,
huge,
um,
things that make a difference in the world.
Is there one person you've thought of?
I could collaborate.
I mean,
Jane springs to mind clearly from a leadership point of view,
someone else you thought that,
that will be the difference if I could get that person on board.
Oh,
look,
I think there's four jets,
um,
that kind of I've thought about.
There's this,
we,
we've got grass and Michelle coming out to Australia.
Who's Nelson Mandela's wife,
uh,
when he passed away and she was first lady of Mozambique as well.
So she's just an extraordinary individual.
Um,
but she's still with us.
so I'd love to work with Nelson,
um,
and,
and get Richard in the room as well,
Richard Branson.
Um,
and I've had the great privilege to work with as well and,
and just see the sparks fly and see what,
what,
what could happen.
Um,
that would be a,
I'd like to sit on,
uh,
right with,
Richard Branson,
Nelson Mandela,
and,
uh,
your good self and,
a conversation that would,
uh,
would be a life changing.
I'm sure.
I know you had a huge,
the,
uh,
busy schedule.
We've heard what you're up to always,
uh,
feel privileged to spend some time with you.
I look forward to,
uh,
seeing the Mullumbimby markets again sometime soon,
mate,
and,
uh,
just to work.
So I really appreciate it.
Thank you for listening to the empowering leaders podcast powered by temper,
a mattress like no other.
And to make sure you don't miss an episode,
click subscribe wherever you get your podcasts.