How do you remain composed and balanced under the most extreme pressure?
Why is having an inner circle of people you can trust
with shared values so important in challenging times?
G'day, it's Luke Darcy.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership,
both on and off the field, has been a lifelong passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective
and I've had the privilege of working with thousands of leaders
in education, sport, industry and the arts
that have helped shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership
where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
Raylene Castle was born in Wagga Wagga, New South Wales
before moving to New Zealand at the age of six months.
Her mother, Marlene, was a four-time Commonwealth game representative and medalist
while her father, Bruce, is a former Kiwis rugby league captain.
Raylene's own sporting career included representative level netball
and a professional football player.
and tennis and following in her mother's footsteps
as a New Zealand Lawn Bowls champion.
Her corporate career included senior leadership roles
with some of New Zealand's leading companies,
Telecom, Bank of New Zealand and Fuji Xerox.
Raylene applies for and gets big roles in the sports executive world,
starting as the CEO of New Zealand Netball in 2013,
being appointed as the first female CEO in the National Rugby League in Australia
with the Canterbury Bulldogs,
then moving on to be the first female CEO of Rugby Australia in 2013.
In her current role, she has become the first woman appointed
to New Zealand's top role in sports administration
as the head of Sport New Zealand.
Raylene, thank you very much for joining me.
It's an incredible life of leadership.
Did you set out to be a trailblazer or has that just occurred along the way?
Yeah, no, it's just occurred along the way, Luke.
It's, yeah, sometimes when you sit and actually hear, you know,
you read out that CV, it surprises even me, I think, you know,
when I actually look back at it.
So it wasn't where I started.
Going out, I just, I think, always just wanted to maximise
the opportunity that was in front of me.
And that's led me to where I am today.
In 2011, you received the prestigious Sir Peter Blake Leadership Award
named after the legendary New Zealand yachtsman.
And to read from the citation,
you're recognised for your inclusive style of leadership,
your ability to build good strategic partnerships
that have benefited every organisation that you've touched.
Now, how would you, Raylene, describe yourself as a leader?
Yeah, well, I think that inclusive is really part of that.
And I think authenticity is the other part,
underpinned by a really good dose of resilience.
And I think if you bring those three things together,
that's, for me, has been really important.
I think being able to relate to people at every level.
You know, I have a favourite quote, which is an Albert Einstein quote,
which is, I speak to the garbage man or the president of the university
in the same way.
And that sort of ability,
to be able to relate to people,
engage with, you know, everyone from, you know, the receptionists,
the people working, you know, and supporting the organisation.
In my early days, it was the truck drivers at Fuji Xerox
who were, you know, driving fork hoists
and being able to sit down on a crate
and have a beer with them on a Friday night
is just as important as being able to be with you today on this podcast
and make sense to those audiences.
So, you know, that and that authenticity underpin
with a good...
A dose of resilience is really the combination, I think.
And I think your resilience comes out in everything that you've touched.
And I'm looking forward to going through so many of those incredible stories.
I love that quote from Albert Einstein.
I haven't heard it in that context,
but a lot of the ladies who have been speaking to you here,
almost to paraphrase that,
they talk about judging people by how they treat those
that aren't in a position of power versus those that are.
And it is fascinating that I did a radio show,
I learned for 11 years,
and I would subconsciously...
I would subconsciously do the same thing,
would have guests come in high profile.
And to me, the insight was, you know,
whether or not they understood, you know,
who was the producer or who handed them a coffee
and remembered names.
So you do tend to gauge a lot, don't you,
from leaders around the way they treat people
at all different levels.
I want to jump, Raylene, to a part of your life where,
and as I said, you have been a trailblazer.
You're appointed as the first female CEO in the NRL,
the Canterbury Bulldogs.
And they had some challenges, big time,
when you landed salary cap issues,
sexual assault allegations and challenges.
They had a grand final that had, you know,
been, I think, taken off them.
You come in and you're really set about cultural change.
You record a membership.
You improve the finances.
You get them to a grand final.
You must be really proud of that era.
Yeah, I am.
It was, you know, genuinely a dream come true for me.
I'd, you know, growing up watching,
standing on the, or sitting when I was really little,
watching Dad Coach on the,
sidelines at Carlisle Park,
iconic rugby league ground in New Zealand.
And then, you know, Dad and I,
his routine was to sit on a Sunday afternoon
and watch the Winfield Cup come in on a Sunday.
And, you know, to then have,
be able to work in that environment
with many of the people that I'd sat playing,
I sat watching play rather with Dad,
like the Terry Lambs, you know, that's really significant.
So it was a really big step.
It was a big career move, fulfilling a dream,
but recognising it came with a,
a fair amount of responsibility,
both to work for a really iconic club.
It did have some challenges as you pointed out.
And, you know, it was a,
it was a club that was not exactly
where the board wanted it to be.
And it did need some, some cultural change.
So, you know, all of those things, challenging,
but hugely exciting in the, in the challenge it presented.
When you walk into an organisation like that,
that it had its, its, its fair share of turmoil
and you are, you know,
trailblazing the way as the first female CEO,
were you conscious of that?
Were you, were you aware that,
that perhaps that was a first
and you needed to, to react differently?
Or were you just confident that your skills
were the right person for the time?
Yeah, I think there's two parts.
The, the best thing that the Bulldogs did for me
was they ran a recruitment process that,
you know, allegedly had 4,000 applicants.
And so they put me through a genuine recruitment process
and got down to the preferred candidate.
And that's, so there was no sort of risk of conversation
around tokenism or any of those conversations.
So that was a, that was a big tick from the board
and certainly gave me some confidence.
Look, you can't get out of bed every morning
taking the trailblazer tag with you.
You can't carry that weight of expectation.
So I've always just approached it as in wanting
to, to take some time to prove yourself.
I don't ever believe that respect and trust
comes with title.
It comes with what you do
and how you do it.
And how you go about engaging exactly
as we just talked about,
how you walk in the front door
and say g'day to the receptionist
and how you engage with the players
and every, everyone in between.
And that takes some time because of what you do
and how you go about it.
And then that's what slowly builds that trust.
And there was curiosity.
There was enormous amounts of curiosity
into who is this woman that's, that's landed.
You know, she's a Kiwi and, you know, the background.
And I, and I understand that.
There was a dozen, oh, there was about six
or eight Kiwi boys on the roster, which was helpful
because they made me feel really at home.
They started calling me auntie straight away,
which was a nice way to integrate into the playing group,
which is another whole level of being a CEO
in a sports club that is challenging
when that people don't necessarily understand
because you've got players that are much more
high profile than you, get paid way more than you do.
That's a really interesting dynamic.
That's not often the dynamic of a CEO.
No.
They're the most high paid and the most high profile.
So those are dynamics, which are not easy
for someone coming into this industry to understand.
So some good experience from Nepal helped me transition.
And I just was about taking it slowly
and recognise that I was trying to build that trust
and respect early.
You transitioned from there, Raelynn,
pretty quickly to another role as a first,
the first female CEO of Rugby Australia,
you were appointed in 2018.
The runner up for that role was Phil Kearns,
who's a legendary Wallaby,
as many would know,
two-time World Cup winning Australian legend of the sport.
You look back on your time there
and the structural difficulties that Rugby Australia
has got and probably still has.
Was it mission impossible?
I don't think so.
I think there was,
I identified two really key things
that I thought were important for Rugby Australia.
One was that it needed a genuine high performance structure
that started,
started with the young boys and girls
who could see themselves working their way through up
into becoming a Wallaby or a Wallaroo.
And also that had to be integrated
and planned with the Super Rugby teams.
And that was not in place.
All the successful countries around the world
had that end-to-end structure.
So the All Blacks in Ireland is two good examples.
So that was something that we focused on really hard
and we did manage to get to a much more inclusive state
by the time I left.
And the second one was,
when the broadcast deal really felt that we needed,
that rugby needed some exposure on free-to-air television.
It had been with a great partner
with Fox for a long period of time,
but all its major rivals were being,
you know, cricket, AFL and NRL
had significant amounts of free-to-air coverage.
And so that was a strategic problem.
So those two things ultimately,
whilst I didn't finish the broadcast deal
that was done after I left,
that was what happened.
They landed a free-to-air partner in broadcasting.
And, you know,
believed that that will help them
grow the engagement of the sport.
Raylene, the former rugby chairman, Paul McLean,
described your treatment at the end at Rugby Australia
as abhorrent bullying.
You were targeted.
High-profile media person, Alan Jones,
went after you regularly.
David Leckie was the CEO of Channel 7
and was pretty brutal in going after you at the time.
It was enormous pressure for one person to cope with.
How did you cope?
I get asked this question a lot, Luke,
and I think,
you know, the thing that's really difficult
about people that comment in the media in general
is often they don't have all the facts.
So they have a perspective, a view, an agenda possibly,
and that's quite difficult.
If you add the overlap social media into that
and the type of barrage I was getting on social media,
sure, that's from the outside really difficult.
The reality is I've got four or five trusted advisors
and those people,
they understand the detail.
They understand the decision-making,
the process,
the strategic approach you've gone through.
And when they say you've got that wrong
or you really seriously question me on something,
that's when I sit up and take notice.
That's when I get that sick feeling in my stomach.
Like anyone else that has respect for the people around them,
and that's, you know, the board, the board chair,
and then probably some people that had some distance
that could sit outside
and actually really knew me and what was happening.
So that's how I manage it.
Those advisors can't be the people
that only tell you the good stuff.
They have to be the people that front up
and give you the really,
the tough and honest feedback as well.
And so, yeah, like I said,
you have to understand the commentary
and the tone and the voice
of those sorts of things that are happening.
But ultimately you have to be concentrating
on doing what you think is right
with those people close around you.
I'm fascinated by that four or five person group
of trusted advisor you got.
And it's such sound logic for me
and brilliant discipline too.
I mean, it's easy to say it casually
that, you know, that noise is full on, isn't it?
And anyone, you know,
I certainly can't imagine walking in the shoes that you did
and some of the horrible, nasty treatment that you got,
I find appalling as well.
But to be able to, you know, reflect back with it,
can you give us a bit more,
is that something that you set up for yourself?
In life to have a mentor group effectively
that has been with you for a while
or have you just adapted given the role that you've had?
Have you changed that lineup at times or?
I mean, I have been fortunate to have some of those people
with me for a long period of time.
And I think that is important
because they know you well enough
and you trust their judgment enough,
I think is really important.
People ask me about mentoring all the time
and I think it's all valuable,
but I think you need someone
that shares your values and your style and your approach
because when you ring them and say,
can you help me with this?
You need them to sort of,
to be able to add value on the same path
where if you have someone that is totally different space,
then they tend to take you off in a different direction
and that can be really hard.
So I think that's important.
They have varied over time,
different people for different roles
and as the needs required
specifically for the role that you're doing.
I've had a couple of consistent ones
that I would talk to.
That's important.
I think the other thing is that
you're sitting in front of a group of people
that you're leading, an organisation, a team
and you have to get the read from them as well.
And those people,
if they are leaning in and are behind you
and where you're going and what you're doing
and responding to that leadership and culture
that you're creating,
not just inside the environment,
but further afield,
that's important.
I think the other thing is
if you're really determined that change needs to happen,
then you've got to be brave enough to stick with it.
Whether that's values-based,
whether that's because you clearly believe
the organisation needs something,
that's the job that you've got put in to do
and it's easy to take sometimes the easy-er option
or the path of least resistance, if you like,
but I don't think that's playing true to my own values.
I think that's the way to go.
Or you're not doing the right thing for the organisation
because change is hard
and change outside of how people like to see it
because they've been involved with it historically
is not always the way to go.
Yeah, I think you can't fake coping.
I mean, you just have to see, you know,
how you reacted under pressure.
And as I said, I'm delving a little bit more
into the group around you
and to digress for a moment,
it's a passion we've been working in the leadership space
and particularly in the leadership space.
In lockdown, we're sort of connecting different leaders
from different backgrounds,
some of them in the sporting world, Raylene,
you know, almost people who understand the same arena,
but as you said, same values.
You know, if you don't align on values,
you're probably not going to be able to support each other.
But, you know, it's been something
that we've seen been really powerful,
almost like your own personal board of directors
can come from different areas and different backgrounds.
So it's a space,
if you want to find out a bit more about it,
we're doing that work.
A leader connect is the work
and it sounds interesting, Raylene,
to hear leaders like you
that actually just develop that on your own
and work together.
And work your way through that.
I'm still just sticking on.
I mean, I just think it was an enormous,
and I love the fact that you had that in your corner,
but there was a time where 11 Wallaby captains
signed a statement, you know,
talking about change in leadership,
but you never lost your cool.
You know, you never got angry in a press conference.
I mean, was there moments behind the scenes?
You must have thrown something at some stage, Raylene.
I mean, how did you manage that?
Oh yeah, I mean, you do, right?
But that's not what anyone's looking for in a leader.
You know, they're looking for the person
that's calm,
and considered,
and thoughtful,
and can deal with those things.
And sure, there's moments where you, you know,
have an enormously large glass of wine
and drink it in one go,
but that's not for public consumption, you know,
because that's not what the people
that are sitting in front of you,
and it's also, you know, like I, you know,
in that moment around rugby,
there was, you know,
people that run club competitions in Darwin
that are looking at the leader of Rugby Australia
thinking that they want someone to be calm
and considerate,
and thoughtful under that bear arch.
They don't want someone that's attacking
and being, creating more media profile
around the already difficult situation
that, you know, that you're dealing with.
So on one hand, I'd say, you know, that's the reality.
On the other hand, I'd say that
at the end of the day, as a CEO,
it's a bit like being the captain of a sports team.
And when you get appointed into that role,
you need to make sure the coach has got your back
and they, you know,
you never have to look behind you.
So whilst those discussions and situations
are really difficult,
whilst you only have to worry about
what's coming in the front door,
you can deal with a lot.
The moment you realise that you haven't got
that support from behind you,
then you can't keep going
because it's too hard to look both ways.
Ultimately, that's what happened.
The Wallaby letter came in
and the board, you know, said to me,
you know, this is, you know,
this is a problem.
That was, there'd been a change in leadership
of the chair and the deputy chair.
Those people had previously been enormously supportive.
Paul McLean was amazing in the transition.
But, you know, there's a group of people
that want to take the organisation
in a different direction.
They see your face doesn't fit.
As a CEO, you shake hands and say,
thanks very much.
Is that hard because you feel like
you haven't finished the things you started off?
Sure.
But that comes with leadership.
You know, it's like I said,
the analogy, the captain of the sports team, right?
So, you have to, when you haven't, you know,
we haven't got their support,
you can't do your job.
And I think when you handle yourself the way you did,
you move on as you have now
to an extraordinary role as the current,
you know, top sports administrator
and the head of sports in New Zealand.
And you're right, isn't it?
Your behaviours and your actions
and how you cope, I suppose,
is where you land next in life.
And you deserve all the success that comes your way,
clearly from afar, watching the way you go.
One of the things I've admired about
reading your story in preparation for this, Raylene,
was that some of the detractors,
and we're talking, you know,
powerful people with big microphones
who really, it seemed, had a set for you.
And you went and met them face to face.
So, Alan Jones is a big voice in this country.
As a broadcaster, for those that don't understand Alan's work,
he's been, you know, a loud voice in radio
for many, many years
and also a former Wallabies coach
and clearly decided that you weren't the person for the role.
You went and sat down with him.
You went and sat down with Phil Kearns,
who was the runner-up in your...
Tell me about doing that.
That takes some courage.
Well, I suppose it does,
but it's the right thing to do, right?
I mean, you can, you know, I think it's important.
They were both significant contributors
to the history of the game in Australia
and they deserved an opportunity to have their say
and to give their feedback.
And I had that...
I met with, you know, 40 or 50 Wallabies
probably over my...
And I offered every single one of those Wallabies
exactly the same opportunity,
which was they could come and meet with me
or ring me, they had my phone number,
with any specific piece of detail they wanted at any time
because, in my view, they'd earned the right
to have that conversation
because they'd worn the gold jersey and I hadn't.
So that was an open invitation.
Ultimately, a bunch of them chose not to do that
and they chose to send a letter to the media
before the letter came to me
or came to the board
and, you know, that's the way they chose to go about it.
But, as I said, that was a process that...
It was a difficult course, it was.
I think the disappointing thing for me
is having tried to take conversations out of the media
behind closed doors and deal with our issues
in a professional way across a table
and that was how I dealt with as many things as I could
within Rugby Australia when that was...
when that's not afforded to you
and it becomes a public debate
before they sit round the table.
That's hard, but, you know, we were where we were.
Is that something that, you know,
transcends into other parts of your life, Raylene?
I mean, you mentioned that they're all wallabies
and they'd earned the right in your mind.
Have you dealt with that in your life in the past?
I mean, we all, you know, have run-ins
or disagreements with people.
Have you been someone that's,
hey, I'll meet you and sit down
in other aspects of your life as well?
Yeah, always.
I think, look, you know,
I don't have to like you to work with you.
I mean, that's the reality.
You can't possibly in an environment, you know,
end up with a long friendship
with every person that you work with
or necessarily even particularly respect the style
with which they go about things.
But if you're placed in a situation
where you need to find a way to work through that
and work forward,
I think that's, you know, hugely important
and that sort of ability to build that relationship,
be professional about how you go about things.
is really important.
And, you know, I'm really proud of the fact
that that's the way I approach my relationships
in a working environment.
If you didn't have enough going on in that role, Raylene,
the Israel Folau story becomes part of legend.
And I know you've spoken about this a lot,
but I'm interested in your reflections.
He's probably the most high-profile sportsman
in Australia at the time,
regarded as the best player in Australian rugby.
And he makes a series of homophobic statements
on social media.
Initially, he's cautioned by you,
if I get this right,
but he does it again.
And it ends up resulting in his role being sacked.
There's an out-of-court settlement that's agreed upon.
I mean, there was no playbook at all for this in sport,
probably anywhere in the world.
You're in the chair and it's you at the front of it.
I mean, how did you go about it?
And on reflection, is there anything you'd change?
I mean, you know,
you couldn't go through something so complex
and not think there was things that you'd do differently.
So, you know, you wouldn't be arrogant enough to say that.
But for all of its really significant complexity,
it was really quite simple.
There was an employee that had breached
their employment contract.
My style would always be to, you know,
sit down and go through a process with someone the first time,
regardless of who they were, you know,
don't make the same mistake twice kind of scenario.
So once, I'm really happy to sit down
and work through with you, but not twice.
And ultimately,
my role as a CEO is provide a safe working environment.
And that was,
I had many staff that didn't believe that was the case.
And thirdly,
the organisation had a set of values
where diversity and inclusion was, you know,
at the heart of that.
So if you don't stand up for those values,
they're not worth, you know,
the paper they're written on
or the organisation doesn't actually stand for something.
So whilst it was certainly complex
because of the, you know,
the people believed the nature of the discussion
was breaking new ground, you know,
I'm not sure it was, we had a policy,
that's where we ended up.
So I'm really comfortable and proud of the decision
that we made and that we stuck to it.
Certainly the board was 100% committed to that process.
The learning though, is that diversity and inclusion
are two words that are important.
Two words that are really easy to say
and actually much more difficult to bring together.
So we talk about diversity and inclusion policies,
diversity and inclusion rounds, you know,
and footy and all of that.
But actually the challenge of bringing
a whole lot of diverse people together
and then allowing them to be themselves
and be completely open and honest in their views
is quite a difficult leadership challenge.
And actually providing an environment
that's safe for people to share their views
and that they do feel included.
Is important.
And all I can say is that you need to express your views
in a constructive and positive way,
recognising that you've got colleagues or people
or teammates or whatever around you.
And if your comments make those people feel bullied
or unsafe, that's not an environment that can be acceptable.
So yeah, I think there's work needs to be done.
Well, I think we, as a society are much more accepting
of diversity and inclusion,
but actually the practical reality of delivering on the ground
is a little more challenging.
Raelynn, did you get support from the playing group
and the coaching staff?
I mean, as you know, in sport,
not every athlete's always created equal.
It seems from my experience of playing sport,
if it was player 45 that was on the edge,
it's an easier decision than the best player in the team,
maybe the best player in the world.
Did they understand it?
Did they think it was clear cut?
I just got to be a little bit respectful, Luke, of people,
in the situation and the conversations I went through.
What I can say is the board, really proud of the board,
never once said he's the best player in the world,
but it's difficult for a playing group,
if I talk more generally, because, you know,
they have friends, they share religious views
and it was not a religious conversation.
And I think that's the piece that, you know,
I spend a lot of time talking about
the fact that I was deeply proud of the fact
that we had a group of religious players
that they held that to the centre of themselves
around who they were as individuals.
And there was respect on both sides of the room
because of that.
And there was group prayer groups and the boys
that weren't as deeply religious were a part of that.
But unfortunately, when that's kind of not the point,
really, the point is that they'd lost a teammate.
They weren't quite sure where they were going.
They weren't quite sure where to land
because they felt that because of the media furor
that their base religion was being attacked,
which was never the point.
So yeah, the conversations were not straightforward.
And there was, you know, a range of views
from the Wallabies and the team is sacrosanct
and no player is bigger than the team,
through to some deep concern for a teammate who was,
you know, regardless of why they were there,
was in a difficult situation.
And so it's a very challenging and emotional time
for everyone involved.
Well, in my mind's going to a story you may not be aware of.
And it wasn't a question that I thought of answering,
but I love your logical brain.
I can see the way you work and I can see that, you know,
you've got values that you stick by.
This one to me is fascinating and I can't quite get my head around it.
AFLW player and the sport has been brilliant
in the world of Australian rules football,
the game that I played growing up, Raylene,
and brought diversity and brought a lot of these conversations,
to the table that hadn't been had before.
And I have great respect for the whole playing group in AFLW.
In the Western Sydney's team,
they have a player of Muslim faith who's become a great ambassador.
As you know, the Western part of Sydney has strong Muslim community.
So she's become a great ambassador,
but she wasn't prepared to play in the Pride round and wear a jumper
celebrating the diversity of sexual choice for one of a bit of a time.
So that story was supported, you know,
and supported by a lot of the other AFLW players.
Do you see that as a very different thing to what you went through with Israel Folau
or is there some crossover in,
how would you have handled that one as a CEO of the AFLW Giants?
Well, I don't know.
And one of those dangerous things,
I don't know enough about the specifics, right?
So, but what I would say is what I was talking about before
is that's a really large,
thriving, good example of where diversity and inclusion
sounds really easy when you put it in one sentence.
Yeah.
But the practical reality of applying it is greatly different.
So if someone comes forward and expresses their view in a respectful way,
explains their logic and says,
this for me is, I don't feel comfortable with this.
You couldn't be anything other than open-minded to that conversation
and supportive of that conversation, I think,
because it's the way you go.
I think the other piece that's really interesting, Luke,
is that you, more and more sports voices loud
around making real change in society,
but not every player signs up to be the poster child for X or Y.
You know, just like some won't wear,
don't like wearing betting sponsorship
or don't like wearing alcohol sponsorship
because, you know, they've got a view on that equally.
And I think that's an interesting challenge
in a way.
Yeah.
I think that's an interesting challenge in a team dynamic
where personal values, it's assumed when you wear the team uniform,
you should sign up for that.
But with some of those things,
more and more of those conversations are coming to the fore.
I love some of the work you've done in the community space as well.
You're the founder of the Minerva Network,
Women Supporting Australian Women in the Business of Sport.
I mean, having a look through the website
and just seeing the great amount of community
that you've been able to bring together.
Tell us about your passion for supporting other female leaders.
Yeah.
There was a group of five high-profile woman leaders
who were sitting around going,
the blokes look after the blokes.
So the senior male leaders in this country
reach out to the young, aspiring male athletes
and say, right, I'll introduce you to this person,
I'll introduce you to that person.
How could we help you go about your,
either pre, during your career or post your career?
So really, that's where it started from.
A group of us sat down and said,
how could we help young, aspiring female athletes
to give them the same opportunity?
So that Minerva Network has grown into four different chapters,
I think, Queensland, New South Wales, Victoria and WA,
and has, or she was about 400 female athletes,
all that are provided with a mentor
and all have the opportunity to be part of budgeting,
public speaking, social media management,
you know, post-career development,
all of those, you know, those types of things.
So, you know, the group have done an amazing job
in supporting that female network.
And interestingly, those athletes now get a chance
to mix those athletes together,
which wasn't always something they got the opportunity to do.
So, I mean, I think any way that you can help,
you know, provide opportunities for that to happen
is hugely important, whether it's, you know,
last week I had a phone call from a young, aspiring,
or actually a radio DJ here in New Zealand
rang me and said, listen, I've got a young, aspiring person
that wants to work in broadcast.
Would you mentor her?
And I said, well, I won't mentor her
because I think that's a really big commitment,
but I will have a coffee with her.
So, you know, I sat down here now,
I had a coffee with her and just, you know,
sort of helped her organise her thoughts, I suppose,
in a way that, you know,
could help her take the next steps in her career.
So, I mean, I think any opportunity to do that
and give back is really important
because I know I was fortunate to have some of those people
do that for me when I was younger.
It sounds like formalising mentoring
has been a big part of your career.
It's been a big part of your life and your leadership.
Can you share a bit more?
You just said then you were on the receiving end
of some great support and mentors.
Have you got a name that you could share
or is there an example of someone who went out of their way
to really have your back at various stages?
Yeah, the person probably, you know,
I have a main probably mentor, David Jackson.
He's an Aussie.
He was running, sitting in New Zealand,
running Kiwi Rail.
And I was with the Toll organisation,
which is a really big organisation as a CEO in Australia.
But I think the biggest alignment is, as I said earlier,
we've got some shared values and approach
in how we go about things.
So whenever I, and, you know, as an example,
when he was here as CEO of Kiwi Rail,
he would go to the very top of North Island
and get in the train with the train driver
and spend the whole trip from, you know,
Cape Reinga to Bluff, basically, in a train,
talking to the train driver.
And he'd get all the goss, right?
The train driver knew who, what was happening,
what was working well, what wasn't working well,
what was performing, you know, where the opportunities are.
And that, to me, is, you know,
the sort of guy that I want to work, you know, closely with.
And so he's been really, really kind to me.
We've had some great conversations,
some really good challenging conversations.
He's, you know, helped me through some difficult times
and, you know, I enormously value his input.
Yeah, we've heard that.
It's a great story to hear, Rolaine.
Brian McNamee on this podcast,
who was the legendary CEO of CSL,
that took that to, you know, the biggest company by market cap.
I mean, that was what he said routinely he did.
Didn't book meetings in his diary, just wanted to walk.
You know, ended up with 40,000 employees, CSL worldwide,
but just wanted to walk and talk, walk past people's desks,
find out from someone obscure about what was happening,
you know, in the inner sanctum of the organisation,
you know, rather than the old version of hierarchy,
which is really...
Passion for leadership, we're talking about.
Geoff Harris, who founded Flight Centre recently,
the same thing, you know, walking into the stores
and finding out from those at the lowest rungs of the organisation
who was the most beneficial.
And have you found that's really related to you
as you've gone on in your working life as well?
Yeah, it has.
And I have to say, it's my single biggest frustration about COVID
is the fact that you get, you know, last year,
I had four months at my dining room table in Auckland
because Auckland was in lockdown, dealing with, you know,
the people that I obviously had to deal with on a daily basis,
40 hours of Zoom calls,
but actually no capability to get that physical
and environmental contact that I really find rewarding
from a job point of view.
And, you know, be able to get a sense of walking past someone
and saying, how's your mum or how's your dog
or did you win footy in the weekend
or what did you think of the Grand Prix in the weekend?
Wasn't that a great performance?
Those are the types of things that you can really get.
You can taste it and smell it.
Around the culture of an organisation.
But if you're not doing that because you're locked behind a screen in COVID,
that's really, really, really challenging.
And as we start to move back into an environment
where we want people to come back into the office
to have that human connection,
that's a real cultural challenge for a lot of organisations
where people and staff have got used to working from home.
It suits their lifestyle better.
They realise that they've got more flexibility
and it might be better for the individual rather,
but it's more challenging for the organisation.
So I think that's a real challenge facing leaders
as we emerge out of this COVID world.
Have you got an idea on that quickly?
I mean, that is the ultimate challenge everyone's now, isn't it?
Trying to, people don't want to mandate things anymore
and legislate days you've got to be in the office.
But clearly we need people interacting more together.
I mean, have you got a system at Sport New Zealand in mind
of how you're going to manage that?
Yeah, I think there'll be a balance.
I think it'll be three in the office and two at home flexibility.
So, you know, that allows you
to have that flexibility,
but recognise that there is real value
in those, you know, conversations
or osmosis type information that you pick up
when you're not necessarily there,
but you're around people.
So that's probably the way
that we're looking to work towards it.
And it'll be interesting to see how it unfolds.
Well, then we're identifying with the leaders
we're talking to a range of different leadership traits
that we think are unique to leaders
that are evolving in this way.
And we see you very much in that light.
And so I was going to ask you a range of these questions.
So please expand as much as you like.
Starting with self-leadership,
we feel like great leaders really have an idea
of what their own sense of self-leadership means.
How would you describe yours?
I mean, I think I said at the top,
maybe authentic, I think is really important.
And not being so sanitised
that you don't show your own emotion.
Like there's a difference between being really angry.
And really quiet, angry and quiet.
That's not the same thing.
But the authenticity of challenging
and sharing that I think is important.
But recognising that the resilience to underpin that
is really critical.
And not everyone has the resilience, right?
It's just, it's the reality.
Not everyone can survive on four hours sleep.
Not everyone can get off a 24-hour flight home from the UK
and go to work in the office and front up
and be sensible and talk stringy sentences together
and deal with really difficult questions.
And not take it to bed with you at night.
You know, it is a somewhere between an innate,
be it, you know, what's inside you as a person
and learned behaviour.
I think it's a combination.
But, you know, for me, those are the couple of things
that I think are really important.
Yeah, and they shine out in all of your examples
of your working life.
We see leaders really conscious
of how they positively impact others in their environment.
I think you've given some great examples
of just the day-to-day and the engagement
and talking to people at all.
Yeah.
All levels of the businesses and organisations you've been in.
How do you go about positively impacting others?
I worked for a guy in my very first job.
I was an enthusiastic marketing graduate
that was, you know, looking to, I suppose,
you know, take on the world, if you like.
And he was a very experienced Xerox executive
that had come from the UK.
And I'd go into his office with this idea
and I'd be like, I've just been thinking
and I reckon we can do this and this and this.
What do you think?
And I always left his office better off
than when I went in there.
So I always had value added to the thought.
He told me you should go and talk to this person.
Maybe if you just tweak that and go about it this way.
So it's something I've really thought about
and that when someone comes and approaches me
with something, an idea, a thought, you know, whatever,
that hopefully I can send them away
just a little bit more knowledgeable
or point them in a little bit better direction
than when they arrived in.
And, you know, like I said,
he taught me that right from my very first job.
And you can always identify
when someone's just not listening to you, can't you?
It's pretty deflating, even if the idea doesn't get up.
The idea that someone's actually genuinely listening
and maybe that can be transformative resonates with me.
How have you gone about creating and sharing your vision
in the various roles that you've had?
I think you've got a front.
That's the thing.
You've got to have strong values
and be prepared to share those values.
Or vision or plan or change environment
or, you know, reset, whatever it is that you're doing.
You've got to be able to talk to that in plain language
that people that understand in the way
that most people are going to be able to relate to.
You know, there's lots of big and fancy words
that you can use, but I don't think you need to use them
if you can just use really sort of straight and plain ones.
And, you know, then be prepared to back that up.
I think with one,
with your own actions,
but also have difficult conversations
and call people out if they're not behaving
in the way that you expect or,
and not everyone can have difficult conversations.
Not everyone feels confident to make the hard decision
and then actually, you know, follow it through.
So, you know, those, but people watch that, right?
And they see that not only are you prepared to front up
and say, this is what we're going to do
and this is how we're going to go there.
And then you work to take the people with you,
but you're also prepared to actually make
the difficult decisions to get to that point.
So, yeah, that combination is important.
We see curiosity as a common theme that's coming up
in leaders that we're talking to and working with,
Raylene, and often curiosity is the launching pad
for how people approach their learning and development.
Does that sentiment resonate with you?
It definitely does.
There's no doubt that curiosity is something
I think is actually interesting.
One of the values here at Sport New Zealand is to be curious.
I think I'd also put with that as being brave enough
to employ people that are smarter than you,
technical experts that are better than you,
ultimately being brave enough to surround yourself
with true excellence and trust that you can lead those people.
And I see other leaders who squash potential,
won't promote people because they feel threatened,
where I've seen the best leaders,
that I've worked for, actually promote that expertise
and bring it to the table and back themselves
to lead people through the challenge, the strategy,
strategic direction or whatever it is in front of you.
So, I've got some really good examples of that.
It's something I try really hard to do and ultimately know
that you might be employing that person that will replace you one day.
But that self-awareness, I think, is hugely important
and really valued by the people around you.
Yeah, certainly.
It makes a lot of sense as well, doesn't it?
But there are qualities that...
Others don't have, isn't it?
Again, I use the word courage again, isn't it?
To put someone in place that, as you said,
potentially could be your replacement.
But in the end, so much success comes from that.
You've had big roles where communication,
in fact, all the roles, communicating with clarity
is something that we really see as consistent to a lot of leaders.
How have you put thought into the way you communicate?
Well, it is really important because if that message can be clear
and people understand it, then I think that helps people
come with you or follow you or agree to make the change
that you need them to make.
So the thought and that sort of authenticity of, you know,
like sometimes when you've got a really...
And I get this feedback a lot.
Sometimes you've got a really complicated message to deliver
and you can't afford to miss anything.
You know, you might read out something that someone's prepared for you.
But by far and away, people...
The feedback I get is you're much better
if you just take the high-level things
and you put it in your own words and talk to it.
So sometimes I've got to be careful with that
because if you don't get the key messages across,
that can be a risk.
So I often will talk to something
and then follow up with a written document
so that we cover off those specifics.
But the, you know, like I said, I've used the word a lot,
but the authenticity of actually putting it in your own words
and looking directly at people
and giving them your version of it,
ultimately resonates much more strongly
than standing up and reading a document
from what's in front of you.
Yeah, you get a real sense of your values, Raylene.
In all your answers, it's really clear what you stand for.
We see collaboration now as something that, you know,
leaders really value and really seek out.
I mean, how important is collaboration to you?
Well, I don't see a world where you can be successful without it
because to think that your organisation is an individual,
your team has all the answers would be pretty crazy.
So, you know, the ability to collaborate
and being open-minded to the challenge
that collaboration brings,
and that requires you to be comfortable
not controlling everything.
So, you know, once again,
comfortable that you can add value to that situation
when you might have a collaboration of two organisations.
And there's space for all of us, you know,
in a lot of these, you know, examples.
And that openness to bring forward
that collaboration,
and have positive tension.
I like to call it constructive tension.
So the tension that creates of different ideas coming together
and what makes it uncomfortable
is ultimately what moves things forward.
If you continue to sit in that comfortable space
where there's no challenge,
then you don't get that forward movement.
Yeah, great answer.
Two final questions that I've been asking consistently, Raylene.
The first one is, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
My parents.
My greatest leaders, really.
The values that they gave my brother and I,
Ryan and I.
The thing, the very practical things that they taught us.
The resilience they built,
and the fact they never treated me any different to Ryan
or Ryan any different to me.
They were just about do your best,
put yourself out there,
have a really good, honest crack at it,
is really the expectation, you know,
honestly lean into something.
If you're going to do it, do it properly,
those types of things.
So, you know, they certainly,
and they've both been very successful in their own rights as well.
You know, good work ethic, manners, shake hands well,
look people in the eye, firm handshake,
you know, all of those types of things,
which all sounds very sort of,
but I'm astounded today at how that's not a thing
the way it should be.
So I think, you know, those base values are really important.
And I, you know, we just had an amazing start to our life
because of the values that mum and dad,
they instilled in us.
Yeah, the older you get when you've been lucky enough as I was,
and clearly you were,
you realise what a gift that is, isn't it?
To start your life with incredible parents as role models
and certainly feeling that bracket.
And it's a common answer and you can just,
people don't hesitate when I ask that question of them
when they've clearly had the upbringing that you have.
In the spirit of collaboration,
we're really passionate about this world of collaboration.
If you could collaborate with anyone in any area of your life,
you know, I think that would be fantastic.
It doesn't have to be work.
Is there a name that springs to mind?
Oh my goodness, there's so many.
But I have an enormous respect for Oprah.
You know, her background, what she dealt with,
how she's stepped through all of that, been successful.
She's been inclusive with the people she's had around her
and taken other people on the journey
and delivered success and support
for those people and then ended up backing them
into opportunities and helping them grow their careers.
So, you know, I'm sure it's not always as bright and shiny
as it looks on the outside.
There will have been enormous challenges for her,
but, you know, I see a lot of the things that she's done
and how she's gone about things.
There's a lot to like there and a lot to learn from.
The opportunity to work closely with her would be amazing.
If you've got any chance of hooking me up, I'd appreciate that.
I'm sure Oprah's listening, Raylene.
I've got no doubt.
And we'll get onto that.
I love the fact that, you know, you went to that place.
We've had, you know, guests talk about Elon Musk
or, you know, people that are inspiring.
We've moved the needle, haven't they, on a world scale?
And clearly she has.
She's spent a bit of time here in Australia, Raylene.
So you never know in the spirit of collaboration.
I'd love to see the two of you get together
because the thing that just pours out of spending some time
with your authenticity, your resilience,
the way you've handled yourself,
under pressure that very few people, I think,
would even know.
And to be standing from afterwards
and to see you so clear on your values
is a great example of leadership.
It's been a real pleasure to meet you, Raylene.
And thanks for inspiring so many others.
Thanks, Luke.
Thanks for having me.
I've really enjoyed it.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me, Luke Darcy,
produced by Matt Dwyer,
with audio production by Darcy Thompson.
To start your leadership journey,
I encourage you to go to elitacollective.com,
take our Empowering Leaders Indicator tool
and understand the impact you have on your environment.
Join us at Elita to learn,
lead and collaborate.
Listener.