A really enlightening conversation with Reggie Butler,
one of the world's most respected leaders in connecting teams
and developing great people.
Reggie gives us the inside word on his work with Google
and the research that Google has done into their highest performing teams.
Clearly a data-driven company that knows how the most productive teams work.
He shares the two words that Google used to describe
their highest and best performing teams
and how you need to bring that same culture to your life and your workplace.
Worth listening to this conversation for that alone.
He also shares his daily practice of helping other people
and he says it's something we all need to add to our own daily routine.
Reggie talks about the five life domains that govern all of our lives,
work, health, family, spirituality and community.
He also asked me to name in order the way I prioritise those five life domains,
which was an enjoyable experience.
It's people like Reggie Butler who inspire the work that we do at Alita.
We'd love you to have a look at our work at alitacollective.com.
In particular, our signature program, Alita Connect,
where we connect diverse and different leaders around the globe
from a range of different backgrounds, from sport, from arts, from the industry,
into these collaborative forums to learn, to share and to collaborate.
Book a discovery call today.
I'd love to have a chat to you about Alita Connect.
Huge thanks once again to the team at Temp.
for their ongoing support of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
It is brilliant to have them on board supporting conversations
like this one with Reggie Butler.
We know one of the great success leave clues moments
is great leaders have a great sleep routine.
Investing in a bed like Temp is a life-changing decision.
It's a mattress like no other.
Reggie Butler is the founder and CEO of Performance Paradigm,
an executive education human capital consultancy,
a learning architect, former adjunct professor,
and inclusionist.
He's an inclusion champion with an established record
of delivering high-energy motivational experiences
for both personal and team improvement.
He has worked with many clients across a range of industries,
financial services, tech, non-profits, consumer products,
and professional services.
In addition, Reggie Butler spends time at the intersection
of racial justice, law enforcement, and NGOs.
His experience runs through equity, inclusion, diversity,
high-performing teams, executive coaching,
and leadership effectiveness.
He facilitates experiences and dialogues focused on how we can be better humans
and collectively improve the human condition,
starting with the people we are most proximate to every day
and the systems those humans create.
Reggie is the go-to person in this space for some of the biggest
organizations in the world, the likes of Google, Mercedes-Benz,
Kraft Heinz, Amazon, Nestle, eBay, just to name a few.
Reggie, it's a great honor and privilege to spend some time with you today.
You know, thanks for asking.
I know a little bit about you and your rise to being a better human over time,
even after your ACL injury.
So I want to talk about how people need to learn how to adapt.
Well, Reggie, let me start there because what does it mean to you to be a better human?
So one of the things is I believe this wholeheartedly,
that we can all do a better job of, and I use a mantra,
and I even have a podcast about it.
It's called Care More.
It's a wonderful podcast, by the way.
And what I tell people is that we can all be better, do better, and care more.
And we are in an age right now, it's really fascinating, Luke,
we're in an age right now where unless you're paying attention,
we will stay apart from another human because we are conditioned
that we're not supposed to be in their spaces for whatever reason.
It's a set of learned behaviors, it's the psychology or the sociology of it all.
But we don't think about the human connection
until second, third, or last in our priorities of life.
And I'm trying to get people to sort of hear the message,
I need you to look up and look around you and pay attention
to the humans around you and see how you can be helpful.
And Reggie, that is an interesting thing.
It's, you know, in Australia, you know, in rural areas,
I grew up in a country, small town of a couple thousand,
and you knew everyone and you said hello to everyone
walking down the street.
And if you drove your car,
sometimes great distances, you'd wave to every car
because there was an assumption that that might be someone you'd know.
I love playing this game now in the park where I live,
where I look up and I try and say hello.
The amount of people that do everything they can to avoid eye contact now
and saying hello is quite disturbing.
Is that part of the phenomenon that worries you,
that people genuinely try and avoid any sort of connection?
Yeah, and there's a little bit of research to bear that out.
And it's a little bit of generational news.
So to speak, but when COVID happened and we were all put into isolation
and it was for our own good and you sort of look at it that way.
And I know what you all did in Australia.
I want you to think about what it did to the human connection.
So if we were isolated and we had to work through our own machinations of life on our own,
whether it's family, whoever it was with,
when it came time to come back to work,
you realize we lost the human connection muscle.
People just stopped using it.
So think about those people who were in a workforce before COVID happened.
They were used to making connections with people,
whether it was in between meetings or like you say,
just being about out in the world and you would make eye contact,
you would talk to people.
COVID happened and everybody was isolated.
When you come back into an environment, I call it return to life.
So in the sort of RTO of it all, people came back and forgot how to do that.
Think about that. Think about those people,
who were hired remotely during COVID,
never went into an office ever.
Now they're being asked for whatever reason,
based on company protocols and things,
to be a part of a team.
How do I become a part of a team that I was never connected to physically?
Take that same formula and think about what most of us do in our life and our day-to-day.
When we wake up,
we always connect with the people we already know,
that we're already familiar with.
And if we're not careful,
careful we won't pay attention or to your point even make eye contact with certain people yet
they're in our space so what we've got to start to do is start to pay attention to who we're paying
attention to and who we are not and that is super critical for the for the improvement of the human
condition moving forward and reggie i live in a city called melbourne which held the title as the
as the most locked down city in the world i i think right through to the end and and i love your
narrative and i'm happy to that perhaps that was for our own good but i had four children at school
who missed two years of school living in our house and watching teenagers have two-year gaps around
social connection you can see that is a gap that you have as you describe it's a muscle you've got
to relearn having been trained to your screen and that's where you connect online and and you lose
the skill of actually connecting in person it's a it's going to be a fascinating stage
i think reggie isn't it to see what's happened to that generation that's missed those pretty
vital couple of years of their teenage life yeah and you know what else luke i'd have to share this
i was talking to a colleague and we were talking about the social connections that people make now
they're not in the physical world they're in the digital world so we've created this new muscle
of being digitally connected to someone in a virtual way and it had become very comfortable
without human interaction people who go to the grocery and you know how there's these
self-checkout lines where you don't have to interact with a human there is a study that's
out there i won't name it yet because all the findings aren't out but here's what it suggests
is disturbing yet not at the same time that if you ask a person if you were to go to a grocery
store where you get your grocery and there was a self-checkout person a self-checkout station
or a person to help you check out which would you choose and they said they could tell by generation
who would rather interact
with the human. And it was really fascinating because people who were, and I'll use the term
boomers for now, but boomers would love to interact with a person, even though there's a
self-checkout option that's supposed to be more efficient. You know what the surprising part was?
Gen Xers are the generation that's coming into the workforce now. They would prefer the
self-checkout to the point where, and this is where it gets so fascinating, is that that store
chain removed the self-checkout option. They would rather switch stores that have to interact
with a human. I'm like, wait, that's the people that we're asking to make stronger human connections
because their normative behavior based on how they were raised in this current society. So I'm
going to take your kids during COVID and unless you give them a reason to interact, they've already
learned how to not interact. It's fascinating.
Fascinating.
And I'm going to take your kids during COVID and unless you give them a reason to interact,
they've already learned how to not interact. It's fascinating.
And again, I put the parenting hat on Reggie because you're having these conversations and
without naming one of my four, but you had a problem trying to enroll in a course
and I just said, you pick up the phone and ring. And she was like, what? I've just named her because
we've got three boys and one girl. But she was like, what are you talking about? Like, no way.
There's no way I'll email, I'll text, but I'm not picking up the phone. And I was just sort of
stunned. But you've probably got to understand that
that behavior hasn't been learned. It's not how they've communicated in the past. And we see that
it is something that you've got to go back and teach. And look, you do that, as I mentioned in
the intro, with some of the biggest organizations in the world. You teach leadership development,
you teach about team and human connection. You do it in a really profound way. It's seen sometimes,
Reggie, as this sort of, okay, we'll do this because it's light and fluffy and we tick a box.
But what we know, the research tells us, organizations that do this well make more money,
they're more profitable, they keep their staff longer. The data is irrefutable,
but there's still a lot of organizations that don't get it. Is that what you're still finding?
Hands down, we're still finding that. What we have also started to notice is that there are
organizations who've always been centered on the human condition as they do their work. And those
organizations are some of the most attractive companies to work for because they didn't change
their formula. What's interesting is that there are a lot of organizations that don't do that.
There are a lot of organizations that don't do that. There are a lot of organizations that don't
change their formula. What we have also found is that there are a lot of organizations that don't
of how this new world is shaping itself, there's not a lot of incentives to be connected. Because
if I can hit my targets, think about that, as a person working for a company, if I can hit my
targets and I don't have to interact with somebody as much as I used to have to based on old
protocols and old ways of getting business done, you realize unless somebody gives me a reason to,
I will naturally not, not because I don't want to, it's because I don't have to. I do a lot of
executive coaching and there was an executive who said, you know, what's concerning to me is that
how my workforce connects with one another in order to problem solve looks very different now
because they don't problem solve together. They problem solve alone. So they go search,
they use confirmation bias to see what they want. They align and have their own fully
vetted points of view. Then they come into a room and try to collaborate, but they've already
made their mind up based on doing the research by themselves. So I want you to think about that,
Luke. If there's so much knowledge available to me that I can problem solve by myself and come up
with what I think is the best recommendation without actually having a conversation with
somebody, you realize what that's going to do to that team over time. You're going to have less
people talking, more people feeling isolated, and not a lot of innovation. And that's what frightens
me about us moving into the future.
Our innovation is through human connection alongside other parallel things that we have to
do in our workforce. But unless we pay attention to it, we won't connect. We've got to pay attention
to that. You know, I got a question for you, Luke. You've been in your field for quite some time and
over at some point you had to change your own personal style. What was the trigger? What
happened to you to make you say, you know what, how I'm doing things as a leader or being a role
manager? How did you change that? Because it's no longer relevant. What happened to you?
Well, it's a great question, Reggie. And I think the curiosity for me is just that desire to follow
things that you love. And that's why it resonates so much with your work, this idea of wanting to
be a better person. And I think that happens to me, you know, when you become a parent and you
get this great mirror back up to you of these four human beings. And I'm always going, that's
definitely my wife's behavior. That tantrum wasn't mine. That has to change. And I think that's
still come from Beck. And the reality is you get to see all of your own faults really, really
clearly as a parent. And you either ignore them or you want to self-reflect and get better. And I
think that to me is that constant, the Japanese line, I think Keizan is constant, never-ending
self-improvement is the way the Japanese think about life. And I think about it the same way.
And it takes you down different paths and you're never not constantly trying to improve. It's why
I think what you're doing is so profound in so many ways.
And I love that you're getting into organizations that get it. And I want to come back to Google
because they're fascinating to me. Clearly, that's a company that knows data pretty well. And they
know how to measure things really well. So they're not mucking around at the shallow end. They're
going straight for the most effective. And you tell me if I'm right, I believe this study's
now quite well known out of Google where they studied their most effective teams
because they can. And they went, well, who's performing the best and why? And I understand
correct me if I'm wrong. The two words they came up with, their most high-performing effective teams
were in a psychologically safe environment were the two words they used. Can you elaborate on
that? Why that works and why that means so much to an organization like that?
Yeah. So if I look at human connection and look at the psychological safety as the underpinning
for why a person feels safe enough to connect with you, let's talk about psychological safety,
where I am in an environment where I feel psychologically safe enough
to share an idea without fear of embarrassment or rejection or it impacting my career.
And every time I do sessions where I talk about psychological safety, I talk about it in the
context of there are levels that look different to people around the globe. And there's a cultural
nuance to it. Most people just use the umbrella term of psychological safety. What Google found
and what a lot of organizations that have really done the good work of leadership is they found
that psychological safety in its four levels is the best way to get people to connect with you.
levels. One of them is inclusion safety. And inclusion safety means that I believe, Luke,
that I am in an environment where I feel like I belong and I am connected to. That means I have
inclusion safety. The second level is learner safety. It's where a person believes they're
in an environment and on a team and working with a leader where they feel like they are learning
something. That means I have learner safety. Then their third level is contributor safety.
I feel like I'm on a team with a leader, with a person that I feel like my voice will be heard.
I am a contributor. And then there's challenger safety, where I feel like I'm in an environment
where I can challenge the status quo and push back without it impacting my brand or my career
trajectory. Now think about those four levels. And think about psych safety at the team level.
If I am experiencing two of those four levels of psych safety, there's a higher probability
that I will innovate and collaborate.
Very differently, because I am experiencing those levels of psych safety. If I don't have
any of them, and I feel like I'm only there to do a job, and I don't have psych safety at any level,
do you realize I don't feel like I belong there? And I will disconnect and disengage
on purpose. So we talk about how psych safety is the underpinning for belonging and inclusive
cultures. And I use the work in my leadership practice, like the highest performing and highest
functioning leadership practice. And I use the work in my leadership practice, like the highest
functioning teams have high levels of psych safety every day. And I'll give you an example.
I was doing a session and a person said, I believe I have inclusion safety. Like, I feel like I belong
here. I'm in an environment. It sort of feels right for me. I feel good. But I don't have
contributor safety. And I asked this to tell me more why. He says, because when I'm in a meeting,
people hire me to bring my knowledge into this organization. So I come into the organization.
I bring up an idea. I bring up an idea. I bring up an idea. I bring up an idea. I bring up an idea.
And somebody says, where did you come from before? You haven't been here long enough. So just
thanks for the idea. But Will, just hold on. He says, that was OK the first time. But when that
happened in succession over a three-month period, I started to talk less. I started to offer less
to the point where I just did my job day to day. Love my job. Love the work. But I stopped
contributing because I didn't have the energy to do it. I didn't have the ability to do it. I didn't
have the psych safety that people wanted to hear my voice. In that same session, Luke, there was
somebody said, oh, I'm not worried about the contributor safety because I will always get
my voice heard because I am. I come to the table as a challenger. They hired me to just blow things
up. I'm a change person. So like, okay, but you know what I don't have and I wish I had? I wish
I had inclusion safety. I wish I felt like I fit in here, but I don't feel that. And I don't know
if I need to, but you're making me think, Reggie, maybe I need to pay attention to that because I
don't do a lot of efforts to get to know or understand people. I just deliver high results.
And he goes, huh, I've never thought about psych safety as a pathway to higher performance.
Never thought about it that way. That's so interesting. It's so interesting.
And Reggie, the reality is because most people in organizations have got to have a focus on
productivity, don't you? It has to come back.
You want to do things that make your organization, whatever you're in, sporting organization,
Google, whatever, it has to come back to being more effective. And when that's the top of the
tree, how we get there is fascinating. I want to talk on one of those pillars for a moment,
the inclusion safety, which clearly you're an expert in and you understand this space as well
as anyone else. I mean, I asked this as a nearly 49-year-old white male. So I understand,
my lived experience, but I feel nervous in this world now, Reggie, where I don't feel like I
discriminate or have any intention of discriminating against anyone, but it feels
nerve wracking now where you miss a nuance or you say something that you never intended to,
and the chance of being canceled or labeled something horrific is alive and well. Is that
a fair thing to be concerned about? Is that something you've got a thought on?
Yeah. And part of,
the solution for something like that is people owning the origins of their fear.
Because when I do sessions and when I coach people, I ask them, what is it that you're afraid of?
Like, why are you not engaging? And they will say some of the things you just said, look,
like I'm afraid I'm going to say the wrong thing, or I'm afraid I'm going to be misunderstood by
what I say. Where did the fear come from? Like, why is that fear troubling to you? Because there
is, there's an entire movement in the world today for people who are marginalized,
or underrepresented groups that suggest this to all dominant culture people. It's like,
I would rather you try and say something and show evidence of effort than say nothing at all,
because your fear is driving your disengagement. And I push people all the time. It's like,
I'm going to be honest, I'd rather see you try, Luke, than sit there and stare at me.
Yeah.
Like, you don't know what to do when I need help. Like, you don't know what to do if something's
going on with my community and you, and all I'm looking for,
is the receipt, the evidence of effort that you at least are trying. Everybody will cut people's
slack for that. It's when people don't try and then make the excuse, I'm feeling whatever
dimension of humanity you want to put in there. And that's why I didn't say anything. That's why
I didn't show up for you. That's not how to make a better humanity at this particular point,
is by being an observer.
Yeah.
You need to be a participant in my life. That's what people want. Be a participant.
So what you're saying, have the courage and have a go, is what you're saying exactly. And I think
you're right. It is, there is this sort of, you know, when you're in the broadcast media or you
are expressing yourself in a way, I think it does come with this level of, I'd hate to say something
I regret. I've got no intention of doing that, but I think your message is a good one, isn't it?
If you show care, you're allowed to make a mistake because I'm just coming from the,
from the right place. And Reggie, your background fascinates me. You've got a master's in education,
but a double major in theater and music. And I understand you really use that, that sort of
double parts of your brain really passionately to learn in an experiential way so that people
can genuinely, rather than just academically understand something, you like people to
experience it for themselves. Can you share a bit of how you go about that?
Yeah. So part of the formula that I use is I believe in the metaphorical alignment,
which leads us to learning through an experience. Luke, I would probably not even hesitate to say
that most of how you became who you are was by living out your passion and your dream and doing
it with somebody. You didn't become who you are by yourself. I mean, you played a team sport.
So it's the shared experience that drives us to change our behaviors and to think differently.
So if I,
I was doing some work here in the US and this was, you know, a few years back though,
with the NBA, the National Basketball Association. And one of the things they were talking about is
the culture in a locker room and how they make decisions based on the hierarchy of players
in the locker room. And that the coach is really sort of parallel to all of that,
even though the coach has given the strategy. So if you start to pull that thread all the way
through and you start to think about experiences that people have, you're going to be able to
start to think about that. And I think that's one of the things that people have. What I use is I try to
mine an experience that is proximate to someone to help them understand that they are a part of the
solution for moving forward. Think about it this way. I could talk to you all day about the
importance of being together and connecting with another human. It's very different for me to talk
to you about it than have you in an experience with me where I, Luke, through literally the
objective of,
a particular module, is to create outsider-ness for you. So I treat you as if you don't belong.
Now, this isn't negative or heart wrenching. It's literally an experience. So I treat you just a
little bit differently than you expect. You are in the presence of somebody else. So what happens?
Your ego pops up. All of these things that make you want to behave differently. And it's in the
presence of other people. What is so amazing about music and theater?
What makes
music work is it creates an emotion that is universal. What makes theater work? Think about
it. It is a representation of the lives we live, yet on the stage, and we watch it and we connect
with it. I take that same formula and go, let's talk about being a better human. Whether this is
a leadership lens or the diversity, equity, and inclusion lens, let's have an experience together
so you don't just know something, you understand something, and you feel something.
That is a trilogy of what I do. I want you to move from knowing about it
to understanding it. And it's beautiful. Once you understand, then you can actually feel something.
We've stopped feeling, Luke. I need us to feel again about each other.
And I understand they're very profound experiences, the sessions that you run,
because exactly that, you get to feel it, you get to understand what it means and what it's like.
You know, I'm glad we're talking to you.
You know what I'm saying? I'm glad we're talking to you. I'm glad you're talking to me. I'm glad you're talking to me.
talking about experiences, Luke. One of the things that I'm so proud of that I've been able to
release in the last few years, it's the two-day experience, how it started off. It's called
Examined Human. And it's a leadership program talking about putting people through a set of
experiences to help them explore what it looks like to be a better human and actually live a
set of behaviors. And those behaviors are show up, be courageous, create visibility, and amplify
voices. And I think of what people can do to be better humans. It's a behavioral output that
people are looking for. Not more talking, not more thinking, but a set of behaviors. So Examined Human,
I hope to bring it to Australia. I have someone who's very interested. And one of the people that
I've been collaborating with and has become a really dear friend now is David Bartlett. He's
with the LOTE agency, and he's been to the Examined Human experiences, and he's really interested in
bringing it to Australia.
Because he says, we can make a difference here with people going through an experience like this.
So I'm really looking forward to meeting you and seeing David in Australia.
He's a great guy, Dave. He's pretty determined to bring that experience out here. So
hopefully we can be part of it. Reggie, it's a unique time, it seems, in 2024 on a global level
around leadership. And you live in a country at the moment that seems more divided maybe than it's
ever been before. And the politics,
are extreme in the United States at the moment. What's an example of a great leader? Is there one
out there you can share, Reggie, that you see? And so that's someone we need to see more of in your
world. Yeah, so I think what it is, so if I look at the positions inside organizations, and I'm not
going to point to one leader more than I'm going to point to a prototype of people who are doing
the work. When things are being attacked, either through policy, legislation, systems, whatever it
is, there are people inside organizations that will say, while that may be happening, it is also,
and if it's a distraction to my business and my people, I will then push back. And I got a lot of
prototypes of leaders who are, you know, having the good fight by standing up for their people
first. I tell people every day in this, in a society that has allowed being disruptive to
another group of people, that has allowed that to become
normative. And in some circles, even pushed as, yes, let's do that. There has to be people who
stand up and go, I don't have to agree with the policy. I don't even have to agree with how you're
doing something. But what I will stand for is stand up for my people. Look, let me give you an example
of something that's been happening. And when I talk about prototypes of leaders,
there was a situation in an organization where they were literally looking at
downsized,
downsizing, right-sizing, whatever word resonates with people. But they had told this particular
leader, let's sit in a room and let's talk about the people that we're going to need to let go.
And the person listened, this particular person I was coaching said, Reggie, I listened to my leader
put their list of all the people that we should let go of. And I sort of stopped them and went,
that's not the right solution. That impacts our people, which then hurts our brand. And he goes,
I don't want to do that. Can we look at an alternate solution versus the first thing we go to
is letting go of our people? And he said, his leader pushed back and he says, but this is what
we need to do. It's what's going to look right in the region. It's what's going to look right
in the market. And the person who was coaching went, that is not a reason to let go of people.
Because in this point, you're not thinking of the people, you're thinking of the business.
And so,
Luke, what I want to share is that is an example of somebody who is showing up on behalf of
creating better conditions for the people and using that as a human-centered approach.
I've got a session that I do, it's called Evolved Leadership, and that the tenets of it are,
it comes in three pillars. One of them is to be human first. The other one is to be compassionate.
The third is to be service-driven. That is what is expected of leaders today.
And that's what that particular leader modeled. He was human first. He was compassionate about how
it was going to impact their people. And he was service-driven. Any leader that I'm around,
I'm sure you've been around, if they were in service of you and what happened to you,
your loyalty is higher, your engagement is higher. You will take one for the team
because the person is indexed and in service of making things better for their people.
The business will still make it.
You know that, I know that. Teams don't die, people retire. Team's still there.
Hey Reggie, I love the message because we really are seeing a shift in that and what
great leaders look like is exactly your language, isn't it? Your podcast is care more and be a
better human and great leaders now have got a lot more empathy. We're seeing that in the sporting
sphere really strongly that the coaching world has got a lot more empathy and care and people-centric
first.
And service-driven away from that hierarchy that the era that I grew up in where the coach was the
boss and you got yelled at and abused. And if you could stand personal abuse, you sort of got
through, but none of us thought that was a healthy way to go about it. And so it's profound to share
these stories because we know there's a long way to go for, but the beauty of it is that, you know,
you're at the center of it. You're seeing the most effective teams are using these traits that
you're talking about, aren't they?
Hey Reggie, you've spoken a lot today about the loneliness epidemic and people's lack of human
connection and your passion to try and recreate those tentacles. I read a stat in the US that
on average, most people haven't got one friend they could call that they could truly confide in.
It's a sad, sad state of affairs. Why are you sounding the alarm on this so clearly? What's
the big message for you? So there's a couple of things. One is,
we are in a divided time right now. And I try to get people to understand we're in the midst of a
poly crisis. So you should look globally. There's wars around the globe. There's, you know, economic
downturn. There's, you know, the racial and social justice reckoning. All these things are happening.
The thing is, it's not that they've never happened before. They never happened in this close of a
succession. And they're right behind one another. And for us to make it through this season, we're
in a time right now, we have to make stronger human connections than we do, than we do about
being better about solving one of the issues. We keep trying to solve one of them and it keeps
stacking up against yet another crisis. And then it stacks up against another crisis. And all people
really want in the middle of this poly crisis is for you and me to know that we can count on one
another. That's what's sounding the alarm for me. I remember here in the US, the Surgeon General,
there's a Surgeon General advisory that says loneliness is at epidemic levels.
Now think about that. Loneliness, talk about a health-related issue that we should all pay
attention to. People are lonely and some people are choosing it because of what society has allowed
to become a normative set of choices. And so that's what makes it, I'm so passionate about
the follow-through to improve the human condition. I'm so passionate about the follow-through to
improve the human condition. And it may feel like it's a daunting task, but every time a crisis
has happened around the world, it is the human connection that made us get through it. You know
that. I know that. But people who are in the middle of the crisis don't get to pay attention
to that because they're in the middle of the crisis. You know, I'm going to try something
with you, Luke. Do you mind? I'd love to. I think people don't pay enough attention to people
beyond just the transactions of getting things done. If I'm your boss, your leader, family
member, if there's something we need to get done together, you were talking about parenting,
people will talk to you and it's about parenting and the transaction of getting things done and
solving problems. I am suggesting that you need, everybody needs to do a better job of
understanding the humans you interact with versus just knowing what they are going through.
And here's my example. There's a thing called the five life domains. The five life domains are
work, family, health, spirituality, and community. Now, I didn't make this up. These have always
been around. Work, family, health, spirituality, and community. I am suggesting that people start
to pay attention to how people prioritize those five things. And they don't always have to stay
the same. Think about that. Work, family, health, spirituality, community. Let's talk about poly
crisis. So I'm going to sort of connect this together. If of those five things, we're juggling
them all at the same time. If you're human and you're living, you're not going to be able to
and you're interacting in a human state, you are juggling those five things. If one of them is in a
disruptive or chaotic state, the other four still get attention and you pretty much can deal with it
because you pay attention to the one thing, you give it your energy. If two of them are in a
chaotic or disruptive state at the same time, the three that are left over, one of them,
they don't get the same amount of energy toward trying to juggle it or navigate it.
Now, imagine this. If you're living and you're interacting in a human state, you're juggling those
three of them are impacted in a disruptive state at the same time. That means the two that are
remaining get no attention. If I am in a relationship with somebody and my prioritization
is family first, health second, work third, community, and then spirituality, if that's my
prioritization and I am working with someone and their prioritization is not the same,
you realize,
we're going to miss each other and potentially be harmful without even knowing it.
Now, I'm going to ask you to do me a favor. Prioritize those one to five. You got people
listening to you. How do you prioritize these now in your life? Remember, work, family, health,
spirituality, community. One would be the one where you spend your most intellectual time
thinking about it and or emotional time feeling it. And five being, it's important, but I don't
tend to get to it.
Put them in order.
I'd start with family. That's the one I think about the most. How do we keep our family healthy
and safe? And then health comes second because I feel like if I don't pay attention to that,
then you can't serve your family and you can't serve your work. So that's definitely a clear
number two. Work would be third. I think as the priority list goes, you want to support your
family and you want to try and make sure that you can provide what you need. So I think that's
well. Community would be fourth for me, thinking about the communities I'm in and how you connect
well and I really value those communities. And spirituality would be fifth. I think there's a
gap there for me on that for sure. Something I think about, but that would be the order for me.
Okay. So Luke, I want you to sort of take this on and have your listeners just sort of
do this prioritization exercise in their own mind. The question is that order that
you just said, what's the order that you just said? What's the order that you just said?
What's the order that you just said? What's the order that you just said? What's the order that
you just put it in? There's two parts to this question. The first part is, has it always been
that way? No. No, it's changed as life evolved. Yeah, absolutely.
Okay. So think about that. And if I am interacting with you and I don't know or even notice when the
prioritization changed, I am still interacting with you toward a priority that's misaligned.
So if at some point work was first and that's how I met you,
and work was important, then something happened in your family or with your health that changed
your priority, and I don't know you enough to understand that, you realize I will continue
to talk to you about work to the point where it becomes unhealthy. I'm always trying to get you
to do better, to perform better. We have to hit these numbers, do these goals, make this thing
happen. And you've transitioned over into family is what matters now. Health is what matters now.
I am telling people, you have to move beyond that. You have to move beyond that. You have to move
beyond knowing a person to understanding their prioritization. But this is our earlier point.
If a person doesn't feel, have psychological safety with you, I will never share my prioritization.
That's why psych safety is so important. You've got to have that. So I then will want to share
that with you. Now I'm going to ask you another question. And it's, is that the order you want
it to be in moving forward? Another great question, Reggie. And I think probably, as I said,
I'm turning 49 in July and I feel like getting to that mid part of your life, I think I've got
the order better than I ever have done before. And I obviously didn't know you're going to ask
that question, but yeah, I think the family one is, you know, maybe it wasn't early. You were
sort of fighting in your own world and your own sense of achievement. And then you realize,
well, I certainly have that. That's the thing that makes me happiest and most connected and
the health priority, you know, playing sport for a living.
Yeah.
And I, and I let it go for a while because you know, you get busy in work, but then you realize
without some daily attention to that, your life is, is, is going to fall away. So yeah, I feel
like I've got it in pretty good shape. Yeah. Yeah. And that, that is, that is like a dialed
in answer because you've been through something and you know that that's what the answer is.
Do you realize how many people are in the world right now? If loneliness is an epidemic,
that's not sharing that with anybody. And even more important,
they haven't done the exercise for themselves. So they haven't paid attention to it. I, you know,
you're using your chronological age as, as the rational reason for why you're thinking that way.
And that is totally valid. There are people listening that aren't your chronological age
and their priorities are very different. What I'm saying to make a stronger human connection,
you should want to know what a person's priorities are. So you can be supportive of the priority,
you're still going to get other things done, but we're not, we're transactional at best.
I believe this, and I don't want any listeners to hear this out of context, but we, most of us,
are selfish first. Like when we wake up, we have a list of things to do, whether written down or
in our head of things we need to do to make our day better, of things we need to do to get things
done through other people.
And we start with us, and then somewhere in the middle of the day, if something dramatic or
traumatic happens, we'll pay attention to somebody else's thing that they need. But most of us are
selfish first. When I am talking about what I need leaders and companies to start to figure out how
to do, is how can you wake up and be centered on what other people need as a part of your daily
routine? Still do what you need to do for you, but in parallel,
can you think about who am I going to help today, or this week, or next week? How can I be supportive
of somebody today, or this week, or next week? I didn't say don't pay attention to your own list
and your own priorities, but we need to start to add other humans to our planning phase of our
days, our weeks, our months. And you'll see a very slight shift toward people are caring about one
another in a different way now, because you did it on purpose. You did it on purpose. You did it on
purpose. It was intentional. You woke up. I got a leader who said this to me, says, Reggie, you know
what I wake up and I do on Mondays now? I ask people on my team, what do you need from me this
week? I don't ask them about their weekend. Their weekend's for them. Why would I encroach on that
narrative? I ask them, hey, let's get started. What do you need from me this week? And people get to
tell me what they need. Will they still talk about their weekends? Maybe, maybe not. I don't need to
use that as the end goal. I don't need to use that as the end goal. I don't need to use that as the end goal.
I don't need to use that as the entryway to get to know somebody. So I say, what do you need from
me this week? You know what happened, Reggie? People started telling me, hey, I've got a doctor's
appointment with my son on Thursday. There's a really big meeting I was supposed to be a part of.
I'd like to see if there's a way I can have somebody take my place.
They would have never asked that question. If the leader hadn't led with, how can I help you this
week? Think about that. I said, somebody else on my team went, son's daughter,
got a special celebration happening at their school. I have never been to one of them. I would
love to go. It happens to be tomorrow. And I didn't put in time off. I didn't tell anybody,
but you were asking me how I can be helpful. That would be helpful. Now, both of those
seemed personal. Remember, work, family, health, spirituality, community. Those were both family
related. Somebody else in this person's team said, you know what? I need you to extend a deadline
because I'm not going to make it by Wednesday. I'm not going to make it by Wednesday. I'm not going to
make it by Wednesday. And I'm telling, I'd rather tell you, ask me what can be helpful. Can you
move some things out of my way and help me prioritize so I can either meet the deadline
or can you extend the deadline? Again, that person's prioritization was work.
But that leader would have gotten none of those answers had he not repositioned his framing for
interacting with his team when something is simple, as simple for something as simple as
Monday morning catch up.
It's so different.
And it's brilliant, Reggie, in its simplicity. And I love the way you ask that question and
explain it. And you're right. We start with our things to do list and I do that, start the day,
but there is time to connect to someone else, isn't it? Find out where they're at and with
their health and their priority list. And so it's a profound bit of wisdom that you've shared today,
Reggie, and I really appreciate it. We use the term here, Reggie, a lot in this podcast,
success.
This leaves clues and you've shared some great wisdom today. And there's a series of what we
think great leadership looks like. And I'd love to ask you a range of these and please expand as
much as you like or as little as you like. But I'm curious very much from your self-reflective
stance to understand. And we start with this idea of self-leadership, Reggie. We feel like it's hard
to lead someone else unless you understand your own sense of self-leadership. What does that mean
to you?
So I believe that there is a
a
there is a version that people have and it's the self-deception of leadership. So some people
think they're a leader and don't know that they are not because they haven't done the work of
allowing people to give them good feedback. And so they're deceiving themselves. When I look at
self-leaders, self-leadership, those people are doing an assessment multiple times throughout
their, their,
year and multiple times throughout their career to see if the version they think they are delivering
as a leader is meeting the expectations of the people they are leading. So we, we sometimes live
in a world of self-deception because we like to think when we're putting these at least positional
leadership roles, we like to think that we're doing it. But if you never create enough
safety for people to tell you, actually, that's not working, you'll never know.
So that's one thing about self-leaders. The only other thing about self-leadership is that I want,
I want people to also always remember and listen, how you led at one point in your life may look very
different than how you lead now and or how you will lead in the future. So we should always be
looking for a way to evolve and adapt and or assess what we need to do to change, but it's in
service of being a better leader, not staying the leader you are. That's just another way I have
people frame it. Brilliant. And I love that thought of self-deception, isn't it? We can live in that
space.
And not asking people to give us genuine feedback around the impact that we're having. How do we
know? And I think that term's fascinating to me, that self-deception, isn't it? We've got a title,
looks like I'm succeeding, but I haven't really taken the time to find out. It's brilliant. We
see leaders are really conscious, Reggie, around the positive impact they have on others in their
environment. And you just described the beautiful way with the five values, work, family, health,
spirituality, and community of checking in on
having an impact on people. It's a profound thing that you said. How else do you go about
day-to-day, Reggie, having an impact on people that in proximity to you is the language you use?
Yeah. So one of the things that I will offer everybody to find the technique that works for
them that is closest to what they already do. So I already meet my team in the morning. I already
talk to them. If I use the example of asking people what they need and I make that a habit,
then it becomes normative.
In my space with the people that I'm around most of the time. The other thing I'm going to ask
people to do is I need you to start to do something you're not used to doing to create a
stronger habit. And here's what I mean by that. If I already meet with my team and I've already
started asking, how can I help you this week? What do you need from me? I also may need to ask
something different because once I've created sex edu with that, there's nothing stopping me from
going, how can I help you? And what do I need to do? And I'm going to ask people what they need to
know about you that I could be more helpful. So look at the nuance of the words. How can I help
you this week? It's pretty universal. Anybody can say whatever they want to say. If I am looking at
a very specific person, not the team, and I go, is there anything I need to know that would make
me more helpful to you? It gives that person an opportunity to tell me something very specific
that is directly related to them versus in a team environment. That's just, it's called, so
there's a book called Atomic.
Habits. And I use a lot of that framing. It's called habit stacking. So I've already have a
habit. I just stack another habit on top of it. And I use that when I coach people. I use that
when I talk to leaders all the time. You already leading, start to add stronger habits and make
sure one of those habits is about making a stronger human connection. We have to be intentional about
the human connection, not accidental. And I hope everybody hears that loud and clear. We are
accidentally kind most of the time. We accidentally,
make connections most of the time, which is why we're so amazed when somebody has a connection.
You go, really? You went to that school? Oh, like that's an accidental connection. I want us to make
the connection on purpose by looking for it, not waiting for it to sit in front of you. So this
whole thing about habit stacking is the, is the other sort of, not, it's more than just a habit.
It's intentionality. And I, again, I want people to sort of hear that. Be very intentional about
the human connection.
And Reggie, I love it. You know, the intentionality is right in the wheelhouse of
the work we do in a leader and in our space, which is connecting these bespoke groups of people that
wouldn't have connected and, and, and might come from really unique, different backgrounds. And it
takes some courage to show up on a screen and say, I'm sitting across from Reggie Butler. He's had
this huge success in his work, but can I share and can I learn? And, and so I love the way you
think about that in a profound way. Performance paradigms,
you've got a really clear vision and you talk about human connection so passionately and
the way you deliver it is, is intriguing to me. How do you go about sharing that vision
with your team and, and making sure that it resonates?
When I think about the work we do, and if we're going to improve the human condition as,
as our mission, I make sure that the people on my team had the ability to improve their lives
based on the work we do. So we live the work. We are the work. I have a colleague that's a coach
and is a phenomenal woman. And she said, being is the new doing. Like we, we do work.
We are the work. Like I am the change I talk about. I am the human connection that I talk
about. And I, and I offer that to everybody that, that works with me. Like, what do you need to
actually be that human connector? What do you need? And I allow people to, to practice in that
space. I'm going to, I'm going to, you know, say this to you too, Luke.
I don't want people to search for something that they think is unreachable. It's not attainable.
We are not practiced as a species on making a human connection first.
We're practiced as a species to stay apart. So if you think about civilization, you think about,
you know, a tribe, a community, when they are on their land, in their space, in their place,
and you look over the horizon and another group of people are coming towards you,
you're going to say, well, I don't know what to do. I don't know what to do. I don't know what to do.
And so our first instinct isn't to go to them with open arms. Our first instinct is to make sure we do a quick
assessment, whether or not there will be harm involved. And then as they get closer, there's
all these social clues and cues. We decide that we should connect, but our first instinct
is to stay apart. So think about that and let that from the birth of civilization and then take that
all the way up to now. Do you realize when we start working for a company, when we go someplace,
we're like, oh, we're going to be working for a company. We're going to be working for a company.
And so our second instinct is to stay separate from people until we figure things out, to stay apart
from people until we know what the rules are in this organization, to know how to act, how to be
in this space. We're not practiced in being connected first. Now there's neuroscience behind
that. And I'll prove it to you in a really quick thing. So when you are interacting with somebody,
there's chemicals. We have a chemical reaction with each other. And I believe that the,
you know, we all know what oxytocin is. We also know what dopamine is. We also know what
adrenaline is. So when you're interacting with somebody on your team and somebody sends you an
email that says, hey, I need to talk. You tell me, Luke, if you get an email from somebody that
you work with and they say, hey, we need to talk one sentence, which chemical do you think is being
released for most people? I think the fear kicks in for most people.
Is my instinct. It's like, what have I done wrong? Not, not, hey, this could be a great
opportunity. I might be in trouble, you know, that's, you know, and I do that myself too,
isn't it? You get a call from, from, you know, a leader in an organization. Hey,
can we meet on Thursday? And that's it. And you go, hey, shit, you know, have I missed something
here? Have I, and it might be, it's a catch up until you're doing a great job, but that's not
your first instinct, is it? We're not practiced in, in letting oxytocin and serotonin,
and those chemicals be a part of our human connection. We immediately jump to cortisol
and adrenaline is just flushing through our system. Like what happened? Oh my goodness.
What do I need to do that? Did I turn in something late? Did I not do something? Is my wife,
is my partner? Like anytime anybody reaches out to us, we should be going, oh, I can't wait to
talk to him. But that's not the normal response. And you know it. And everybody listening knows
that. I want you to think about which chemical, this is about the neuroscience of it all,
what chemical do you make course through another person's body when you talk to them? Anybody who's
listening to me right now, think about the person you love. When you talk to them, what chemical
are you making release when they interact with you? Is it cortisol? Is it dopamine? Is it
adrenaline? You got to think about these things because it's really important that we pay attention
to that. Now I'm making what feels like it's a little light of it, Luke. It's so serious though.
There's, there's a, a serious lens that I want,
people to understand. We, when we interact with another human, we change their biology
and I'm dead serious. We change people's biology and I want us to be responsible
when we interact with people. Some of the offhanded comments we make to some people,
it changes their biology. If fear is an emotion, they start to exhibit everything that comes,
trickles along with fear, will make a person not want to connect. So we,
to pay attention to the clues and cues and look at neuroscience as the reason that what I'm talking
about is validated. We should pay attention to it. And we know that Reggie, don't we? That people
get sick in work environments that aren't healthy and it morphs into literally disease. As you said,
it changes biology. When you're in an unhealthy environment, you don't think you can escape. It
affects your family life. It affects your relationships. It's, it's, it's profound.
Reggie, I want to ask you, we see curiosity as a,
as a common word that is really something across leaders and they use curiosity to approach their
learning and development. Does that ring true to you? Yes. Um, so I started, I use that as one of
the fundamental core tenants of learning retention. Um, there was a, um, um, a guy named Jim Rohn. He's
passed away. And one of the things he said in one of his talks and teachings, he said that when the
brain is frustrated,
it shuts down. Learning can't get in. Learning doesn't stick. He also suggested through his
studies that when the brain is fascinated, analogous to being curious, we learn more and
we retain more. So I want you to think about that. There's a difference between being frustrated as
you go throughout your day in a state of confusion, trying to figure things out versus
curious or fascinated by the possibilities that will make you lean into learning. So curiosity
holds a very,
very high space in my work in terms of us getting to next. If people were more curious about race,
identity, culture, and heritage, uh, about how people move in the complexities of culture, we
would have much better outcomes, but we're not curious about it. We're mostly frustrated by
different opinions around race, identity, culture, and heritage to the point where I actually had to
create a product called rich dialogues, race, identity, culture, and heritage. Cause I believe
people don't talk enough.
They don't dialogue nearly enough to move past the level of uncomfort, um, the level of discomfort in order to get to this, the complexities of what makes us all beautiful. We don't talk enough. We sit in our positions and we try to convince each other about why the way we're thinking is the way to think. That is not helpful. It's interesting, but it's not helpful all the time.
And Reggie, communicating with clarity is another dimension of leadership. We see you're an incredible
leader.
You're a communicator. You get your words across in a really, uh, unique way. Is that something you've, you've dialed into, or is that just you as, uh, as the way that you've been able to evolve?
So I will tell you, so I, I've leveraged my theater background, uh, in that context. I want you to think about this story. So I have, I have always, um, been in front of an audience. So theater and music taught middle school, taught high school, adjunct professor.
So that means I've always stood in front of somebody delivering knowledge towards somebody. I'm a classically trained pianist. I eventually had a band, uh, played in front of crowds. So it's always been me working the craft and science of making a connection through verbal acuity and creating an emotional experience for people.
So I've crafted that my entire life, not knowing that would take me to this space in this moment.
But I've always been in front of people, always passionate about delivering a message. And to anybody who's entering this space, and I'm not talking about DEI and leadership, anybody who is entering the space of delivering messages, you need to put in the work.
Being passionate isn't enough. I got a lot of people. It's like, Reggie, I'd love to do what you do. I'm so passionate about, and they give me whatever the topic is. This doesn't mean you should do it. You should practice first.
And then get in front of people and deliver that message. So you are confident that they will be confident after they hear your message. No, I've been doing this all my life, my friend.
And Reggie, how important has collaboration been for you in the work that you do?
So I honestly believe this. People should never think they can do anything alone. I don't know where people sort of picked up the reasoning that suggests I can make it by myself. It's always been about collaboration. There's always people.
Great minds.
Great minds occupy spaces all the time. You just have to tap into it. I believe there's a great mind in every room. In every room. I just need to give voice to that great mind, create space for that great mind to actually be heard. And I love to amplify the thoughts and framing and perspectives of other people everywhere I go.
There's a great mind in every room. I love that thought, isn't it? But a lot of them don't get heard because, as you said, the environment stopped there.
To allow people the ability to share their wisdom with you. Reggie, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
I would go toward family. So I would say it's a combination of people, but my mom and dad. And the reason I use my mom and dad is because they both had two very different styles. And I was a product of multiple perspectives on how to survive and thrive. So I was raised military. I was never on the road. My father was already back from his travels.
When I met him. But he was the person that put structure and discipline in my life. And I learned from him. He also became the manager of the band I had. He traveled with me. So I got discipline and organization from him. And my mother was this beautiful spirit that was always in service of other people, no matter what they were dealing with, no matter what they were going through. She always showed grace and compassion.
And so I lived a life of seeing both of those and learned how to.
Learned how to navigate both spaces at the same time. That's why, Luke, when we when we talk about some people say this human centered work is or are soft skills. I push back. The soft skills are absolutely the hard skills that people need to master.
I can master those other technical skills by learning more and practicing more for me to master the soft skills. I have to make connections with people.
And that that's why I say you have to do the work. So my the role models in my life, the leaders in my life were my mom and my dad first. And then as I go through different stages in my life, there was a professor at the university. There was a CEO at a company I worked for. So I've had different leaders at different times. Thank goodness, because what I learned was there's always a different type of leader based on situations and seasons in life.
Yeah.
that i met later in my life i would have never listened to earlier in my life so i'm glad that
i went through my first leaders first that seemed to be set up for me and i love when people go to
their family when you've had the the great uh good fortune isn't it to have that role modeling so
close to home it's a it's a it's a gift in life and i feel very much the same with that with my
parents and in we're obsessed with collaboration in in the work we do reggie and i wanted to ask
this question to finish on in the work that you do is there is there someone you would identify i
think god if i could collaborate with that person it would be a great in any of the passions in your
life um you've got so many of them is there a name that springs to mind in terms of collaboration
that you'd like to work with i don't know it's for different phases of my life that's hard to
answer because i would say if it was in the in the music world um one of my idols that sort of
shaped how i view music was prince and
everything that he delivered to the world and how he stood up for the rights of his music
i would love to be in collaboration with him not to do a song specifically but to be in a space with
somebody that multi-talented that delivered meaning purpose and messages through his music
love to collaborate with somebody like that i mean he's not with us anymore but i can take
any number of artists that are out there now and we'll love to have a collaborative session
about being a better human using music as the
you
pathway to creating stronger um connection that that was that on the music side um
there have been many many leaders that have been in space most of them are u.s based so of course
um you know mlk maya angelo there's just a lot of people that i would love to have spent time with
i'm gonna tell you something luke some of the people that i think most people are listening
for are looking for seem to hold the title of hero and they're just what i think they're
doing i call people who are ordinary doing extraordinary things that i would like to for
people to collaborate with we keep looking up to find people to look up to when they're literally
right across from you that's where i sit i all the time and that's a beautiful uh way to finish
this conversation uh reggie there's extraordinary things happening right in front of us every day
and people uh i get so full of uh optimism when have a conversation like this with someone who's
someone like you who's influencing people every single day and unfortunately we we see the
mainstream news and it's full of a lot of negativity but i'm with you i'm full of optimism
for great people doing great things and uh i love the work that you do reggie it's been a great
honor to spend some time with you today care more i can't wait to go and uh listen to some of your
work on the podcast and be a better human it's a great message isn't it i i think if we all start
there we're going somewhere pretty special so thank you so much reggie for taking
time to speak to me i really appreciate it yeah thanks for having me luke i'll i'll say this to
you you are making a difference in people's lives by continuing to do this work this way because
you're getting the voice of other people into the space we need to hear more from other people so i
appreciate you for going this far it is why i said yes we look we looked we did a lot of work
making sure this was valid and it is you're you're doing really good work and i appreciate
you being in that space because you are changing people's lives
that's what it's all about very kind reggie we'd love to see you here in australia i know it's on
the list so hopefully uh sometime soon we uh we see you down under and um again that's a great
honor to catch up with you thank you so much i appreciate it i want you to be better do better
and care more be better do better care more absolutely thanks reggie all right thanks so
much thanks for listening to another episode of the empowering leaders podcast huge thanks as
always to our great friends at temper and we encourage you to check out
our leader connect program new episodes are out every wednesday morning at 6 a.m