This week's conversation is with an amazing leader
and a great friend of mine, Richard Oppie.
Richard is the Vice President of Global Brands
at beverage giant Anheuser-Busch InBev, based in New York.
Richard's incredible success in the corporate world
is a great story in itself.
He now oversees the branding strategies
of some of the world's most iconic beers,
like Budweiser, Corona and Stella Artois.
In this conversation, we get behind-the-scenes insights
about the controversial World Cup decision
to ban Budweiser from their stadiums
just before the event kicked off
and see how Richard and his team
took to what could have been an international marketing disaster
and flipped it into an iconic campaign for the brand.
Richard is a great modern leader
and is changing the game in brand and marketing
around the world on a global scale.
His passion for what he does
is one of the fundamentals for the work we do
at our leadership business, Alita.
We're incredibly humbled and proud to work with people
like Richard Oppie at Alita.
If you're interested in learning,
leading and collaborating,
you can find out more about what we do
at alitacollective.com.
There's some great resources there.
I encourage you to check out
our signature Alita Connect program
to get started and to understand how people like Richard
are leading in your world.
Richard Oppie is Vice President of Global Brands
for Anheuser-Busch InBev,
the largest consumer goods company in the world
with leading beer brands in over 100 countries,
including Budweiser, Corona, Stella Artois and many more.
Given the scale and reach of the business,
Richard's role is arguably
the biggest marketing job in the world,
a role Richard secured before his 40th birthday
on the back of his reputation
for making courageous decisions, innovation,
creativity and consistent success.
Rich, great to see you back.
You're in your old hometown of Melbourne,
fresh in from New York.
Been an amazing time in your life.
Thanks for having me, Darce.
It's good to be back and back in the studio.
Now, Rich, I think the first time we met,
we might've crossed over at Junior Footy at Auskick
if I'm wrong.
I'm not sure.
or close enough to it.
I was doing Breakfast Radio at the time
on Triple M with Eddie McGuire and Mick Malloy
and my co-host Mick Malloy broke a story
on our show about Victoria Bitter.
For those listening,
the famous VB in the town we're in
is the drink of choice for everyone,
really, in the state of Victoria,
one of the most famous beers in Australia.
And there was a story that there was going
to be a change in the recipe,
back to the original recipe.
And from what I remember, Rich,
that nearly got you to the point
where it got you in a fair bit of trouble,
your association with me in that story.
Can you pick it up?
Is my version right?
What do you remember from that one?
We're going back now,
but I remember having a chat to you at football
and then on Monday,
there was a leak,
was it the Mickey leak,
back in the day,
talking about Victoria Bitter
going back to the big cold beer,
back to 4.9% alcohol.
And yeah,
I wanted to know where that came from
and I certainly didn't divulge
the conversation,
I had with you at the time.
Well, so Mick was doing a segment
called Mickey leaks on the back
of Wiki leaks was the biggest story
in the world at the time.
So he wasn't really a newsbreaker,
but that was a story close to his heart
as a man who loved VB more than anyone else.
And the fascinating part was
that I had no insight at all on that.
So you and I hadn't spoken about
that being the case.
So he'd somehow got his own version
of that story,
but your colleagues at CAB at the time
were calling you Ricky leaks,
thinking that you'd leaked that story to me,
which was not true.
No, I don't know where Mick got it from.
I thought it must've been,
you know,
someone obviously in the industry
that, that spoke to him about it,
but yeah,
they called me Ricky leaks,
but to be honest,
it worked in our favor in the end
because that campaign sort of took off
from there and it ended up being
the PR headline.
And I think from memory,
when we go back,
we actually brought Victoria Bitter
back for the first time on Triple M
at like 6,
7 a.m.
in the morning.
Which is what I love about,
you know,
you and I spoke in the intro
about your innovation
is that you saw an opportunity
straight away and thought,
well,
this is a story that's happened.
You end up sponsoring the show
straight away.
We hold a VB,
we built a VB fountain,
you know,
in Mick's honor.
And it was as authentic a story
as you could.
No one loved Victoria Bitter
more than Mick Malloy.
It was a sort of DNA of our show,
but you know,
the old sort of marketing world
would have been,
that's a drama,
stay away from it.
But your instinct was,
hey, this is good.
We need to,
we need to,
need to follow it through.
Yeah,
because Triple M,
they were,
it was so big at the time
and we just thought Mick
was perfect for VB.
He just loves his beer.
He's genuine.
It was authentic.
And so we thought,
let's run with this.
And so we actually got Mick
and I remember Ed came down
as well to the brewery
and they saw Victoria Bitter 4.9
coming off for the very first time.
And then I think we were upstairs
at the motel.
Because I remember
having the headphones there
with yourself
and,
and Mick and Ed
and it was packed
and we had like,
I think a lot of people
must have had the day off
that day on that Monday
when we relaunched VB
back to 4.9.
And I think we went on
to sponsor some
Bunga Bunga parties
which Mick was obsessed
with Silvio Berlusconi
at the time.
I look back and think,
you know,
you'd be taken off air
for some of the things
that we did back then.
You'd probably be cancelled
but it was a different time.
It was a lot of fun.
All done in good spirit
and I think the authentic message
was right.
I mean,
the story was that VB
for tax reasons
lowered its alcohol rate
and then the consumers
got it, didn't they?
They went,
hey, you know what?
We're not going to save tax.
We're going to bring the beer
back to what it was.
And again,
that's your marketing hat on.
It was a good campaign.
Yeah, I think that was
one of the lessons I've had
actually over the years
in marketing
is one of our principles
at AB InBev
is the consumer
is the boss.
And when you make decisions
when you're not putting
the consumer first
and you're trying to make
more money in the short term,
which is,
what we were doing
essentially,
I think back in the day
was sort of making
an extra $20 million a year
by dropping the ABV
because of the excise tax
and actually gave an excuse
for people to walk away
from Victoria Bitter.
So we wanted to take
that excuse away
and we went back
to the big cold beer
and people did flock back.
We actually got VB
back into growth there
for the next 18 months,
which was great.
And, you know,
it was great just to see VB,
you know,
get back to its best.
Yeah, I love that.
I mean,
you can hear that slogan,
isn't it?
You know,
consumer first,
but when you actually
put it in place,
the customers are smart enough
to work that out,
aren't they?
And say,
okay,
we're going to give up
a big financial saving
because we are,
you know,
putting you first.
Now,
I've got to jump,
Rich,
because to the next story,
how much of it you can share
will be interesting.
We had one of the great trips
I've ever done.
On the back of that,
we ended up going
to the Super Bowl in New York,
February 2014,
MetLife Stadium,
one of the great sporting events
I've ever been to in my life.
And, you know,
Eddie, again,
probably planned the trip,
but always got too busy
and couldn't go.
So it was you,
Mick,
and I,
and lots of fun over there.
But that probably spawned
another great story,
really,
sitting around at the bar,
enjoying a couple of cold beverages
and Mick pitching to you
the idea of a show
called The Front Bar,
which has really changed
the game here in Australia
on the back of that conversation.
You know what?
I sort of reflect now
on my time in the beer industry
in 20-odd years ago.
And they were some
of the best times I ever had.
That trip to New York,
I mean, I've been lucky
to go on a number
of Super Bowl trips
and World Cup trips,
but that one with you
and Mick was up there
with one of the best.
Mick, absolute ripper,
and it was a lot of fun.
And, yeah, you're right, actually.
One of the nights
we were just talking
about Carlton Draft,
and he was talking
about marketing
and what's the brand about.
And I was just explaining
it was the beer
that mates drink
at the bar.
You know, when they're
not taking themselves
too seriously,
you know, it's the beer
that was like
the egalitarian beer.
And the beer you drink
at the pub
when you're watching the footy
and you want to have some fun.
And then he spoke to me
about this idea
about a footy show
type concept.
And he said,
you know, could you imagine
like me and another comedian
and an anchor,
you know, at the bar
as mates, you know,
talking about footy
and having fun
and having a few beers.
I'm like, yeah,
that's exactly what I'm doing.
That's exactly what
Carlton Draft is about.
And I was like,
that's a great idea, Mick.
And we had a few more drinks
and then the stories
started getting better
and better as they do.
And then I remember saying to Mick,
let's make sure
we pick that up again.
And I wasn't sure
if it was just, you know,
Mick had a couple of beers
and telling a few stories.
But to his credit,
the first week
we got back to Melbourne,
he came and formally pitched it.
And there was like
Aidy Brown, I think,
was with him at the time
and his brother,
Rich Malloy.
And it was one of those ones
where I thought at the time,
let's have a go.
You know, let's have a crack.
It wasn't a big investment.
And we first of all
kicked it off at the All Nations.
And I remember back in the day
we were looking,
okay, which channel
do we put it on?
And I spoke to,
I won't use his name
because everyone knows him,
but a good friend,
a friend at Channel 10.
And I said,
we've got this great idea.
Mick's idea with Rich Malloy.
It's called Front Bar.
Took him through the idea.
I reckon it can take down
the Channel 9 footy show.
And he laughed at me,
like literally laughed at me.
He said, you are kidding yourself.
You know, good luck.
So we ended up putting it on
afl.com.au on digital.
And then from there,
it grew to Seven Mate.
I think it was late on a Friday night
before eventually we got onto
the main station Thursday night.
And yeah, the rest is history.
And I love that.
I love that show.
I still watch it,
still stay in touch with the boys.
And when I look back in my time,
that's one of the best things
I've been involved in.
And it was Mick's idea,
Mick's genius.
And I think for Carlton Draft,
it was such an authentic partnership,
which I think is why it works so well.
Yeah, for those who are listening
and maybe don't understand
the Front Bar,
getting players back,
legends who can tell great stories.
And the brilliant,
it feels like you're sitting at the pub
with three blokes,
you want to have a beer with,
telling great story.
I mean, the concept is so brilliantly simple,
but the show, you know,
is just outstanding.
And credit to you, you know,
to back it in ahead of its time
when the TV stations
weren't really prepared to go near it,
to put it on the internet first.
And it's still, you know,
Mick and Andy Marr and Sam Payne do it.
And as a guest to go on that show,
it's a show you want to go on
because you just,
you can't help but laugh.
I think everyone goes on
and has a great experience.
I do have to tell one story
from that trip,
but we do promote
responsible service of alcohol.
I know you're in the business of doing that,
but we used to love being in New York
because instead of getting up 6am
to do breakfast radio,
it's one o'clock,
maybe New York time,
12 or one o'clock.
So you can have a couple
of quiet beverages, Rich,
and you can turn up the next day
and do your job
and have a bit of a life.
Breakfast radio can, you know,
can take away the joy of your life.
But Mick had decided to kick on
one of those nights, mate.
And,
and maybe a little later
than you and I had decided.
And our guest in studio
was John Butler
from the John Butler Trail,
legendary Australian rocker.
They go pretty hard.
I'll never forget this comment.
So Mick,
it may become a little bit later,
turned up late to our show,
even though it was starting at one o'clock.
And John Butler walks into you and I
and says,
I think you've got to send your boy home.
I don't think he's good enough to go on air.
And I'm thinking,
if you've got a rock star
telling your on-air host to go home,
you know,
you've had a good time in New York.
I'll maybe leave that at that.
Hey Rich,
great success you had at,
at CUB
and some of those stories with the front bar
and bringing back VB.
There's many more of those
that make up your success.
CUB gets bought by this global behemoth,
AB InBev,
the Budweiser Brewery.
For those who don't know the,
the backstory of that business,
majority owned by Jorge Lehmann,
the,
the genius Brazilian private equity
superstar,
man,
that Warren Buffett describes
as one of the best investors
and he reveres him
for his investment skills
and they have a reputation rich
for finding young guns in business
and promoting them regardless of age
to senior leadership roles.
And that's exactly your story
as I understand it.
Can you tell us about the culture
that you walked into
taking on this huge global role
and what that's been like for you?
I really feel fortunate
the career that I've had
and had,
as we sort of say,
sort of touched on.
I've got so many fond memories
from the CUB days.
And then in 2011,
we were acquired by the second biggest brewery
in the world,
which was SAB Miller,
a South African brewery.
And that was a great company as well.
And they were people that were passionate about beer,
loved their beer,
but was very much more old school.
And I was part of the global
sort of marketing leadership team there
representing Australia.
But I was by far the youngest
on that leadership team.
So I remember going to those meetings
and I felt really young,
which was always a little bit intimidating.
And then in 2016,
we were acquired by AB InBev
and my remit was being APAC South.
So as well as running marketing for Australia,
I also looked after India and Vietnam.
And I was sitting on the global marketing leadership team
and I've gone from by far the youngest
to one of the oldest,
and it was incredible.
So what age are you there,
like at that stage,
in your late thirties or?
Yeah, so that would have been,
I would have been 36.
And you're on a global business that scale,
the biggest consumer goods company in the world.
You're one of the oldest in the leadership position.
One of the oldest.
So they're all around my age.
And I really felt at home amongst this group.
They were young, dynamic,
there's a lot of energy in the room.
And one thing that we talk about AB InBev is meritocracy.
So it's actually not about how old you are.
It's about what you deliver, your potential.
And if you dream big and you deliver big results,
you get rewarded.
And that's what I love about the company.
And it's got a very powerful culture.
It's this culture of ownership
and everyone,
everyone really acts like they're a genuine owner of the business.
And it's got a very clear purpose.
And that is to dream big,
to create a future with more cheers.
And everyone there dreams big.
And you really can create a future with more cheers,
a future with more happiness,
with more celebration,
more innovation,
more sustainability.
And the best way for me to describe AB InBev,
it's like it's one of the biggest CPGs in the world,
but it has a mindset of a startup.
You know, we really move at speed with agility
and we try and minimize the bureaucracy that you get in big organizations.
So, yeah, I feel like, you know, I found my home when I became part of ABI.
Yeah. And the backstory again, you know,
you know, the story of the genius three musketeers from Brazil.
They, you know, bought some of the biggest brands in the world,
you know, Heinz in America, Burger King,
and then, you know, the famous Budweiser.
So that's dreaming big, isn't it?
And you feel like,
that culture genuinely flows through to day-to-day in your job and what you do.
Yeah. Even now, those people that had the chance to read Dream Big, the book,
it's incredible.
The fact that, you know, the three that you talk about that sort of founded the business
in the early days, a small Brazilian brewer that bought Antarctica and became a big brewer
in Brazil, that then went on and bought Interbrew, you know, think of the likes of Stella Artois,
and then went and bought Grippo Medello, like Corona,
and then when no one thought that they could, they went and bought Anheuser-Busch,
which is really, you know, Budweiser in the US, and all the way to buying the second biggest
brewer in the world, SAB Miller.
I mean, you talk about dreaming big, it doesn't get bigger than that.
So it's something that they live and breathe in the culture.
You feel it, you get caught up in it, and it's incredibly motivating to know you've got a company that will dream big,
and will aggressively go after it.
We're sitting in Melbourne today, Rich, the World Cup.
Our time was played last night, the World Cup final, Argentina beat France in one of the great World Cups of all time,
and Lionel Messi becomes arguably in the conversation for the greatest players of all time.
But for you, a couple of days out, Budweiser, synonymous with the World Cup, you're a major sponsor.
You have beer banned from the stadiums literally a few days out.
Tell us about...
Yeah, it's fair to say we had a pretty intense month with Budweiser, and, you know, we've had a team working on this for 18 months to two years,
you know, and for some people it's been like full time.
So you can imagine the emotions when we get the phone call to let us know that they're banning Budweiser in the stadiums.
And so we went straight into scenario planning and sort of working from, you know,
there's obviously the more emotional response was let's pull out, you know,
we've got 1600 people that were coming over that were part of the AB InBev family with customers and wholesalers and celebrities and influencers.
We took over the Budweiser, the W Hotel became the Budweiser Hotel, which was the best hotel in Doha.
They had the best nightclub in Doha.
Which became the Bud Club.
So we were all geared up for this big activation.
So to have that pulled from us sort of a week out was a big challenge, big obstacle.
And so as we were working through it, obviously the time difference, we had a team in the UK because they're on the same time, similar time to Qatar.
One of our talents in our team who runs our newsroom thought that they would capitalize on this moment and went out with Well.com.
That's awkward.
And before you know it, it's blown up and it's gone viral.
And so...
Can I ask you before you move on to that?
Someone in power in your team.
Yeah.
That's a pretty big call on the Budweiser social media account.
Does the bureaucracy have to get approval for that?
Or did someone just go with gut feel and go?
So it's a good question.
We have our protocols and when it is linked to sort of banning
alcohol, something as sensitive as this, it should have been escalated
but unfortunately time differences and us being asleep
when it started to leak in the newsroom
she thought she'd do the right thing as an owner and to be honest
when you think about it in hindsight, she knows the platform incredibly well
and the tone was spot on
at the time. It was brilliant but it probably should have been
escalated and so people that know the story will know we actually pulled it
down. I woke up in the morning and had like 100 text messages
the head of Budweiser globally, the VP rang me and said look we're going to have to
work through this, this has just gone out and
I was really impressed with the way that the team handled it
like the head of legal, just very professional, pragmatic
always thinking the bigger picture, always like what are our principles
how are we going to handle this
and we spoke to the person at the time and
she took it very well and understood that that one probably should have been escalated
so we pulled it down and that actually created even more intrigue
into why we pulled it down and understanding the sensitivity
of this was we had a lot of people on the ground in Qatar so you have to always
put your people first and be careful that you don't ever put them in danger
and also we were very conscious that we are at late stages
and we had a negotiation with FIFA for the 2026 contract
which is North America so it's Mexico, Canada, US, very important
that we wanted to get so we didn't want to do anything that was going to potentially damage
that negotiation so it was a very tense time
but we all got together as a team and we thought how do we
turn these lemons that we've been dealt into lemonade and so we
called it Project Lemonade and we
we decided that people
the players can play for more than just the World Cup
they can play for the beer and so we went out the next day with the tweet
new day, new tweet, winner takes all, bring home the bud
So within 24 hours you've moved to
that campaign, for a decision that big that's pretty quick
and that's one of the reasons I just love the company so much
the speed that we moved at, you have the 4 or 5 decision makers
in the room across marketing
PR, legal and said this is the call we're going to make
and we're going to, we don't know exactly how it's going to happen
we don't know which country is going to win, is it 100% feasible
but we're going to make it happen, we're going to work it out
so we were cheering, I was cheering last night for Argentina
because they know how to party, they know how to have fun
and to see Lionel Messi win
was historic, one of the best games ever and so
Messi's going to bring home the bud with Argentina
and we're going to put on one of the biggest celebrations ever in Buenos Aires
So literally you're going to fly in all of that unused stock
and the image is great isn't it, and have a party for the winner
and winner takes all was the message
It was like everywhere, the hashtag bring home the bud sort of took off
we had containers, they were Budweiser containers
saying bring home the bud, we're dropping in cities all around the world
Brazil got a bit excited, they thought they were going to bring home the bud
and they had dropped them in all of them
in all of their cities
and so then the consumers started getting behind it which was great
and then Neymar posted saying he wants to bring home the bud for Brazil
so it really started to build up and get a lot of traction
and yes, Argentina are the ones that are going to enjoy the celebration
and it's going to be a great party
You'd like to be on the ground in Argentina today
that would be some serious fun
Now Rich, I know you've had a huge passion for leadership in a senior, senior role
all the way through from a young age
and a huge sense of having a positive impact in your leadership
and we're really grateful you joined our space, A Leader Connect
Matt and I, my great mate who's actually sitting outside the studio today
we're going to have some lunch after this
and it's been awesome to connect with you again
and see what you've brought to the table
but hopefully as well, it's a group that we love
it's a really fascinating group
Benjamin Northey who's the CEO of the Melbourne Symphony Orchestra
one of the most revered conductors around the world
and I just love sitting across from him in the same format here Rich
and what a brilliant, creative brain
Michael Voss, you're a gun junior footy player Rich
you nearly went down the AFL path
Michael Voss, one of the best players ever
and a unique person in that world
Dr Chris Brown, just a genius
Chris, incredible person in his place
Trent Robinson, legend of NRL
and a lovely guy and love the way he goes about
can you tell us about what it's been like catching up
and connecting in that world of A Leader Connect?
It was an honour
just to be part of that group
to be honest
because Voss, the first promotion I ever did in my marketing career
was on Carlton Meade in 2001 with Michael Voss
Really?
Yeah, so that brought back memories
That was their first premiership wasn't it?
Yeah, they won three in a row
Three in a row then
around then
so it was great timing
and really good bunch of guys
who have been incredibly successful in their own fields
and I love the sessions
they go for an hour and 15 Matt puts in the diary
but it's one I always prioritise
because I really enjoy it
and they go so quickly
like it's like, it's already up
it's one of the quickest meetings you have for the week
and everyone has a different perspective
and so we do talk about
you know, leadership and challenges that we're facing
and it's been really fascinating
people will bring to the table
a challenge that they're facing
and then you get different perspectives on
you know, how you could handle it
and it's about the questions that you ask
and I remember vividly
probably the third session we had
Trent Robinson who's the coach of the Roosters
and he's a very impressive guy
and he was talking about one of the challenges he had
leading into the finals
and it was just one question that Vossie asked him
that got him to think differently
about his plan
and I won't give it away obviously
because it's always confidential those conversations
but Robbo was like
hey Vossie, I hadn't thought of it like that
you know, and it's just like a different perspective
the right question being asked
to get you to think differently
and so it's been incredibly valuable
and one that, you know
we've finished the sessions
but we love it so much
we're continuing with it
Yeah, it's great Rich
and I love that idea, isn't it
you've got brilliant people
and you know, you're running at it
running at an incredible, you know, schedule
every time I see you're in Colombia or
somewhere in a different market
you know, running global brands
but the fact that you take that time to dial the other 15
Chris Brown was telling me he was in Iceland
in the back of a Kombi van
3 o'clock in the morning
dialing in to make sure he didn't miss
and you know, he described that
as wanting to be a better person after those sessions
that's someone at an incredibly high level
and so, you know, it's fascinating that you guys take the time
but it feels like
you don't know what you don't know do you?
when someone comes from a different world
there's some real value
when having that shared opinion, isn't there?
There is
and I think with those sessions
I find that
the more open you are
the more vulnerable you are
the more you get out of it
it's almost become
it's like a personal board
or
for me it's like a little mentor group
because it's good to talk about people
to people that are not connected with your work
and
I haven't even met these guys
face to face
because I'm on the other side of the world
but
we just have this implicit trust
amongst the group
where we throw things out there
that we open ourselves up
and I think that's what
has sort of galvanized the group
and
you know, we get so much out of it
and so I think these will be like
hopefully it's sort of mentors that
I can continue to stay in touch with
for quite some time
and you know
if I have problems going forward
you know, these are guys that I'll reach out to
and to get their point of view
because they come at it from a different angle
I hear there's an inter-season trip
being planned in New York mate
your new home town
and I've got no right to be there
but I'm planning on being there
come along Rich mate
I've enjoyed some time
in that part of the world with you
and again
you know, we often say
we love collaborating with people from
you know, small business or
people working in education or the arts
you don't have to
you know, be the global head of marketing
to be part of one of these groups
we love meeting people where they're at and
they're great stories
people as busy as Rich
to take the time to reflect and learn
so again, I'll give it a plug
if you want to check out elitacollective.com
and our signature program
that Rich is just talking about
it's called Elita Connect
now there's a famous quote Rich
that you know well
from your world
half the money I spend on advertising is wasted
the trouble is I don't know which half
it's attributed to John Wanamaker
it's almost a hundred years ago I think
or even longer
known as the forefather of marketing
he was a successful merchant in the US
from what I understand
can I pick your brain on this for a moment
a lot of people listening
who started a business
or want to grow their space
in whatever field it is
I mean it's a hard question but
what's the key in your mind
from all your experience in marketing
what's some lessons we can learn from you
it's a big question
and I think
in regard to that quote
more and more
you can measure these days
you know, particularly through digital
so you know
you can see what your cost per acquisition is
you can see what your ROI is
so these days
it's much easier to be able to sort of justify
the extra spend on marketing
being able to see the impact that it has
on building brand equity
and then ultimately
how it drives conversion
and so most people understand the funnel
from awareness to consideration
to conversion
so we track all of that
and that's why sort of
it's not as fluffy these days
as what it might be
it might have been back then
but I mean from a marketing perspective
you know, I think the big thing is
most people that are looking to start their business
or start a brand
is to think about
how are you going to differentiate your brand
you know, in that field
and then think about
functionally
how is it differentiated
and then emotionally
how do you differentiate it
because what I see is a lot of
direct to consumer brands
that are quite transactional
so they're more around product
and price
and they drive very much about conversion
they don't do as good a job
as sort of building a brand
building the emotion behind the brand
building distinctive assets
that make the brand stand out
so distinctive asset is like
it could be the logo
it could be the colour
it could be the shape
think of the VB bottle
think the VB jingle
these are distinctive assets
that are incredibly important
when you're building a brand
and then
it really then comes down to
if I really make it simple
is physical availability
and mental availability
so physical availability
if you can't find that product
that brand
you can't buy it
and so it sounds simple
but it's the most important thing
and then at the same time
mental availability
when people are open
to buying that product
you need to make sure
your brand's top of mind
and that's why
you need strong distinctive assets
and you need to make sure
that your brand is going to cut through
so that
and people sometimes don't think about this
but even if I look at beer brands
when you hold that beer brand in your hand
it says something about you
it's like a badge
and that's all the meaning
that you build behind that brand
that's so important
yeah it's a really great explanation
I'm not surprised in any way shape or form
I'm still wrestling with
the intuition part as well
clearly you can measure the digital
more than ever
but there's an intuition to say
bring back the bud
isn't it in 24 hours
that you can't mistake
I suppose those decisions
are part of your history
and your skill
that you bring to the table
I read in research for this Rich
that I didn't realise
the Chinese market
is the biggest beer market
for ABM beer
is that correct
by some factor
and that you think
they're the most sophisticated
in digital marketing
am I right in saying that
and why is that the case
yeah China I think
are ahead of the game
when it comes to digital
I'm on WeChat
I still try to find it hard
to get my head around
all of their digital platforms
and even with DTC
within beer
they're well ahead of the game
DTC explain that
direct to consumer
so where you can
order your beer online
and have it delivered to your door
within 30 minutes
is that going to be big
around the world
is that happening in your space
more and more now
it is
happening more and more now
so we have Zed Delivery in Brazil
which is becoming
quite sizeable for us
we think it will get to
10 plus percent
of the beer market
but it's more
once you have that channel
and you've got everything from
you know when you spend marketing
on that digital channel
you then know what the conversion is
and then you can get a lot of insights
and test innovation
that will help you across
the other 90%
and across the other channels
so we think it's really
going to be important for us
more the direct to consumer
moving forward
we have a brand called Tadar
which will be our global
direct to consumer brand
that we sort of launched
about a year ago
so I'm sitting at home
there's an app
I want a six pack of Budweiser
I can get it delivered
anywhere around the world
is that where it ends up
exactly right
you'll be
you're on your phone
you'll probably do reorder
get the same sort of six pack
and then
you know we have a commitment
that you know within 30 minutes
we'll have it delivered
to your door
cold
so yeah
it's going to be a bit of a game changer
in many places around the world
yeah that's a compelling offer
when you think
how
you know
where we've come from
from
you know six o'clock close
here in Melbourne
wasn't that long ago
was it
you couldn't get a beer anywhere after
that is a huge transformation
isn't it
with that sort of technology
available
going forward
I like asking this question Rich
because
I talk family
you know
with you a lot
because I'm passionate about it
you're living in New York
you've got this incredible global role
you're on a plane every other day
it's an incredible
chapter of your life
but you move Rose and your three kids
to New York as well
and
you're
I know really passionate about the family space
but how do you balance
doing something as significant
and busy as you are
and keep
the success going on the family front
it's a challenge
I think it helps having
an incredibly supportive wife
and
Rose has been
amazing with our move to
to New York
actually over the years
you know
very supportive
with the three kids
I try and do my best to
compartmentalize
when I'm at work
and when I'm at home
I always try and make sure that
I'm present
you know
that I'm present with the kids
that I'm setting the right example
that I'm not on my phone
and
you know
when I'm at work
I'm pretty intense at work
and so
I try and
break that up
and
and when I'm at home
you know with the
with the kids
I love watching their sport
so
the weekends are really all about
you know
Rose and the kids
I go to
all their different sports
you know
sort of running around
New York City
in the car
from you know
basketball
to
to baseball
to NFL football
and so
it's been quite different
to the Auskick days
that I used to see you at
and then
and cricket
but
no it's
it is a challenge
one thing I'm very
but I always talk
people go
how do you go with
work-life balance
and
I've always struggled
with that
because work's always been such a big
part of my life
but I also know that
family are clearly
my number one
two and three
priority
but I call it
work-life integration
you know
so how do I
make sure that
you know
I can be the best
I can be at work
and how I can be the best dad
and the best husband
and
it's a challenge
but I think
the thing I really focus on is
being always being present there
I've seen you firsthand
at a barbecue mate
you are the king of the kids
you've got
a natural
ability to do that
but yeah
it is interesting
because you don't want to miss the point of life
either do you
you have this great chapter
and
you know
to have a connected family
but the upside is
what a unique experience for your kids
you know
they're going to have this incredible
chapter
and I hear they're going beautifully
over there
Rich we're really passionate about
what modern leadership looks like
and we feel like there's a real shift
you know
what your company does
is promoting young people
with
as you said
this energy and passion
but we're seeing
that shift away from the old hierarchy
which you spoke about
you know
where
no matter what
you're going to have to wait your time
and you know
the
we often use the term
the boss is in the corner office
and it's very hard to even
get a
a knock on the door
and we see there's some
common traits
that we want to talk to you about
starting with self-leadership
we don't think
anyone's really
been able to lead well
without an idea of self-leadership
what does that mean to you
self-leadership
when I think about
leadership
you know
I think about
strong leaders
really care about
humans
not employees
and that's
one thing
that's sort of stuck with me
over the years
that people want to feel valued
you know
as a human
not just another number
in the organization
so really caring about people
having the ability
to have empathy
to be able to
nurture
those relationships
and
you know
I think
that's
really important
and when I think about
self-leadership
I don't really
haven't thought too much
about self-leadership
but when I think about it
it's more about
for you to be able to lead others
and care about others
you need to also be comfortable
with yourself
and
I think
having
being
physically fit
so that you can
help
handle the stresses
and be able to lead others
and be mentally fit
and in a good place
means that you can give more
to other people
and I think
it's really important
self-leadership
is
you know
also links to being
having self-confidence
and I think
it doesn't matter
what role you're in
a senior leader's role
it's tough
you know
you need to have
that self-confidence
you need to have conviction
at the right time
I find particularly
in marketing
because everyone's got an opinion
and
it's always
often polarizing
there's always going to be people
that's going to disagree with you
and
so you need to be able to
listen to people
listen
look at different data points
but then you have to make a call
and you're going to have
the confidence
to back it in
and so
when I think about
self-leadership
I think
having that self-confidence
is critical
and also
to make sure that
having that self-confidence
that you have
you stick by your values
you know
you stay true to who you are
and sometimes
if the
organization
doesn't align to your values
then you're in the wrong place
yeah
I know you're really
passionate about this dimension
which is
the positive impact
in
the environment
and
how you do that on a daily basis
it's
all one of your great skills
you consciously think about it
can you tell us
how you've gone about that
idea of
positively impacting others
yeah
I talk to the team a lot about
the
the power of
positive energy
I came across this
presentation
years ago
by this lady
Amanda Gore
and it really stuck with me
and she spoke about
the power of energy
and
that you can wake up in the morning
and you can make a choice
to either be
an energy giver
or an energy sucker
and
it's a choice you can make
they're both as powerful
as each other
they're both contagious
and
I wake up every morning
I try and get to the gym
if I can
and
I always
go to work
with a positive mindset
before the kids go to school
every day
I say kids
don't just have a good day
have a great day
and they roll their eyes
every time
and they're like
dad we're
and
but I know that
even if 10% of it gets through
I'll be happy
that they have a great day
and when I go to work
you know
you
you don't
sometimes you underestimate the
impact you have
on other people
and
when I go into
a meeting
you know
I make the choice
that I'm gonna
I wanna have a great meeting
I wanna greenhouse
rather than what we call
shithousing
and a lot of it's sort of
body language
so I'll start a meeting
with a bit of banter
a joke
have a bit of fun
tell them I'm excited
about the meeting
and then you get the best out of people
because people are gonna be more
put their ideas out there
that you can greenhouse
and talk about
whereas if you go into that meeting
and you're
grumpy
you've just had a fight with your
your wife
the kids are doing your head in
and
you can just suck the energy
out of that room very quickly
and be an energy sucker
and you'll watch your team
just go into their shell
and
it's something that's really stuck with me
now of course
there are times
when there are tough times
where you have
always gotta be authentic
and you have to deliver
tough messages
but most of the time
you can make a choice
whether you're gonna be
an energy giver
or an energy sucker
and all my life
I prefer to be
glass half full
than glass half empty
yeah it's a brilliant
way to think about it
you know
my wife Becca
always talks about
your energy
speaks well before you do
so even before
as you said
you've opened your mouth
like the body language
and
a smile
or
you can impact people
massively
can't you
as you said
we all have our rough days
but when you start your day
with that mindset
it's such a powerful thing
isn't it
and I don't know
if you've noticed it
but
if I'm home
and I've got things going with work
that are stressing me out
I try and compartmentalize
but if I'm grumpy
the chances are
the kids are gonna be grumpy
yeah
whereas
if I'm up and about
having a laugh
having fun
the kids are usually
in a much better place
and so
I think it's as important
as home
as it is
as a work
and so
you've got a choice in that
isn't it
you can genuinely
create that
if you want to
creating and sharing a vision
we've spoken already about
you know
some of your
visions coming to life
in interesting spaces
you know
from supporting the front bar
or
bringing VB back
we see leaders are really conscious
about how they go about it
dream big is
AB InBev
how have you gone about
creating and sharing
when I think of
a vision
one that springs to mind
is
the marketing leadership team
so
AB InBev's always been known as
as we touched on earlier
a company that's been
phenomenal at M&A
they've been known for
zero-based budgeting
known for
procurement
and frugality
can you explain that before
you know
we know their mergers and acquisitions
are enormous
what's zero-based budgeting
what does that mean
zero-based budgeting
is
you know
often a lot of companies say
here was your budget last year
here's your budget this year
plus 10%
minus 10%
and depending on how the numbers are looking
at AB InBev
it's more about
regardless of what happened last year
what's the plan
how are we going to win
and what's the cost going to be
bottoms up
so it's a blank page every year
yeah essentially
that's the
so you almost throw out last year's budget
and so
do it again is it
yeah
that's essentially the
the concept of it
and how it works
and so
you know if you dream big
and you've got incredible plans
and you're prepared to
you know
that you think you can grow by X amount
you're going to need this
there's your marketing
and here's your plan
here's the cost going to be
you need to be able to back it in
and then you normally get a target on it
and you know we
the way our remuneration works is
you know our bonuses are above the average
and so bonus is really important
but if you're going to go after it
you're going to take a target on it
it's going to impact your
your pocket at the end of the day
whether you're going to get your bonus or not
so
it is a very important concept
so yeah
that was
that's zero-based budgeting
that's what we're known for
but what we haven't been known for
is our marketing
and
that was
when I
I remember
we were in Mexico
we had our global marketing leadership team conference
and
we had this conversation
we were like
I'm sick of being known
as a zero-based budgeting company
a company known for mergers and acquisition
why aren't we renowned as a marketing company
you know
a company that can grow organically top line
because there aren't many more other companies to buy
where we're going to be able to take the synergies
and increase our bottom line
we need to start driving top line growth
and so
there were lots of debates at the time
and we decided
you know what
we want to be the best marketing team in the world
and
we decided
how are we going to measure that
and really the two big measures were like
we want to be known as
the creative marketer of the year at Cannes
which is
you know
probably the
the biggest reward you can get
the biggest award for marketers
in the world
and then
we also want to be the most effective marketing company
in the world
which is
the
the FES index
and so it's been a big five-year journey
and it hasn't
been a fluke
so we've sort of put systems in place
and it really came down
we call it the three P's
so people
sorry for those listening before you
you know
you've just won those awards on a global scale
which is a remarkable achievement
to
put you
you're competing with the Nikes
and
they're the previous winners
sorry before you continue on
yeah
yeah it was
this year
we sort of had all
all-time volume high
so the highest volumes we've ever had
at the company
our brand equity
which we call brand power
is at an all-time high
and
this year
we won
creative marketer of the year
at Cannes
and number one
for the most effective marketing company in the world
so
you talk about dreams
you talk about dreaming big
you know five years ago
we were ranked 42nd
and
we said we wanted to be number one
and people laughed at us
at first
you know
AB InBev
you know your M&A company
and we're like no
we're gonna be the best marketing company in the world
and
credit to the team
that have been involved
Miguel Patricio was our CMO at the time
and
he really led the way
to foster this creativity
across the entire organization
and he put the right people in place
that were modern marketers
and
then we created culture and capabilities team
across all our markets
and then
we put processes in place
so we created like a creative spectrum
the way we talk about the work
from a one to a ten
and we set up like a brain trust
we would have external and internal people
to talk about the work
to make the work better
and then we
sort of overhauled our partners
and we got the best people around us
the best agencies around us
and having those all set up
you know
it wasn't just one country
that was being recognized
we had basically all our countries around the world
being recognized as the best marketers
in the world
which ultimately became the global company
so
it's been something that
I've been privileged to be part of this team
and it's been an incredible journey
great story
all around
we see leaders are curious
and they
have curiosity as a way
that they approach getting better
and learning
and developing
is curiosity a word that resonates with you?
for sure
and
when I think about curiosity
you know it's big for marketers
to be curious
always trying to sort of find that edge
I think one thing about curiosity
is we always always ask the questions
the why
you know
and we don't just ask why once
like why
why
it might not be the fourth or fifth why
until you get
the insight
or the nugget
or the root cause of the problem
that you can then
ideate against
and
come up with plans
that can
you know
create opportunities
so
I think that's quite important
as you work your way down
to what the real problem is
that you're
that you're going up against
and then we're quite fierce on the
problem
rather than
the person
so we
we make sure
we never get personal
we go hard at the problem
and I think
you know
a question we quite often ask ourselves
is like
well why not
you know
if there's a good idea there
why not
let's give it a go
and if it doesn't
it doesn't take a huge amount of resource
you know
it's worth having a go
and we
we talk about this concept of
bullets versus cannonballs
and I think where people make a trap is
they go all in on the cannonball
rather than shooting multiple bullets
calibrating the bullets
and then shooting the cannonball
and
you know
a good example was
we launched a brand Great Northern
just in Queensland
for three years
we calibrated that bullet
before we went national
and shot the cannonball
and now it's
the biggest beer brand in Australia
we did the same with Cubs
we did the same with Carlton Dry
it was like three years in
in Western Australia
where we just shot that bullet
we calibrated it
we had
Kim Sturgio
and Dean Turner at the time
that were right behind NWA
and then we took it nationally
and it's you know
it's top three or third or fourth
biggest brand in Australia
and
I think even the front bar
was a good example
calibrating the bullet
online
afl.com.au
before it went on to the main station
so
a big thing for us is
be curious
test and learn
and
shoot a few bullets
work out what's working
before you go big
it's a great lesson
and it applies to
so many different spaces
I love the way you described that
marketing
communicating with clarity
hand in hand
and it's all about
communication stories
can you give us an insight into how
you think about
your communication
I think communicating with clarity
is critical
and
one thing we
I think about is
how do you
manage
to make the complex simple
and the simple powerful
and
there's always so many
so much data
so many data points
how can you pull out
the right data
to be able to tell
a powerful story
and
I've seen over my career
it's become
more and more important
storytelling
and
the ability to be able to tell
a story
in a simple
but powerful way
and
I actually think it's
what differentiates
a lot of leaders
from middle management
to senior leaders
and as you
when you're presenting
to the executive team
to the board
very smart people
they don't want you waffling on
they want to know
what's the problem
what's your recommendation
and then let's have the debate
and you need to be able to
pinpoint
what the problem is
very quickly
tell your story
give your recommendation
and
I think that's critical
yeah
it's a great
you know
the storytelling aspect of it
isn't it
as you said
without waffling
people pick that up
pretty quickly
but
in a business your size
I suspect
there's not a lot of room
for error
on the way you do that
collaboration we see
is something that leaders
genuinely pursue now
Rich more
than ever
I mean
you're in
over 100 countries
around the world
how important
has collaboration been
collaboration's
very
very important
I've learned over the years
that
it's more about
I
you know
and you're sort of worried about
yourself
and performing
but as you mature
and you become more experienced
you realise it's about we
and you need to play your role
with the rest of the team
if you're going to win
not that dissimilar to
to sport
to corporate
so you start changing
the language
and the tone
it's very much about we
and then as you
get to more senior leaders position
it actually becomes about you
and
you know you can't deliver results
on your own anymore
you have to deliver results
through other people
so it's all about getting the best
out of others
and how can you
better understand these people
give the clear direction
and
you know
global roles in particular
you need strong collaboration
and when you're building
global brands
you want
positioning to be clear
consistent around the world
you want clear creative tracks
you need to be clear on
the do's and the don'ts
so that you can provide a framework
for the local markets
but they have freedom
within that framework
and
you know
World Cup
we just activated over
76 countries
and
you need to have
empathy for the different markets
the different restrictions
that they have
and
you know
often I talk about
to the team
that
you need to have them
the markets
with skin in the game
that's why we set up
steering committees
went for each brand
and
you know
you have a brand
so you have representation
from the different markets
and it's a little bit
it's like a piece of string
when you
you can't push string
on the markets
and
when you try and shove things
down their throat
it's never successful
they've got to pull the string
they've got to pull you in
and
you've got to work together
you know
for it to be successful
to
to really build these global brands
with consistency around the world
yeah
fascinating stories
I mean
you think about that
76 different countries
with all the nuances
and all the restrictions
and regulations
but trying to tell one story
it's a great analogy
isn't it
if you force something on anyone
all the research says that
it's never taken well
isn't it
never succeeds
but
I'm assuming in practice
you've got to live that every day
to get it right
Richard it's a
it's a brilliant insight
it's a fascinating story
but asking these
two questions of everyone
who's been the greatest leader
in your life
that's a
a big question
you know
my parents have had a huge influence
over me
um
if you ask
who's the best leader in our family
it's Rose
100%
um
when I think about
my career
there's been so many people
over the career
that's one thing I
I really feel fortunate
I've had so many great leaders
and
I've tried to pick the best out of
each of the leaders
to try and help shape
the way I lead
um
I mean
the one that comes to mind
it's probably going to sound like
I'm sucking up
but
I know this is a
a global podcast
you probably won't listen to it
but if I
if you will now
I'm very impressed
our CEO at the moment
our CEO
is Michelle Ducaris
and he
he took over
about 18 months ago
and I was always impressed with him
but
he's done a
sensational job
he's come in
and
you know
the first thing he really did
was like set
the vision for the company
and that was
we dream big
which has always been
in our DNA
to create a future
with more cheers
and then
instead of creating like
a three year plan
or a five year plan
he developed
the ten year plan
so he's already looking
ten years out
for the company
and then
you know
structure always follows strategy
so he's put a
you know
a new structure in place
that makes a lot more sense
uh
the way we're now together
as a commercial organisation
and the way he simplified the business
into how we're going to lead
and grow the category
how we're going to digitise
and monetise
the company
and then how we optimise the business
so essentially
how do you pay down debt
what do you do with that money
to drive future growth
and it's just so simple
but everyone understands
the strategy
which
for such a big
complex business
the way he's been able
to simplify
the complexity
and
and with clarity
is
is so powerful
and
he's someone
that
I think we touched about
earlier
with self confidence
you know
he's not arrogant
at all
he's self confident
and everything
every time you're in a meeting
with him
he asks the right questions
he asks tough questions
he sort of leads you down a path
that you know
you normally get the answer
and he has that self confidence
given the experience
and success
he's had over the years
and that conviction
that
you know
you're heading down the right path
and
what's his background
Rich where is he
in the business for
so he's been in the business
for
25 plus years
so he's
you know
a lifer
at AB InBev
you know
across
multiple zones
so Brazil
he's a Brazilian guy
and
had a lot of success
in Brazil
in the early days
then he went and ran
China
and
you know
Michelle
was one of the big reasons
why we've been so successful
in China
with the likes of Budweiser
he really championed
our China business
and then
he went and took on
the big challenge
to run North America
and
for the last
five years
he was running
the US business
and obviously Canada as well
so
he's run our three biggest
zones
he's delivered
amazing results
and he was rewarded
to take on the CEO role
he's just a very
very impressive guy
Rich
we saw you handing
the trophy over
to Harry Kane
recently
so
we know
the level
you're dealing at
but
in the spirit of collaboration
which we love
if you could collaborate
with anyone
on anything
is there
a name
that springs to mind
I'd love to play soccer
with Harry Kane
but
I think from a business perspective
there's a guy who
you might not know
but his name's
Scott Galloway
and
he
is one of the smartest guys
I've ever come across
I've only met him twice
so I don't
I don't really know him
I'm not friends with him
he started a
profit
which is
like a marketing consultancy
that's been very successful
and he mentors a lot of CEOs
and he's got a podcast
that I listen to
yeah
every week
it's on Pivot
it's called Pivot
with Kara Swisher
it's one of the top podcasts
business podcasts in the world
and he's also got the Prof Galloway podcast
and
I learned so much from him
he's
so smart
everything from
you know
he thinks the way CEOs think
he's
gives you an insight
into what the big businesses are going through
what their challenges are
how
he would handle the different situations
he's not a fan of Elon Musk
but he
you know
to tell you the whole story about
what's happening with Twitter
and the impact that's going to have on Tesla
and
he also gets quite caught up in like
the geopolitics of the world
and so he's got a very
you know
very thoughtful view
on the world
and I learned a lot from him
on what's going on in China
versus the different markets
and then how does that
impact
could impact our business
so
very very smart guy
if I ever went into business
yeah
if he took my phone call
yeah I'd love to collaborate with him
The Scott Galloway podcast
is that how you find it?
Yeah
look up Pivot
it's Scott Galloway and Kara Swisher
Pivot
and he's also got his own one
Prof Galloway
but the Pivot one I love
because it's more Kara Swisher interviewing Scott
so you hear more about Scott
his other one
he's interviewing other people
but he's
he's phenomenal
I love it Rich
I know you're on a tight schedule
you're back home with the family
so to take some time out
we really appreciate
it's always great to
to see you mate
I love what you've done
on a global scale
you haven't changed at all
straight back to family
still getting told off
by your brother-in-law
and fronting up to the family Christmas
which is awesome
and thanks again
for being part of a Leader Connect
we're really rapt to have your insight
and leadership as part of that
and long may it continue
no problem Das
it's been great to catch up again
and credit to you and Matt
the Leader Connect
is something I think is really powerful
and it's going to have a big impact
so if people have the chance to be part of it
I highly recommend it
very kind mate
thanks again
thanks Das
Empowering Leaders was presented by me Luke Darcy
produced by Ed Gooden
with sound design by Matt Currie
to start your leadership journey
I encourage you
to go to elitercollective.com
take our Empowering Leaders Indicator Tool
and understand the impact you have
on your environment
join us at Elida
to learn, lead and collaborate