Richard Guida grew up in the tiny sheep and crop farming town of Tamberlup, 290 kilometres
south-east of Perth, from remote country Western Australia.
Richard's life of leadership and success in corporate Australia is a remarkable story.
From 2005 to 2017, Richard was CEO and Managing Director of Wesfarmers, Australia's largest
private employer.
He's currently the Chairman of listed companies Qantas, Woodside Petroleum, Chairman of the
AFL, WA Symphony Orchestra, the Channel 7 Telethon Trust, the Juvenile Diabetes Research
Fund Australia, and former Chair of Australia's B20, a key business advisory to the World
Economic Forum, which includes business leaders from all G20 economies.
Richard, that's a lot on your plate.
It's great to see you.
Thanks for taking the time today.
Great to be with you, Luke.
Appreciate you doing that.
I look at your story of leadership and how you've been in some of the most high-profile
leadership roles in Australian public life.
And from a small sheep farming town in country WA, can you share with us, what do you think
are the traits that have enabled you to be in those positions?
A bit of luck on the way, Luke.
I actually think growing up in the country was a wonderful upbringing.
Mum and Dad were the best farmers in the world, but I saw drought, I saw poor commodity prices,
I saw external factors impacting.
And it built a bit of resilience, I think.
It built a bit of self-reliance.
And so I think that's helped on my journey.
It also actually gave me an ambition not to be a farmer, because I saw that life was challenging
for Mum and Dad.
So I've always been ambitious, still am ambitious, to do things to make change, hopefully for
the better.
And I mentioned life.
But I've had some luck along the way.
I was lucky.
I got a great education at boarding school in Perth.
I was lucky enough to be a Rotary Exchange student way back in 1978 in upstate New York,
and that was important for me in terms of looking at capitalist society, if you like,
in the US.
I had a great tertiary education.
And when I left university, there were more jobs than there were graduates.
So I was able to have a lot of fun at uni.
I met my wife at university.
But I've always been driven, but hopefully with a sense of balance, but a pretty clear
idea of where I wanted to get to.
So that sort of ambition, Richard, at a young age, as you said, great life experiences and
great education, but did you have that focus to get to these sort of roles?
I was silly enough when I was young to tell my friends that I wanted to be Prime Minister
one day, which they continually remind me of.
Thank God for Australia, that never happened.
So yeah, I sort of always wanted to be in a position where I could be a decision maker.
And I love that.
I love being in a position where you make decisions.
Now, the reality is you get some right, you get some wrong.
When you get them right, it's fantastic.
When you get them wrong, you get your head whacked.
But I sort of rather be that than sitting in the background.
Not being that decision maker.
Well, you become CEO of West Farmers 2005.
Speaking of making decisions, it's only two years into your term that you acquire Coles.
It's a $20 billion takeover.
And I think, Richard, correct me if I'm wrong, that's still the biggest corporate takeover
in Australian history.
Is that still the case?
It was at the time.
Probably not now, Luke.
But what was interesting about that from a leadership point of view is, you're right,
I took over in 2005.
In 2006, we had an opportunity to acquire a business.
And I sort of had this...
It's a bit of a naive view on leadership at the time, which was everyone in the team
will march together shoulder to shoulder.
And I sort of worked out through that period that actually leaders have to lead.
And I made a couple of bad calls during that potential acquisition in 2006 because I wasn't
prepared to lead.
I was hoping that everyone would be lockstep.
And so I sort of learned in 2006 that actually as a leader, you have to lead.
So when the Coles opportunity came along in 2007, I sort of determined to myself that
I was going to lead this.
And I was going to...
I basically put everything else aside and got to work on it.
And that was, I think, significant in how we were able to navigate our way through,
which was a very complex time because the first waves of the global financial crisis
started coming through in 2007.
It was a big acquisition for West Farmers.
But what I'd sort of learned in the preceding years helped drive that outcome.
And it was an amazing year.
And following 10 years that I was CEO, it transformed West Farmers.
And Richard, it's interesting to hear you talk about having that chance in 2006, wanting
to get everyone to march with you and talking to a lot of different leaders from different
backgrounds.
We generally feel there's a shift.
There's a shift away from the old school hierarchical leadership into a more collaborative
approach.
We're sitting at the AFL house here this morning, and you look at the senior AFL coaches are
much more collaborative than the predecessors in the past.
But you just said really clearly then, leaders need to lead.
How do you see the change in leadership now?
Well, look, I think it's incredibly important when you're leading an organisation to have
really good people around you.
And it's a real challenge when you've been a peer of those people.
And then you're elevated to be the leader.
And because your expectations and standards or mine certainly changed.
But so I think that's really important.
And having good, diverse voices, whether it's a board, whether it's a management team, is
important.
And more often than not, as a leader, I got great information and the decision was already
made.
But there are times when it's a hard decision.
Often with people, they're really hard decisions or it's a hard, you know, we're going to do
something and we're prepared to put ourselves out to make it.
And that's when I think leaders have to lead.
And I'll often say that to young people, you know, it's definitional in the word, leadership.
You have to lead.
So I would not describe myself as autocratic, far from it.
You know, I'd certainly describe myself as a team player.
I think you're right about coaches.
I think you're right about leaders.
Generally.
But I still think the best leaders in their own way lead.
And I look at Mandela.
I look at people like Gail Kelly, who I think was a phenomenal corporate leader in Australia.
I look at some of the political leaders who have made a big difference and can look back
on their term and say, we got things done.
And it's because they were prepared to be held accountable for making decisions that
they led on.
So you think the balance is there where you can...
You can still give everyone a voice.
You can still listen to people.
You can still be collaborative.
Yeah.
But ultimately, if a hard call comes, you need to own it as a leader.
Is that...?
Yeah.
And so I'll try and give a reasonably quick example.
During Coles, as I said, the first ripples of the global financial crisis started coming
through.
And that changed what we were planning to do.
We were planning to do a joint venture with private equity to acquire a number of the
businesses in the Coles group, including Coles and the...
Supermarket and Coles Liquor.
And then their ability to fund it fell away because of tightening of liquidity.
The private equity groups bought out?
Yeah.
So I went for a run, plod, in Perth.
And I came back and I asked one of our guys to run some numbers on what it would look
like if we're doing it on our own.
And unsurprisingly, the numbers were good.
Because the debt that Westfarmers could source was cheaper than the debt that private equity
partners could source.
And so I went to the board the next day and said, I think we should still do this.
And here's what the numbers look like.
And that was the brave call, if you like.
There were two brave calls.
One was to spend a couple of billion dollars buying equity in Coles and that early on.
And then going ahead on our own.
Because we could have pulled back at that stage.
But I'm glad we didn't.
So sometimes you've just got to make a call.
And when they work out like that, it's probably a career-defining moment in lots of ways.
It goes the other way.
You're probably not sitting here in a lot of different roles, potentially, which is...
100%.
My wife, Janine, said to me, because there was a lot of media on all this, and early
on there were lots of doubts.
There's always doubters.
And you know that from where you are now on everything.
And she said to me one stage, why did you do this?
I said, well, you know...
People said you're putting Westfarmers at risk.
I was never going to put Westfarmers at risk.
I said, just put my job at risk for a period of time.
We could handle that.
I'm always interested in people who do great things over a sustained period of time.
What daily routines and hacks to get through?
I mean, you hear it's the AFL season launch.
There's so many balls in the air in your world.
What do you do day-to-day to keep you healthy and successful?
I'm an incredibly supportive life partner.
So, you know, Janine and I have been sort of great best friends almost since my first
year of university and married for, I don't know, we're coming up 40 years soon.
So that's been a great help for great kids.
And so I think I've been able to have an appropriate balance of focusing on family
and prioritising that at times.
I've tried to...
I've tried to remain reasonably fit because I don't think you're any good to anyone if
you're not and if you're not healthy.
And I've had pretty good mentors.
I've had great mentors actually through my life who've from time to time corrected the
course I was on, you know, when I was too focused on one thing and not focused on another.
And a healthy...
I'm not bad.
I take my roles seriously.
I try not to take myself too seriously, Luke.
And so I...
Hopefully people would say when they talk about me that I'm not high ego.
I mean, I think if you want to be an ASX company CEO, you've got to have a degree of self-belief
and so that implies ego.
But hopefully people would say he's pretty balanced and he's relatively low ego.
And I actually...
I'm not worried about what people say about me.
I worry a lot about what they say about the organisations I'm involved in and that probably.
sort of helps me a bit as well.
You mentioned some mentors along the way.
Can you share a few names and their impact?
Is that...
I work for a guy, Michael Chaney at West Pharmacy.
He's my predecessor's CEO.
And Michael's been a friend and mentor for a long period of time.
You know, really good values and some guidance early on in my career about just making the
right call on ethics.
Because on integrity, it's not...
Luke, it's not black and white.
You know...
You know that.
And I always say now to people, if it's a shade of grey, fall on the right side.
Don't...
And I think Michael was...
Gave me great direction on that.
I was very lucky through my time as CEO of West Pharmacy.
I had a mentor, a guy called Chris Bartlett, who was a Harvard School professor.
Chris grew up in Queensland.
He was a King's Cup rower.
He was a good rugby player.
He was at McKinsey and Alcoa, I think, and ended up as a professor at Harvard Business School.
And Chris and I would...
We'd speak either face-to-face or on the phone every two weeks.
And he was a true mentor.
And he was the one person I could have the very, very blunt conversations with.
And there were two-way conversations.
And he would say things to me like, Richard, our last six calls, you've raised this as
an issue.
When are you going to do something about it?
Sort of stuff, you know.
So I had a person in Chris who was just an incredible sounding board through my time
as CEO.
Because leadership can be lonely, Luke.
And everyone says it.
And early on in my tenure as CEO of West Farmers, I thought, oh, no, it's not...
You know, this is great.
And then after a while, you think, oh, no.
There are times when you are on your own.
You know, people come in, you should do this, you should do that.
And they close the door and walk out.
And you've sort of got to think, well, what are we going to do?
And so having a sounding board was great.
And I talked earlier, Gail Kelly, she took over Westpac at a similar time I took over
West Farmers.
I always had a great relationship with Gail.
You know, she's...
Mother of triplets and a female major bank CEO in Australia was just, you know, I think
is an incredible person.
And so people like that, you can pick up the phone and talk to her, always really valuable.
It sounds like you're smart enough to formalise that, you know, the Harvard business professor
to make that something you did as a routine.
Sounds like a really smart thing.
Richard, if there's one criticism that you hear about you, it's maybe that you don't
have a big public presence in the high profile.
Chairman?
Right?
And it's hard to get access to you.
And is that part because of, you know, the CEOs that you work with, Alan Joyce at Qantas
and Gil McLaughlin at the AFL, Meg O'Neill at Woodside, you allow them, you empower them
to do their job.
Is that your natural style or have you sort of adapted it because, hey, I've got really
capable people in those roles and I'm happy to take a back seat?
It's a bit of both, Luke.
So it's more my natural style.
I mean, I hate opening a newspaper and seeing a photo.
So maybe that's the farm boy bit in me.
I don't know how you go with that.
But I'm pretty clear on the difference between executive and non-executive roles.
And so I had three great chairs when I was at West Farmers, Trevor Eastwood, Bob Avery
and then Michael Chaney.
And they gave me the scope to be the CEO, to be the face.
That's when required of West Farmers.
And they were supportive in the background.
They were challenging when they needed to be, critical if they needed to be, but incredibly
supportive and also focused on the long term.
So I think I saw three very good role models as chair.
And I'm, you know, I'm non-executive chair.
I'm non-executive.
And Gil runs the AFL.
And the commission is, which is, I think, a brilliant structure.
The commission.
It looks at the strategies Gil and the team sets.
We hire and fire the CEO.
There's things we do as non-executives.
But we don't run the AFL day to day.
And I don't run Qantas.
And although I get people ringing me up saying, where's my bag?
And Alan Joyce is an enormously capable CEO, as is Gil.
And one of the joys in my life for the last two years is seeing Meg O'Neill move into a leadership role at Woodside.
And then blossom as a leader.
And, you know, through her first time, we talked about Coles with me.
Woodside merged with BHP Petroleum Assets last year, which was similar size, massive.
You know, I think $16, $17, $18 billion.
It doesn't matter.
Big, big merger.
And Meg led that very early on in her tenure.
And I think she's already seen as a very, very, very highly capable CEO.
She's got terrific relationships with government and industry.
And it's been a joy for me to see her grow.
And, look, there's a bit.
I've had that.
I've done that.
And I don't seek the limelight.
I seek the AFL to be as good as it can be, Qantas to be as good as it can be, and Woodside to be as good as it can be.
And hopefully I can play a role in that.
But I know that I'm not the day-to-day person running it.
I know I get held accountable when we make mistakes.
And that's fine.
Richard, I want to talk about, you know, living in WA, you've come at a period of time where Western Australia was effectively cut off from the rest of the world for two years.
And towards the end, you made some pretty strong statements around not being sustainable.
If we look back, did we learn anything from the leadership in that time with a little bit of reflection there?
Oh, look, I could talk all day about that.
Actually, to its credit, the Western Australian Government's doing a review of its policies in COVID.
And I hope.
As a nation, we do a proper review of that.
And so I'll be pretty blunt in my input to the Western Australian Government.
I felt, yeah, I said a lot through those two or three years that leaders lead.
I think Gil McLaughlin and Alan Joyce did phenomenal jobs through the most challenging period.
They had great teams around them.
And they'd be the first to say that.
But for Qantas to survive COVID, for the AFL, frankly, to survive COVID.
To give the delight to our supporters that we did was pretty amazing.
I think we lost balance on risk management through COVID.
And early on, it was really difficult because no one knew where it was going.
But after a while, once a vaccine was developed and protocols were developed, it was, I think, far more manageable.
I think there were people like Gladys Berejiklian.
I absolutely canned by some people.
And yet I'd look back and say that that was a better way of treating people.
Because I reckon we just lost some of our humanity through COVID.
And I think it was all based on one thing.
And, look, if you took the same zero-risk approach that Western Australian Government apparently took
or appeared to take through that period, no one would drive vehicles anymore.
Or if we did, we'd drive at five kilometres per hour.
And you wouldn't play football.
Qantas would never fly an aeroplane.
Because, you know, there's always a tiny – you know, you just minimise the risk.
So I think we got that wrong.
Hopefully we can get it sorted.
You know, Australia was relatively better off than the rest of the world.
I think we're lucky in a broad context with the leadership we had.
I just think we lost a bit of humanity through that period.
And we lost perspective on where it was all at.
And I think it was really powerful to have senior people with influence like you,
you know, question that narrative because, you know,
it was an event that we hadn't experienced before.
And I think your words are really profound.
You know, we did lose humanity.
It was a pretty rough couple of years around the world.
But, you know, even here in Melbourne, we took kids out of school for two years.
We, you know, I looked – you're lucky to live in an expansive house.
I looked at people in the commission flats who couldn't get out with four or five –
there was some cruelty that went on that's got lasting consequences.
And if we don't have these conversations in leadership,
how are you going to learn next time?
Yeah, we need to.
And we all – I mean, I've made plenty of mistakes, Luke.
And we – I often thought about those people in the housing commission
where English is second language and those kids miss two years of school.
What's the impact going to be in 10 or 20 years' time?
And we had – we had two children in Melbourne, a daughter here most of the time.
And at one stage, you know, and she'd planned to get married, I think, in 21.
In Perth, that got cancelled because borders got closed.
And she – I don't know.
I don't know.
And she was lucky.
She had a partner and the two of them were happy together.
But her mental health suffered like many people in Victoria.
And at one stage, I said to Janine, you might have to go to Melbourne.
And I'm not sure when I'll see you again because you're not going to be allowed back to Perth.
But you might have to go to look after our daughter.
And they're cruel decisions.
And, you know, there were people who weren't able to fly interstate to see dying relatives.
There were people who weren't able to be in the same room as their husband
or father or mother dying or weren't able to go and pick up bodies.
And there was some crazy stuff.
And hopefully, as you say, we can have a sensible conversation about how we do it better next time.
I want to ask you about this sort of cancelled culture world we live in now.
I love you saying openly you make mistakes.
We all do.
It's part of how you grow.
Hopefully, you don't make them, you know, two in a row, particularly some of the big decisions you make.
But we want to try and encourage – are you concerned, particularly in the –
we like to attack Qantas and we like to attack the AFL
and it doesn't seem to be that good-natured capacity to slip up occasionally.
Excuse me, is that a concern for you?
Yeah, it is.
And you've put it well, Luke, because, I mean, there's more instant feedback on this stuff now.
And it's quite personal.
So I've actually pulled back from social media a bit because,
it'd just kill you if you took seriously what people say about you.
I don't know if you – where you're at on – because you'd get plenty of feedback as well.
Well, I share this story, Richard.
I'm sorry to jump in, but Luke Hodger, you know well, and he – I've told this story.
He doesn't mind me telling it.
One of the greats of our game, a Colac boy, not the similar background to you,
but as iconic a leader as we've got in our game.
I did one of the first games in commentary with Hodgie and second game he'd done it.
So you're learning and you're nervous and at halftime,
he went to check his phone to see how the kids were going and he scrolled onto social media
and he showed me some of the stuff that – I'm going, if Luke Hodger's copying, you know,
you are an idiot, you can't speak, you can't – I just was dumbfounded.
And it knocked Luke Hodger out.
It knocked him around in the second half.
And I think, God, if someone with that level of resilience is susceptible,
what are our teenage kids going to be able to cope with?
It's crazy.
Yeah, and in a high-profile role, it's like Gil McLaughlin.
He at the AFL or Alan Joyce.
I mean, Alan Joyce and his partner Shane bought a house in Sydney
and it got eggs thrown at it and toilet paper and, you know, vandalised.
Now, Alan's – at the end of the day, Alan is a great guy.
He's been a superb leader of Qantas.
Do we get everything right?
No, but is Qantas as good as any airline in the world in my view?
Yes.
And did we get through COVID?
We did amazingly well, yes.
And I don't think we cut people any slack these days.
And politically, you know, you'd ask the question,
why would you be in politics these days given what they cop?
I remember Gil saying to me one day, you know,
even for the most popular decisions we make at the AFL,
there's still people who hate it.
And they express that hate.
Look, it's really interesting.
I think we've sort of got to get the balance slightly better
than we've currently got at the moment.
And so I've done a couple of speeches at graduation ceremonies
at universities and things in recent years.
And I say – I try and say it in a positive way.
I say to these unbelievably well-educated kids who are going to be our leaders
going forward, if you want to make change, make change.
But having an opinion on social media is not –
you're not the one making –
you're far better off being the one criticised who's made the change
than being some anonymous person on social media having a go.
And in my view, that's what –
we should be applauding the people who are actually doing stuff
and recognising from time to time we get it wrong.
You know, we were talking about West Farmers earlier and Coles
and things like that.
Look, if the West Farmers Board had acted like –
social media does this way,
I would have been fired 15 times in my 12-year tenure.
But they took a view, which I'm forever grateful,
that I'd learn from mistakes.
I'd hopefully grow as a person and grow as a CEO.
And they also took a long-term view.
And they knew that we'd make mistakes from time to time.
But hopefully, as you said earlier, we get more right than wrong.
And you actually – you know, you come out – you're ahead of the game.
You're a winner.
But if –
if I reacted to every time someone said I need to make a change at Qantas
or, you know – everyone loves Gill, obviously.
But, you know, I tell you, it would just be a –
you know, we'd be rotating through people and things like that.
So we've got to – I think we've got to get better at it.
And I'm going to be – I'm now 63, Luke.
You know, I've got a Woodside AGM coming up soon.
I'm going to have people coming along with the AGM
saying you're not doing enough on climate change.
There's – there'll be some who are legitimate,
will have a very good, healthy debate.
There's some who just don't want us to be in business.
My response to that is fine, but that's not my job.
My job's not actually to – my job's actually to make Woodside as good as it can be.
Yeah.
And your agenda is to get us out of this business.
There's no point in us talking.
There's no conversation.
Yeah.
So what – sitting back at that stage of your life, you said 63,
someone that's listening to this and about to start an entrepreneurial journey
or whatever passion they've got, what advice would you give?
I reckon that word passion is really important.
I think you've got to love what you do.
And so I would say for almost every day of my working life,
I've jumped out of bed in the morning wanting to get to work and wanting to do things.
There was one period where I worked for someone who I lost respect for
and I didn't enjoy.
I didn't enjoy it at all.
And so I made a change because I couldn't deal with it.
Left the organisation?
It wasn't quite like that.
Basically, I said I was going to leave the organisation and they went,
oh, is there a problem here?
And they worked it out.
Yeah.
But that was a brief period in my entire career.
Otherwise, you know, I jumped out of bed this morning.
I thought, this is going to be great today.
I'm looking forward to seeing you.
Gil and I are going to do a walk around Marvel Stadium in a minute,
which will be interesting to see where that's at.
I've got to –
We've got a Telethon Trust meeting later today.
We raised over $70 million for kids' health in Western Australia last year.
So I'm passionate about it.
And I say to our kids and to others who listen to me,
you're going to be working for a long time.
Make sure you enjoy it and work with good people.
Yeah.
And be proud that you can do something and make a contribution.
One of the reasons I love AFL is because of what we do.
We do it in the communities.
And you talked about Tamblup.
And I used to go on a Sunday with Mum and Dad and drive the car
and we'd back it up against the fence and watch.
In those days in Tamblup, the Farmers and the Williams,
you know, Geoffrey's father and the Williams play footy.
And we've got a holiday house down on the south coast of WA,
a little fishing town called Augusta.
And the Augusta Abalones kicked off again two or three years ago.
And they play about –
They play about ten games a year, five games at home.
And it's just so brilliant because the whole community comes to watch
the Abalones play local teams in footy.
So I just think we do great stuff in the AFL.
And if you can be part of that as an organisation, that's quite fulfilling.
What a brilliant name for a team.
The Abalones.
I'd like to see them play one day.
They'd love you.
You should come play with them.
Well, they haven't seen me lately, Richard.
I'm not sure if I can help the Abalones too much.
But it's true.
Before we hit record, all we wanted to talk about was who did you tip this week
and where are you going to be tonight.
And you can see that passion comes out.
Well, the Abalones, the coach is the local Tyler.
The runner is the local gas, Rob Gossie, the local gas guy.
The first aid lady is the local IGA checkout woman.
It's the whole community.
You know, I'm sure the police.
Breath test people on the way in.
And then go.
You know, because it's just, it's one of those, it's, you know,
it's what footy does, which I think is bring communities together.
And that's why I love the involvement of the AFL.
We love going and seeing the elite men and women.
And, you know, you're lucky enough to have played
and been a very good player at that level and would have met amazing people.
But footy's big in the community.
And if you haven't been to a country footy game and, you know,
I lived in a place called Roxby Downs in Central Australia
and to see what it does or to go up to the Tiwi Islands
and watch a Tiwi grandfire.
Oh, if you can't get joy out of what footy does in that space,
it's hard not to.
I know you want to finish, but a few years ago I went up to the Kimberley
as a West Farmers team, but with another group,
just looking at Indigenous disadvantage and issues.
And we went to this little remote town in the East Kimberley.
I think it was called Ring of Soak.
And Colin Carter, and you know Colin,
an AFL commissioner, chairman of Geelong, was on the trip.
And he was a director of West Farmers at the time.
And this local community that we flew into had heard
that this Geelong person was coming.
So they all expected a Geelong AFL player.
Gary Avlett was coming.
And Colin rolled up and, you know, Colin carrying a bit of weight,
less hair than me.
But they were all incredibly passionate.
And this oval.
Was, and we've all seen photos, but this oval was a dirt and stone oval
with a tree at centre half forward.
But footy was sort of their life on a weekend.
So you're right.
Great privilege of our club chaplain in my era used to run a red dust role models
and take us as players out to remote communities and you'd stay out for a week.
Literally forged these relationships where you could come back
and someone would take your name, you know, and you'd come back
and you'd meet Luke Darcy.
Two years later and just say, that's my name.
It's not my name now.
It's, you can't describe, you know, the joy of, there was a,
I had a great teammate, Matthew Croft.
It wasn't at my high profile, but they loved Matthew Croft.
There was a couple of Matthew Crofts running around
in the Tiwi Islands there at one stage.
I'm not sure if there's a Colin Carter.
Hey, Richard, so I had a great privilege of sitting down.
I love these conversations.
You learn so much from them and see these sort of key common traits
around different leadership positions.
I was keen to ask you about them and fascinated to get your response.
And we think it's hard to lead anyone else unless you have a sense
of self-leadership.
Does that resonate with you?
Yeah, yeah, it does.
And I think that goes to your values.
It goes to your own sort of compass, personal compass.
And I've always said if you're not prepared to do it yourself,
you certainly can't ask anyone else to do it.
So, yeah, it does resonate, yeah.
We think our leaders are really, modern leaders are really conscious
about every moment.
And having a positive impact on whatever environment they're in,
is that something you think of?
Yeah, it's interesting.
One of the things I've always tried to do, Luke, is be positive
even when things were terribly difficult.
And sometimes they are.
And there was a, you know, when I was looking to retire
as CEO of West Farmers, there were some internal candidates.
And one of the internal candidates and I had a terrific conversation
and this person is someone I really admire and respect.
But there were times when that person was not able to put a front on,
which is actually we're going to work this through,
we're going to be positive.
And you can't have a leader come into a place like the AFL or whatever
just like the world's going to fall over because that impacts everyone.
So I think you've got...
You can't internalise all the issues because if you do,
you're not going to solve them.
The best way of solving issues is to make sure your team's aware of them
and you're bored or whatever.
But I think as a leader, you have to have a positive.
You have to be able to say, we're going to work our way through this.
It might take us a bit of time and it might be hard,
but we're going to work our way through it.
And that's why Gil's leadership through COVID
and Alan Joyce's leadership through COVID was so powerful.
I think because Alan said,
Qantas was six weeks away from insolvency basically,
but tough decisions, really tough decisions,
but people respecting that because there was an optimism
that we'd get through it.
And jumping off on this topic, I hadn't planned to do it,
but Gil was incredibly, always is when you see him
and remarkable effort for the whole AFL and Gil in particular
and his team through commissioning.
You're in the process.
You're in the process of the replacement challenge.
That creates a level of angst in a game like footy.
We all want the answer and everyone wants to know.
Everyone wants a timeline, Richard.
How are you handling that situation?
And obviously it's really capable people in this building we're here with now.
How do you handle that?
Well, actually, I'm loving it, Luke, to be honest.
I mean, because I think the reality with Gil is he made an announcement
in where it was April last year saying he would finish up
at the end of last year.
And then the Hawthorne.
And then the Hawthorne was getting lobbed on us.
And, you know, we, Gil and I, got a terrific relationship
and we just felt inappropriate for him to go at that time.
And don't forget, last year we're still sort of getting through COVID
and restrictions and a whole lot of things like that.
So we're in good shape.
I'm enjoying.
Why are you loving it?
Because I'm having, I'm spending time talking about pretty important stuff
with really good people.
Yeah.
Fellow commissioners.
Also, you talked about people in this place at AFL House,
people outside of AFL House.
There's some really interesting people whose names have come up
that I've been able to have one-on-one conversations with
and then conversations with the commission.
And it's, I really enjoy it.
And it's arguably the most important thing we'll do as a commission
is to appoint a CEO.
So, you know, I'm going to make sure we get it right.
And people said, oh, you took too long to appoint a CEO.
Woodside, Meg was acting CEO for four months.
We went through a process which was really challenging
because of COVID travel restrictions at the time.
We made the right call.
And if we make the right call, I'm happy.
And I'll wear the flack on the way through.
You've got a big smile on your face.
Does it run the risk that those that are in the team,
that there's a distress level for others as can?
Is that a potential negative that it looks as though maybe, you know,
you haven't got people.
It can fill the role.
Has that become challenging?
Well, hopefully the candidates have all had enough feedback from me
and others on where the process is at.
Yeah, there's, as you know, last year we did media rights.
As I said, the Hawthorne thing,
there's a few things on the go at the moment.
Tasmania is not unimportant for the AFL, I think.
And Gil's doing a stupendous job on that
because it's not just negotiations with the Tasmanian and federal governments.
It's working with the 18 clubs as well.
And, you know, we'll see whether we can land Tasmania.
If we can, it's a big deal for the AFL.
So there's a few things going on that I think are more appropriately handled
while he's still in the seat.
And Gil's been amazing in that I've got no doubt his phone's been ringing,
but his commitment to the AFL is, and, you know, no one has seen,
if anything, we've just seen a more engaged, more fired up CEO,
not someone who's looking to exit stage left at the moment.
And you don't have to be a cheerleader.
The record of Gil and the rights and the AFL's health
and coming through that speaks for itself.
And I think everyone in our industry can't be anything apart from universally
admiring the role that Gil's played.
And, you know, I love that you're enjoying the time.
I find that interesting.
We see, you know, in a lot of the roles you're in,
leaders are really conscious of how they share the vision
for what they want to do.
How do you go about that in the various roles that you've got,
creating and sharing a vision?
So I reckon it's different as a CEO than as a non-executive.
I love being chair because I think you've got more influence as a chair,
obviously, than you do purely as a non-executive.
And so in my view, the vision of the AFL is something for Gil
and the team to come up with.
For the commission to critique and hopefully critique maybe help make better
but then come behind and support.
And the same with, you know, listed companies and the like.
I think, though, having clarity of direction is incredibly important, Luke.
And as a leader, one of the reasons I said Michael Chaney was a great mentor
was I was always very clear with what Michael wanted from me
as someone working for him.
So hopefully the people...
The people who work for me, either as executives when I was a CEO
or now as CEOs, are really clear.
And the first thing is integrity is non-negotiable.
You know, we're not compromised on that.
If you're a listed company, then it's pretty clear that you're looking
to create value for your stakeholders, including your shareholders.
And for the AFL, you know, we have a vision that we all jump
in behind and you and I, the way...
The conversation we've just had basically goes to that vision
about how we make the game better and inclusive for all Australians.
So...
But that clarity...
So you have to be clear in your own mind about where you're going, I think,
and then being clear, making sure that others are clear are important.
And the bit on integrity is, I think, really important.
Holding people accountable.
I think that's really important for results, good and bad.
But as I think I said earlier, I don't worry what people say about me.
Although if they question my integrity, I'd worry about that.
But I do worry about what they say about the organisations.
And I hate the integrity of organisations I'm involved in to be attacked.
And so they're things that, to me, become not negotiable.
And I think I heard you in a very similar vein, just saying we're going
to have lots of debates.
And...
And lots of blues, and you can disagree, but integrity stands alone.
And a question on that, that's a separate conversation.
And, yeah, it makes sense, yeah.
And it's one of the interesting dynamics about, I think,
a management team, Luke, and a board, is you actually want lively debate.
You want diversity of views around a table.
Because you'll get better outcomes with it.
But when you leave, you've got to have a unified voice.
And if you don't...
If people play politics, that can be very destructive in an organisation.
And so I think how you manage boards around confidentiality,
but having that openness, and your own management teams as well,
I think becomes really important.
And, you know, there should be a diversity of views,
but eventually you should come to a landing.
And once you've come to a landing...
And if you can't live with that, go and do something.
Then you're out.
Go and do something else.
So I'm bored.
Even if you disagree, eventually you have to come to a united front.
And without that, there's no harmony, yeah.
And one of the challenges of being a chair or a CEO
is getting to that position without compromising on every front.
Because sometimes you think,
geez, do we actually make a decision here or not?
So anyway, it's one of the challenges.
Richard, we see leaders are really curious people.
And curiosity is a way that they launch into their own self-improvement and development.
Does that word resonate?
Does that resonate with you, curiosity?
Curiosity, yeah, you know, sort of deep scanning.
I can't help myself but be looking at what's going on around the place,
whether that's economically, whether that's politically, whether the whole...
So I'm curious.
I have a view on a lot of things.
I have to hold myself back sometimes.
I've made the mistake plenty of times in my life thinking I'm right
and something worked out that I wasn't.
And that's why it's really good to have people around you
who can have a different view.
But yeah, I think the world's in a really interesting place at the moment.
I've got four kids, first grandchild now.
So I want the world to be a good place for them to be in.
And so I'm really interested in stuff.
Sometimes I think, no, let it go, let others deal with it,
and I'll go up to the farm and run around the sheep or something.
But there's others.
I just can't help myself.
And I have to pick up the phone and ring someone and say,
are they serious about this?
Are we doing this?
So yeah, I'm...
So you hold yourself back on purpose, do you?
Sometimes.
Yeah, because you just think it's not worth it or...?
Yeah, sometimes because I think actually they don't know.
Someone doesn't need to hear from me on this.
So yeah, I'm probably a bit better than I was five or ten years ago.
But have you picked up the phone and thought,
you know, I can probably reach people that others can't?
And have you done that from time to time as well on an issue?
That you care about?
Yeah, I have.
And hopefully I don't abuse that.
So hopefully people respect it.
Yeah, and I'm lucky and I've got a really good network of contacts
and I've got people who reach out to me from time to time as well.
So that's fine.
But one of the key things is I listen to my kids a lot.
You know, they're great kids.
And I think sometimes you've got to make sure you look in the mirror
and say, who are you?
And do you really understand some of the stuff that's going on
and that's important?
So, yeah.
Which is a great parenting skill, isn't it?
As you get all your great teachers are there right in front of you.
I know I get plenty of feedback from my floor as well, Richard,
whether I like it or not.
Communicating with clarity is another dimension of leadership.
We see people in roles like yours are very clear on their communication.
How have you gone about that?
Well, yeah, I think I've, you know, there's been a journey, Luke.
I've learned to be a bit more direct with people without,
hopefully without being sort of rude and impolite.
But so I can have very direct conversations with people with, you know,
whether it's Alan or Gil or Meg or directors because I think that clarity
is important.
And do I enjoy sitting down with someone and say,
I think you did a really rubbish job?
No.
You know, I don't know who enjoys that stuff.
But have I learned to sit down and say, actually, you know,
you could have done that better and these are what I think you should have done.
I think I'm a lot better at that now than I was 20 years ago.
And it's a skill I think you sort of have to develop.
But also, you know, I've also, I've had feedback along the way that people
felt they weren't getting enough feedback from me.
And I was shocked when I got that feedback.
I thought, oh, gee, I'm pretty good at that.
And then I reflected on it and said, actually, no, I'm not.
I'm bloody hopeless at it in the circumstances I was talking about.
So, yeah, hopefully I'm a bit better.
It also comes with relationships, I think.
Once you build trust with someone, you can have that much more direct conversation.
Well, you really see that shift to collaboration.
How important has collaboration been for you?
As a leader?
Well, there's nothing better, I think, as a leadership team
in agreeing something and then making it happen.
Early on in my schoolboy life, I rode.
I wasn't a great rower.
My brother was a much better rower than me.
But I rode because I got better food at the boarding school.
But those moments in an eight when everything comes together,
I don't know if you ever rode,
but those moments when everything clicks and you're at one,
is one of those magic, magic moments.
I keep sort of thinking about that sometimes in corporate life.
So the best times in my corporate life were in an office with a whole team
working on a difficult issue, whether it was an acquisition
or just a challenge in the business and working our way through it
and coming out, that is so good.
And particularly when the best ideas come from the most unlikely source.
And I love that sort of stuff.
I love that sort of teamwork, collaboration.
Yeah, it's great.
Yeah, and I love hearing you say that.
The rowing analogy, I didn't know nothing about,
but my daughter, I've had this great joy of watching her.
I have a proud dad moment here for a moment, Richard,
but they competed over in Henley last year.
And it's the ultimate team sport, isn't it?
In an eight, they had this incredible success and won over in Henley.
And you're thinking,
one person puts that oar in the wrong spot once, and it's unlikely.
And you look at the crew and you think,
God, that doesn't look like they should go fast.
But sometimes when it works, there's magic in it, isn't it?
And you actually know when you're in a crew, you can see the puddles.
So you know who's working and you know who's not.
You can.
And we've all been there.
We've all been not on our game.
Yeah.
And you know, yeah.
And you know when you're not on your game.
But when it all clicks, it's pretty magic.
Yeah.
I can't help it, you know, that poor Olympic moment,
which we'll never forget, and I shouldn't bring it up,
but thinking of the Olympic final in a team situation like that,
where clearly you couldn't go on.
But, you know, that would stay with you for a long time, I'm assuming.
Two final questions.
Richard, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Oh, I think Mandela's the –
you know, and I think he's –
what he did, what he went through, his humility,
his clarity when, you know, after years of being locked up.
I was lucky enough to see him at Harvard back in 98 when I was over there,
and it was one of those literally spine-chilling moments,
and it was with a whole bunch of other students at Harvard.
Did he come and do a guest lecture?
He was given an award, which I think only previously had been given to Churchill
and one other – it might have been FDA –
one other – so the third time ever that this award had been given.
And it was at Harvard Square, and, you know, I was –
at the time in 98, I was, what, 38, but there's all these Harvard students,
and it was just unbelievable to be sort of in the distance, but in his presence.
I just think as a leader, he –
he exhibited the things that you'd want to see, as I said,
humility, grace, direction, compassion.
Amazing.
Yeah.
I think we're about to get wound up in the Brownlow room here at the AFL.
I think our meeting's about to expire.
One final question.
It's handy when you've got the chairman here.
I'll get my final question away before we get to –
in the spirit of collaboration, I love – you know, I read out the start.
You're raising money for juvenile diabetes research.
The Western Australian Telethon is iconic in what it's done.
All your passions.
If you could collaborate with anyone, maybe Mandela might be the answer.
Is there anyone that you thought, if I could collaborate with someone,
that would be it?
Like, such a – you know, I love doing the work here with Gil and the team
and in other places.
I'm a massive admirer of Barack Obama, and I met him at the time of the Australian G20
in –
in 2014 when I was running the B20.
And he's a farm boy from Tambalup sitting next to him
and having a conversation with the President of the United States,
which was pretty surreal for me.
And I had a genuinely good conversation with him.
And he invited me to the White House, but, you know, subsequently,
there's no way he can get through all those bloody protocols.
But I'd love – I'd love to work with him on something
because I just think he's an outstanding person.
You know, not without his faults, and I've read his books.
I don't know if you've read his books.
And, yeah, he – but I'd love to do something with him
because I reckon he'd get some stuff done.
And just the class and the humility, the way he's handed himself post his time as President.
See, I mean, you speak about he must have wanted to pick up the phone from time to time.
He hasn't spoken out, has he?
He's just – he's – talk about values and integrity there at the top of the tree, aren't they, Richard?
It's been a class act.
This is a hugely busy time.
I think every day is a busy time.
I appreciate you taking –
some time to spend with me, and good luck for a big year.
Pleasure, Luke.
Yeah.
Thanks again.
And go the doggies.
Yeah, thanks.
Thank you for listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast,
powered by Temper, a mattress like no other.
And to make sure you don't miss an episode, click subscribe wherever you get your podcasts.