The legendary footballer and pundit Rio Ferdinand
is today's guest on the Empowering Leaders podcast.
He's passionate about leading by example,
honest about the journey he's taken to become a better communicator,
especially on the home front,
and has some incredible insights to share
about harnessing the power of your competitive spirit.
He also talks candidly about his relationships
with the great Sir Alex Ferguson
and quite possibly the most famous person,
not just player in the world, Cristiano Ronaldo.
He has a huge intelligence and an appetite to evolve
and to be curious, where are the margins at
in terms of researching sleep, researching physiotherapy,
researching setting the ambience in a room with crystals.
He does mad stuff, talking to NASA about recovery.
There ain't many players that are doing that, if any.
Rio Ferdinand epitomises everything that we do at Alita
and it has been a great privilege for us to have Rio collaborate
in our Alita Connect program.
We curate groups of five to six people from around the globe
to come to Alita Connect.
We come together to learn, to share and to collaborate.
You can head to alitacollective.com
and we would love to chat to you
or book a discovery call today.
Big thanks as always to Jason Nicholas
and his team from Temper Bedding,
the best mattress in the world, NASA approved.
We know great leaders like Rio Ferdinand value sleep
and investing in a mattress like Temper
is a decision you won't regret.
Rio Ferdinand is a legend of English football,
former England captain and represented his country
on 81 occasions, including being part
of three FIFA World Cup competitions.
He's one of the most decorated English footballers of all time
and regarded as one of England's greatest ever players.
He's an English football and Premier League Hall of Famer
who captained Manchester United
to a Champions League final victory in 2008,
one of 14 trophies he won
across an extraordinary professional career.
Rio is an officer of the Order of the British Empire
for his services to football
and his incredible contribution
in the Rio Ferdinand Foundation
addressing the issues of inequality Rio experienced
growing up in England.
Rio is a respected broadcaster,
documentary filmmaker,
start-up investor in We Are 8,
a social media platform for good,
a father of five and respected
for his leadership qualities from a young age.
Rio, it's great to catch up with you.
Thanks for taking the time.
It's an extraordinary life that you've led
and look back at your professional career,
captaining Manchester United,
captaining England.
When I read that back to you,
what are the thoughts on when you reflect back on your career?
Yeah, satisfaction I think is the most important thing.
I think you set out,
in a career,
whatever industry it is,
you set out to kind of do well
and fulfil potential
and to gain the respect of people
that are in your industry
but also outside if that's possible.
And I remember when I signed for Man United,
I think in my press conference,
that's what I said.
I said, if I can leave this club
when I walk out the doors,
as long as I've etched my name
in the fabric of the club in a good way,
which will mean having to win some stuff,
then I would see that
as being a success
and I'd like to think that I've probably done that.
You're 23 years of age
and you were named as captain of Leeds.
You go on, as I said,
to captain England,
captain of the famous Manchester United.
What were the traits, do you think,
that people saw in you
to have you as a leader at such a young age?
I think the fact that I could communicate
would probably be one of my strongest points.
I think communication is something
that's enabled me to have an afterlife in football as well
in some of the businesses that I'm involved in.
But on a football pitch
and in a,
in a football environment,
I think communication and connecting,
listen,
a group of men,
one of my teammates,
likened it to being like 25 sharks in one room
and being able to kind of connect those dots
and connect those people
from different backgrounds,
different ages,
really is important in cultivating a good environment
that's conducive to winning trophies,
not only winning a trophy,
but winning on for a long period of time
and consistently.
And I think that's a key.
Obviously,
performance has to be,
they have a high standard consistently as well
on a day-to-day basis,
setting them standards on a day-to-day
was definitely key as well.
So those areas there were probably the first things
that probably stood out,
I think, for any manager
who's kind of contemplating giving me the armband
and making me the captain.
Listen, I think you'd notice
being somebody who's been involved in sport as well
is that being able to talk to different types of people
all in different ways is so key
in making sure that you hit the right notes
with people.
To create a place where people feel like
they're okay to make mistakes,
they'll get caught and held by other people
in a change room,
but also where they know there is a level of expectancy
on a regular basis.
It's an interesting description,
25 sharks swimming around the one room.
And it makes sense to me
because effectively you're competing first and foremost
for your own spot in a team,
particularly at the high level
of English Premier League football.
And you've got incredibly talented people,
lots of big ego,
lots of people who think they should play
a role that maybe someone else has got.
And so it's not an easy mix, isn't it,
to get team harmony,
but you obviously had a way of being able
to relate to everyone,
even if they came from different backgrounds.
Do you feel like that was a real skill of yours?
Yeah, definitely.
And I think that 25 sharks,
the analogy is like you say,
every single player in that squad
of 26 players think they should be starting.
There's 26 international players,
we play for their countries
and there's probably 10,
maybe 11 captains of their countries
in our dressing room at any one time.
So then to make sure that you create
a harmonious environment is absolutely imperative
because the moment you have one
who's a little bit disjointed
and steps out from the crowd
and is allowed to do that,
that becomes a bit of a cancerous person
who then spreads
and you can gain followers
and people that stand alongside him
because they're not in the team as well.
And then that obviously then becomes a big problem
for the squad,
the starting 11,
the management staff.
So that has to be managed.
And I think the manager doesn't really,
that's weird because Felix Ferguson
never really came into our changing room
on a day-to-day basis at a training ground.
He allowed not only the person wearing the armband,
but like I said,
there was other leaders in there as well
to really manage the standards as well
and punctuality, respect.
And I think that's a huge thing as well
is making sure that there's respect
in the dressing room between teammates
is a huge thing.
And the players have to manage that.
Like if someone steps out of line,
they do something wrong
or the intensity is not right on the day,
there has to be the ability and the space
for someone to challenge someone about that,
but also to receive that in the right way.
And if it isn't received in the right way,
that person needs to be told.
I'm fascinated that Sir Alex was someone
that really left the locker room to the players.
He didn't want to mingle and mix
and socialise in there.
That wasn't his go.
It was something that he let the players go,
and as you said,
run that space themselves.
Was that different to other managers?
Yeah.
I mean, some managers would come in,
not a problem,
and come in and see,
put their head in there once a week.
I don't think a lot of managers come in there a lot,
but I was there 12, 13 years,
and he probably came in three or four times max.
And one of them was to say goodbye.
So I think the importance of,
and I think that's one of his greatest attributes
for Alex was that his ability to delegate
and give other people,
the space to kind of run their area of the football club,
whether it be logistics,
whether it be S&C,
whether it be the physiotherapy,
the doctor,
them areas are run by those people.
He was the overarching body that looked over things,
and if it wasn't working or there was mistakes,
and then you obviously go and see him,
but he would leave people with the ability
to go and do what you've got to do.
You're here.
I think that's a good thing he always used to talk about.
You're here because you're good enough.
I've seen something in you that makes you good enough.
Go and do that.
That really gives you the confidence to go and perform.
Real, look, from an outsider looking in,
and we all loved your era and one of the great eras in sport
and the legend of Sir Alex Ferguson
and what you guys achieved,
but it looked like if you fell out with him, though,
it was a pretty short conversation,
and no matter how big you were,
if you're David Beckham or Raya Ferdinand
or whatever it was,
if you didn't quite fit,
could he be quite brutal in that scenario as well?
Yeah.
Obviously, everyone's heard of the hairdryer
where he unloads and gives it to you.
But I'll be honest,
I see a few people go back and forth with him.
Beck's one, definitely.
Roy, but I think it wasn't just like you had a problem,
there was an issue and it was done and it was over
and then you're gone.
It wasn't like that.
He was a fair person.
But once he made a decision on you,
that was it.
It was a definite.
And to be fair,
I had a few run-ins with him
where I would challenge a decision
or I wasn't happy about certain things.
And I think if he believed it was coming from the right place,
then...
in time, he'd get over it.
He wouldn't hold that grudge.
But if he believed that there was a bit more to it
or there was some skullduggery
or it just wasn't the right thing for the team,
then he wouldn't accept that.
And again,
if he thought you was a problem for the dressing room,
he would act very quickly.
And I think that's a really good trait
that I've kind of seen
and you'd take on into any walk of life.
You feel something,
you think it's not right,
you think it can harm the long-term processes,
get rid of it.
Well, reading your history,
you grew up in the council estate
in the tough neighbourhood of Peckham, South London.
Your parents separated when you were 14.
For you and your brother, Anton,
to go on and play professional football
feels like a remarkable story for me.
How did you find a way to succeed
given the challenges that you obviously faced?
It's weird.
Everyone says,
oh, challenging background.
It was obviously that we wasn't blessed
with loads of resources.
There was a lot of kind of untoward
stuff that would be going on around us
and on our estates
and police always there
and lots of issues that are going on.
But I do always look back
and just like it does bring a smile to my face
because there's lots of happy memories there
with my friends
and different cultures
and different people,
different backgrounds.
A lot of them I'm still friends with now.
So yeah, it was difficult,
but I think I was one of the fortunate ones
that my dad didn't choose to just go
and leave us.
Yes, my mum and dad separated,
but my dad lived on the next estate.
He made it a point of not moving far away.
Discipline was a huge thing in our household,
whether it be for my mum or my dad.
And so I always had someone to answer to.
And I think that's a lot for a kid.
When there's a lot of temptation
and a lot of kind of opportunity
for making the wrong decisions,
you do need to have that somebody
or that figure in your life,
whether it's a parent or a guardian
or a family member that you go,
oh, if I do make that decision,
what would they think?
And I had that
and I was fortunate enough to have that
with both my parents.
Obviously, my dad was a bit more
of a discipliner than my mum,
but for both,
I would add the respect of them
to kind of think about certain decisions
I would make.
And Rio, you were a champion gymnast as a kid.
You attended Central Ballet School in London
as an 11-year-old for a number of years.
It's an unusual path
to be a champion of English football.
Did you look back at
and think that they were helpful for you,
those early disciplines of ballet
and gymnastics?
Yeah, 100%.
I think it wasn't normal
for a kid from a council estate
to be going and doing gymnastics and ballet
three or four times a week.
But initially, it was just for adventure.
I was able to go off my estate,
go and meet new people, girls.
I was of that age.
And just going and speaking.
And again, that was part of my journey
in terms of being able to communicate with people,
having to forge new relationships
and new environments.
A way out of my comfort zone.
I've done that since I was 10, 11 years old.
So that then became one of my strong points
as a footballer.
New environments,
talking, communicating,
and getting in.
And so it helped me not only
from a physical aspect
with how difficult both of them disciplines are,
but definitely from a social aspect,
it really brought me on to no end.
You look back at the Manchester United era
we've spoken about briefly under Sir Alex
and you think,
you won trophies for fun.
League titles and Champions League titles.
It was an incredible era of success.
How would you describe,
what was the culture that enabled
that consistent success over such a long period of time
right throughout your career?
How would you sum that up?
Yeah, I mean, listen, it was wonderful times
and the memories are endless.
But one of the key things I think when I look back,
there's many things that it could have been the reasons for.
Not one of us will have the definitive answer,
but I've got no doubts in my mind
that one of the good contributors,
or that every single thing we put our hands to
was a competition.
Whether it be on the team bus playing cards,
whether it be playing computer games,
on travelling, in hotels,
whether it be playing table tennis pre and post training,
whether it be doing, I don't know,
a basketball warm-up game.
Every single thing we'd done was a competition.
And the training games were harder
than the real-life matches
in terms of competitiveness.
Every day, it was like Friday before a game
was like eight-a-side game on the pitch.
And how many times did the manager have to stop the session
because it was getting a bit overheated
or it was just a real competitive energy
that just spread throughout the squad.
And there weren't many in there
that didn't have some sort of competitive energy
outside of the football pitch at some point of the day.
So that definitely contributed because it was always on.
And I think, to me,
that is the thing you can't manufacture in an athlete.
You have great skill and you can have great athleticism,
but to be an absolute animal,
competitor is probably the number one ingredient,
I think, in almost every sport.
So it's fascinating that you went straight to there.
You think that competitive edge set you apart
from the other teams?
Yeah, because you can't,
I don't think you can switch that will to win on and off.
Like, I play with my kid now.
He's three years old and I have to beat,
I just beat him.
He's got to learn the hard way.
He's got to learn.
And if I do let him win every now and again,
I do think like, why have I let him win?
And it's such a stupid little thing.
And you think, well, there's no competition,
but in my head, there's always a switch.
It's always competing.
I don't know why.
Or if I go on the dartboards in the office upstairs,
I have to throw three,
I can't come off there unless I hit a treble or a bullseye.
There's a competitive nature to everything.
And I just think that if you can be passive
and switch that off and then just go, yeah, next time,
that then trickles and filters in
to your everyday training regime.
And you're happy.
You're happy.
You've got habits on a daily basis.
And so, I don't know,
but even when I'm doing my punditry now,
I've got my foundation or with We Are Right,
you want it to be the best.
I want this to be the best social media platform
that does the best work for people
and the benefits of people are huge and for the environment.
These are the things that you,
I don't want to have a platform where it's better
for citizens to go on there and have better experiences
or they can gain more somewhere else.
This is just the way I am now.
Well, we're really privileged to cross over with you
in our Leader Connect space.
We bring together diverse groups of leaders
from five or six at a time from different backgrounds.
You're with Andy Cohen,
who's a global executive from JP Morgan,
Andy Walsh from Red Bull and Liminal,
Jude Bolton, who's a bit of a legend of Australian football,
and your great friend Zoe Kalar, who founded We Are Right.
We love the idea of people coming together
to sort of learn and share from different backgrounds
who maybe wouldn't have got together.
Can you tell us,
how the Leader Connect experience was for you?
No, I have to say thank you, by the way,
to Zoe for bringing me on
and just to kind of making me aware of it
and getting in a group of such esteemed professionals
from different backgrounds.
And I think there's always parallels.
One thing I've learned in retirement,
the amount of parallels from different industries
that cross over and things I've learned
and taken from sport can cross over
into many of the businesses that I'm involved in
and can only enhance them.
And likewise, the other way around.
Yeah, it's been phenomenal.
And the ability just to even have the communication
with these guys and to hear their stories and experiences.
And most importantly for me,
just their perspective on certain things and topics
has been invaluable.
I mean, the notes, if I show you my notepad
of when I was doing the calls,
I haven't really had an experience
where I can make so many meaningful notes
from other people's experiences.
And I think that's one of the things
that's definitely a big takeaway for me.
Well, Mikel Arteta has been a great champion in our space.
He's in his third group now
with other leading coaches from around the globe.
He puts all of his leaders at Arsenal
and his assistant coaches through the same program.
And he loves that continuous learning and self-improvement.
From what you know of him and his recent success,
what do you think would motivate someone like that
who's so curious and wants to learn
someone like Mikel Arteta?
Yeah, I mean, once I was told that he was on these courses
and I'd done a few of them myself,
so I could...
I wasn't surprised.
I could totally see how and why he's here.
Like you say, I think he's a curious being,
first and foremost.
But he's a man of detail.
You can tell that.
He's a man of detail.
And from listening to the players that he's coaching now,
that there's a lot of details.
And again, his perspective and his viewpoint
on a lot of different aspects of their games
are coming from a different angle
to what they're used to hearing or seeing.
So that enlightens them.
It educates them.
But again,
you get that type of approach from a manager
that's a bit left-field.
You do start going,
whoa, this guy's different.
And then the belief comes.
And then that translates to the pitch at some point.
And I think they're starting to see the benefits of that now
through results.
The last two years, very close.
But I just see it as a matter of time
before he's one of the best coaches
in our game in the Premier League
because of his attention to detail
and his willingness to keep evolving and working.
And educating himself.
Ryo, people listening to you will think
what a dream life it is to be Ryo Ferdinand.
And you've had incredible success.
And I want to talk to you about some of your business success
and where you're at in a moment.
But when you read your backstory in preparation for this,
you've had more than your fair share of hardships
and setbacks in life as well.
And I read of the passing of Rebecca, your wife,
at 34 years of age from breast cancer.
And hard to imagine how difficult that would be.
You wrote a book about it, thinking out loud about that.
Tragic passing.
Can you share with people how you overcome tragedy
and setbacks of that nature in your life?
Yeah, I mean, it's a difficult, difficult time, I think.
We prepare for a lot of outcomes in our life
and scenarios that come up in our life.
But one thing we're not taught,
and it's never in any fairy tale books,
is death being a part of your life.
We never prepare kids for dying.
We definitely don't prepare people to lose people very young.
So when it happens, there's no book that you can get
that goes, right, this is a template.
And you add to that as well another layer that we have three kids.
So three young kids from eight downwards.
So to have to tell three young kids
that their mum's going to have to go to sleep
and never come back is the hardest thing I've ever had to do in my life.
And I don't imagine I'll have anything,
I hope I don't anyway, as hard.
So yeah, I mean, listen to...
Being not prepared for anything in life is difficult,
but that was a real bolt.
And she went in hospital, actually,
and it was about six or seven weeks later,
then she passed away.
So it was a really quick kind of passing.
And that type of thing definitely puts you in a place where,
right, what the hell do I do?
And just sitting there asking yourself those questions.
And I think...
I was very fortunate that I had kids.
And as much as you don't want them to go through it,
but they were probably the biggest help for me
in that I had to get up every day.
I had to continue a structured life
and continue showing them that there is normality beyond this.
So getting up, going to work,
getting up, getting them dressed,
doing breakfast and taking them to school
as normal as possible
was a big thing for them to continue their life
and to get back to some sort of normality.
Because it'd be quite easy to just kind of fold up
like a pack of cards, really,
and just like, right, give up.
And I'll say, I said this in the book
and the documentary that I've done around it,
is that like, I'd never understood suicide before.
I still don't understand it totally,
but I appreciate when somebody might have thoughts like that.
When you think that, right, where do I go now?
There's no way, there's no light at the end of the tunnel.
But I think, again, I was very fortunate.
I was fortunate that I had good people around me,
family, friends.
And unfortunately, to be fair,
my mum became like the second mum,
but she then passed away about 18 months, two years later from cancer.
So it was a bit of a double whammy.
But again, that support system
and one of the probably biggest things that came out of it,
as much as I was a good communicator in a change room,
I was a terrible communicator to do with feelings and family.
And I'd never had to really consider that.
And it wasn't until Rebecca passed away.
And then my mum left shortly after where I have to talk and communicate to my children
because I need to get and extract conversations out of them to see how they are more.
But they're difficult conversations that I've never really been good at having.
So I had to break down to embarrass myself.
Because now my kids are very good communicators, confident kids.
And you put them in a room, you wouldn't know that they've been through what they're doing.
So that's how I kind of gauge where we're at.
So they're doing really well.
So you really found that you had to find a way to just be more open on the home front with your emotions
and learn to discuss more openly with your kids because of what had happened?
Is that part of what happened out of, yeah.
Yeah, yeah, definitely.
And I think, again, like just having those conversations.
I had to kind of do a documentary to force me to go and have therapy and to speak
and to open up about feelings and stuff.
Because I don't think without that pressure, I'd have found it easy to do it.
So once I had that kind of pressure, I went and done it.
And then I started to be engaged with other people that have been through similar experiences.
Then you've got a lot of questions as to what do you do?
How do I get my kids to open up?
And how do I get my kids on the right path?
So all those conversations are beneficial to me, but then hugely beneficial to my kids.
Yeah, I really appreciate you sharing that because I'm sure there's lots of people that have not maybe seen the documentary
that are going through it.
Yeah.
And to hear where Ferdinand had to sort of find a way and the way that you did is a really compelling story.
I love the We Are 8 story to change gear.
And I love what you're doing.
You're an incredible champion of this world.
And to hear you say you approach that with that same spirit of I want this to be the best.
And Zoe Killar, the founder and CEO, is a remarkable person, a great friend of yours.
I feel like it's one of the huge issues society is facing is the impact of social media on our kids, on a generation.
And for you to be a huge advocate for creating this platform for good, can you share with why it's caught your attention
and why you're so passionate about We Are 8?
Yeah.
I just – Zoe, first and foremost, the founder and CEO, she's an incredible lady.
I think also the ability to stand side by side with a woman in a world where there aren't loads of tech startup founders who are women
and who find it hard to maybe get investment sometimes, who find it hard to get.
I think also the ability to get traction in that industry, to stand shoulder to shoulder with someone,
but not only that, with the platform that you look at and go, well, that is the antidote to a lot of the negativity
that surrounds a lot of other platforms.
And it's there, it's alive, it's working, and it solves many a problem that you're thinking, well, how do we solve that?
I've always thought before, how do we stop toxic?
How do we stop negative behavior on social media?
How do we stop social media's controlling the algorithm and you seeing what they want you to see?
How do we see our friends again on social media?
Well, We Are 8 has created a platform.
Zoe's created a platform that does that.
But not only that, it gives you the opportunity to earn money through the platform.
Money will drop into your account through watching adverts.
But then the great thing is you, as a person,
can then actually have the autonomy to go, right, I want to pay it forward to that charity and help that charity over there and help the environment.
So there's so many layers to this that are positive that I was like, after five minutes listening to Zoe when she pitched it to me, I was like, listen, stop.
I don't need no more.
I'm good.
I've been looking for something like this for a long time.
And this isn't a platform where you go, listen, guys, come off of everything else because everything else is terrible.
Yes, there's bad elements to other platforms, but we're saying, come here, just see what's good, what can be done.
And if the right values are at the start and the starting point and the foundations of a platform, this is what it looks like.
Yeah, brilliant.
Check it out if you haven't.
We are right.
It's genius in its simplicity.
But as Ro said, it's doing all the things that I think a lot of people are searching for and worth having a look at if you haven't been part of that We Are Right community.
We love the saying, Ro, that success leaves clues.
And I love sitting down with people like you who've had remarkably successful lives.
And we see these patterns that emerge of what great success and leadership.
And we see these patterns that emerge of what great success and leadership stories look like, starting with self-leadership.
And I wanted to ask the question, what do you do, Ro, in a busy life with five kids and businesses and you're broadcasting and you've got a lot going on?
What do you do to fill your own cup up so that you can lead the other people in your life?
Go to the gym.
I go to the gym.
Keep active.
Probably three, four times a week I'll go to the gym.
And that hour is like, that's my time.
The way I'm uninterrupted by outside noise or outside responsibilities.
That's my time to do what I want to do.
And family walks.
When we go on a family walk, because I've got five kids, two of them are now living away from home because they're playing football.
But when on the weekends we have the chance where all of us are back in the house, like we had this weekend just gone.
It's just like the house is noisy.
It's a mess.
There's things everywhere.
Everything's not in the way it's meant to be.
But I love it.
I love the carnage.
So having a loud, happy house is another thing where I can sit back.
And go, yeah, this is not long ago I would have dreamed to have this.
And so enjoy it.
We think about the impact that people like you have on a daily basis.
What's one thing that's always worked for you as a leader that you would never change about yourself and your style?
I think give the right example.
Set the standards.
Set the example.
And be consistent with it.
I think that's always been something that, whether it's been through playing football or through the various companies that I'm involved in, always turn up.
And deliver.
And I think that's always the, whether it's, sometimes you might hit the standard that you're looking to and it's the standard you've set the bar at.
But your intentions are always there for that.
And that desire, the dedication, application is unwavering.
Ro, in terms of vision, can you tell us a story of a visionary leader that has inspired you along the way and why you felt compelled to follow their vision?
I think.
I think it's Alex Ferguson.
I think I had the best leader that I've had, I think, in the Premier League that we've seen.
I think in terms of leading men, leading hard people to please, you know.
And the way that he would, like I said before, the way that he would kind of give you the space to lead and go out there and believe in who you are.
And I think that we will be successful.
Talking that into existence, we will be successful.
We will win.
Listen to me.
Believe in what I'm saying to you.
I won't see you wrong.
But also, making sure that you are really understanding that you are here and I believe in you.
I have brought you to this club because I know what you're capable of.
Don't need to change much.
Go out and just do what got you here.
Continue that.
And I think a lot of people get kind of twisted a little bit when they go into a new role or the speed at the...
The place they work in changes because there's a new vision that they think they automatically have to change what they're doing and change who they are.
If you're there and you're being kept there, there's a reason why.
Because you're doing something right.
Until they tell you, you know, you've got to do something different.
Just continue what you're doing and don't feel pressured to actually, oh, I've got to really change.
Add bits, yeah, but not a whole outrageous change of approach or the way that you're doing things.
And he was great.
And Sir Alex Rio, over such a long period of time, a continued success.
And winning so regularly.
Did he just stick to that consistently?
He didn't move the needle too much?
He just knew what you're going to get from him?
Yeah.
Sir Alex wasn't massive on tactics.
His coach has done all that stuff.
He was...
What he was great at, and I think that's...
Sorry, that's another thing, part of the first question and the second.
But his ability to treat each and every individual differently and as a separate case.
He didn't have this blanket treatment.
Managers were like, one size fits all.
I'm going to approach everybody the same because I ain't got enough time in a day to deal with you individually.
He would be very much, listen, guys, right, you.
This is how I'll deal with you.
I'll be very aggressive because I know that you can take it and your response will be a positive one.
Or he needs an arm around the shoulder.
He might need me to joke a bit more.
He might need me to soften up.
You know, everybody had a different approach.
He never praised me once, really, to my face.
Very, very rare that he praised me and the Mania Vidic.
But he probably thought, well, if I praise Rio too much, you might get a bit too confident
and think things are just, you can chill out a bit.
Where I was always on my edge of my seat wanting to go, listen,
aching for that bit of kind of encouragement or go to the press and talk about us defenders a little bit.
He never done that and he kept us hungry.
Rio, curiosity is a word we see a lot in people that have continued success and sustained success.
How do you carve out time to be curious and then integrate that into your day?
Is that something?
That resonates with you?
Yeah, I'm crazy curious.
I'm so curious that I end up signing up to so much stuff that is just way beyond what I should be.
My wife goes crazy.
A new business, a new idea because I'm so curious about, it's like AI.
I'm so like curious about AI now and I'm just like downloading every, all the chat GPT and all this stuff
and just kind of just getting into it and seeing how it works.
And yeah, I can't help it.
Something comes on the system.
And I'm like, well, I don't want, I don't want to be in a conversation where I'm way off it.
I want a little bit of an understanding at least.
Rio, have you got an example of a great collaboration in your life you can share with us?
In what sense?
Yeah, we're just obsessed with the idea of people collaborating on passion projects
or things that have worked well for them where they've gone and reached out with different people.
And that greater sum of a couple of people getting together has been a story of success.
Yeah, I think two people.
I think Zoe Collar from We Are Right.
I think her positivity.
I think her energy lights up every room she goes into, whether it's on a Zoom call or in face.
Just her appetite for work and for breaking down barriers in an industry where a lot of people will go,
okay, well, it's quite a saturated market.
There's a couple of platforms that have got an absolute stranglehold on it.
It's impenetrable, but she looks at it very differently because of the foundations
and the values of what she's built.
And being super confident in that and unwavering.
She's been great in being alongside her for that.
And yeah, a guy called Saul Klein.
He has a fund in the tech world.
And as I said, when my wife passed them years ago, I was obviously in a bit of a lost soul
and I needed to be out and working while the kids were at school.
And he used to have like a dragon's den on a Monday.
Every Monday.
Every Monday of startups coming and pitching him their ideas and stuff.
And he said, just come in.
Cause I met him at a web summit and I'm interested in tech anyway.
Never really had my foot anywhere.
And he said, come in and just sit in the corner and just take it and see where you're at.
And you might invest in things.
You might not, whatever.
And I might throw a few questions.
And he just started throwing questions at me every now and again.
I just think, what does he want with me?
I don't even know this world.
And he's like, listen, a different perspective is always needed.
Doesn't matter where you are.
I'm in a bubble of tech.
Like having you here for that is great.
So that collaboration of me giving something to him,
but also me learning so much in terms of investment and how and who and what and why
in terms of investing was like huge for me in those formative years
of understanding a little bit of investment in tech.
It's a brilliant story.
And we love that idea of, as you said,
a sports person sitting in a room with a tech entrepreneur,
but the way your minds think being the sum of the greater parts
being such a worthwhile thing to achieve.
You mentioned communication being a real strength of yours as a young,
leader and your managers and senior people saw that in you.
Have you got a mantra that you've lived by in terms of your communication?
Yeah, I think it's direct,
but don't put too much words on someone's plate where it becomes confusing.
I think I always felt as a young person,
if someone said too much and brought too many things to the table at once,
I lost the focus of what I'm actually doing.
And I'm concentrating on something that's not really going to make me a better player.
It's going to only confuse me and distort.
A lot of the things I'm going into so clear lines of communication,
getting the message across with real clarity and transparency.
Um, also with respect, um, there, there's a couple of,
I think the imperative and what they see in me.
Definitely.
Well, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
I'd have to say my mom and dad really, um, just for one thing that again,
like one more thing on your question before is that if you're going to talk to a group of
people,
or talk to teammates and,
and,
and challenge teammates,
you got to make sure that your house is in order.
I've always felt that as well.
There's no way I can give advice or say,
you can't do that or you shouldn't do that.
I'll come down on someone when I'm late every day or I'm letting things pass or drift in my routine.
So I have to be on it to be able to have the conversations that you have as a leader.
Um, yeah,
my mom and dad,
I think will be the people that I look to because they've had something that has been an imprint in
my life and stuck with me forever and will do.
I'm sure to the day I die,
which is a work ethic.
My mom worked all the hours God sent to give us the opportunity to have food on the table or travel
from A to B.
Um, same with my dad traveled from one part of London,
go to the other work,
come back to our part of London,
then travel to another part of London to take us to training three,
four times a week.
Um, that again,
not telling me anything,
but just doing it.
And me seeing that is something that I,
I haven't imprinted in my life now and work ethic is something that I don't think anybody could doubt when they,
when they talk about me.
Rio,
we're a bit obsessed with this idea of collaboration.
I love the story you just told about Saul Klein and you getting together and learning the tech world through him.
You've got access to people all around the globe through what you've achieved in sport.
If you looked and thought,
geez,
I'd love to connect or collaborate with that person on one of the passion projects you're involved in.
Is there a name that springs to mind?
That you've always thought of if you're thinking about impacts and shifting an industry or shifting the volume of people,
Cristiano Ronaldo is the man on the planet to do it.
You've seen what he's done.
We just opened his own new social media channel.
YouTube gone crazy,
broke every record possible,
um,
for a project that will be around helping and the wellbeing of other people to get someone like him on board to do that,
I think,
it's definitely a definite blue sky thinking where you go.
I'd love to have him because he,
there aren't many people in the world that have as many followers as him,
but could also who also have the ear of all those followers.
There's a lot of people with a lot of followers,
but I think when they say something,
there's no real meaning behind it.
No one really moves.
This guy has the ability to move cultures and people,
man.
It's just like of all age groups,
of all demographics.
It's just,
I've seen it with my own eyes.
It's crazy.
So yeah,
that would be the one.
And Rio,
final question.
I've got to go back on Cristiano.
I think he scored his 901st goal this week was in the news more than anyone in the history of the sport that you love.
You got to see him as a young,
young kid.
Was there a genius at that age?
Did you realise you're with something special?
And how do you rate him in terms of what other great players have achieved?
I think in terms of talent,
I don't think there's any other question.
I think we all thought immediately when we laid eyes on him,
wow,
wonder kid can do anything.
It could be anything he wants to be.
No one really saw him scoring 900 goals.
I think he'd be,
everyone would be lying if they heard he said,
oh yeah,
get 900 goals because he wasn't a goal scorer when he first came.
He was an entertainer,
but he almost,
it's like what he's done in the game of football is almost akin to changing a sport.
Almost.
He went from an entertainer to being just an out and out goal scorer,
changed positions totally.
So,
to be honest,
I don't know.
So to think that he's actually become one of the best in the world as a winger,
entertaining,
and then went on from there and became even better as a number nine striker,
he's changed,
changed his roles completely.
People find it hard to have one great career.
He's had two in one career in that sense.
So that then takes me to the thing I think that sets him apart from everybody else.
His intelligence.
He has a huge intelligence and an appetite to evolve and to be curious.
Like,
he said that word again of finding the margins.
Where are the margins at in terms of researching sleep,
researching physiotherapy,
researching setting the ambience in a room with crystals like he does mad stuff.
He's got like he's he's talking to NASA like about recovery.
Like there ain't many players that are doing that.
It's funny.
I mean,
he's looking for the extra extra margins to not only better himself,
but obviously look at the length of time.
He's played football at the top is we've not seen this before.
We haven't seen it.
And he's groundbreaking in that sense.
And in terms of goats that have ever played the game,
he's 100% in at the top table with whoever you want to put there.
Rio,
it's been a great privilege to spend some time with you today and find out more about your story.
Um,
you know,
we are right to an incredible legacy along with everything else that you've got in your life.
And you can see where the patterns are for remarkable success and really appreciate you taking the time.
Be great to cross over with you.
In the leader world.
And thanks for taking the time.
We really appreciate it.
Top man.
Thank you very much.
And I'll be back on soon.
I've missed a couple,
but I'll be back on.
Don't worry.
We'll look forward to that.
Thanks for it.
Great to see it.
Cheers,
mate.
No problem.
Really good.
Enjoyed it.