A Listener Production.
G'day, it's Luke Darcy.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership both on and off the field has been a lifelong
passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective and I've had the privilege
of working with thousands of leaders in education, sport, industry and the arts that have helped
shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
I was joined by the creative genius that is Rob Sitch from Working Dog.
We chat about how to lead an entire film crew on set, changing career paths and the benefits
of failing.
Now, one of the real challenges in sitting down to chat with Rob Sitch is the overwhelming
feeling of underachievement in your own life and that's what I've had in preparation for
this conversation.
Rob, a graduate of the University of Melbourne in 1987 with a Bachelor of Medicine in Surgery
and instead of pursuing a career in medicine, Rob's path has led him to be a game changer
and a game changer.
He started universally as a world-class comedian, actor and legendary director.
Rob's collaboration with the team at Working Dog has produced some of the most successful,
iconic and culturally defining moments in Australian television, film and radio history.
Starting in 1986, The Degeneration, The Late Show, Frontline, Funky Squad, The Panel, Thank
God You're Here, Have You Been Paying Attention, Utopia, The Castle, The Dish and many, many
more other mediums, books, radio, extraordinary career of success.
And Rob, it's always a great pleasure to catch up with you.
Thanks for your time.
It's always great to catch up with you, Luke.
Now, I want to start as a 17-year-old, you're at Melbourne Uni as a medical student.
By the time you're in your early 20s, I understand you were running the emergency department
at the Wangaratta Hospital.
You can correct me if I'm wrong.
How did that set you up for life?
There's two elements to that.
One is, it still surprises me that you used to finish your year 12 quite young back then.
I was young for my year and we finished young.
And so, I started university, I often say this, I was doing medicine at 17, I mean, surely
the state of Victoria should have stepped in and put me into that.
And then I took, I have my medical career, I took a couple of years off to do various
comedy projects.
And so, I arrived maybe after my degree took eight years, so maybe I was 24, 23, I arrived
at Wangaratta and used to be rotated up there.
And to say I was running it, I was somewhere between the doctor and the work experience
kid.
But that's a great thing to be rotated up to the country.
I joined the local aero club, the local tennis club.
It was probably, it was sort of October, November, December, beautiful weather in the country.
It was just the best time.
I understand that you delivered plenty of babies along the way.
And you're still in your early 20s though, right?
Yeah.
And, you know, an emergency department of the hospitals got some unique challenges attached
to it.
Do you feel like that did set you on a path?
I was literally only saying last night that I look back and I can't, it sort of feels
like a different person doing that stuff.
The country is different because someone came in and said they've hurt their back in a rodeo.
All right, okay, well that's only in the country.
But it was, I've done all the, fortunately I got up there, but it was at the end of the
stint and I got up there as, you know, the nursing staff were enormously supportive.
There was, you know, every known specialist consultant hanging over in another part of
the building in an ICU to back everyone up.
So it was, you know, lots of, you know, cuts and sprains and all sorts of things like that.
But I really enjoyed the practical side of medicine, you know, doing, stitching up cuts
and any sort of procedure.
Yeah.
And still to this day, you know, I remember putting in IV lines.
It's a really funny thing.
You get a knack and a great sense of satisfaction when you get good at something like that.
Not so much fun when someone's not good at that, from my experience, Rob, either.
Well, you know, the funny thing is it's interesting you raise that because even after all these
years I was, I was actually on a stint at Albury and this wonderful gentleman came in,
and he was, he had a blood cancer from being, from memory being involved in one of the atomic
tests in, the British atomic tests in Australia.
And that was the assertion, I think, in a given time where we think that's the answer.
And I went up to put in an IV line and for once in my life, I failed the first time.
And, and this is a gentleman who had it a hundred times and had learned to dread it
by now.
And I tried it again and failed again, eventually.
And the consultant came up to me after and said, I think I'll do it next time.
And he'd obviously, and I just, of all the people you didn't want to let down, I'd walked
in as, leave it to me.
And you go, oh, and it's funny what sticks in your mind, I've never forgotten letting
that guy down.
I can remember, you know, having various operations through, through footy and, and the IV drip
goes in and, and you often get the, whoever's on the wards, oh, good news, you know, Rob's
here today.
It's going to be a pain free one for you.
I always felt that set up a fair bit of pressure for the person that was trying to do that.
Well, hey, I want to go back to, hear a lot about the Melbourne University reviews and,
and where you probably started your creative performing and, and career in some, in some
ways.
Can you, can you take me back to there?
You're a medical student, you're performing in the reviews at university.
Was there a clear time where you thought, hey, I'm going down the creative path here rather
than the medical path?
No, there wasn't because I didn't do any, you know, this acting at all until I was maybe
21, something.
I didn't do it at school, had no interest the first year, second year, but it occurred
to me, you know, university is a time when if you don't roll the dice on a few things
that are going to make you nervous, you probably never will.
So, and my football career had pulled a hamstring, I think it's fair to say.
So I went, oh, look, I'll, I'll try out for the, you know, one of the college players.
And I was like, oh, I'm going to try out for the, you know, one of the college players.
Yeah.
And it wasn't even considered.
And then tried it again the next year and I was, my role was to do the sound effects
on stage.
And I thought, I felt even as a, as a newbie, I felt that was beneath me.
And then a friend of mine who was doing medicine said, how about we try it for this law review?
And I didn't even think we were eligible.
And so we auditioned and got in, but it turned out the director had the heart of gold and
basically took in everything.
Everyone that auditioned.
So we had a cast of 60 at one point.
We had our own ballet about halfway through the second act in order to give everyone a
job.
But I, I love that.
I just went, oh God, it's like, it's, it's like a sporting team, but it was, it's co-ed
for a start, which helps.
And it was just a really, really enjoyable time.
And then we did it next year and then someone said, look, let's take a year off and tour
it around the country.
And so it's back then.
Well, look, it's, it's, you had no obligations to speak of, and I had a wonderful, the Dean
of Medicine at Royal Melbourne Hospital at the time, a guy called Dr. Roger Mellick.
You know, I went in, I thought he was going to talk me out of it and the opposite.
He said, oh, that sounds, that sounds really interesting.
I'd do that.
I thought you were going to straighten me out.
He goes, oh no, that sounds like a lot of fun.
I'd grab that if you can.
And so that's, you know, biff.
You know, sliding doors, had he said, oh no, I don't think that's right, I wouldn't have
done it.
What a great piece of advice, isn't it, Rob?
That's unique, isn't it?
To go to someone that you're expecting to talk you out of, which is a pretty risky move
and you're on the path and you end up finishing your medicine and surgery, as you said, eight
years of study.
But how did that decision go down with the family when you said, I'm taking you off and
I'm touring our show around the country?
I reckon a few raised eyebrows.
I think I had a father who made a decision, I'm never going to tell you what to do.
But I reckon that he was about to play his joker that day, he went.
Because you know, going back a few generations, our, my sort of generation, sort of everyone
started going to university, but you know, my dad and his brother and sister and their
generation before them, the university was such a big deal.
So when you got the opportunity and, you know, I think from memory.
It was, the government didn't charge for uni when we were there.
So it was looking a gift horse in the mouth in his eyes.
And Rob, you mentioned the director at the Melbourne Uni Review having a heart of gold
and opening the door and allowing you through at the start.
And I wanted to delve into that because I've, I've spoken to a few people in preparation
who are close to you and they talk about your brilliance in acting and your natural brilliance
in comedy, but it's the extraordinary gift they see for you when you're a director and
in that particular role.
Can you explain that?
How have you gone about the craft of directing and, and what sort of skillset have you brought
to it?
We, we, it's an interesting evolution for us.
We decided really early on, realised really early on that, that everything in comedy is
writing.
So, you know, you might write a film like Die Hard, a suspense thriller that you can
hand it over to director and, and there's a bit of wriggle room to how you shoot it
and how.
You can, how you edit it and the music and all that.
With comedy, the timing and the, and the way that the lines are delivered are so specific
that you, in a way, directing was a way of protecting the writing and acting was a way
of protecting the writing.
And even then we got to the point where we started buying, back in the day, it was very
expensive editing machines and we used to buy them in order to edit it the way it was,
the way we heard it.
And so in a way with comedy, you know, you can write music and then hand it over to the
orchestra.
In, in comedy, you've got to write the music and learn how to play the instruments and
then get out the front and conductor as well, I think is the best way of explaining.
Yeah.
It's fascinating, you know, insight into that.
And I, I, as I said, I was talking to people close to you and, and they were going back
to, as an example with The Dish, you know, in 2000, unbelievable film and an incredible
success.
And, and sort of picturing you on set with over a hundred people.
Yeah.
And every one of those hundred really want to take their pulse from what you say.
And they're, everyone wants a little bit of your time, but you've got all these pressures
of time and you've got pressures of weather and you've got actors who need your direction
as well.
You've got the telescope in that example that someone had booked.
And I think you've got, you know, every hotel booked in the town.
It's a lot of things coming at your way as, as, as, as the director and the, and the leader
in that example.
But they always talked about your sense of calm and your empathy for the actors and everyone
on set.
Was that a natural thing for you or is that something you've really thought about and
developed?
It's funny you say, it's funny when we were up using the Parkes radio telescope, which
is one of the largest in the world, I remember we, we, I, we had to finish one day because
a German radio astronomer had flown out to Australia to track a black hole.
And I don't think he was in the mood to be pushed back.
I, I, I don't think.
I think it's, directing is interesting.
I remember my father seemed to, you know, he loved being, you know, being in charge
of things and captain of things and all that.
And I said, I once asked him, I said, why, why, why, why is that streak in you?
And he said, I don't know.
I just really love organising fellas.
And I thought, oh, that's interesting.
He enjoyed it.
And I went, that's not me, but directing is really interesting because there's a goal.
And so therefore it's not that I enjoy the organisation of people because a film set,
it's amazing the way numbers explode and the trucks explode and all those sorts of things.
And when you drive up, you go, holy hell, I've got to run that thing.
But there's always a goal with a movie, you know, and in some ways, the great thing about
film sets is, is they're the closest thing to a military operation.
Everyone's got a title.
Everyone knows their job.
Everyone knows their role.
No one salutes and says, yes, sir, no, sir, but it's like that.
The professionalism is really high.
Yeah.
So there's, there's not a great level of uncertainty.
So you've got to make decisions, but the support mechanisms are there, the planning's there.
It's a, it's a really, it's a really great system that's been worked out of, you know,
over, over a century now, but it's often the thing I did enjoy was the goal, but it's funny
where you were talking about Wangaratta Hospital.
When I was in the emergency one day, a local guy that used to come in and consult the emergency
department.
He told me something.
He said, when you're at your most stressed, put your hands behind your back and leave
them there.
And I went, what?
And he goes, just do it.
Trust me.
And what he was saying was, there's no point getting into tears.
There's no point flapping your arms around, is just, just be still for a second.
And I think directing's a bit like that.
It's, there's a million opportunities to just freak out.
And say, oh, for whips sake, would everyone shut up and stop asking me questions?
And that doesn't get you anywhere.
And so I think once you go the other way, it actually becomes enjoyable in its own way,
is that you can be in the most stressed, most severe, and someone comes and says, there's
no, there's no iceberg lettuce for your lunch and you're going, okay, well, that's changed
to ridicio.
Okay.
That's, there's funny stories about great directors.
Better than me.
Better than me, who, you know, in the middle of organizing the Gandy shoot with a hundred
thousand extras, where someone comes up and asks some completely trivial questions.
And I remember reading a story and you just can't break the faith of being disciplined.
It's a, it's a great insight, isn't it?
If your hands are behind your back, then you naturally, I suppose your, your body language
changes into a calmer, calmer sense.
And it's fascinating.
That's carried over from your medical world into, into directing on set.
You hear occasionally, Rob, leaked audio off a movie set where an actor's going.
Absolutely ballistic and, and, you know, some emotional tantrums and were film sets
historically a bit like the old footy clubs that we grew up in, where there was a lot
of yelling and a lot of, that was the way you got your way through, or was your approach
a bit unique for its time?
How, how would you view that?
I reckon most film sets by the time we arrived were pretty, pretty sane places and pretty
disciplined places.
And there's, it's funny in Australia, I think, you know, the no dickhead rule that we're,
the Sydney Swans made famous, I reckon that that's a bit of a cultural thing in Australia
is that you can get angry for great reason, but you can't get angry because you're a prima
donna.
I don't think that, I think that that's, does not go down well at all in this country.
No, it's a good, that is a good insight into a part of our culture.
I think we should celebrate, isn't it, as that tends to work its way through pretty
quickly.
I wanted to just talk about your collaboration.
It's quite unique.
Rob, effectively, after medicine, all your working life has been with the working dog
team and Santo Cholaro, Tom Gleisner, Michael Hirsch, Jane Kennedy, your beautiful wife,
of course, was part of that.
To really have one group you've worked with all the way through seems to be an amazing
achievement.
Is that good luck, good design, or how do you equate that success over such a long period
of time?
I reckon luck is very underestimated as a factor in all our lives.
I reckon.
I describe my career as the hobby that got out of hand and it didn't start as a big plan.
I look at the current young generation and you can see them, they're quite methodical
about looking forward.
You don't get the footballer out of the country at 22 who goes, oh, I just turned up at Carlton
and I played 180 games.
People are plotting these things from a very young age.
I wasn't like that at all and I don't think we were like that.
It was one project to one project.
Once we sort of formed a group and a team, I think we fully expected eventually everyone
to slowly leave and suddenly your Ringo Starr doing a drum solo for a charity gig.
But I think we're all sort of ... I think what we ended up valuing ... and this is a
gone for every project.
When you have a project you think it's a really great idea, the one thing you learn really
quickly is there's a big dip after the initial fun.
It often takes a lot of pilots, a lot of uncertainty, a lot of hard work that can end up in tears.
We sort of worked out that we didn't want to do a project by ourselves generally.
When we'd raise it, we'd all look at each other to see if ... It's a bit like turning
the keys to the nuclear weapon.
You want it ... Everyone's got a key and unless they all turn, we're not going forward.
I think possibly we ended up enjoying the collaboration and that no one wanted to go
out and do their solo album.
I heard someone describe great partnerships recently as you need shared vision, shared
values and complementary capabilities.
Does that resonate with your group?
You have to line up on certain things and your skill sets are complementary.
Is that sort of what ...?
Yeah.
You sort of find out you're good ... A couple of us are better at this and better at that.
Instinctively, I always like directing because I like preparing and I liked having everything
in my head.
It's almost like it's a job where you can say to somebody, to everyone else, leave it
with me.
I can get this done and we don't need ... All of us don't need to drive ourselves crazy
doing it.
Yeah.
But Jalaro, who I work with, will often say, leave the editing to me, I'll do all the editing
and you just know that he'll probably put 50% more time in that's necessary but 5% of
that is quite necessary.
Yeah.
You're just never sure which bit is ... Actually, funnily, he's got an Italian saying, I can't
remember in Italian, but something like, the superfluous things are often the most necessary.
Yeah.
I reckon, when you play to your strengths ... When you're doing something, you're doing something,
you're doing something that's not right.
when you're doing something in your strength you're happy to go that extra mile and that's
that little bit of to what to someone else it might look superfluous but it's part of the
superfluous ends up being you know quite important and rob do you guys have sort of structure or or
rules around that collaboration it's as you said for your whole working life effectively it's been
such a success are you guys just go with the flow and and it's worked out it's a bit like that jane
you know the james bond seat with the ejector seat you know we but we sit in the ejector seat
we've got the right to eject ourselves like everyone knows if at any at any moment all of
us can bail if we want to um and outside of that there's only enough only enough there's there's not
many rules because the collaboration you know if we do a script it's we do 10 drafts of it so
if the fifth draft you're not
looking for you for the others to go that's brilliant fantastic it's um you're fully
expecting i call you to call them dental appointments because you don't go to the
dentist to have fun you go along you're saying mate i know i've got problems fix them
and i sort of uh and i sometimes when people yeah you know younger people come and show something
and they're showing it because they want positive affirmation and sometimes i've got to go that's
great
great but now you've got to get used to the the 360 degree feedback yeah and you guys were
comfortable with that early on to just say we're not precious about about something we've written
or no no because you get very sensitive to you're looking around and you and you're seeing people go
yeah yeah like the feeling of a great friend who you trust and admire being underwhelmed isn't
it it's a it's a sobering experience
and you can add another layer to that partnership rob because you you married the beautiful jane
kennedy which comes out of that collaboration at the start of my you know working with your wife
and and partner and your beautiful five kids as well did that change the dynamic was that
did you have to think of i'm sure it did in some ways but um clearly it has uh provided
enormous success as well it does i mean kids change everything i you know i think we all know
it but we know it going into it um and we we sort of get reminded of it and we sort of get reminded of it
during it and then looking back you're going boy it changes a lot so your outside life changes a bit
you know i was used to love fishing and golf and whatever and as i said that pulls the hamstring
pretty quickly um but but work we've kept we've sort of kept i think the smartest thing we did
early on was we got an office and if you've got an office it means you can you can run away from
your responsibilities
i want to talk about lots of areas i want to talk about lots of areas i want to talk about lots of areas
about your hobbies of uh of fish and golf and a few other things in a moment as well but i love
the opportunity to catch up with you from time to time and i tend to fire parenting questions your
way rob because it doesn't feel like there aren't many forums to do that i've enjoyed having
this longer form format because you know the leadership of business and family life always
seems to cross over and uh and i do quote one of your uh sayings you passed on there's a daniel
patrick monaghan quote that you shared with me once the richest inheritance any child can have
is a
stable loving disciplined family life it resonated with me and and my food do you think we share
enough uh you know parenting tips it doesn't seem as though we uh get together and do that often
enough as a as a community i don't think we guys aren't good at it for various reasons but i think
one of them is i don't think fathers quite i don't quite understand what role what the secret
source is in what we do like you know from the studies that that fathers are incredibly
important
um but you think you think unless you teach your kid you know how to change the motor in a in a
station wagon you go i haven't taught my kid enough but i sort of i've come to the conclusion
that it's all the tiny moments you know it's a bit that daniel patrick monaghan was a very very
smart man a senator he was the senate seat that hillary clinton took over from and he was a he
was a scientist by by training in a way he was like an epidemiologist of sorts
and at the end of all this sort of science he came to that very really simple conclusion is that
you know giving kids a stable loving upbringing and so i sort of think at the end of it um
uh i i thought one of my kids was going to take up fishing or golf or something
but i sort of comfort myself with the fact that that quote's probably the key
yeah it resonates certainly with with me and i've spoken to you before and you
about those parenting moments we all have them where you just i've had a bit of a shocker there
you know in terms of you know i've had a bit of a shocker there and i've had a bit of a shocker there
I lost my cool or I didn't get that one right.
And your reassuring words have always sat with me.
It's like, hey, you're there.
The fact that you spend enough time and you care and you think about it,
that sort of first, second and third has been your thoughts.
Is that still the case?
Totally does.
It's funny you say this.
I hope he doesn't mind me saying this.
Once a year I have a little golf trip and one of the people
we play with is Jonathan Brown and a bit like you, superstar AFL player,
but captain and all.
And one of the things I look forward to every year is I talk
to him about parenting.
I think he enjoys it too.
We scratch our heads and we go, what did you do then?
And you think we'd be talking about the glories of Lee Matthews
and the premierships and we end up going, jeez, it's hard, isn't it?
It's funny, isn't it?
For all the things you do, it is right at the top of the tree, isn't it?
And no perfect answer to get it right.
Segueing from that.
Rob, I spoke to you about a passion, which is really the genesis
for this chat and leadership podcast that we're talking on in the work
that we've been doing in a business called A Leader and you've met
a great friend of mine, Matt Wadowitz, and you formed a collaboration,
which I spoke to you about, and you were generous enough
to be part of it.
But I don't think I actually told you fully the real story of that
because it was Marcus Bondempelli, a 25-year-old captain of the Bulldogs,
quite an extraordinary young leader, and he came and heard about the fact
that there were these groups getting together and he really had you in mind
as someone he wanted to collaborate with, which I thought was brilliant.
You know, at that age, I wish I could think like that at that age
or even this stage of your life.
And Pat Cummings and Andy Lee, who's Pat Cummings' Australian cricket superstar,
Andy Lee, who's just a champion of a person and an incredible success story
in everything that he's done, Andy Lee.
So can you tell me about that group and what it's been like?
Well, it's been wonderful because I think everyone approaches these things
and it's interesting.
I'll go back to films.
One of the curious things when you do a lot of directing is the one thing
you keep asking actors is, you know, is, oh, what's that director like?
And I remember speaking to Sam Neill about it because I can't,
I'll get this wrong, but the last two directors that are directing
before me were Steven Spielberg, you know.
You know, it was like...
It was like a who's who.
And I said, the first thing I said is, look, you know, you might see a few moments
that are below par in the next six weeks.
Sam was great.
He said, look, honestly, all sets are a bit the same.
And that led me to ask him, how do other people direct?
And you realise that when directors direct, they never get directed,
so they never see what other people are doing.
I'm sure AFL coaches are like that when someone comes over
for, or any sporting, when someone comes over for another club,
you want to ask them, and how does Wayne Bennett handle that situation?
And you realise in some leadership positions, you end up being in a silo
and you have the least contact with people like yourself.
And so I presume in that way we were trying to get an eclectic group
of people together that are doing things, you know, at the pointy end
of whatever, you know, cricket or TV or, you know, AFL.
And just compare notes on how you handle situations,
often really domestic situations.
You know, how do you handle a really young, talented kid
that's not getting the best out of it?
How do you handle the front alphas?
How do you plan your day?
You know, how do you get rid of all the noise or a stone out of your shoe?
And, you know, it's funny.
You go into it thinking, well, I don't think I've got anything to offer.
And, you know, you'll say something and someone else will pop up and say,
I didn't realise that.
It's a trick or a hack.
And you go, oh, you've got to do that.
I've been doing that for 25 years.
And, you know, you can hear everyone picking up their pen and writing it down.
And it's funny.
It was a process of all of those things because in some ways, you know,
Marcus Bondimbelli is doing things at a higher intensity, you know,
a higher octane rate in some ways than all of us, you know, at a young age.
And so, you know, you sort of sometimes you're asking,
he's got more to tell.
He's got more to tell you at my age than, you know, you would imagine.
I love the sharing economy of us.
And as you said, to take the time out to reflect and be giving enough as you have,
Rob, with what's on your schedule.
And I know from what I understand, the sharing of that and the practical stuff
day to day that, you know, you can always add, can't you?
I suppose that constant never-ending self-improvement theme for people like you
and I suppose that group have all got that natural tendency is a good thing.
And we're looking at, Rob, as this sort of shift in leadership now.
A little bit from that old hierarchy to now this collaborative, self-learning,
self-driven environment that we're seeing is really the trademark of a lot of leaders
or outstanding leaders in this time.
Is that what you're witnessing, that there is a generation now that are much more
collaborative and self-reflective?
Yeah.
No, and I think that people are realising you should professionalise mentors.
You know, you shouldn't just trip over them and go, oh, maybe it'll happen to me.
Is that you've got to, in a lot of ways, you've got to make it happen.
I don't know about you.
I was from a generation where, you know, you never, it was good luck if you ran
into someone and you could ask them questions or you, you know,
wrote them a letter or something like that.
And now I think you can fast-track that process.
You know, you can really reach out.
It was, I think I'm right in saying that the current AFL premiership coach,
literally about two or three years back, got quite reflective of the situation,
sought out a whole bunch of people to give feedback.
And it's probably the missing link because when you run into, as I say,
when I run into another director, you know, I've got 27,000 questions to ask them.
It never occurred to me to professionalise it and say, well,
why wouldn't every person that does a lot of directing grab a couple
of other directors and make a regular get-together or some kind
of WhatsApp group, signal group?
One thing that came up was really interesting was I read a book
by a guy called Chris Hatfield who was a,
an astronaut, a former fighter, Canadian fighter pilot, test pilot,
was maybe one of the first Canadians ever to go into space,
went up to the space station for six months.
And he wrote a really interesting book because he did a clip
that became famous.
He did a cover of the David Bowie song and recorded it
on the space station because he took up a guitar.
And it landed on YouTube as they were in the Soyuz craft
coming back to Earth.
And so when they got, he landed in Kazakhstan, they opened the latch,
you know, still steaming.
And the Russian expert got the latch open,
leant in and he goes, hey, Chris, I love your video.
And so it had hit six million views by the time they left
the space station to come back out.
So a publisher approached him and said, I'll write a book.
But there's a chapter in the book and he talked about when you go
into a new situation as an expert, highly trained,
about taking a back seat.
And he said it even, and he talked about being a one or a zero.
And it was this chapter in the book.
He said it even mattered when he turned up to the space station.
And by sheer chance, I was on a conversation panel sitting next
to Chris Hatfield one day.
And after we finished, I said, listen, I've got to ask you
about the book.
And I want to ask you about the chapter about being a one or a zero.
And he stopped and he said, if no one's read the book,
people always ask me a question about space.
If they've read the book, the one thing they ask me about is
that chapter, about turning up to an elite situation, highly trained,
and not making a dick of yourself.
Yeah, it's a great story, Rob, isn't it?
That clip is so famous.
Can you explain a little bit more the one and the zero for those
that don't understand what that means?
There's a brilliant story around, that I've heard you tell before,
around the selection process for those elite astronauts who are obviously
all at a seriously high achieving level.
Yeah, so they're all guns.
They're all the best of the best.
But people are making judgments about you all the time.
And he surmised,
that the one thing people don't want is someone who's trying too hard
or a pest or trying to garner plaudits or applause or just turn up
and do the job you're trained for.
And, you know, he called it being a zero.
And he said the mistake everyone makes is they turn up
and they want to be the hero day one.
And he said it's not needed because the people who are running the show
when you turn up really want you
to make a contribution but not get in the way
because the process has already been worked out.
He explains it much better than that.
But I think everyone makes the mistake that you go,
oh, my best way of making a contribution is, you know,
trying so hard on my pest.
I might be mixing stories here, Rob,
but I remember talking to you about potentially there was,
when those guys got together, it was a cocktail function where other,
you know, people were trying to make a contribution.
Experts were looking at their behaviour and how they turned up
and interacted with others at literally a function
where they thought they weren't being assessed.
Is that part of the criteria?
That's right.
They thought they were assessed for something else,
but the people were just looking at them going, you know,
is he the type of astronaut that I can put up with for six months
in a space station?
Rob, you mentioned some of your hobbies and you've been described to me
in the past few days in research as a man of many hobbies
and you've been described to me as a man of many hobbies.
And you mentioned fishing and golf and you've got your pilot's licence.
I think you've got your helicopter licence as well and go-karting.
I never finished my helicopter licence, but that's something, you know,
if I didn't have five dependents, I think I'd go back to.
That's on the list.
But you tend to turn your hobbies into these extraordinary.
Look at fishing and then, you know, the series you created,
A River Somewhere, you end up fishing in the Bhutan and Wyoming,
Venezuela.
So you take something.
But the way your mind works, it goes to an intricate level.
Tell me about the fishing part because I want to talk to you about golf as well
and how you approach that.
Fishing was funny because I used to listen to Rex Hunt's fishing show
before I fished and I used to  I've always enjoyed impersonating people
and I used to walk around impersonating Rex Hunt and Tom Gleisner,
who was a fisherman at the time, I used to turn up and I'd go,
you know, folks, I was up on the banks of the Acheron and I cut my teeth
and so I became.
I'm knowledgeable about fishing, having never fished because three years
of listening to the Rex Hunt fishing show.
And one day Tom Gleisner said, look, how about, do you want to go fishing?
And I go, oh, yeah, that'd be great.
And so one Sunday we headed up to a lake near Daylesford in Victoria
and it was just the most magnificent day and we were casting our little lures,
got a couple of redfin trout, you know, taking our lunch in there,
the birds were chirping and all this.
And I go  and I just  as we were driving out, the sun was setting
and I just thought it couldn't be more perfect.
The filtered light came through and landed on a sign saying,
fishing prohibited.
So he'd taken me to a place where fishing was prohibited.
Your approach to golf is a fascinating insight for me as well.
So it's unravelled many a person, the game of golf, me included.
But
Yeah.
And you've played for a long time.
But tell me the story.
You went to the elite golf program at Victoria University and said,
take me on.
What age were you?
Oh, we were mid-30s, late-30s.
So we were surrounded  what happened was a friend made the point,
they said, why would you only have elite training methods for elite players?
They're probably more useful for hacks like us.
And so we were all, you know, as I said, we were 24,
which isn't
so much a handicap as a participation ribbon.
And I've always loved science and he had a contact
at the Victorian Institute of Sport, a guy  we were quite innovative.
A guy called Vern became quite famous for developing these programs.
You know, golf was the one that, you know,
people were walking around with a beer belly and he sort of
he was one of the people that ushered in what was called the flat tummy golfers,
you know, the Tiger Woods and all that.
And we thought, well, if we're going to do exercises and drills and sort of things,
why would we do the dumb ones?
Why wouldn't we do the smart ones?
So we went down to the VAS and he was kind enough to speak to us
and we put that to him.
We said, why don't you let some hack golfers do your program?
And he said, oh, gee, that sounds interesting.
And so we set about, you know, doing all these  you know, now it's commonplace,
but back then it was groundbreaking.
And it was very little weights.
And it was all body weight and resistance bands.
And it was really  it was interesting as well as being fun.
And so we worked at it.
And, you know, I'm sure  someone said to me at the end of it, you know,
my aim was to get down to single figures, which I did.
And I said, what was the real secret?
And I said, it's probably playing twice a week.
After all that.
Yeah, extraordinary, isn't it, to see.
Yeah.
There in your life and you can see there's a systematic and thought out and getting a
shortcut going to who's the best in your area.
Is there other habits and things that you do daily, Rob, that set you up for success?
Funny enough, I make no mistake.
I reckon I'm as haphazard as everybody.
The biggest thing I find is it's  you've got to let the habit do the work for you in
just about anything.
that's you know if you leave it to your to your vibe on the day it's it's not that's what i said
about one of the best things we ever did in at working dogs we got an office and we got an office
sorted out properly and sort of there was no formality to turning up but you know informally
we ended up everyone you know gee well if you're going to turn up every day at 8 30 i better i
guess i better that and then and that's a i think that's a really good habit i can't remember
the sort of science on this seems to vary but you know 30 days 50 days creates a habit
and after that i think it the effort of something gets hard because the habit does the work for you
now rob we've been talking to a range of of leaders in this space and and finding that there
are a handful of dimensions or characters of leaders in this 21st century style which you
sum up perfectly the way you approach life and the way you
approach life and the way you approach life and the way you approach life and the way you
approach your directing and everything in your life and answer these as expansively or as short
as you like, but you might be over it by now, but-
Fruits, fruit, kiwi fruit, kiwi fruit.
That's it. That's over. You've got it in one. We've been talking about self-leadership first
for people as probably the dimension to start with. What do you think of when I
ask you about self-leadership? I struggle a little bit with discipline.
I go, in some ways, I envy having the people that have an elite sporting ability at a young age.
I reckon if you had to pick the best training ground, I think sport does it. I think it's fun.
It's physical and fun. My thing was the best thing that ever happened to me, I think there's
always a, I keep saying, there's always a bit of luck in how things turn out. My luck was finding
that the creative,
arts were team-based and I went, oh, this is, I'm not in the under 14 Bs. It's the same fun,
but it's actually, you can do it at a higher level. And the team aspect was the thing that
really captured you, Rob, the fact that you could creatively work together?
Yeah. Some people wake up one day and I want to be a solo artist. I wanted to be in a band.
And clearly you have a positive impact, having been around you enough,
on your environment. How do you think about positively impacting other people in your
environment? This is a good subject because I declared before we talk about, I don't know
the answer to this. I reckon advice is a really, really hard thing to give. And so I sort of skirt
advice now because it's sometimes, it's like you're speaking at a frequency no one's hearing.
But one of the things that I think is helpful is you talk about mistakes.
And I reckon you're, that's a way, it gives the person the opportunity to turn it over in their
own heads and work out what's to learn from it. I think coming through the front door and goes,
here's what you should do, I think is, has got a very low success rate.
Yeah, that's interesting. So you're, the actual straight up, a bit of advice just doesn't land,
but you're talking about being open to your own mistakes and saying, hey, this is something that
has gone wrong with me.
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Save yourself the heartache. Don't do this.
Or don't do this is no good. But it's saying, you know, just in case this overlaps with you,
here's a big mistake I make, or here's something that I, if I had my time over again, I probably
could have, there's a better shortcut than that one. And I think talking like that
resonates with people a bit more than, and I sometimes think even people that ask for advice,
it's a bit of a, it's a bit of a, it's a bit of a, it's a bit of a, it's a bit of a, it's a bit of a,
it's, you can't give them advice. You've got to couch it in terms of, look, this may not apply to
you. Here's a, there's a bit of a split in the paths here. You know, I took this path and it
didn't work out. You know, if in doubt, take, go the other way.
And historically, that's something that never happened, is it? We never, people, you know,
admitting you had a fault or a mistake or wasn't really an option for people in leadership roles.
If you've got an example, Rob, is there, I mean, you look at your career and everything looks as
though it just turns out to go.
Is there a mistake that you could share with us that comes to mind that maybe humanizes you
slightly? It's funny. It's funny. When, when we get together, the things, the things you exchange
are not, are not the success stories, are they? Like funny stories, success stories aren't the
funny stories. It's true. It's, it's, it's sort of, it's kind of like, I can't, I can't think of,
you know, moments when,
you know, you're an absolute idiot.
But, but like, it's, it is funny. It's not so much a work thing, but I, all of us at Working Dog
and, and all of my wider comedy friends, our currency is, is stories where, funny stories
at the expense of yourself. Yeah. They just seem to be funny. It's like, like it's one,
I had the privilege of, of going to,
to launch the dish in South Africa. We were, quite a lot of countries picked it up and we had a
relationship with a distributor and we went over, this one hurts. We, we went over, over there and
they said, we landed in Cape Town and they're really hosting just wonderfully. And they said,
oh, did you want to go out to Robben Island?
And I said, you know, which was the prison where Nelson Mandela was held. And, and I,
and I wasn't hearing the full thing. And he said, oh, you can, we leave early at seven and I'm going,
God, I'm so jet-lagged. And then we've got to get up really early. And so I sort of didn't fully
hear it, but we can get in there before the tourism, because we can get a tour with, and I,
and I didn't quite hear what was said. And so anyway, we, we arrived at the boat, took out the,
the sort of the wardens that looked after the place
and there was this quite a diminutive sort of fellow
of Indian descent who was waiting for us and I wasn't properly
introduced to him and he was talking to one of the people
on the boat and anyway, we started, he started walking us
around Robben Island and he seemed to know a hell of a lot
about Robben Island and I'm going and I knew a fair bit
about the story and I think I said something like at one point,
you seem to know a lot about Robben Island.
Where did that come from?
It probably wasn't as bad as that.
Don't tell me it was Nelson.
No, he said, well, I was imprisoned here for 27 years with Nelson.
Oh, wow.
And I've gone and then the pennies dropped.
It was Amit Kothrada who was, there was five, six and as the words,
I don't know that I said it as badly as that but he was as generous
as that back to and he just smiled and he said, well,
you know, being in prison with Nelson for 18 or something years was
and as I'm looking at him, he's looking at me, he's going,
you've got to take a few deep breaths now, my friend.
I love that overlap and that to me is the overlap of sport, isn't it?
A currency is exactly the same thing.
You don't talk about your success, you talk about the many moments
like that.
That stays with you for a while, that one.
Yeah, that stayed with me for a while.
It's incredible.
One of the dimensions we talk about, Rob, is the ability to have a vision
and create and share it.
How do you think about that in the context of what you do,
creating and sharing a vision?
One thing I think with us is you've got to have an idea you love
and that gives the momentum and then it's the goal.
But we don't put all the chips in one basket.
We test and we do pilots and our industry has sort of in some ways
lost the art of that.
You know, in the old days,
there was a lot of development before you went to air and now things
have almost got to be ready.
So we take a lot of that offline and try and enjoy that process
because, you know, you've got to get rid of the easy mistakes
before the public see it.
Yeah, the goal, I think a big goal helps.
I reckon a big goal is I think that that's the shorthand way
of communicating with everyone.
And prepared if you've got something, get it out there.
Get it out there, test it.
Yeah.
Is it the gap between you having an idea and testing it?
Is that pretty sure?
Do you tend to put them out there?
Yeah, we tend to test a lot because, I mean,
the whole digital industry can do that so easily these days.
So in all that beta testing they do, it's a test.
A lot of the great inventions of the world were really just tinkerers
doing test, test, test, you know.
It's sort of when you read the Dyson vacuum cleaner,
you read his story.
He was, you know, it wasn't quantum physics.
1,287 iterations, I think, or thereabouts in his shed at the back
having nearly sold the farm.
It's a great story, isn't it?
Really running out of money, you know, and just one after another iteration
to get that right.
Well, actually, if he's still listening, Luke,
could he come up with a better battery?
We'll get on to Sir James and give him that feedback.
I've heard you talk a lot about curiosity,
and we see that as being a really shared trait of leaders like yourself.
And then people with curiosity and how they approach their own learning
and development, does that resonate with you?
What are your thoughts on curiosity?
So that comes, you know, some things come easily to you,
and that does for me.
I've always been really curious as a person,
and so I sort of think that's effortless for me.
It's funny, if you can tell someone to be curious,
I think you either.
You either are.
I reckon one of the most underestimated factors is enthusiasm.
I think a lot of people think it's cool to be, you know,
a bit of a flat affect and a bit, you know, a bit emotionless.
And I don't reckon, I reckon that undersells the influence
enthusiasm can have.
In fact, I think, you know, just about every subject on leadership,
there's a Winston Churchill quote, but I think this is Winston Churchill
who said,
success is maintaining enthusiasm through repeated failure.
And there's a lot, I reckon there's a lot in that.
I reckon enthusiasm gets you up.
Talk about communication a lot, Rob, and speaking in the recent days
to a couple of your close friends, and they've talked about your ability
to communicate as being extraordinary and in the director's chair
or wherever you are to just have a way of being able just to hit
the right note at the right time with the right person.
Is that something that, again,
has that come easy to you or the way you communicate with clarity,
is that something you've had to work on?
I reckon you get, if you haven't thought it through enough,
you get a bit wordy.
You just crap on a bit.
You circle around the point just looking for a place to land.
But sometimes, you know, you, I think that's why a lot of people,
you know, say, oh, they have sleepless nights.
What they're trying to do is think of a really simple way to explain their
point, and that's worth a lot, I reckon.
I reckon, you know, it's, I don't think you want to be giving
10-page papers on what you're trying to solve.
I reckon a couple of simple sentences is the big key, you know,
and I reckon when you're running a shoot, you have to set the tone.
Sometimes the tone goes off a bit, and you just want to,
before a read-through, I'll think about it all night.
I'll go.
Literally give myself a word limit, you know, two sentences and a let's get
started, and, you know, sometimes, so it's not banging on about how we all
need to just concentrate a bit more.
It might be something for I reckon we're turning up a little underprepared
after lunch or, but I reckon one or two sentences, if you keep it short,
it has a good effect.
If you bang on, I reckon you're diluted.
Yeah, word economy.
That's interesting.
That is interesting.
But make no mistake, Luke, I can crap on with the best.
I'm talking about my best moments.
I was self-reflecting as you were saying that as well, Rob,
and I probably held you here a bit longer than I probably promised you as well.
Collaboration is another final dimension that we're talking about a lot
and that all the great leaders that we're seeing coming through are collaborators,
and you've identified that at a young age that you said you weren't a solo artist,
you wanted to be in the band.
How important is that collaboration?
How important has collaboration been to you?
I think that's possibly the area where you do need to know yourself or, you know,
what's that old saying is when someone tells you who they are, believe them.
Well, when your instinct tells you who you are, don't put your square peg in a round hole.
You know, if you really are that solo person, then be the solo person.
And if you're not, you know, it does go back to that.
It takes a bit of flying hours to be a good collaborator.
But, you know, patience is always in short supply,
especially when you get a whole bunch of driven people together, you know.
So I think we all, a bit of manners, a bit of patience, you know,
but I don't think it's a sin to be driven.
A couple of final questions, Rob, that I've been asking across the board,
and I'll start with this one.
Who has been the greatest leader in your life?
That's really, really interesting.
Because I saw...
There were moments when people had a huge effect in a short period of time.
And I was saying that the Dean of Medicine at Royal Melbourne Hospital was,
you know, you don't get there by chance.
And all I remember was I was fully expecting to be, you know,
the severe guy out of the Paper Chase movie, you know, the Harvard professor.
Who doesn't take prisoners.
And I'm sure he was all of that.
But sort of just that moment of kindness and understanding and mischief.
He goes, geez, take a year off and tour a show.
That sounds good.
Like that happened so quickly.
And he said something to me once, and I went,
I've never forgotten and tend to repeat it a lot.
When you think about all the things that people aim at,
he just sort of...
He dropped his voice once to me and he said, you know what, Rob,
at the end of the day, what we really, really value is the respect of our peers.
And he went, God, that's a really powerful...
Like you see that in footballers.
You see it in every form of life that don't underestimate how important
that incentive is to garner the respect of your peers.
Amazing how much impact one moment can have, isn't it, as you said,
potentially a pathway.
And life changes on that one conversation.
It's an amazing story going all the way back to your life in medical school.
Final question, Rob, and I'm supremely appreciative of your time
and I've always enjoyed any moment to catch up with you.
But in the spirit of collaboration, I wanted to ask you if there was one person
anywhere in the world at any time that you could collaborate with,
is there a name that comes to mind?
Jeez, that's really...
There tend to be.
There tend to be someone.
And funnily enough, you go, as an actor, if you had the right thing,
it'd be someone like, I know this sounds funny, someone like Will Ferrell.
You go, because I've met Will.
And the minute we sort of thought the complete opposite of what you thought,
Hollywood star, we were going to ask him to do something
and he just stopped and went, what's that?
How do we do that?
And he went, oh, God, what a dream.
As crazy and silly as he is, he's a really smart guy
and he really loves the outcome.
Like in a, I think it is in a silly sense, or someone, I don't know,
I said this the other day, is I'm not sure whether I actually do shows
because I want the end product or that I want the social life
that's attached to doing shows.
I've realised at this point I really enjoy the social life
that's attached with a project.
And so someone like Jon Stewart,
who did The Daily Show for many, many years,
I reckon guys like that are really good at setting up a good social life
attached to the project.
So just understanding that, Rob, the enjoyment for you is, you know,
not so much the end outcome of whatever success looks like,
but the collaboration and the team and the enjoyment along the way.
Is that the thing?
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
I don't know.
I don't, everyone, I've met a lot of people often,
often,
you know, American friends who, they do projects and they get to the end of it
and there was no fun involved.
And I reckon I've reached a stage where I'm not up for that anymore.
You know, Gia was a terrible shoot, but the film was great.
I don't, I don't, I don't have that in me.
Aligned with you very much on that, Rob.
The joy of the teams that you're in is really, for me,
the same essence of where the fun is, whatever you do.
Well, it's funny.
I love hearing sporting teams say, in actual fact,
it often goes hand in hand.
And often when you look at those Netflix docos and all that sort of stuff,
you, you, the best teams often got, got on pretty well.
Agree.
And, and you realise, you know,
lucky enough to play sport for a living for, for over a decade.
And, and, and when you do that,
that amount of time and you literally shower together three times a day,
there's not much left in terms of if you don't get on and they end up being
these great lifelong friendships, which is the real joy.
We spoke about the, would you be jealous because you didn't win the ultimate
prize and that was definitely there for a while.
But what you realise is that you get these great friendships for life out of
shared passion and I'm very fortunate to have been part of that.
There's something interesting about the ultimate, ultimate prize.
There's a, there's a psychiatrist or a psychologist in Los Angeles who's
become famous for giving therapy to, you know, elite actors.
And he, he talks about something like Oscar syndrome and that is,
he sometimes have to prepare actors that are red hot favourite to win for the
aftermath because in their mind,
they've been so focused on that being the purpose of their life.
And he has to explain to them that there's going to be this slow shock that
sets in after you win, that everyone's life goes back to normal.
And 99.9% of people don't care.
And he said, it's a real syndrome.
And I sort of think if you broaden that out, if you take him at his word,
it sounds like, you know, he's been doing it for 20 years.
It sounds like it's true.
Sometimes you're so goal orientated, you make the mistake of thinking,
achieving the goal solves everything.
And I think we all suspect that's not how it works.
It's a great point you make.
And I can relate to when you, having finished working in the media immediately
after playing footy, you finish your career, everyone wants to win the
premiership and you don't.
And there's that pang of regret about not achieving what you essentially set
out to do.
And then I had the, for the first seven years after I played,
it'd be in the winning rooms grand final day every year and interviewing
often players that end up being old teammates of mine that had gone on to,
and it could cross down to you in the rooms.
Here's Brian Lake, you've won your third premiership.
And part of you is trying to say, for God's sake, man,
if you had to try that hard when we were playing,
I might've been able to achieve it with you.
And then speaking to mates who did go on to win one and their reflection,
Rob, you know, over a beer would be, do you know what?
It wasn't as good as you thought it was going to be.
It was, it was great,
but it didn't change your life shortly afterwards you were back.
And I'm not sure if that was more frustrating or, you know,
it definitely took me seven years to get over it,
but I can relate to that for sure.
And it's amazing how soon after you have to put the bins out,
just like you did before.
Rob, I love catching up with you.
I'm always inspired and enlightened by any conversation with you and really
appreciate your time and lots of fascinating thoughts as always,
and really appreciate everything that you do.
And,
and it's great to catch up with you again today.
I love chatting Luke off and on air.
Thank you.
Thanks Rob.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me,
Luke Darcy produced by Matt Dwyer with audio production by Darcy Thompson.
Start your leadership journey.
I encourage you to go to elitacollective.com,
take our Empowering Leaders Indicator Tool and understand the impact you have
on your environment.
Join us at Elita to learn,
lead and collaborate.