Our next guest on the Empowering Leaders podcast
is Roger Gillespie, the founder of Baker's Delight.
I love catching up with him in person
and the strong sense of values comes through,
his passion for ethical leadership
and the idea that everyone in business should win,
your suppliers, your customers, your partners.
It's an incredible legacy that he has.
Everyone wins.
You stay in business longer.
If there's a lopsided relationship, it doesn't work.
Look, if you don't treat your wife well,
she won't stay around.
It's the same thing.
You've got to have a win-win.
Very closely aligned with the work that we're doing at Alita,
where leaders are getting together to connect,
to learn and to share
and what we think is a life-changing opportunity.
I hope you enjoy this chat with Roger Gillespie,
the founder of Baker's Delight, as much as I did.
Roger Gillespie is a fourth-generation baker.
In 19...
In 1980, he and his wife, Lesley,
opened the first Baker's Delight in Melbourne's Glenferry Road, Hawthorne,
with the aim of making enough money
to be able to choose the schools they wanted their kids to attend.
40 years later, Baker's Delight has over 700 stores
across Australia, New Zealand and North America,
becoming one of Australia's greatest-ever business success stories.
Roger and his family are celebrated
for their outstanding contribution and philanthropy,
including the Prime Minister's Award for Excellence
in Community Business Partnership
for their work with the Breast Cancer Network Australia.
They've raised over $20 million in the past 20 years.
Roger, it's great to catch up with you in person.
I really appreciate your time today.
Well, it's a pleasure to be here, Luke,
and thanks for the invitation.
Can I go back to 1980 to start with...
You opened that first store in Glenferry Road, Hawthorne.
Could you believe 40 years later
that you'd employ more than 15,000 people in a 700-store?
I mean, was it even possible in your mind?
It was possible, but it wasn't a dream at that point.
People often say, well, where did you get the idea?
Well, the idea just evolved.
We had one store,
and then there was another opportunity for another one,
so we took it, another one, another one,
and then a whole lot more people wanted to be part of it,
so we just kept going.
And I'm an addict, I should mention.
I'll fess up straight away.
I'm addicted to opening bakeries.
If I don't open one for a month, I get the shakes,
and I have to keep at it.
Well, does that come from your dad?
I'll jump into there, because there's a famous line,
I think he said to you, you know, as a baker himself,
people always want to eat bread.
It was...
Pretty reasonable thought, isn't it?
Yeah, yeah.
Well, and that's been true so far,
and it's looking good for the future.
You started with a business partner,
a guy by the name of Gary Stevenson,
and a handful of years in, you're buying him out.
Can I ask you about that?
Was that a difficult thing to do?
And I suppose if you're Gary, does he look back and think,
gee, I might have been well advised to hang around
with Roger and Leslie?
Yeah, well, sadly, we've lost contact with him,
and I'd like to be able to catch up with him.
I haven't seen him for, I'd say, 15 years.
I think we had a celebration.
We hit 25 years, and he came along to that.
But he wanted to follow his dream and be in the IT world,
so he'd had enough of bakeries, so he said,
I want to get out, so we bought him out.
There are lots of bakeries around the world, Roger.
Why has Baker's Delight, in your mind, been such a success?
Well, I think it comes from our actual name,
which ironically we don't have the same name in Canada,
but we...
are equally successful.
But we live to delight.
You know, when we thought of the name, we said, well, we're bakers,
and we want to delight every customer,
and we want to be delighted as bakers
when we pull a loaf of bread out of the oven.
We want that delight to be felt in our own staff
and then pass that delight on to every customer.
And we still are true to that, to the name,
and to ignite that passion for anyone who wants to join us.
So when I used to recruit franchisees,
I'd say,
you have to be so enthusiastic about, you know,
delighting every customer that you've got to walk through a brick wall
and then crawl across broken glass if you want to be part of this business.
That's how enthusiastic you have to be.
And that's sort of instilled.
It's part of our culture that you've got to be committed
to delighting every customer every day.
And it is the values that when you read about your history
that you live and, you know, you train people and crew.
And you're a great part of the communities that you live in.
And all the stores are really attached to their...
Can you kind of pick on what you said before?
Because it's interesting.
You think of this great brand now, Baker's Delight,
and it's a brilliant name, and you live it with your values.
But in Canada, where you're growing, you know, exponentially,
it's Cobb's?
It's Cobb's Bread, yeah.
So why the change in that part of the world?
Well, we tried to use Baker's Delight there.
We got the lawyers to do a company search,
and there was a company there called Bakery Delight,
spelled slightly differently.
And they sold muffin mix.
And in Australia, we'd be able to sort of cohabitate using the brands,
for different businesses, but we couldn't do it.
So we asked them for permission and offered them some money.
And they quickly turned to their lawyers
and asked for 10 times more than what we'd offered them.
And our offer was 100 grand, and they wanted a million.
We didn't know whether we were going to succeed or not.
So we said, well, we're opening them as company-owned bakeries,
so they're company-owned bakeries, Cobb's.
And then we discovered later that it also stands for Canada's Own Bread
and a few other acronyms,
Cunning Old Baker.
And the same sort of design.
People go into our Canadian stores and discuss it.
This is a rip-off from Baker's Delight.
And similarly, Canadians come to our store here and say,
this is a rip-off of Cobb's Bread.
So we talk about you and your values, which you're renowned for,
and I read about you really obsessed with win-wins for your franchises.
Is their success paramount to you?
Yeah.
Your ongoing success, and you talk about the loyalty to your suppliers.
Some of them have been with you for decades and decades,
and it's customer first.
I love that message, Roger.
In a world now where I feel like everyone in business is trying to get a win
over someone else, or there's got to be a winner and a loser,
can you explain why that's worked so well for you?
It was – I don't know when we first sort of realised that that's the way we work,
but it's every relationship we have has to be a win-win.
So whether it's a customer,
whether it's a customer coming and getting love for bread,
the customer has to be happy to pay whatever they pay
to receive the product they love and enjoy.
We have to be happy to pay for the price of flour.
We have to be happy to pay certain rents.
Sadly, that doesn't happen as often as it should, but it's getting better.
So it's just everyone wins.
You stay in business longer.
If there's a lopsided relationship, it doesn't work.
If you don't treat your wife well, she won't stay around.
It's the same thing.
you know, you've got to have a win-win. Everyone has to be happy, both sides of the equation. If
you're not, it doesn't last. Simple as that. Well, it sounds like old-fashioned values,
Roger, but when you think about it, it is good business, isn't it? And it's sustainable,
and it's happier business, isn't it? And I mean, you know, you get a win over someone and they
lose. I mean, I am a bit of a believer in the karmic cycle comes around eventually, isn't it?
So having said that, I mean, it's not utopia, is it? I mean, you have people that don't work out,
but franchisees that aren't up to it. And so I read some of your language there, and correct me
if I'm wrong, hire slowly, fire quickly. So explain a bit more about why that's important to you.
Well, if you've got an infection in your body, if you don't deal with it, you'll get sicker.
So it's the same, you know, the old saying of a rotten apple in a case causes all the apples to
go off. So you've really got to weed the garden regularly and get rid of the components that
aren't working. If you don't do that, the...
The negative drags down the positive and the whole thing goes pretty ugly. And we don't want that.
So your instinct is when you get an instinct that someone's just not up to it,
you really should act quickly.
Yeah. Yeah. Have to. Yeah. And sadly, we don't always, but wherever we can, we do.
I love self-made stories. And it's so brilliant to sit along across from you now to tell...
To someone listening to this who wants to start, wants to have a go, has got an idea,
what do you say to an aspiring entrepreneur?
Be clear on what you're trying to achieve, get good people to help you, get good legal advice,
but be committed, 100% committed, you know, walking through the brick wall and
crawl across broken glass. It will be harder than you think, it will take longer than you think,
and it will cost more than you think. So if you go in with your eyes open,
realizing those three things, you're more likely to succeed. But if you're half-hearted,
it won't work. You've got to be 100% committed,
and really get other people supporting you, and get other people on board to
celebrate your idea and make it happen with you.
But genuinely have a go. I can see that in you.
Exactly. If you don't have a go, you know, like your early career as a football player,
18 men line up on each side, same weight, same, you know, but the ones who are more determined,
more skilled, follow the coach, do the job properly, they come out the winner. Simple.
That's how life works in almost every situation. Baker's Delight, Roger, is a genuine family
business.
It is you and Leslie who founded it, and now the succession planning, your daughter,
Elise, her husband, David, are joint CEOs in this part of the world, and your son, Aaron,
heads up the North American business. We all know families have ups and downs, businesses have ups
and downs. How have you treaded that path so successfully to be able to manage, you know,
family and siblings and kids working together, and you working with Leslie so effectively?
Well, we started with the next generation 15 years ago. We had a fellow called Michael Andrew,
who sadly passed away three years ago. He chaired our family council, which we set up about 15 years
ago, and the kids weren't really interested at that point. All of them were working in Canada
and living in Canada. Our daughter and her husband lived there for eight years, and they were working
together, and they were working well, but Elise wanted to come back to Australia, and her husband's
South African. He didn't care where he lived as long as he was with her. It's their 12th wedding
anniversary today, by the way.
But they, so they came along to this first meeting, and KPMG prepared a whole lot of information about,
you know, where the assets were and blah, blah, blah. And then we had another meeting six months
later, and then Michael said to them, well, remember the last meeting? And they all looked
blankly and couldn't remember anything from the previous meeting. You know, the first couple of
years, we'd meet twice a year, and then they suddenly became interested. Well, I say suddenly
after two or three years, and they're more and more interested. Now we meet four times a year,
as a family council, to look at our philanthropic interests as well as our business interests and try
and look at Baker Slider's owners. So we just had a three-day retreat in Canada last month to do a
sort of high-level review of where we want to go with the business and where we want to go with
our other investments and our philanthropy. So it was fantastic. But if you don't do those,
put in the time and start early, like the kids were in their 20s when we started. They're now
both in their 40s.
And it's working, I think, very well. You know, they've taken control. I'm chairman of the board.
Leslie's on the board as well. We go to the office for other things. I'm going to office today for a
separate meeting, nothing to do with Baker's Delight. And that's more often the reason I'm
there for other things rather than Baker's Delight. So it's worked well. But get in early if you want
to do succession plans. When we were in Canada, we also went to this business association meeting,
so family business association.
I don't know how often it happens, but it happened to be on where we were there and our son's on the
board of it. So he said, come along. And amongst the various presenters, there were a whole lot of
families presenting. Some stories were good and some not so good. There was one fellow there.
He said, oh, yeah, I got cancer in 2007 and I thought I better do something about my succession
planning. I'm just getting started now in 2022. That's a horror story. You know, the guy's in his
70s and just getting started. It's just, you know, it's a horror story.
It's crazy.
Well, it's really generous of you to share that story because, you know, family is personal and
yours is such a great example. But we also know families that achieve success, particularly,
you know, high net worth families, the complexity. And there are horror stories out there everywhere,
aren't there? And you would have seen them in the community where siblings, you know,
turn on each other. And so what you're saying is initially you weren't going to try and convince
them to be part of Baker's Delight. It was just about planning and giving them a line of sight on
every area of the family.
Yeah, yeah. Because if something happened to Leslie and I, well, I had a bunch of assets that they had
to look after and philanthropic commitments that they had to follow through. So, you know,
they're equally, you know, there's our daughter-in-law who's not in the business, but
she sits on family council. She's equally committed to all of our philanthropic endeavors as our
two children and our son-in-law. So, but it's been a gradual evolving process. It's not something
that we've forced on them.
Continuing to own Baker's Delight, that was a conscious decision by them and it's a conscious
decision again as of last month that they want to stay as owners. Whether they stay as executives,
that's up to them in the next few years. But for now, they're executives and they're owners.
So, that could change in the future, the executive part, but ownership is very clear in their minds.
So, you've got to be clear on what your role is, whether you're an owner, whether you're an
executive.
Or whether you just want to sit on the beach and take in the dividend. None of us are that
way inclined.
And I suppose there'll be people listening to this where they'll say, you know, it's
a potentially an easy to scale. I would argue against that actually, that often it gets
more complex with more assets and more things. But I'm sitting here listening going, it's
a good message for, you know, a father of four and at whatever level it is to include,
you know, not wait until tragedy or the end, isn't it? To start those conversations now
around sharing.
Yeah.
And family council can happen at any level, doesn't it? You don't have to have enormous
assets to distribute.
No, exactly.
So, it's a great message to pass on. And part of your profile, I understand, was the
Myer Foundation's Leadership Institute. And you were promoting responsible leadership
and ethical practices. You were part of that. It was inspired by the Aspen Institute in
the US.
That's right.
You know, who recognized there was a lot more focus on management rather than great leadership.
Can you tell me about your passion for ethical leadership?
Yeah, I don't know where that comes from other than seeing unethical leadership. You
know, that's sort of my inspiration is to say, well, no, there's got to be a better
way. And I served on the Kranlana board for 20 years until it was merged with Monash University
a few years ago. And that's the Myer spin-off you're making reference to. And I stayed on
that because I believed in what they were doing as an enterprise and that there needed
to be more ethical training.
There's a lot of ethical training, particularly in big companies, but it happens in small
companies as well. People do the wrong thing. They cheat on suppliers. They give out the
wrong information. They tell one supplier what another one's doing and that sort of
stuff. And it's just bad for everybody. It doesn't end well. So I'm motivated to see
more people behaving ethically because it's better for everybody. It's the basis of the
win-win philosophy. You know, it's just so simple to do things properly and look after
people probably and live ethically. If you don't, I think it's a bad way to live.
And Roger, that's the basis for this podcast. What you said then effectively is trying to
share stories around what we think great leadership looks like. And we think a real
shift around more people understanding what you got early on and that is ethical leadership and
the idea of being self-reflective and collaborative and wanting to pass on and share and learn from
each other as well is our stories worth telling because you sometimes zoom out and you see
globally, we've got examples of leadership that's heading the other way as well. And we know it has
a devastating effect on people. You work in a business where someone hasn't got a sense of
great leadership, but can be a horrible thing for people, can't it? I've never worked in
such an environment, but I imagine it would be horrible. And I've seen it from a distance.
And then you look at...
What's happening in the world now with Ukraine and Russia, it's just, it's horrible as all wars
are, but it's unnecessary as well. And there's no reason for it other than one man being a
megalomaniac is what I'd say, but there's no ethics there.
And devastating.
Bad ethics and devastating outcomes.
Yeah. It's horrible. Often when you sit down for a podcast, Roger, you do what I just did. It's like
700 stores and great success and family planning. And...
That overlooks the bumps and the hurdles along the way, which there has to be many. I mean,
can you share one? Was there a famous time where you think, God, I made a blue there or a mistake
or one that you had to rectify?
One that springs to mind, it must be 15 years ago now. For some reason, we got investigated by the
ACCC. There's some franchisees accused us of doing the wrong thing. And the ACCC did this investigation.
And in the end, the...
We were exonerated. There was nothing to have to fess up about. But it was a horrible thing because
we knew we hadn't done anything wrong. But these other people who thought we had, or for whatever
reason, complained to the ACCC and it was enough for them to do this investigation. But in the end,
we got this very nice long letter, which we had framed and hung in our office for a few years.
And since we've renovated, that's disappeared.
But it was a...
A fantastic response from the then head of the ACCC. So that's one thing that sticks in my mind.
Other horrible situations where franchisees get sick and die, horrible.
Yeah.
But it's just, that's life. We met a widow of a franchisee in Canada just last month. This fellow
died only a few months ago. When he started his training about three or four years ago to become
a franchisee, he was perfectly...
Well, just as he opened his bakery, he was diagnosed with some sort of cancer. Then he was
treated, overcome, and then it came back three years later and he died. But horrible. But it's
nothing to do with us. It's just that you live in a community of hundreds or thousands of people
within our business. Things are likely to go wrong. People... There's another one I was talking about
recently. A fellow had three bakeries, it'd be 15, 20 years ago, and became a gambler,
lost his money. He was a gambler. He was a gambler. He was a gambler. He was a gambler. He was a gambler.
everything his wife his daughter you know estranged from him lost his bakeries lost everything and
two million dollars down the drain horrible but you can't do anything about it other than
you know help restore the businesses that are serving that community that the people lived in
and that's what we did we were able to find new franchisees for those businesses and
everything resumed normality in that particular town and now it's a booming area with a few more
bakeries in that area so it's fantastic to do it but when you're in the middle of a horrible
situation like that it's just it's where you've got to stand up and be decisive and do what's
right for everyone involved you can't just live in hope and you know pull the blanket over your
head and think well that'll pass you know it doesn't pass you've got to make things pass you've
got to say well that's not
right so we're going to fix it and life isn't about an absence of challenges isn't it it's
they're there and you i could see your mind going how many do you want because of course that that's
the truth but you can feel your sense of values kick in and it's like how do we do the right thing
in whatever situation uh arises and so yeah i appreciate i don't know whether it's just in me
but i tend to forget the bad things and remember the good ones you know like uh my wife and i have
a breakfast every day we get our computers out and see how sales are going around the
world and we've just opened a bunch of new bakeries in canada and they're doing remarkably
well so we zoom in on them so how they're going and yeah and then occasionally go what about the
ones that are not going so well so we better have a look at them as well but you focus on the good
news and then make that happen more that's amazing how much the the bad news can just sort of not
someone's got to do something about it and fix you know if the bakery's a bit slow we've got to put
in more effort to make it happen but the the good news sticks in your mind more and that's
practice isn't it you've got a smile on your face from the moment i met you in the lift a moment ago
and i i said and that is a practice you can actually put into play can't you actually spend
more time i mean you know if you pick up the daily news feed and you focus on that that that's going
to drive you mad because that's full of negative news but the joy is there in front of you if you
if you celebrate it can i ask you a quick question on on scale because it happened you opened the
first 15 bakeries yourself and you had a few partners and then you bought them out and and
uh and decided to open the first 15 bakeries and then you opened the first 15 bakeries and then you
decided that from 1988 you're going to have a look at the franchising world which was coming
into play with some american multinationals but from 1988 to 91 you went from 15 to 43 stores and
then in two years 91 to 93 you went from 43 to 200 yeah and then 10 years later you added another
400 stores in 10 years i mean that is incredible scale yeah what was the secret to that um basic
profitability and that attracted people to the business
and it was a fantastic atmosphere for people to work in because so we had a lot of friends and
family uh one stage we had about five different bank managers who um saw what we're doing and
left the bank and became uh franchisees they've all moved on since but it was just success bred
success the old story so um when you're on a roll you've got to roll fast you know when you're on a
good thing stick to it if you're not on it get on it it's uh
it's simple um and we're doing that in canada now like we want to we're putting the foot down
it's one of the things we decided last month we want to uh have 700 stores in north america
as soon as we can get them probably by 2030 and we've got 160 odd there now
uh we want to add another couple hundred in australia so um why not why not i love it and
i love the story of your bank managers and who left the bank and you know looked at it and said
this is a better opportunity for me
um another you know brilliant story of of success roger i've been asking a range of
different leaders from different areas sport and industry like yourself or from the art social
venture around what we see dimensions of what great leadership looks like that we've been
identifying across the course of this podcast and through the leadership business uh that i'm part
of with a leader and we start with self-leadership we think everyone who's got a sense of uh of great
leadership understands their own self-leadership does that term resonate with you
it means being responsible for yourself and for whatever else you're committed to whether it's
being a director in a company whether it's being a manager whatever it is whether it's being a
father husband uh you got to be what that role you know says you should be and what you think
you should be as a husband father uh manager director whatever uh and being aware that you've
got to fulfill those responsibilities i don't take anything on if i can't be
responsible for whatever it is and i do a lot of different things so and i'm lucky that i get asked
to do these different things but it's it's exciting uh and it's easy to take on new challenges if you
get excited by the opportunity um if it doesn't excite you don't do it uh and i don't mean
excitement you know lucky or achieve at a party or you know it's it's true to your own uh feelings
belief values to say well no that fits in with what i'm doing i'm not going to do that i'm not
you know like i would never become a director of a casino uh but i'd be a director of a range of
different other things as i am but so it's got to fit your values um and push your own buttons
so yeah well that that energizes me it doesn't and it challenges me uh and it's always a challenge
to say well to take on a new role um but if after a little while it's not working for you well
do something about it either find out why it's not
working for you why it's you can't be bothered reading the board papers or why you can't be
bothered going to a meeting and i don't experience that everything i'm involved in i'll stick to and
do it as well as i can if i start losing interest that's when i put my hand up and say i've done
enough time to move on pretty clear thinking roger the way you approach uh things in life you
can you can have that sense and that that you know description of self-leadership uh you know
all the various interests that you've got we see leaders a very uh the 21st century leaders who
are having an impact roger very conscious of how they positively impact everyone in their environment
i mean clearly that's a huge part of baker's delight success i mean how did you think about
the positive impact on others well i think it came from the understanding the win-win
formula or philosophy you know a long time ago and how if you face your
life optimistically and then say well this person i'm talking to to potentially become an employee
a franchisee or whatever the relationship is fits the bill you know they're they're the right fit
if they don't not the right fit will you end the conversation say thanks for coming
but if you got the right people it's more likely to be a successful outcome but if you've got the
wrong people forget it so you just got to keep looking for the right people
to do the right job it's a common theme that i've you know in different spheres isn't it and
there's lots of ways to describe it but you know everyone has that experience i know
finding bakers is always a you know a lifetime challenge for you the expansion's there but it's
finding the right uh people who've got that constitution too to get up at two o'clock in
the morning isn't it yeah yeah and they've got to be happy to do what we're doing and it's the
same with franchisees that if they don't love the business it's not going to work
we see ladies are really conscious about how they create and share the vision that they've got
baker's delight at a really clear vision i mean we heard you talk about a family retreat you know
recently how have you gone about creating and sharing that vision well over the years until
covid hit um we've had annual conferences uh we've got one now coming up in september
you know on the gold coast we'll have hundreds of people there that's about you know sharing
the culture as well as you know having some
motivational speakers and others but it's just talking about what we do and then getting
like-minded people together from all around the country and maybe from other countries we operate
in to just share their their vision and and view we were due to have our a conference celebrate our
40th anniversary you know two years ago covid put an end to that and we wrote a little book about it
as well called delightful um we've since given that book to all the franchisees but it was going
to be that conference but it's all about you know understanding and deepening their relationships
with everyone the network as much as we can uh so we have all sorts of get-togethers whether
i call them pod groups so it's an area manager we'll have 20 or 30 franchisees they get together
and talk about their business what the challenges are how things are working not working and there's
just a range of different ways of getting people together uh we do a news letter every week called
crumbs uh goes to the network and we've got a lot of people that are getting together and we've got a lot of people that are getting
everyone the network there's an australian edition a new zealand edition and a north american edition
um and that's all put together by the local people in each region uh so it's just a range
of different things to do to celebrate success and commiserate any bumps along the way it sounds
like you've systemized that though just listening to the language that you genuinely you know and
and the pod groups you know around 20 is that sort of where you felt the the maximum amount was well
it depends on an area manager how many bakeries are in their patch so that
maybe a smaller number because the uh there's two or three people that own two or three bakeries so
it's uh could be 30 bakeries in most of them but could be 20 franchisees or 25 or 30 depending on
how many multi-store operators there are roger we see leaders uh the word curiosity comes up a lot
that the great leaders like you are are very curious and through that curiosity they're
constantly wanting to learn and they're constantly wanting to learn and they're constantly wanting to
learn and improve does this curiosity resonate with you oh coming into this new building here
and seeing this studio i'm very curious you know i'd love to have a look around when we're finished
to just understand how it works i've just i see cranes work all along when i say well how does
that work i'm just forever curious i can't understand enough you know see things growing
why does that plant grow quicker than that one i'm just this you can take on too much of a burden
of inquiry but curiosity i think it's funny saying curiosity can be a bit of a burden of inquiry but
it's not a negative and it shouldn't be curiosity is what has made humanity the success we are you
know the human ingenuity there's no end to it you know we have these squabbles which is horrible in
you know we said earlier in ukraine and russia but it's tiny compared to the seven billion people
living on the world or seven half however many we've got the progress that humanity's made you
know we're in the flight path in hawthorne you've probably seen the planes come over your area as
you think about that 100 years ago there was no international no jet airplanes nothing now
there's millions every day flying in 1918 there were no deaths in commercial aircraft
anywhere in the world and for what that one year there's been dead since because unfortunately that
max i think the boeing plane killed a few people but it's such a safe industry millions and millions
every day flying somewhere
and i'm curious about that i'll just i love it i've got a pilot's license myself but i'll just
the miracle of flight you know it's just and then all the other things that happen in our world you
wake up in the morning hit a bit of plastic on the wall the light comes on then you go to your
bathroom and someone's delivered fresh water for you you know these are miracles that we just take
for granted every day but it's bloody fantastic 100 years ago wasn't there like my father was
born in 24 uh 1914
only 30 years after electricity started being generated like the change that's happened for the
invention of electricity is just miraculous so curiosity is just fantastic and
put petrol on that fire of curiosity don't kill the cat i love your enthusiasm for it i can feel
it in your in your body like my mom as you were talking uh roger my mom was going to kevin sheedy
the great uh richmond and essendon the afl legend as he is sheeds and and hearing him say
once and i was like oh my god i'm gonna die i'm gonna die i'm gonna die i'm gonna die i'm gonna die
you know they only put wheels on suitcases about 30 years ago we used to carry those
things around on our backs you know someone sat there and worked out it might be smarter to wheel
them you know and you take that for granted there's there's simple opportunities in everything
we do uh communicating with clarity uh roger we see leaders are really conscious you know
particularly with a scale business like yours we heard the crumbs newsletter and and and clearly
there's a strategy on it can you share with us about how you've gone about communicating
in addition to win-win you know constant improvement is you know a theme of ours that
so if you're doing one thing why can't you do it better so always looking for ways of improving
communication so um and improving everything so but the you know i forget when we started doing
the crumbs newsletter um 30 years ago i suppose but and we catalog every edition so that someone
wants to reference back to it i think it's a good idea i think it's a good idea i think it's a good
idea i think it's a good idea i think it's a good idea i think it's a good idea i think it's a good
idea but it's communication by word is one thing via spirit is the other you know and i like to
think the baker's light spirit is the thing that keeps us going you know that pledge to delight
every customer and how do you communicate that other than through action it's not words it's just
someone you know you get a young junior in one of our bakeries in glenfrey road horse on the
one uh 16 year old coming in for a shirt first shift she does some preliminary training but the
real training is there on the job and she finds one of the other team members who she respects and
looks up to or heed and they follow no words just they listen and follow uh it's so communication
is very multi-layered um it's not just words uh it's spirit it's following it's
listening um it's a whole range of things and just keeping you know your focus on where you're
trying to go and making the best of whatever the situation is constant improvement yeah
beautifully uh beautifully said uh how important has collaboration been i mean ultimately important
is it you don't get to the scale that baker's delight has without wanting to collaborate and
and share how have you gone about that collaboration how important is it
utmost important
it's because i'm a baker my wife's a science graduate when we started we did everything
ourselves then things get more complicated can't do the finance so you got to get kpmg you can't
do computers so you got to get a tech person and and then our suppliers we collaborate with them
to make sure we buy enough you know product of every year and get enough into the warehouses
so it can be distributed and it's awfully complicated uh you know it's
to get flour and all the other ingredients to the bakery twice a week uh in all of those
locations when there's floods and the collaboration is just when we had floods in
queensland recently there was one flour rep there who drove an extra 200 miles or 200 kilometers
just to get a few bags of flour to one of our franchisees so i rang uh when i heard this story
i rang dick haran who owns manila flour mills
and uh he answered the phone put on speaker he said good day roger i'm here in brisbane oh good
on you dick because i've just rung to thank you to pass on our thanks to i don't even know the
guy's name who went out of his way to deliver that flour and he said well he's here sitting
next to me just heard what you said and johnny you know dick's son was there as well so like
we've got that relationship and it's easy to collaborate so manila come up with new ideas
make our bread better they've formulated the i don't know whether you buy the high low loaf
i do yes absolutely manila was collaboration with them to come up with a formula to produce that
and to improve it what we're doing now is different to what we started with whenever we started but
it's every aspect of our businesses collaboratively you know whether it's with marketing agencies
technical bakers we have our own tech bakers but they work with other people to produce new
products it's just
all over the place and you see your range improving it was a self-indulgent question
they're coming up uh here roger as a celiac uh gluten-free bread so i i i walk past and i smell
the bakers delight joy and i go yeah it's not and we know that's a you know a much more expanded
spa i suppose that's hard when you've got non-gluten free have you thought about entering
that space at all we have but it's as you would know it's less than one percent of the market
yeah very small and
it has to be in a sterile environment so we can't make gluten-free products in on site yeah yeah and
then to bring it in it's just not what we do so we'll leave that to the specialist
i'm highly disappointed but i have to pass that on yeah yeah because the uh the convenience and
the fresh bread coming out of your bakery with the pills i understand why you can't do it but
asking um these two questions uh you know the empowering leaders podcast is is the title of uh
of the conversation we're going to be talking about is the empowering leaders podcast and we're going to be
having roger who in your life has been the greatest leader uh to personally i've been in your the
greatest leader and influence in your life well uh my first thought before i saw that clarification
was nelson mandela um and because our son son-in-law south african we've been to south
africa a few times but uh but not while he was in power um but probably uh my wife
uh without thinking about any further
she's um so clear in her thinking so decisive such a strong moral compass um
inspirational from health and fitness perspective uh everything about her yeah it's a great answer
roger that smile's booming as you as you say i love you and mandela i can clearly the values
and the and the history and i i love asking that question because you know he's a question without
notice and people immediately i'm like oh my god i'm so sorry i'm so sorry i'm so sorry i'm so sorry
you know that to get the instinct but you know i suppose uh you know to have a partnership like
that you know of all the things that you've achieved i often think the same if you're
fortunate enough to have a an incredible uh life partner it's about as good a gift as you can get
yeah yeah yeah oh yeah i'm very lucky in the sense of collaboration roger we're obsessed with what
collaboration looks like if i could ask you that if you collaborate with anyone you've got a range
of incredible uh that make us delight clearly and your philanthropy and we haven't really touched
dcna and a number of other causes that i know you get behind if you collaborate with anyone on
anything does someone spring to mind uh we're involved in a thing called the world mosquito
program and we work closely with the director of that who's an australian he lives in france
world mosquito program will eliminate dengue fever from the world 390 million people a year
get dengue fever out of four billion people are exposed to it so it's a global problem
a permanent pandemic but they've this fellow called professor scott o'neill has come up with
a way to deal with it um i won't go to the detail here but he is an inspiration uh he's been able to
get the gates foundation on board um and many other welcome trusts from england and many other
supporters including our family foundation so we talk with him once a month um whenever he's here
we catch up with him uh we've been to
indonesia colombia vietnam uh to look at the work as well as you know it's big labs at monash
so he's a great collaborator um and we've seen him collaborate with various people around the
world from all levels of government uh because that project works in 12 different countries now
from brazil colombia and south america panama uh all the pacific island nations australia is now
free uh india
indonesia vietnam um you know but it goes on so that's but when you talk about collaboration you
know i'd love to be able to collaborate with um warren buffett we own a few shares in uh warren
buffett's you know berkshire hathaway but what a unbelievable guy 91 he's still investing a
billion here and a billion there and he's just uh amazing uh clear mind uh him and charlie munger's
incredible what a guy you know i could just uh
so it depends what you want to collaborate for and who with so the best collaborators
right now for our business bakers like cobb's bread my wife our two children and their partners
uh and then all the other people who work for us but as far as the the best people to collaborate
with on building and setting the future for banks like cobb's bread for those i've just mentioned so
very lucky roger i love uh finishing on that and i'll see you next time
that note uh from one bakery in glenferry road hawthorne very close to uh where i live uh to
working on solving uh and ending dengue fever in the world it's an incredible life story it's a
really fortunate that you're prepared to share it i love the values i love uh you know what you're
doing and continue to do and uh as i said at the start i really appreciate you taking the time
thanks a lot thank you it's been a pleasure look empowering leaders was presented by me luke darcy
produced by matt dwyer with audio production by darcy thompson
your leadership journey i encourage you to go to a leader collective.com
take our empowering leaders indicator tool and understand the impact you have
on your environment join us at a leader to learn lead and collaborate