A Listener Production.
G'day, it's Luke Darcy.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership both on and off the field
has been a lifelong passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective
and have had the privilege of working with thousands of leaders
in education, sport, industry and the arts
that have helped shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership
where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
Ros Kelly, in many ways, is a pioneer of female leadership
in Australian public life.
Graduating from the University of Sydney with a teaching degree,
Ros became the first person on either side of her family
to complete tertiary education.
Initially working for five years as a secondary school teacher,
Ros's first entry into public life saw her elected
to the ACT House of Assembly as the member for Canberra in 1974.
Ros Kelly was elected to the House of Representatives
and became the first Australian federal MP
to give birth to a child.
In 1987, Ros became the first female Labor Minister
when appointed Minister for Defence, Science and Personnel.
Post-political life, Ros Kelly's leadership has seen her succeed
in the business world as Chair of the National Breast Cancer Foundation,
appointed by the Queen to the Commonwealth War Graves Board
and awarded an Order of Australia in 2004
for her service to the community, environment and women's health.
Ros, it's a great honour and privilege to spend some time with you.
Thanks for joining me.
Thank you, Luke.
Anything I can do for work,
women, I do.
That, I think, is the first lesson for women like me
that we've got to be there to support other women.
Well, you created so many firsts, Ros,
and paved the way for female leaders in Australian public life.
When you look back, and I'll read that back to you,
is there a sense of pride?
There is a great sense of pride,
but sometimes I look back and I say,
did I really do all that?
And I think this is the point we need to make
right at the beginning,
that when we set out,
as particularly as women,
I didn't set out to be a cabinet minister.
I set out a step at a time
to first of all get to university
because I knew if I didn't get to university,
I didn't have the education I needed to go forward.
So, one, you've got to get the education.
Two, when I was teaching, I loved it,
but I felt I wasn't developing enough.
So then the next step,
I saw this opportunity to get,
I got involved in politics.
And then, so everything was then,
I did, first of all, did the ACT assembly.
And then I got into the House of Representatives.
Now that sounds easy,
but in those days,
there were no women in the House of Representatives,
none, none.
And the only reason I ran for pre-selection
for the seat of Canberra,
which was then held as a conservative seat,
was because I looked around and I thought,
is there any other woman that's got a chance of winning this?
And no.
So everything has been one step at a time,
seeing the opportunity and going for it.
And that's the real lesson we've got to say.
You're not going to actually always set your heights
as the ultimate.
Let's just take it a step at a time,
learn how we go as we go,
and then take that next,
whenever the chance is there, go for it.
Ros, can you take us back to the environment
of the late 70s, early 80s,
when you are running for public office?
And what,
what it was like?
You know, read with interest that the advice for you
to appeal to the electorate was that you needed to be
the mother with a roast lamb in the oven.
And that image needed to be portrayed
because that's what, you know, the electorate wanted.
But at the same time,
as a young mother returning back to parliament,
you were widely criticised for not being a proper mum
because how could you do both those things at the same time?
And how did you stay sane
with all that pressure going on from all angles?
So this, again, is you've got to be true to yourself.
And,
you've got to believe in yourself.
So the first step for me was the hardest one.
And that was running for federal parliament.
Because when I made that move,
I really thought that I would wreck my first marriage.
And I did.
But I still,
because I knew that that partner was not accepting
of me continuing to grow in that way.
But then I said,
I said to myself,
this might sound bizarre to now,
I don't want to get to 40 and feel I should have done it.
I wanted to have a go at it.
And if I failed,
well, you know, the consequence,
at least I've experienced it.
So that's why I ran for federal parliament,
because I thought it was a very, very hard step.
And remember in the previous parliament,
there were no women.
So there was no sort of stereotype.
There was no stereotype view of how you behave.
So this is, again, this problem for women.
You can't do it like the men do it.
But on the other hand, like Julia experienced,
there are aspects of it that the community can't deal with.
So for me, I was in a marriage that was difficult.
I had no children at that stage.
And, but the,
and I did some survey work to see what people thought of me.
And,
and I found that about 8%, this was Canberra.
So they're very enlightened.
8% said, we don't care whether you're a man or a woman.
So that's right.
8% said they wanted a woman,
about 8% said they wanted a man.
And the rest of them said they didn't care.
But what they did say is they said they,
I seem to be an expert on things,
but they didn't know anything about me.
So my secret weapon became my Cocker Spaniel dog.
So my dog and I went everywhere together.
And the theme was again, more of a related to women.
It was Rose Kelly Cares for Canberra.
So this was the beginning of that sort of culture
of leadership where women are more caring.
And I'm not saying, I mean, that's not,
all women aren't like that, but that's the way I am.
And that style of leadership is very hard to fit
into the parliament, which is very natural and very
aggressive.
So that became a big issue in the future.
Ros, I want to come back.
When we spoke on the phone, you mentioned that you want to talk about choosing the right
partner in life.
I'd love to come back to that discussion because you touched on it briefly there, but it is
an under-discussed element in life and leadership, and I'd love to explore that with you further.
But I just want to go back a bit to that time and you breaking new ground, as you said,
there were no women.
They just didn't exist.
You're there.
What the environment was like for you, I read that there was only one time you felt compelled
to take the floor of parliament, following a comment from the MP, I think it was Michael
Hodgman at the time, who said something misogynistic and sexist.
And you took the stand and you said, I'm a woman.
Women are here to stay.
We demand the same respect as every other member of this house.
That was a stand that you took.
What was it like for you in politics at the time?
I'll never forget that day.
My legs were actually shaking.
I was so nervous because the whole...
Normally.
They will scream and yell at you.
But I stood up and I said, I want to make a personal explanation.
And everything went quiet.
And I made that point about, you know, we just demand to be treated fairly like everybody else.
Because he had made a misogynist comment.
And I let it go at the time because I was sort of thinking, you know, what do I let it go?
And then I saw it in the handset and I thought, no, no, I can't let this go.
But I remember my first time I got into parliament.
We were in the old parliament.
And there were two other women with me.
Joan Child, who was an older lady, a lovely woman from Victoria.
And Elaine Darling from Queensland.
Both a bit older than me.
Anyway, the three of us were in the House of Representatives in the old chamber.
And one of my colleagues came along.
And on top note, as the parliament's about to assemble for the first time, he looked at and was sitting next to Joan.
And he said, geez, he said, not bad enough having you sheilers here.
Well, I've got to sit next to one of you.
So that's really what it was like.
And but it's been like that in everything I've done.
And I think it will be to many of you listeners, too.
I mean, the House of Representatives is one thing.
But then you move on.
And it's the first time I was, you know, my first portfolio was junior defence minister.
There'd never been a woman defence minister.
So you had to get in.
Then you had to prove yourself again, prove you could do the job.
And I remember I went on my first exercise.
That is a military exercise in the Northern Territory.
It was called Operation Dusty Trooper.
So we went up to Operation Dusty Trooper.
And all day I noticed people, the soldiers, going around a little circle.
And I remember the brigadier kept saying to me, a minister, would you like to use the facilities?
Stupid me, didn't know what they were.
Until later in the day, I said, oh, yeah, there's a toilet around.
Keep me a shovel.
And they said, oh, minister, we've made special arrangements for you.
And there in the middle of this area, a square, it did have Hessian around it, was a tin dunny.
And, of course, if you put your bottom on it, it was, you know, you jump.
And so you use the ground.
Afterwards, I came up and I said, brigadier.
I said, you do not have to make special arrangements.
From now on, just give me a shovel.
And, you know, it was just showing that you could do things in your own way.
You didn't have to do everything like the boys, but you had to prove yourself all the time, all the time.
And so whatever you do, women have to do that.
And they're still doing it.
That's the tragedy of our society today.
You can't just be accepted of who you are.
Although, I want to congratulate the new Albanese government.
Because there is, I think we've come a long way.
Because there's this wonderful young woman whom I mentored and helped in the campaign called Annika Wells, who's the member for Lilly.
And she's about 38.
She's got three young kids, a set of twins of one and another little one at five.
And I said to her, the big change will occur when you get offered a portfolio and you make the judgment on whether you can do it,
rather than be told.
I was often told I couldn't do it because I had two young kids.
And that's where I think we've improved things so much, that it's up to us to make the call, not for other boys, the boys around, to decide for us.
Ros, you mentioned off the top, if you can do anything that empowers women.
And in that spirit, Ros, a lot of this podcast to me is about we're seeing a great shift in leadership,
away from the hierarchy and the command and control and the boss who's got the corner.
And to more self-reflective and more collaborative.
And that obviously includes female leadership, because naturally, you said not all women, clearly,
but there is more empathy naturally with female leaders.
Is that the sort of shift that you're seeing in modern leadership yourself?
I hope so.
I don't think it applies everywhere.
After I left public life, I worked in the mining and construction industry.
I think there are still issues.
We can't close our eyes and say everyone's into sort of coal.
So I think we need to take a step back and say to women,
what is the sort of leadership that is, is there such thing as a feminine leadership?
I think there is a leadership for you as an individual.
And some men will roll like this, but these are the ingredients of it.
I think that we, listen, I think women are good at that.
We consider, we act, and we communicate.
with passion but through all that I think we are resilient
and we recognise, I think women recognise that our type
of leadership is collaborative and we don't have the answers
to everything.
I think that's where we do change because there's so many men,
you know, who think they know everything but I don't think
I know any one woman who thinks she knows everything
and so I think we're very good at team building.
I think that is a great style of leadership we have.
Now, I'm not saying men can't do that.
I think my husband when he was running Westpac was a good team leader
recognising that, you know, you've got to build a team
but women particularly are very good at that and so I think
the best companies recognise that now.
Not all companies do but I think the best do.
The smartest ones are, aren't they, in understanding,
as you said, that it's not just ticking.
It's ticking your box.
It's the skill set that, you know, naturally occurs
in the feminine side of the world compared to the masculine
side of the world.
You mentioned briefly when we spoke about young girls
in the playground are natural leaders, you know,
and if you study before there's any perception placed
on young girls, is society sort of coaching that out
of young women?
We need to coach that back effectively.
Roz, is that the advice you give to young girls
who want to follow your path?
I think we need to.
I think we need to do a lot more work at the high school level.
Somehow we lose these girls in teenage years where they become
less secure in themselves.
It's really about being happy with who you are and, as you know,
there's so many pressures on boys and girls but so many girls
lose their sense of self in their teenage years and I loved being
a school teacher because I think there's so much we can do
with those young women at high school.
We don't, I mean, parents and parents have got to remember
they've got responsibilities as well but it really is high school
where I think so many of those girls have got to realise
that it's good being me, it's good being me and social media
is doing so much damage to their whole being, self-image
because you can't be a great leader if you don't believe in yourself.
That's so fundamental.
So every lesson that I've had along the way, as I said to you,
it's been a step at a time but I've believed in myself
and years and years ago I remember I was sitting
in a Labor Party forum and I was sitting next to this marvellous man
named Peter Walensky who was well known as a senior bureaucrat
and went on to be ambassador and head of foreign affairs.
And I was sitting next to him and I said,
Peter, do you think I could run as secretary of the branch,
which is really where I started in public life?
And he looked at me and he said, Ros, I always say,
I look around the room and if I think I can do the job
at least as well as anyone else, I go for it.
And that's what I think we've got to say to all women,
young women and older women.
Have a go at this.
Have a go.
And it is.
And it is critical that we keep having it,
encourage that when they're teenagers.
Yeah, great piece of advice, Ros.
And I think sometimes when I have the pleasure of sharing stories
like yours, Ros, people look at it and they say,
how could I do that?
Look at the success.
Look at all of the achievement and right from your early age.
But we often overlook the challenges along the way.
And you write very openly about your challenges
and building resilience along the way.
And you don't get to be the first female Labor Minister
of Australia without building some of that resilience.
Resilience.
And along with your success, there was a really tough ending
for you in politics.
It became known as the Whiteboard Affair.
You write about that in your book.
Can you share with the listeners your experience of that
and how you coped?
There was a lot of personal attacks on you at the time.
How did you cope with that?
See, I think in public life, you've got to sort of dissociate
the job from the person and probably you have to do
in other fields of work because I knew that I was,
you know, I was, you know, I was, you know,
I was allocating sports grants and to compare
with what's gone on recently.
I mean, I did give more to Labor seats than Liberal seats,
for sure, because they had greater need.
What I probably didn't do was have the proper paper chains.
And in the end of the day, the time I was attacked,
the way I got through that was to say this is really
about me, the politician, not about me, the person.
They never accused me of being corrupt.
Or they accused me of being political.
And so that's where I had to sort of dissociate
to keep myself intact.
And there was a huge amount of pressure because at the same time,
my husband, David, had moved to Sydney and he was working in Sydney.
So every morning I'd have to get the kids to school
and my little boy had moved to a new school.
So he'd be crying.
He'd cry while I was putting him into school for about half an hour.
And I'd have to deal with him, then get into work
and deal with the latest little attack that was going on.
And I got asked every question in Parliament for three months.
Imagine the pressure of that.
And that you've just got to, unfortunately,
that's the sort of thing you've got to be able to deal with in public life.
And I think it's only got worse with social media.
But underpinning all that, you've got to say,
have you got this supportive relationship
and hold you together?
And that's where I think we go back to one of your earlier points, Luke,
which I think we should come back to,
how critical it is to have a good personal relationship.
And that might be your partner.
It might be your best friends.
But for me, it was obviously my husband,
but I had some great friends who helped me through that.
One of them was this fabulous Melburnian called Lindsay Fox.
Really?
Yeah, Lindsay used to ring me every morning,
every morning without fail.
While I was going through that.
And he'd just say, hi, Roz, just ringing to say I love you.
That was it.
And, you know, that was just so fabulous.
People helping you when you're down.
Another great guy.
And it is interesting that most of these were men.
Another great guy who's running a mining company.
And I'd met him, obviously, in the context of work.
And he rang me and he said, look, what you're going through,
I don't quite get it all.
But he said, I appreciate it.
I appreciate everything you've done.
And when this is over, if you want to leave public light,
I'd love to talk to you about things we can do together.
Now, just having someone who in the middle of your depth
or the trouble you're going through to help to pull you up,
I've never forgotten that.
And I think that's another good lesson for us as women.
We need to support other women who are going through that sort of thing.
And I've seen that now with some of the more, you know,
when some of the women in Australia have got into a bit of strife,
I've been a bit of a listening ground for them.
When I was living in London, I housed a few people as they came over.
And it's really built my friendships with particularly some other women,
but not just women, but other men.
It's a great story that you share.
I mean, Lindsay Fox is an incredibly well-known Melburnian,
created a business that is legendary, a multi-billion dollar business,
Lynn Fox.
And, you know, that's an interesting story.
It's not necessarily what people would associate with Lindsay Fox,
picking up the phone.
I love you.
You, in that era, men weren't great at saying that even now,
but to have that, and I suppose I am interested, Roz,
in talking about, you're really open about, you know,
you were married to Paul Kelly, the political journalist,
and now the editor of The Australian.
And that was, you know, balancing being a politician yourself
and having a political journalist for a husband.
And it wasn't a partnership and a relationship that worked for you.
And then your marriage to David Morgan,
who people know really well as his incredible success,
firstly in the Treasury,
but as the CEO of the Westpac Bank.
You said to me really clearly, this is,
and it probably is the most important decision you can make in your life,
isn't it?
Your partner and your friendships around you who support you,
but we don't talk about it enough often, Roz.
Why do you think that is?
And how can we be good at that?
So every single women's group or group I've ever talked to,
I say the first, the most important decision you make in your career
is who is your partner?
Or you either have a partner,
or you don't have a partner.
That's another decision.
But then who's the support group around you?
Everybody needs a support group around me.
Now, I have to say one of my,
one of the things I've been able to do since I left public life
is be a bit of support to my niece,
who's the Lord Mayor of Melbourne, Sally Capp.
And I remember Sally came to me some time ago
when,
you had this other very wayward Lord Mayor,
to put it mildly.
And she said,
do you think I should have a go at this?
I said, so, of course.
Everything prepares you for this.
And it's been lovely for me
to be able to be a bit of a support to her
because she knew nothing about politics,
like very naive about it.
And Andrew, her darling husband,
is so naive about it.
And so I've had to be there at the end of the phone
to give support,
to him in particular,
to say, look, it's only politics.
Because, you know,
so that it doesn't always have to be your partner,
but you have to have a network around you
to keep you balanced and supported.
And those decisions you make on who those people are
and who you can trust are fundamental,
fundamental to how well you're going to be able
to go in your job.
There's one other thing I want to talk about too,
that again, doesn't get much of a mention,
and that's looking after yourself.
Women are notoriously bad at this.
And I was true.
The worst example of this was I had my baby in 1983,
my first child born in the house of preps,
there was lots of controversy about whether you go back
to work or not.
Well, I feel I had to go back to work
because we had no maternity leave.
There was no facilities, nothing.
And I was the first one,
I was the first to go.
So when you're the first, you're always conscious
that you've got to do it, be perfect,
or you've got to try and be perfect.
You never are, but anyway.
So I went back to work and I said, you know,
despite all the criticism, look, I've got to do it my way.
You know, I had David supporting me.
I had my mother.
So I went back and did this job.
But I went back after five days.
And then, to make it worse, I kept working right through.
So I went back in August.
The following November, I had another child.
So I'd worked all the way through before Ben was born in November,
the night before I said I was at a ball.
And I said to the Prime Minister, oh, I've got to go.
I'm having a baby tomorrow.
I did that on the 4th of November.
I know that the 11th of November I was laying the reef
at the war memorial.
And I know I was at the opening of the election campaign.
And then I did an election campaign.
So all of that.
Then on Christmas Day, I was at home and the Keatings were coming
around for Christmas lunch.
And all of a sudden, I just started vomiting.
My body just said, enough is enough.
Now, that was nuts to do all that.
And I keep advising women, and I've seen my own daughter
and daughter-in-law have babies now.
And I say, how did I do it?
Why did I do it?
I do not know.
But because you're the sort of pioneer, you think you're indispensable,
you're not.
And that's all nonsense.
It's all nonsense.
So you've got to look after your body.
And I think it was only then after I got breast cancer later on
that I said, there are lessons in all this.
And I just think everyone, men and women, but particularly women,
because they put everyone else first, have to look after yourself.
You did mention Paul and Anita Keating were your dinner guests
for Christmas that day when you were sick.
And you had friendships and relationships and partnerships
with them.
Iconic leaders in Australian history and iconic prime ministers
like Paul Keating and Bob Hawke.
Can I ask you, maybe start with Paul Keating.
It was a great friendship of yours and with your husband,
David Morgan, as well.
What type of leader was Paul Keating?
Paul led from the front, always.
And he believed when he reached a conclusion, he'd listen.
He'd always listen to your views.
Then he'd reach his views, and he just went for it.
And that...
You know, at that time, it was so important because we were bringing
about major changes.
And I remember a few times in the Cabinet Room, he'd come in,
we'd call the Cabinet meeting, and he'd say, okay, we're about,
here's a paper, we're privatising the Commonwealth Bank to die.
We'll do it first thing in the morning.
And some of the others would go, what?
We're not doing this.
And he'll say, well, if you want me to be Treasurer, you are.
He always knew he had Bob on side, of course.
Because they worked very well together.
So, no, he led from the front.
But Bob was...
Bob had this great skill, and that's why I think they were brilliant together.
Bob was able to bring the community with him.
And that's, I think, what we need today, too.
More of a conversation about issues.
Leadership from the front, but bringing the community with you.
And, you know, Richo always used to say, you know, the mob usually get it right.
And they do.
As we saw in the last election.
But, you know, people aren't stupid.
You know, when reforms need to be done, you need a conversation with the electorate
and get them to understand what's happening.
And that's the style of leadership they were.
It was, I was so privileged to be part of all that.
So privileged.
You mentioned Senator Richo, Senator Graeme Richardson,
who was a legendary numbers man, I suppose, in the Labor cabinets that you were involved in.
And I'm fascinated, Paul Keating, you write about him as a man of obsessions,
whether it was budgerigar breeding or French China or clocks or economic reform.
If he had something, no matter what it was, he was obsessed with getting it through.
I want to ask you about Bob Hawke.
And you had, obviously, clearly an incredibly close relationship with him.
They talk about the charisma of Bob Hawke.
You write a great story in your book about you driving along in your Mazda 121 to a shopping centre in Canberra.
How about I tell that story?
Because I was a new candidate for office and so was Bob.
So we were elected at the same time.
And so I thought, oh, I'll use Bob in my election campaign.
So little did I know, one of the reasons he really loved being in Canberra
was because he was having an affair with Blanche Delpuget,
who was also one of my constituents.
But I didn't know that at the time.
Anyway, so we were driving along Highmarch Drive in Canberra
and we pulled up at the lights.
It's near the hospital there.
And I had my little yellow Mazda with signs,
Ros Kelly Cares for Canberra.
And there was a little beetle next door with the roof down.
And Bob looked across and there were these two gorgeous looking women there.
And they saw Bob and they said, oh, hi, Bob.
Hi, Bob.
And Bob saw them, responded.
They stopped at the lights.
Bob got out and got into their car and disappeared for two hours.
When he turned up, I was in the pharmacy, one of the pharmacies in my constituency.
And he just wanders in, starts chatting to the pharmacist
and gets sort of the best shampoo for his hair.
That was Bob.
And the Australian public loved him, Ros.
Loved him.
They were enamoured with him, weren't they, right across his political life for a moment.
But I must say he was a very generous, spirited person.
So, you know, towards the end when the leadership stuff was,
oh, it was so terrifying.
It was terrible for me having to vote for, well, vote for Bob against Bill Hayden
and then secondly to vote for Paul against Bob.
That was like, those moments are harrowing in politics, harrowing,
because your gut's hurt, you know.
And you know the time has come, but you don't want them to go.
But, you know, for the gut, you've got to do the right thing
for what you believe in for the country.
Anyway, during those leadership things,
I voted for Paul because he was just like my brother.
And actually, Bob was great.
He never actually asked me for the vote because he knew that my vote went to Paul.
Anyway, afterwards, after we'd both left public life, I went to see him.
And I said to him, Bob, look, you know I always appreciated your leadership
and I love being part of your leadership team and I hated the way it ended
and I'm sorry that I couldn't vote for you.
And he looked at me and he said, look, Ros,
he said, they did, the Labor Party did me a favour.
He said, it made me, gave me the opportunity to marry Blanche
and she's been the love of my life.
Now, what a generous spirit, what a generous spirit.
And, you know, in politics, you need a generous spirit.
Like, you can't just wish that things have been different or when you left politics,
when I left politics, even though, you know, I was, I was battered and bruised.
I stopped for a while and this is why all of us have got to do the same.
Life doesn't work out always the way we want it to.
We've got to sit back, relish, indulge with the people we love,
and then look for the next opportunity.
And that's, again, what leadership is.
You know, you've got to know yourself, be good to yourself,
rely on your friends, and then look for the next opportunity, the door that opens.
There are incredibly wise words, Ros.
As someone who's lived your life experience, and I'm really looking forward to doing this
because in the work we're doing, we're seeing these consistent dimensions
of what great leadership looks like and to have your thoughts on it.
And you've gone to some of those places already, but please be as expansive as you like, Ros,
on these different dimensions of leadership.
But we start with self-leadership, and it's where you were going all the way along, I think,
which was, you know, you need to have that sense of self before you can lead others.
Is that what it means to you that you need to identify?
Identify that in terms of self-leadership?
Yes.
You need to, well, you need to know who you are.
You need to know what your strengths and what your weaknesses are.
And with the weaknesses, you can develop them.
You can work on them.
But you need, when you're with a team, you need to have people, for example, I was running
the Breast Cancer Foundation.
I am a really good marketer.
What I'm hopeless at is the absolute detail of things.
So I surround myself with detailed people.
Like, why was I successful in an environmental company?
I was full of engineers, full of engineers who are great on detail, but not particularly
good at marketing or, you know, knowing how to synthesize issues.
So you need to know what your strengths and weaknesses are.
And I think that's fundamental to leadership.
And you need to listen to people around you.
You don't need to necessarily change your opinion on things, but you need to listen.
And you need to listen.
And then you go for it and you sell it and you believe in it.
I think one hard thing for women, and I'm sure, I'm not sure I've got the right balance
on this now, you've got to be true to yourself.
So then how much have you got to play the game?
When you're in really hostile environments, you've got to be really conscious of everything
about you.
Like after I left public life, I worked in the mining industry.
Now, when I went on a mining site, I made sure I always wore all the appropriate safety
gear.
I looked like everybody else.
When I went down mines, I behaved like everyone else.
I'd go and chat to people in a way.
So I was still myself, but I'd always know I'd have to dress the way everyone else dressed
because, well, they were the rules of the game.
Yeah.
You've got to play those to a degree.
And when I was recently, I was a War Graves commissioner and total British environment.
I was the only woman for a while.
I was the only non-Brit.
So they expect Australians to behave in a certain way.
I wasn't as forthright as I normally am, because if I said everything I thought, it would have
been very hard to get anything done.
So you've got to be smarter than everyone else.
You've got to work your way, work out how to be yourself without changing yourself,
but know the culture you're working in.
There's some brilliant subtlety in that answer, Ros.
And I love picking it up from different leaders in different ways.
You're having an interesting conversation a couple of days ago on this forum.
Ange Postacoglou has become a legendary coach of Australian soccer and have just won the
title at Celtic.
And he describes that.
You know, he's coaching in Japan or coaching in Australia.
He's been in Australia for a long time.
And Scotland, you know, he's got to be a chameleon.
He still knows exactly who he is, knows exactly his sense of self.
But you know, you're foolish if you don't think you have to, you know, bend to the environment
you win to be able to influence in a positive way.
So it's fascinating to hear you in your world in a very similar light.
We see leaders, Ros, are really conscious around, you know, good leaders in a modern
sense around how they positively impact others in the environment they work in.
How did you go about that?
Does that resonate with you, positively impacting others?
Yeah.
I think sometimes we don't realise the influence we have.
I find that now I often, you know, that program Misrepresented that was on, I think that was
one of the first times I realised that there's a whole generation of young women out there
who appreciate what you went through, appreciate the sort of leadership you had.
And often now I'll be going to a shop or I'll say, oh, you're Ros Kelly.
Oh, thanks for what you've done for us.
And because I think I was uninterested in survival that, you know, I wasn't really conscious.
People generally aren't that good at coming forward, but it's amazing how many, since
that, as you get older, they come forward and say, oh yeah, you did have an influence
on me.
But I think you can do that wherever you are.
You have a huge influence as a school teacher.
I remember I was at a function in London, in Australia House in London, and the ABC
journalist covering it came over to me and said, oh, you taught me at Dixon High School
or Narrabundah High School, and you had a huge influence on me.
And I thought, oh, oh, wow, am I that old?
But, but, you know, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's,
it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's.
You know, I just think you've just got to be true to yourself and you don't go into
these things to influence other people, but it is amazing how you do.
And you've got to be conscious of all that.
I think that's what too, social media has brought in new rules of the game.
You're always, you're always on.
You're always on.
Keating used to say, oh, when I get into parliament, I switch to Vaudable.
Well, in a way, when we're all...
Yeah.
We're always out there because anyone can take a film of us.
We've got, as leaders, we have to be conscious of that, have to be conscious.
And would people like, would you like, would your children like to see you in that context?
So many places to go on your, on your answer there, Ros.
My mind's going to Paul Keating on the floor of parliament and what the incredible orator
that he was.
And he certainly, as you said, flicked the switch to Vaudable at times, but did it in
a way that very few people...
Yeah.
...have, in terms of leaders creating and sharing their vision and really conscious
about it, your life has had many parts.
I love that you started as a school teacher.
You were part of the old Commonwealth Scholarship Fund where your uni fees and allowances were
paid, but there was a five-year term.
You had to be a teacher.
It was a brilliant program when you think back, you know, it captured people like you
who were passed on.
Yes.
And we, you know, generally think teachers are under-celebrated for the influence that
they have.
And it's great.
It's great to see how you influence someone's life and they come back many years later to
show you, getting back to creating and sharing the vision of your life, were you conscious
about that?
And how did you go about creating and sharing the vision for the work that you did?
I think I didn't do anything about, I think in, when I was in federal parliament and everything,
I was into survival.
I think, and I think also maybe I feel like when I was in parliament, I didn't do enough
to support other women because I was just into survival.
Yeah.
I was into surviving myself.
It was only really after I went to London, David, I was running the Breast Cancer Foundation
and David got the opportunity to run a private equity firm after he'd given up Westpac.
So we moved to London because I'd never lived overseas.
And there I got this, the governor general was the Quentin Bryce and she was coming through
London and the high commission had asked me to put together a group of women for her to
talk to because at that stage I'd got involved with a group called Women on Boards.
So I invited, we invited, you know, 50 or 60 women and we had a conversation about what
are the lessons we've learnt from things.
And so I interviewed Quentin and at the end of that, she said to me, why don't you keep
doing this?
So I did.
And so for the next seven years, when I was in London, I interviewed numbers of women
who were Australian women coming through.
And some British women who were friends of Australia, we had a big audience.
And what we do is we talk about the lessons we've learnt and how they can help other women.
And we're doing a similar thing now I get, I'm involved at ANU doing this as well.
So there, you know, the things where I can get other women to talk about themselves.
I interviewed Julia, Julia at one stage in London and you, you know, after she'd left,
after being prime minister, I said to her, for example, with the speech, the dramatic
speech she gave on misogyny, I said, do you think you made the call, left it too long
to make the call?
And she said, probably.
And then we were able to talk about women being in that context in a workforce.
When do you speak out?
How do you speak out?
You know?
So there are lessons that that's what I want to do now.
I share the experiences, good and bad, a lot of my mistakes, but you want to share them
and talk frankly about them to help other women.
That's brilliant, Ros, and a great contribution along with all the other contribution of your
life.
I mean, can I ask you with all that, that knowledge, and it's a hard thing, we're always
looking for soundbites in life, aren't we?
But for young women listening who've got ambition and want to pursue leadership, I mean, what's
your advice?
What's your advice to someone, or start a business, or create their own path?
What's your advice to young women generally?
Have a go.
What's the worst thing that happens?
You fail, and you learn by it.
It's really interesting in our society where you never ... In Australia, we're never allowed
to fail.
But if you're in the United States, a failure's almost a badge of honor.
You just jump onto the next thing, they call it pivoting.
But you go onto the next thing, and we think, don't be scared of failure.
Just have a go, and think about it, plan, learn as much as you can, listen to the experts,
and make the call yourself, have a group of supportive people around you, and have people
who believe in you, but have a go and believe in yourself.
Yeah, brilliantly said.
We see leaders have curiosity as a common part of their nature, and they are curious
and through that curiosity, Ros, they're really open to how they learn and improve themselves.
Does curiosity ring a bell with you?
Yeah, but it's interest.
I suppose you could call it curiosity.
I'd call it more enthusiasm for life.
So just this morning before I talk to you, I've been talking to a friend of mine who's
starting a new business in the environmental field, and it's so exciting, and I'm now really
enthused about it, because I'm curious.
I want to follow through some of the climate change stuff that I started many years ago.
And so I'm curious, but I'm enthusiastic for life.
So I think you could almost call it that.
Yeah, and that's a great way to think about it, yeah, that enthusiasm.
Through that lens, it certainly resonates with me.
Communicating with clarity, Ros, we see is a common trait.
Yeah.
Of great leaders in recent times, I mean, it's a great skill of yours.
You can hear it in the clarity of the way you're speaking to me today, but also when
you were in politics.
Did you give that thought?
Did you work on your craft of communication?
Well, I'm a schoolie.
You see, I'm trained.
Every school teacher is trained in how to communicate.
And you've just got to remember our audience is really school kids.
And I always say to people, when you are absolutely bored out of your mind with an
issue, you know the electorate is, the people you're trying to talk to are just coming to
terms with it.
And I think people forget that the most important thing is your own conviction when you speak,
the passion that you have for it.
You've obviously got to know the logic.
And it's got to be based on your ethics.
But the most important thing is the pathos, the passion, you know, to sell your story,
to convince someone to be with you, to go up that hill.
David always said to me, you know, he said, when I was in treasury, everything was about
the ideas.
You'd excel and you'd get everyone around you because of the great ideas.
When he went into Westpac and he had then 40,000 people, he had to convince everyone
to go up the hill with him, a totally different style of leadership.
So I think you've always got to look at what is the task ahead.
But communicating clearly and bringing people with you and listening to people and making
them a partner in the outcome, I think is really important.
And Ros, collaboration is the final dimension we're talking about, that people in leadership
now are really conscious of how important collaboration is.
Is that been part of your leadership style?
Has to be.
Because it goes back to the point.
The point I made, you've got to know what you're good at and what you are not good at.
And so you need to build a collaborative team around you.
And I do think there's much more of a realisation of that and that women's style of leadership
is collaborative.
It isn't conflict.
One thing I think people hate is women fighting other women or making it personal.
So, you know, just bringing people with you.
Recognising sometimes that there are some people who won't work with you, there's some
that won't work with you.
Well, they should just go.
And if you're in a culture where you have a leader and it's not someone you have the
same ethical values of or someone you believe in, you shouldn't be there.
You shouldn't, you should go and try something new and you'll feel a lot happier in yourself
as well.
Yeah, that's, you know, sage advice there, Ros, isn't it?
You know.
And I've got to go back and work out who said it, you know, the great partnerships.
You need shared values first and foremost.
Without that, you're no chance.
You need complementary capabilities so you can complement each other and shared vision.
So if you take the values part out, in your view, Ros, you're not aligned on values, you
go and you have to change.
You go.
Well, it's the same as a marriage, a partnership, isn't it?
Any sort of partnership, whether it's your marriage, whether it's your friendships, whether
it's your work environment.
If you haven't got a shared value system, it won't last.
It just won't last.
And so it applies to everything.
And I think companies now have started to realise how critical that is, or maybe not
all of them.
I think too many of them are still based on how much the bottom line, how much money
you make, particularly some of the big, they're not the retail bankers, but, you know, some
of those hard edged American companies.
But I do think more and more of the bigger companies realised that if they're going to
manage with a lot of people, it's got to be shared values.
Yeah.
Brilliantly said.
Ros, I've been asking these two questions of all the leaders I've had the privilege of
sitting down with.
Who has been the greatest leader in your life?
Probably Paul.
Probably Paul Keating.
Yeah.
Mark.
Mad.
Passionate.
But, you know.
But, yeah.
Yeah.
Really brought about change.
And, but it's really hard to separate him from Paul, from Bob because they were, the
style of leadership was, was the essence of who they both were.
So one was the communicator, one was the sort of the hard boy.
And the combination of the two of them was pretty amazing.
And to be part of the government then was phenomenal.
Have we lost that in political life, Ros, that combination where they're very different
personalities, aren't they?
Paul Keating and Bob Hawke.
You couldn't get polar opposites, but that collaboration, as you said, it worked, didn't
it?
They respected each other's strengths.
It worked.
It worked until it didn't.
Yeah.
And I think that's a bit of the boy stuff and the testosterone and the conflict.
I think Anthony Albanese is a different style of leader.
I think he is much more of a collaborative leader.
I'm hoping we'll see this in the new government.
The final question, Ros, is in the spirit of collaboration, has there been anyone in
all of the many areas of success you've had in political life, in charitable life, in
all of your business world that you've thought, if I could collaborate with that person, and
you've mentioned extraordinary people, Bob Hawke and Paul Keating.
I want to ask you actually before I go about Bill Clinton too, because you came across
Bill in your-
Oh yeah.
I was going to say to you.
Could I ask you about that before I go to the final, because you're a minister for defense.
You come across the legendary Bill Clinton who-
No.
I was minister for the environment and I went to Washington and I was meeting up with the
head of the EPA there, a great woman called Carol Brana.
And she said to me, do you want to come to the Earth Day speech by the then president?
And I said, sure.
Sure.
I'd love to.
I'd be honored.
So without any notice, I went along.
I was on the front row and in comes Bill Clinton.
And he comes along the front row to shake hands with us.
And he shakes hands to Carol and Carol introduces to me.
And he grabs my hand and he looks into my eyes and he says, oh, Roz, he said, so wonderful
to have you here.
We're so privileged.
He gets up to speak.
And before he speaks, this is the president of the United States.
He says, well, I'd just like everyone before I speak to welcome Roz Kelly, Australia's
environment minister here.
Australia is so special to us.
And we're so thrilled to have her.
Would everyone, would you stand up, Roz, and everyone can welcome you.
Well, I was a goner.
Like how good was that?
That was pretty good.
They talk about the legendary charisma that he had and you experienced it first up.
Yeah, I sure did.
My husband always asked me the question, what if?
I said, no, no.
Never happened.
Because you know you'd be a chance.
I think.
You never.
That's.
But that was a great privilege being in part of all that.
And do you know what?
When I was, I think there are some fabulous women leaders.
One I've always been fascinated was, was Indira Gandhi.
And just that sort of style of motherly leadership, which you could do in a culture like India.
But wouldn't be appropriate here.
But to look at some of those great leaders who in their time just made such an impact.
I mean, that is just a great privilege.
I read quite a lot about the history of some of those women.
Yeah.
I didn't quite get to the final point about, has there been someone through your journey
that you thought I'd love to just collaborate with them on any part of your life?
Is there another name that springs to mind?
Well, I think it is.
I would have.
I really, really would love to work on some of those big change, charity change things.
Like with, I think I'd really like to work with Hillary Clinton.
I've just finished reading her account of not winning.
And oh my God, how different the US would have been if she would have got elected.
And to think of what she put up with.
So do.
I mean, I just, I would love to have spent more time with her comparing notes.
And I know her and Julia have done that.
And they've done a great podcast together, which everyone should listen to.
So Julia and Hillary Clinton have.
Yeah.
Fantastic.
I've done a podcast.
Yeah.
Look that up.
That would be, that would be fascinating.
And you're right, isn't it?
To think what you paved the way, you know, in the early eighties and late seventies.
But to see, you know, on the international stage, what Hillary Clinton had to put up
with.
What politics she sit on.
And the language that was, you lock her up, chanted at her.
Oh, it was terrible.
And the book I read, you know, I've been, as I said, I've been reading her book about
what went wrong.
But what they go through, the sort of campaigns.
I mean, any human being getting through, going through those, you know, the pre-selection
processes to start with, you know, even before you even get into the main race.
Oh, it's inhumane.
Ros.
Your book is titled A Passionate Life.
It's an extraordinary life of leadership and success and openness and, you know, starting
with very humble beginnings.
You read about where you grew up and to get yourself a scholarship at university and go
on and paved the way for so many people, especially women in Australia.
It's a great honor to have been able to sit down with you and I really appreciate it.
Thanks for joining me today.
Thanks for the program.
Thanks, Ros.
Thanks a lot.
Empowering Leaders was presented by Me.
Me.
Luke.
Darcy.
Produced by Matt Dwyer with audio production by Darcy Thompson.
Start your leadership journey.
I encourage you to go to elitacollective.com.
Take our empowering leaders indicator tool and understand the impact you have on your
environment.
Join us at Elida to learn, lead, and collaborate.
Listener.