A Listener Production.
G'day, it's Luke Darson.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership both on and off the field
has been a lifelong passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective
and have had the privilege of working with thousands of leaders
in education, sport, industry and the arts
that have helped shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership
where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
Russell Halfcroft, in many ways, is the public face
of brand marketing and advertising in Australia.
Russell's 24 years in the advertising industry
included five years in the UK, co-founding and running his own agency,
eventually becoming chairman and CEO of Young & Rubicon Brands Australia
in New Zealand.
Russell's love and passion for advertising has been highlighted
on the ABC TV's Gruen, one of the most watched shows
on Australian television every year, co-hosted by Russell and Will Anderson.
Russell's diverse career has included stintings
at Network 10 as executive general manager,
chief creative officer and partner at PricewaterhouseCooper,
founding partner of Sayers and now co-host alongside radio legend
Russ Stevenson on Melbourne's number one breakfast show on 3AW.
Russ, it's always great to see you.
That's the nicest intro I've ever had.
Thank you.
I put some thought into it, Russ, because it's a diverse
and creative passion-filled life that you've had
and there's been some big leadership roles in amongst it
and you've managed lots of people.
Russ, there was a quote I heard attributed to you,
and this may be wrong, please correct me,
that work-life balance is bullshit.
Yeah, I did say that.
Do you stand by it?
Yeah, I do.
What do you mean?
I just think that it's one and the same thing.
I don't think they're two separate parts of your life.
I think that my life is work and work is my life.
I'm very happy.
It's not that I'm a workaholic and I don't want to go home.
I just don't see it as a line.
I don't see it as I'm going to stop work now,
I'm going to start life now.
I think work and life.
I think work and life is the same thing.
Would Kate agree with you?
Yeah, well, she's hung out with me a long time.
I think she would understand that, yeah, she would get that,
in that that is me.
You know, I'd be, I just, if I'm not working, what am I doing?
You know, I feel that that's where my energy comes from.
Yeah, and I love it.
I love how you explain that because I agree with that too.
I think because you've, I can't imagine you sitting in a space
that you weren't passionate about.
So you're not really, if the term work means something arduous
that you don't want to do.
That's right.
Then it's separate, isn't it?
But I think, you know, that concept of saying, you know,
there's other dimensions to you, Russ, and other parts of your life.
I'm going to talk about some of them.
If you get that out of whack because you focus solely on your income
driving part of your life, then that becomes an issue.
Would you agree with that or?
Yeah, okay, so that's good.
Yes.
Because I'm not a spreadsheet person.
I'm not looking at my personal spreadsheet.
That's not really what's, that's not what's driving me.
So it's not a focus on that.
It's interesting, isn't it?
Even when I was, you know, the dishwasher, I was very happy, you know,
in the bar doing the dishes and picking up the ashtrays.
I worked in wool stores.
That was pretty full on.
I was the only person that hadn't been to jail working in the wool stores.
I learned a lot there too.
Yeah.
I think that, you know, not to be hung up on this conversation,
I'm fascinated by your outlook on it, Russ,
but I think most of us feel like there's buckets of our life
that you want to give some attention to and clearly, you know,
work, however you describe that, is one of those buckets.
Yes.
And, you know, that idea that you're striving to make sure
that the other parts, the family parts, the contribution parts,
you know, the time you spend outside of that,
do you give that thought or is it just, you know, you just?
No, I think you're right about this.
I do think that it's important to really reflect on priorities.
I genuinely do think that that is the case.
And I do try and get some, you know, think hard about priorities.
And I do reflect on stuff that I know I should be better at,
most definitely.
And I reckon over time, over like the last two decades,
I've got marginally better at the stuff I'm not that good at, you know,
but only marginally.
So it's hard, right?
But I do, as part of trying to improve, I write a lot down.
So the notion of journaling or the notion of diaries,
the notion of really reflection, I do actually very,
I genuinely believe in that.
And I genuinely believe it's a powerful tool that we should all do.
Yeah.
So what's your habit?
I'm leaning, Russ, and it's, you know, clearly an audio medium,
but that, you know, happens to me just every day,
where you're constantly taking stuff down.
I'm flicking pages of highlight and scribble.
That's right.
Is that you?
Is that how you go about it?
If there's an idea or something that catches your mind,
you carry a notebook and.
Yeah.
I'm a little, yes is the answer.
Broadly speaking, yes.
I mean, I have a bit of a system that I've used for a very long time.
I actually put it to bed for a couple of years,
but it's found its way back into my life, which I'm thankful for.
Can I delve a bit deeper?
Were you prepared to share the system?
What do you do from that perspective?
Yeah.
Well, I.
So I just have a, I have a diary, a specific diary,
which is a page per day.
And so on that page there, I then divide it into half.
I make sure that I write down what I'm doing every single day.
So yes, I have it in a digital context,
but I also make sure I write it down.
I just, just the pure act of writing it down.
I think really for me,
it ensures that I really appreciate it and have a really strong
outlook.
You know, I want to know what's coming.
And I think the digital world doesn't allow that enough.
Um, and then I, on the right hand side,
that will be all the things that need to be done on the weekends.
I just write the, the weekends.
It's not the page isn't divided into two on the weekends.
I'm just writing about what's happening, what's going on,
what I want to do, what should have happened.
Um, reflections, um, which I find to be a,
a really strong thing to do for me.
Um, because it does allow that time just to sit,
maybe relax into it a bit.
Cause if I'm not relaxing into it, well,
then I'll just keep going a little bit, you know, without thinking.
And you said it disappeared for a couple of years,
but you started again.
What happened?
I, I think it was, um,
probably starting the radio it because as you know,
Luke, it becomes, it, it's a very tiring enterprise.
For those listening, Russell was, uh,
I mentioned in the intro, uh,
um, the, the half alongside, uh, Ross Stevenson on 3AW Breakfast,
which is the extraordinary success story of radio in Australia really,
and dominate the, the ratings and, uh, very much sought after, uh, spot Russ.
And you're how long into that?
That's, um, it's probably 20 months, 20 months.
Yeah.
And change of gear for you.
It is, it is.
And so that, that becomes, it's, uh, you know, it's tiring, it's tiring.
And even if you're like me, it's still tiring, you know?
So.
I've had to sort of really work on how do I, how do I actually make my day work?
Um, and you know, making your day work when you get up at, you know, a bit after four
and go to bed a bit after eight, that's a very different life.
And so I've had to sort of rewire.
Um, and I think that's probably the right words as well.
Like you've got to hardwire yourself, don't you?
Yes.
It's a hardwiring exercise.
I think I'm there now.
So that's good.
And so maybe I'm sort of getting back into my old rhythms.
I think I saw you about.
Eight weeks in and you look like you've been run over by a bus, Russ.
And it is a, it is just a huge discipline, isn't it?
To, to get that right.
But you've got your spark, uh, back, which I'm, I'm not surprised, but you're right.
The discipline, um, having done it for 11 years, it's, uh, the discipline counts, doesn't it?
I want to switch to one of your great loves, uh, Russ, the Melbourne football club.
And in recent times, the extraordinary success that, uh, 57 years of premiership drought
that was ended, uh, last year, beating the team that I love.
Yes.
Bulldogs.
Um, in fact, I might jump into, there's a great leadership story there that I, and I,
I promise you, I'd ask you about this.
Max Gorn is the captain of the club that you love, the Melbourne football club.
I look at him as an outstanding leadership story.
You know him well, Russ.
How, how would you describe him?
Um, incredibly, he's very, he's a gentleman, he's a gentle person.
And yet he is fierce about ensuring that he gets the best out of himself and the best
out of the club.
It's a really wonderful, I, I really, I'm at, at, at a really banal level.
I love people that are soft on the outside and as hard as on the, on the inside, right?
I think that they have great appeal to me and that's definitely Max, right?
There's a soft element to him, which is very appealing and endearing, but geez, he's hard,
right?
And so, you know, he's had two knee reconstructions for goodness sake, right?
And, and took a while to get going.
And then as soon as it clicked down at, you know, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the,
the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the,
you know, it clicked and away he went.
It, and he works hard on himself.
He is a very good leader.
Um, there isn't anyone on that list that wouldn't feel that Max is connected to them.
So what is there?
42 on a list and the, and the lists turn over pretty significantly, you know, so he's been
there for more than 10 years.
He's probably, I don't know.
He's probably had 160 different players, you know, maybe not as many as that.
certainly 100 over that period.
He'd know all of them.
He'd know all of them well,
and he'd make sure that he's touching everyone, so to speak.
He'd know their partners.
He probably knows the name of the pet, right?
He is that sort of person, which is a great skill in life, isn't it,
to really have genuine interest in individuals beyond their, you know,
just the capacity to perform on the footy field.
He's got great empathy with people.
I always knew he was going to be a great leader.
I could see that right from the beginning.
Don McLarty and I were big fans and others on the board.
Of course, Jim.
Jim was onto him straight away.
We were really happy when he arrived at the football club.
And the joints thrived, you know.
I always knew he was – it's easy to say, but I did.
I always knew he was going to be the captain,
and I always knew he was going to hold up that Premiership Cup.
I was convinced of it.
And in fairness, Russ,
you have said that publicly and privately for a long period of time.
And I love that you saw that in him because, you know, he's quirky, Max.
He's such a great guy to be around.
But the era I played in, I don't think Max would have survived quite
or thrived as much because, you know,
his quirkiness wouldn't have been as celebrated at the start.
I remember when he did his second knee injury, and I thought,
that's a shame, you know.
He won't ever get to how wrong was I because,
to do what he does now, and as you said,
and do it with a smile on his face.
He's not the old school Ruckman where, you know,
you have to try all the bluff and bravado.
He's tough as anyone that's played, as you said.
But I think, as you said, that care and connection,
which is, again, part of what we're seeing.
Great leaders now have got that in spades.
You're making me think of a game, I reckon, five or six years ago.
So Max is still on his way, but you could tell that, you know,
things are going well.
He was clearly an important player.
He was an important player.
We're playing North Melbourne.
Goldstein's going really well.
So what they've done is they've worked out that what Max does,
he starts on one wing on the 50 arc, and he's going to run,
basically he's running along the wing as the ball's going to be kicked out.
This is just, you know, some method that they've created.
And he has targeted the entire, you know,
the entire 50-meter arc, smashed, every single time.
But at no point did he do anything other than just keep going
and keep going and keep going and keep going.
And I watched it closely throughout the game,
and it just made me love him even more, right?
It's like, I'm just going to keep going.
Yeah, it's good.
It's an inner determination, Russ, isn't it?
You mentioned Jim Stines, and for those that don't follow Australian
rules football, another extraordinary figure,
another close friend of yours.
I had the great pleasure and privilege of playing against Jimmy Lott,
spending a lot of time.
Was he hard to keep up with?
Oh, yeah.
He was scary.
He was a real idiot.
What he did was, you know,
to bring that running capacity into that role when no one had ever been
out of cover of the ground.
He was running better than the midfielders were running,
winning all the mid, and you'd stand in them,
and you'd think, geez, he's not that big, the Irishman.
Surely we'll be able to, you know, get on top of him.
But what you underestimated, which everyone knew in the end,
was this talk about resilience and toughness as well in Jimmy's
inimitable fashion.
It's a great history for your club to have Jimmy hand the jumper to Max
and to see that.
That must have been, on your list of great days,
I'm tipping.
That was up there, wasn't it?
And you know what?
I watched it on the couch with Kate, and that was it.
And in a way, you think, oh, that's sad.
But no, it wasn't sad at all.
I was thoroughly happy being there on a couch with my wife,
and that's it, you know.
We would have liked to have been at the MCG, of course,
but we weren't, and we couldn't be.
And it was just a stunning day and a stunning evening, I should say.
We had a fellow that used to, a footballer that used to live with us,
and, you know.
And he was, just started on the list, so this was 10 years ago.
And he sent us a text at halftime, don't worry, don't worry.
Their fitness will come to the floor.
And then about 10 minutes into the third quarter,
he sent a text saying, have you noticed that Patraca
isn't even puffing yet?
You know, and so I took strength from that.
Yeah, I was calling the game on Triple M,
and Jason Dunstall were working with, said,
about that halfway mark of the third quarter, said,
Melbourne can't win.
And I wanted to kill him.
Because you just don't say that, Russ.
And I could still sense that there was plenty of Melbourne.
Well, the Bond, when the Bond kicked 19 points ahead,
and he was on his way, obviously, to just dominate.
He's such a stunning player.
And how good is he as a leader?
He's unbelievable.
He's easy to love.
Not just being a Footscray supporter, he's very easy to love.
So, yeah, we got into, yeah, we started to panic.
What type of leader do you see yourself as, Russ?
I like people to shine.
I like people to feel that they've got the opportunity
to genuinely be their best.
I like, you know, it's cool now to say I like diversity,
but I've always liked diversity.
You know, I've always sought out people that were agitators,
people that were different,
people that had a really interesting perspective,
creative people.
I've always had a great affinity with, you know, creative people.
I'm reasonably creative myself, but nowhere near, like,
the serious X factor that, you know, I've really enjoyed working with.
So if you sort of seek those people out and you finish up leading them,
as I've done on, you know, for quite a long time,
you've got to like them, you know, and you've got to want them,
you've got to allow them to shine, you know,
and you've got to want them to do well.
And then I think coach them, but not in a heavy-handed way.
I think that that's going to fail as well.
Coach them.
Coach them with a small C and delicately, you know,
go to places which are really important, I think,
for your collective success.
So in particular in my advertising life,
I needed creative people to do well.
So I needed to work out how to manage them because for me to do well,
I needed them to do well.
And what will often happen in a sort of an advertising agency situation
is that the management will,
will,
will not allow creative people to shine because it's safer, right?
So I, I was always up for, you know,
going to places which were really interesting and I,
and I would love leading the way in,
in selling ideas, you know, and selling concepts.
I really wanted to do my best for the client by convincing them that ideas
were really important, right?
So I don't know.
I sort of feel like I was both, you know,
at the front when I had to be,
but I was much happier just coaching people along and giving them a hand
at being their best.
Russ, there's a couple of things on that, that I've, you know,
I'm immediately interested straight away.
And I think you gave the caveat and said, you know,
saying you like diversity is cool now, but, you know,
clearly that has been part of your life.
And people like me, I'm finding it is an education.
You know, if you're, I'm a, you know, middle-aged now,
white male, Russ, who hasn't had, you know,
the exposure to being,
I suppose on the receiving end of what it's like to not be included.
And so, you know, in reality, you have to teach yourself and say,
a lot of Australians have a very different experience.
But so was it your creative sense that drew you to those people initially
that thought, hey, this is going to be great for me as well,
as much as you wanted to look out for other people?
Yeah.
I think that, you know, my father used to say to me, everyone's the same.
Like he'd say, we're all a balance sheet.
We've all got assets and liabilities.
And ultimately the balance sheet looks the same, right?
He was sort of very into, and, you know, he's, he's like us.
He's white, you know, he's got a, he had a very middle-class background,
but a very creative person.
My grandfather on my mother's side, he was a pharmacist in Footscray
and I'd go out there and work there.
And, you know, over summer, that was a pretty diverse, you know,
range of people that he was, he was very interesting fellow out there
in that he is very charitable and he was a sort of a leader out,
you know, in Footscray.
Um, the head of Rotary out there for years and, um,
had a great sort of generosity of spirit.
Um, again, was all, everyone's equal.
Um, that I think when I think about it now, I think that was a big part of me,
me growing up and I, you know, I mean, people that are tall have always annoyed me,
you know,
A bit of short man syndrome, Russ, along the journey.
You know, and people that were quick, they annoyed me as well.
I wasn't, I was never fast enough.
But, you know, but ultimately in there, and then it was a really powerful thing
that happened to me when I went to the UK.
Um, so I arrive as, as an Australian fella and I get a job at a, at really one of the
very best agencies in the world.
It was called Lowe Howard Spink, um, which now is sort of, there's still the Lowe group
around the world, but Lowe Howard Spink, London based, unbelievable agency.
Just at the point that I was there, I just got very lucky.
And being an Australian, they absolutely loaded me up with prejudice.
They loaded me up with that.
I was clearly a colonial, um, that I was fundamentally racist and that I had to be a
sexist.
All right.
That was just, they, they really genuinely loaded me up.
That was the British perception of what a young Australian would be like coming across.
Did that hit you in the face?
It absolutely did.
And then when I would say things that were maybe, you know, inappropriate, they, they
were on.
They were on to me very quickly.
And, and I learned a lot really fast when I was there.
And I, and I realized that I was coming from some prejudice.
Genuinely, I was, you know, I went to an all boys school for starters, right?
So that can have an effect on, on how you see life.
Thankfully, my, I, I only have sisters and all my cousins are girls slash women.
So, you know, I was always surrounded by women.
However, you know, there's going to have, there's going to be an effect, right?
So I, I, I think I was educated very on in my professional life.
Well, early on in my professional life that, um, you needed to just have a really broad
perspective.
And, and, you know, in the UK, it was fascinating in that they were really into getting different
skill bases from different areas.
You know, they would love getting the comedian from Essex, you know, and then they would
love to get the Northern, the Northern English person who was just the freak illustrator.
And they really sort of sought, this is a particular in the ad world maybe, but they
really sought difference.
Um, and I got along.
I got along really well in there in the end.
Well, you know, once, once I got over what, you know, their prejudice to me in the end,
they were pretty keen on me.
So, you know, we, we did well in the end.
I'm not surprised there.
Uh, so going back to what you, your first comment, you said that, you know, in leadership,
you found that for, for people in your role, it was safer to not let creative people shine
and thrive.
Why is that the case?
And what did you do to allow them to, to sort of, to thrive?
Well, I think in the, see, there's a, there's a bit of an interesting thing in that.
Um, commercially, you, you want the client to be happy, um, and you want them to be happy
because you want to, you want them to keep giving you money, right?
So, so sometimes you'll try hard to make it as easy for them as you possibly can, right?
And often the path of least resistance keeps, keeps everyone happy, right?
So, so you're acting as a servant to their needs.
Um, and that's okay to a point because you must be very conscious that you're not wasting
clients' money.
Well, all right, so they might have a good idea.
They may, they may feel very strongly, believe very strongly that what they want to do with
their money is right and it may well be right.
So you can facilitate that, but equally, you've got to be onto it.
You've got to be onto, no, there's a better way to do this because, you know, a client
spends a dollar, that dollar is either going to work reasonably well or work really well.
So let's work hard to make it work really well.
That is the path of least resistance mainly.
And you have to work really hard to get people to do it.
And you've got to find the language, I think, in order to help people understand it.
You can't say, Hey, Hey Luke, see this idea.
It's awesome.
It's going to sell.
You've got to work a bit harder than that, you know, trying to, trying to convince people
that is worth the, in many cases, millions of dollars of investment.
It's worth it.
And you've got to find the right argument to get people to understand that it's worth
it.
So I really enjoyed that challenge.
And, and in a leadership sense, getting people to do it.
Yeah.
And getting people around you that help you with that challenge.
It's, it's a great skill.
It's a, because you've sold ideas, Luke, right?
It's hard to do.
Yeah.
And, and in particular, I think in Australia, I don't like talking us down.
I like, I'm sort of, I like talking us up mainly, but we do like saying no.
And it's an easy word to say, and my God, it's a powerful word.
In business, no, you get stopped in your tracks, right?
Yeah.
So I used to say to clients, look, it can't be done.
Can we just agree that you're going to say maybe?
Before we start, let's get to maybe.
Let's get to maybe.
You do that up front, would you?
Yeah.
And, um, I used to play tricks as well with, um, just putting things on whiteboard, you
know, on the whiteboard.
One of the lovely tricks is you put on the whiteboard, assume good intent, and they wouldn't
know that you put it there just before the meeting.
They think that it's there because, you know, someone hasn't wiped down the whiteboard.
And as you do, as you do, when you walk into a meeting, you always,
you know, sort of scan the room and you'll just sort of see there, assume good intent.
I was convinced that they had this wonderful sort of subliminal power that the client would
actually, you know, behave in a different way.
Well, these people, they've got good intentions in mind, you know, they only have my, the
client's best interests in mind.
I'm going to assume good intent.
So I was very convinced that that was a, you know, a powerful way to conduct a meeting.
Did, you know, we did okay.
So maybe it worked.
One of the old sayings in the advertising world is that 50% of all advertising doesn't
work and 50% does.
We just don't know which 50.
So you're going to have to trust us.
And, uh, and the 50 that does is really power.
I love passion, right?
And I love it comes in so many different forms.
And your love of this space to me is so interesting.
And so could you just, for those listening that don't quite understand, and I'm thinking
maybe some of the great ad campaigns in history that come to mind, just to maybe share with
us why you love it so much.
Well, it's, it is genuinely the, the connection of commercial, commercial power and creativity.
You know, that, that's, that's ultimately the advertising space design also plays a
role, you know, so beautiful design.
So that tissue box that we're looking at there right now is a shocking bit of design, right?
So I'm highly unlikely to pick that one up in preference to a better design box.
And I feel a bit lazy that I left that out before our conversation started.
So you can do things well, or you can do things badly, you know, in a, in a commercial, in
an idea sense.
So I suppose ultimately my interest is in ideas.
And, um, I've always liked.
I liked a good idea and just throughout, you know, all my life, I've always just, I
don't know, my sort of core conversations about ideas, not just advertising ideas, just
ideas of all shapes and sizes.
So I, I just like them and I like what they can do.
And then in a, in an advertising sense, in particular, in the old mass media world, you
know, when 80% of the Australian population watched the eight 30 movie on a Sunday night,
whether it was on seven, nine or 10, and you would see an ad, you know, you'd see you ought
to be congratulated.
You know, Meadowlee, Margarine, and we, you'd see like literally 80% of the population would
see it at the same time.
Was that how big it was at the peak of, uh, of free to air TV?
The 80% of Australia was watching.
Yeah.
A given.
And you, you would roadblock the, uh, the commercial break.
So what a roadblock was, it was seven, nine and 10.
You would buy in this example, a Meadowlee ad at exactly the same time on every channel.
So if someone dared flick the channel, then they were going to see the same ad anyway,
right?
So I used to love saying, was that common?
Was that, Oh, you have to have a lot of money to do it.
You're a big advertiser.
If you did it.
Yeah.
I used to say, you know, who invented the remote?
So whoever, whoever invented the remote control wasn't into advertising.
Remote control is completely stuffed advertising because you know, if you go right back to
when I was a kid, you had to get off your couch to go and change the channel.
So of course you had to watch the ads.
Anyway, people avoid ads now.
I don't know why they do that, but they do.
I remember when the first remotes came in, it was a, you know, I remember, you know,
some people used to sit on the couch with a pool cue and you know, that was sort of
your chance to press the button and change channels.
But I used to love, um, when, when we purchased the Big Bash, when I was at 10 and we purchased
Big Bash, I used to love going around, you know, selling the ad space, selling to big,
you know, big advertisers.
We'd tell, talk, talk to them about Big Bash and what we were going to do with Big Bash.
I said, look, the best thing about Big Bash is that the cricket gets in the way of the
ads.
I'm sure Cricket Australia would love that.
Yeah.
Six balls, then an ad.
Well, no, no, no.
It's an ad, then there's six balls.
I don't know, you could get away with that, with saying that.
I didn't quite get out of you, just an ad that people will know and why it's, why it's
good and why you have such passion for it.
Well, okay.
So if we think about our world, our, the, your, the great game you've played brilliantly
and the game I'm passionate and love and, you know, the AFL has done some brilliant
ads over, over, well, 20, 30 year period.
You know, I'd like to see that.
Which was a brilliant, a, seriously, that is a brilliant campaign where they were able
to sort of compare the, the skill, the skill of, um, a Australian rules athlete to the
skills of athletes from all around the world.
That was a very, really significant idea.
The Campaign Palace did it originally.
Campaign Palace is one of the great agencies, Luke, which, uh, which I'm sad to say doesn't
exist anymore.
Um, in fact, when I was the head of Y&R Brands, Campaign Palace reported into me and I, and
my, the bosses in New York, we decided that we couldn't go on any longer, any longer with
Campaign Palace.
That was sad.
Campaign Palace then moved into George Patterson.
Um, and George Patterson created that beautiful campaign.
You might remember where, you know, one of the opening scenes, you've got Gary Ablett
Jr. dodging a Toyota Land Cruiser, you know, and we had Chris Judd outrunning a stallion.
And I think we had Brownie on a gridiron field.
Um, oh.
And, uh, who was on the ice park, on the ice hockey rink?
I can't remember anyway.
We had a whole series of athletes comparing and beating, you know, global athletes.
It was good.
My mind went to, uh, Wayne Carey, the Roo Boy at his, at his peak, which was a Nike
ad too, which had a bit of that, him bowling over large objects and, uh.
And I got sent today a VB ad with Warnie in it.
Oh, wow.
Yeah.
And actually I'll, I'll flick it to you after this.
It is just a, it's a, it's a great.
It's a great commercial and it just shows the passion that people, that the people creating
the ad, it was George Patterson at the time for VB, the, literally you can see the passion
that the people making the ad have for Warnie and the passion for him to perform really
well and the passion he had for Cairns, obviously.
But it was just a really fantastic, great little, great little commercial.
We have to jump off there just for a moment, Russ.
We're sitting in the week where, um, we tragically lost Shane Warne and, um, anyone who was lucky
enough to come into his orbit.
As I know.
You did.
And I felt fortunate enough in, in the, the times you saw him, fortunate enough to have
some very funny and enjoyable nights, uh, involved with him.
Extraordinary person.
So unique in Australian culture who owned his mistakes, Russ, I think.
That's it.
Better than anyone I know.
That's right.
I think that was a superpower for, for him.
What are your thoughts when you, when you reflect on that?
That's absolutely his superpower.
And he, he was, he was so, actually, I think he was very objective about himself.
I think he had a very clear perspective about who and what he, what he is, was.
And he, he, he could be ashamed of himself, right?
But he was willing to admit that that wasn't good news, you know?
And I think that is, there's great power in, in that.
I actually think he was a very clever man.
I, I watched him last night.
They repeated the Lee Sayles interview.
And you could actually see a really strong intellect there, you know?
So we all know that he had cricket smarts, but I think that that might be underdoing it.
I think he was a really emotionally clever person.
And he was able to, well, he could think people out, you know, on the cricket field.
But I think that he was able to really sum, sum, summarize a situation at a very high level.
Like high EQ, they would call it, wouldn't they?
Like, and I, I, I genuinely think that's the case.
Just one quick story.
I was, in 2015, I was at Lords watching Australia play England.
And I was lucky enough to be asked into that, you know, the beautiful pavilion, the members pavilion.
Amazing.
I was.
I was asked to go into the Australian dressing rooms after they'd won.
And as I walked into that pavilion, there is this stunning portrait of Shane Warne.
So that in itself is interesting.
That is in the MCC, Marylebone Cricket Clubs, you know, that stunning pavilion that Shane Warne's there.
What's more interesting, he's in position 1A.
Like, they've put him in the very, the very premium position.
Such was how he was seen by the English.
They thoroughly loved him.
They loved the man.
And I think that he felt very comfortable there.
I think he felt that he could be himself there.
And they would have loved that larrikin nature, of course, you know.
Yeah.
You know, and there's that lovely, you know, and he was sort of like, he was a walking headline for the sun.
Right?
They would have loved him.
And we'll talk to you a bit about communication, which is clearly a huge part of your success in life.
But I, it was an amazing communicator too, Warne.
Yeah.
From even a social level.
I used to marvel that you'd be calling the footy in a St.
Louis game and you guarantee wherever he was in the world, you'd get, you know, if you, if you called something that he didn't like, you'd get a message or he was very inclusive if you were in town and there was something on.
He was extraordinary at collecting and collaborating people.
We missed one of them.
Lovely thing.
You know, Russ, whenever I had the pleasure of being in your company, you've got a great energy.
You know, you've always got this, you smile, you're up and you always feel inspired, you know, from spending some time.
Is that always been you?
Is that, is that part of your DNA or is that something you worked on?
No, I think it is me.
I think, thank you for saying that, Luke.
Um, on the radio the other day, my, um, stepmother, she's known as Elizabeth the second, my first, my, my father's first wife is Elizabeth, Elizabeth the first.
She's still alive.
My father's no longer alive.
And my father's second wife is also Elizabeth.
She's known as Elizabeth the second.
Anyway, so she was, um, on the radio talking about a project she's working on at the moment.
And, um, anyway, so they picked up on her surname and they said.
Oh, are you related?
And she said, yes, I'm Elizabeth the second.
And they said, um, is there anything, you know, can you tell us anything about when he was a younger fella?
He said, well, in the mornings he used to come down and he'd go to the shower singing, just call me angel of the morning, which was like, the tragedy is that's true.
So maybe I've always been a bit like that.
Just, you know, positive.
I have, yeah, I am a positive person.
On talkback during the pandemic.
Um, I used to occasionally be.
Accused of having, being, uh, being false positive, which, which was good language, you know, cause at the time things were a bit heavy and I was sort of, I'm not trying to find the positive things.
It's just, I suppose that's how I look at it.
And it's unique, Russ.
And it's such a special gift to have that around people.
Cause I think we think the human mind often does catch the negative too often and more often.
And you hang on to those things that are challenging and not celebrating the things that, that are more joyful.
So, uh, it is great.
Hopefully it's not too false too often, but yeah.
I don't suspect there's anything false about anything you do, Russ.
We're talking through the lens of leadership a bit today and we've been identifying, we're seeing a real shift in the way leaders are about being more collaborative, Russ, more self-reflective.
It seems a new era away from hierarchy and command and control.
And at the moment in America, they're calling it the great resignation.
In Australia, I think the phrase has been termed the great reshuffle.
Are you seeing that, that, that trend as well?
And is, is, is leadership.
Going to play a role in that?
I actually, you know, you know, if we, if we're talking about politicians, right, politics, you still, in the end have to have a great perspective about where we're going to go and why we're going to go there.
And you have to have, I think the ability to sell that as well.
Yeah.
I think that that is something which, which we've seen in a political, when we see it in a political sense, we know it and we like it.
I do think that leadership matters.
It matters enormously.
I actually respect all politicians.
It doesn't matter their colour because they're doing it and I'm not.
Yeah.
I genuinely do.
Right.
So they are, they are putting themselves in that position.
They're putting themselves up for all that, you know, the debate and the, the ups and the downs and they can, they can, they can get scarred pretty heavily.
Yeah.
Right.
And so I do respect them.
Um, I like to listen to them and I like to try and think it through.
Um, I have a, I have a leaning in a particular way, but equally I might, I might hear some arguments from, you know, the other side.
You go, well, actually, you know, that makes a lot of sense.
But I, yeah, I do.
First and foremost, I respect them.
Yeah.
And that's great.
But again, it's, it's your natural inclination.
And I, and you know, when you're reflecting here, you say that I do.
And so we should, because I know I could never do that or never want to do it.
Well, you could do it if you wanted to do it.
But I wouldn't be prepared.
We'd be all be better off if you did do it.
I'd be not prepared to put up with what would be required and the sacrifice and the cost.
So you're right.
It's easier to, from the outside say, I don't necessarily like where it's heading, but if you're not prepared to put yourself in the arena on that one, you're not going to do it.
And you're probably right.
We probably do need to pay a bit more respect.
Hey, we started talking about this just before we started recording.
Interestingly, we got onto the schools and we've, we've, we've, our kids have gone to the same school and we're talking from your lens, creativity that pours out of you.
One of the most watched TED Talks ever.
I'm not sure if you've seen it.
So Ken Robinson, 73 million people have downloaded it.
Have you, have you seen it?
The title is Do Schools Kill Creativity?
It's a, it's a great TED Talk.
Go and check it out if you, if you haven't seen it.
It resonates really strongly with me.
Did it have the same effect on you?
Fundamentally.
The, it's really interesting.
There's some data that was done and I'll, I'll have to paraphrase it because I can't remember precisely.
But when NASA was trying to find the super freaks to put in a rocket and send to the moon, they, they created some studies, some research, I should say, to find the individual that was highly analytical to be expected, but highly creative.
All right.
And they created this research that could in effect measure creativity.
And then they, over the years, and they still use this research, they've, they've discovered that, you know, that 95% of five-year-olds have got creativity at the genius level.
When they're 10, it's about 75% of 10-year-olds.
When they're 15, it's sort of 35%.
By the time we're sort of young adults, most of the creativity has been taught out of us.
Uh, that is clearly a problem.
It's pretty sad when you, when you point it out as directly as that.
Yeah.
You can track it.
I'll, I'll have to send you the actual data, but it is, I'm broadly right.
There's another thing on YouTube.
So watch that one.
The, uh, that.
Sir Ken Robinson's TED Talk.
Yeah.
Watch that.
The other one to watch is the, um, the spaghetti, uh, challenge.
And the spaghetti challenge is you've got 20 strands of spaghetti, sticky tape, and some string and chewing gum or bubble gum, you know, like a ball of bubble gum.
Yep.
You've got to build the tallest tower with spaghetti.
You put bubble gum on.
Now, accountants are terrible at it.
Um, good news is architects are pretty good at it, but you know who else is really good at it?
Kindergarten kids.
And they're really good at it because they collaborate and they, when it doesn't work, they don't care.
Yeah.
They just, they just keep going until they find some sort of solution.
It's another beautiful example that yes, school absolutely does teach creativity out of kids.
Um, you know, my, it's rather nice story in my family.
My father was.
The ducks of, of art at school, my grand, my, my son was ducks of art at school and he said, oh, good on you, Louie.
Well done ducks of art.
He said, dad, there's only six people doing it.
He said, well, yeah, there was only six people doing it, but 240 had the opportunity to do it.
So that is a, that's not good, is it?
So at, at a school, at a school, big school, plenty of resources, 240 kids, six people do art.
Yeah.
Right.
It's just mad.
So there needs to be far greater effort put into.
And especially as AI becomes a huge part of our lives, um, where the AI, the bots, the machines are going to do so much, um, so much and lit analytical work.
The thing that we've got over robots is creativity.
Yeah.
So we have to work much harder at that.
So the rote learning aspect and the, you know, the textbook learning needs to be upended clearly and, and engage kids.
Is it as simple as that?
It is as simple as that.
And there needs to be a complete overhaul.
I mean, it's fascinating, isn't it?
When you, when you go to school, you're, you're, you're measured on a one, one-to-one basis.
Your teacher measures you.
What have you done in your work life, which is just you?
Right.
Almost nothing.
Nothing.
Yeah.
We, you absolutely have to collaborate, cooperate, create together.
And now that happens in other fields at school.
You do your house sports or you do your footy or your cricket, whatever.
So yes, it's not like it's devoid of the notion of the collective, but.
Yeah.
It's not really taught as core, as a core curriculum.
And that is genuinely, that's genuinely a problem.
I'm rather proud of the fact that, so second, the other son, I don't even know what he got for VCE.
I'm not even sure he got double figures.
Right.
I can also tell you, I don't care.
Yeah.
And he's a highly creative cat and he is doing really well in life.
Right.
So it, and I, of course that's a nice story because it's him, but I do feel like we're
just, there's too many kids with high creativity, high capability that are just streamed in
another direction and it's sad.
It's a, it's a great conversation, Russ, one to explore further another time.
And I think this obsession with an ATAR or a score, what does it mean to Russell Howcroft
or anyone really?
I mean, there's probably a couple of disciplines where that makes sense, but for everyone else,
there's a, there's a huge disruption that is required.
On that note, Russ, we've been, I'm fascinated with your creative brain on this because we've
been identifying.
And the work we're doing, a business called A Leader, supporting educators and leaders
in sport and industry and the arts.
And we're identifying these different traits that we think make great leadership.
I want to ask you about these different traits.
So please expand, Russ, as much as, as you feel comfortable with, in your hands with
that.
One of the, one of the traits we're seeing is self-leadership is a big thing that most
people have an understanding of.
Yes.
What does self-leadership mean to you?
Well, I, I really like that.
And, and haven't we discovered during the pandemic that self-leadership is real, you
know?
So the individual who gets out of bed.
And they're, they're by themselves.
They've been by themselves in their own workspace at home.
I mean, obviously we're talking about laptop workers, but they've self-started and they've
got on with their day.
And what's been, I think, very interesting for people is the notion that you can trust
the vast majority of people, um, which is something that I've always believed in there.
You know, it's, it's just as a silly aside at an agency that I started when I was 29.
I had a thing called the trust tract as opposed to the contract.
Cause I thought a contract, the first three letters is a bit of a problem, right?
So the notion that we should all, uh, back to school when I was in year 12 at school,
I'd try it.
And I was on the, you know, there was a school council or something.
I tried to get them to take all the locks off the lockers.
I said, well, why can't, surely we should trust people first and foremost.
Right.
And then if individual X is found to have done the wrong thing, I had gone into someone
else's locker.
Then the punishment.
Is really heavy, right?
So first and foremost, you trust second of all, you punish very, very heavily.
That to me is a far better perspective, especially with young people.
We're going to trust you all.
That's a better perspective.
How did that idea go, Russ?
Cause I love it.
Yeah.
There's still locks on the lockers.
It's just, it is, it's extraordinary that, that first and foremost, we want to sort of
assume, assume ill intent, right?
It's just, it's just not on.
So self-starting is.
I think it's about trust and it's about, yes, people are, they know they've got to
get on and do a good day's work.
Cause they know if they don't, they're not going to get paid at a really basic level.
And the notion that everyone is a leader, I think is really important.
And you know, when you do values, I wrote the values when I was at network 10 for the
network.
And one of the values was everyone's a leader.
And then that, I think if you practice that, then that really does, it's got a chance of
embedding it into culture.
Something I learned at PWC, they do this thing called a value share, a values share
where they literally in meetings say, okay, who'd like to share with us a, a, our values
in action.
So the other day I saw Luke do X, which reflects our, the value of meritocracy.
Good on you, Luke.
It sounds really weird, right?
It's almost Scientology.
However, it really works.
I, I, I'm a full convert.
I think it's a brilliant thing to do.
I'm the chair of the Australian film school at the start of every council meeting.
I do a value share and it's, it's an opportunity for people to talk about how the school is
reflecting what it wants to be.
It's brilliant.
You know, I love it, Russ.
And we talk about this a lot on this part, even, you know, celebrating what people are
doing well.
It's been a missed opportunity so often in the past that we find just having that moment
to reflect and say, Hey, first and foremost, we move on to the next.
What, what can we say?
I love doing it through the, the lens of value.
I love your trust track as well.
I think that's such a brilliant thought.
Did people, did you change it?
Did you?
I love it.
So you're the staff member.
I was 29, started an agency and, and when new employees came, they got a trust tract.
That is why we love the creativity of you, Russ.
We see leaders also a dimension we, we talk about really conscious of how they positively
impact others in their environment.
What's the lens through which you say that?
Yeah, well, vulnerability, of course, that it is, again, it's a bit of a, it's a bit
of a cliche now, isn't it?
But we do see it and we see that it's really powerful.
And, um, well, Luke Sayers is, uh, he was former CEO of PwC.
He started the Sayers group.
I'm a founding partner in that.
He's now the president of Carlton.
Here is someone, he was a, he, he embodies that new style of leadership, right?
He's, he's.
He is that, you know, when he's led thousands of people to PwC, right?
And basically doubled the business over his eight years as the boss.
And he is a perfect new style president for a footy club as well.
And that, that, that's the style of leader that he is.
And he wants input.
He's prepared to show vulnerability.
He's prepared to, you know, demonstrate when things are right, when things are wrong, wants
to talk about it, asks really uncomfortable questions.
You know, it's like, are you really asking me that?
But he does.
It's a, it's a very interesting, and I think what it does, it, and it's, and it's all in
an, in, in an environment of trust.
Cause if you're, if you're on his team, then he trusts you.
So there's no, there's no risk associated.
Just you say it as it is.
I think that's a really, that's a very powerful thing, isn't it?
If you feel vulnerable, you are unlikely to play a open, honest, trusting game.
If you feel strong and part of a team, you will be able to play.
In that new style of leadership.
Yeah.
It's brilliant to celebrate that style and see the success.
It equates to commercial success and it equates to happiness and more productivity.
And, um, I look forward to, to, to hopefully chatting to Luke at some stage.
Yeah.
You should get him on here.
We're very keen to, to, uh, to catch up with Luke Sayers.
I'll follow up that idea.
Yeah.
The idea of leaders creating and sharing a vision, I feel like is right to your forehand,
Russ, because you've done that through your world regularly.
How have you gone about creating and sharing a vision?
It's an interesting one, Luke, because I agree with you and I enjoy the process of developing
vision.
Um, I, I believe in it.
I really believe in core purpose.
You know, it's, again, it's sort of, it's become, it's become something that brands
talk about.
I'm not as interested in it from a brand point of view, like core purpose of a brand,
you know, soap to make you clean.
I'm not, you know, that sort of, it's a given, it's a given, you know, and so what they do
is that we're going to.
Because we make people clean, we're going to clean the world or, you know, they, they
try and find a.
Esoteric sort of.
Yeah.
Doesn't work for you.
Not really.
In, in that sort of consumer brand world.
Yeah.
Not really.
Um, you just need a proposition that sells, right?
We clean really well.
Yeah.
There might be underlying things, how you build your soap.
That's important, right?
I, we don't use slave labor, for example, right?
Yeah.
So I, I sort of get that, but corporate purpose or purpose around team, um, I really, really
believe in that.
And, and.
Finding the right words is a, is a very, it's an interesting exercise.
Um, and if you get it right, it can be, it can be extremely powerful and it is something
that you then can practice every day.
You know, I mean, I'm PwC again, core purpose, building trust in society and solving important
problems, right?
So we're going to build trust and we go and we're going to solve important problems.
Well, did it, did I like going to a place every single day that did that?
Right.
Yeah.
And, and they fully practiced it.
Every single day.
So I had great joy in, in, in, in, in working in a purposeful business.
And then I've done a lot of work with clients around core purpose, which again, I really
enjoy.
Nailing it is hard, but I'll tell you what's harder is getting them to spend the money
on distributing that core purpose to their staff.
So what will often happen is you'll do a job with a, a board, a CEO, an executive suite,
develop core purpose, and it gets turned into a PowerPoint.
And it may be a t-shirt, you know, it's sort of not a lived and breathed experience.
So, so getting your leadership to understand the value of, of, of sharing that down.
And so you're, so, so paraphrasing your, if it's authentic, authentically done and, and,
and some businesses, Patagonia clothing is a legendary business, you know, probably started
what B Corps look like.
Yes.
Uh, organizations that sign up to a set of values that mean they live things like, um,
you know, their impact on the environment and sustainability and a really powerful, you know,
powerful way.
So that's a subtlety for you.
If you're authentically doing that, you're on board.
If you're trying to grab a link to tick a box, it doesn't work.
Not really.
I, I, there was a, there was a book written a long time ago around lighthouse strategy
and lighthouse strategy being build the lighthouse and then put out the beam and then the beam
will catch consumers.
Yeah.
And then, and they're your consumers.
So the peak, that picture in your mind is, is a really good one.
And I sort of use that picture when I think about purpose.
So purpose being the lighthouse and then it will be attracted, right, to people will be
attracted to that, to that by the beam of light that you push out there.
I actually do believe that.
And I think that core purpose done well at a corporate level in effect becomes your advertising.
Yeah.
You don't have to put a whole lot of other layers onto it.
That, that should be enough.
Yeah.
That's fascinating from an advertiser that, uh, if you get purpose right, it's more powerful
than any advertising.
That's a really interesting takeaway for me, Russ.
We're seeing leaders see curiosity as a, as a real, a real strength.
And, you know, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I,
I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I,
like you and they, and their approach to their own self-improvement learning through curiosity.
Does that, does that make sense?
You got to have a library.
Yeah.
I think I genuinely, you must have a library.
You must forever be looking for things, new things I think are really important.
I mean, I, I used to read a lot in terms of books.
I'm, I'm trying to get back into reading books, but I always used to business books.
I used to love business books, you know, marketing, advertising, any business book.
If you could leave a, if you could leave a business book with, you know, one thing that
helps you, you know, be better, then that was probably, you know, worth the read.
So yeah, I, I genuinely try hard to, I don't know whether anyone's more curious than Ross
Stevenson.
I mean, he's, he's up there.
Um, I try and catch up to him most days.
He's deeply curious.
That's a great thing.
That's a great skill of his, of course.
But yeah, uh, one mustn't be closed, you know, and you certainly must never think that you
know everything.
I mean, obviously.
So always being on the lookout for, and I think being on the lookout for truth is not
really accurate either.
I'm not big on that one.
I think that there's always two sides to the coin.
It's quite interesting when you think about the idea that truth was a bit of a game that
was played.
Ancient Greece, we're talking here, Dars.
The, the notion that you, we would debate in order to find the truth was a game.
Really?
Yeah.
So, you know, Plato.
So it's, it, it does depend a bit on it.
It's, it's in the eye of the beholder.
There was always, there's always.
There's always different forms of the truth.
And I think sort of discovering both sides, sometimes I can be a bit contrarian because
I quite like, actually, it isn't like that.
It isn't like how we all think it is and coming up with a contrarian way, which maybe isn't
that endearing sometimes, but it's sort of, I think it's important.
Well, I find that fascinating.
You're going back to ancient Greece, but we're, you know, in an era now of, you know, the
concept of fake news is, is such a common term.
Yeah.
On purpose.
And then, then this search now to, to, to look up something that, you know, may be relevant.
I agree with your perspective.
The idea to be able to debate truth is a really important thing.
Yes.
Now we're getting debate on, on censored, people getting canceled, people being taken off these
massive platforms because your opinion, you know, is regarded as dangerous.
Yeah.
I mean, that, that is a, do you, is that a new thing or you're saying that goes all the
way back?
Because I, I find that a little, right, I mean, we lived through the last two years of
lockdowns and pandemics and things that should have been really heavily debated.
Yep.
Don't feel like that's been available.
None.
And information, whatever version of truth has been pretty hard to find.
Yeah.
Well, it's very interesting because at, at, it's good, this is a good discussion you've
asked.
I, at my, at, right down to my bootstraps, I'm a hardcore libertarian.
I'm, I'm liberal with a small L, right?
I, I like discussion.
I like debate.
I, I, people, people being forced to do things that they don't want to do, I, I, I find it
really hard to, to support that.
Yeah.
Just generally, you know, in a, in a, in my heart.
However, the rational part of these, of the discussion and the argument also has to be
taken into account.
And so I found myself every day over the last two years in conflict.
Yeah.
Because in my heart, I couldn't stand a lot of what was going on, but in my head I could
understand it.
Yeah.
Because as were you, you're in a place to talk about it.
And try and have the discussion and try and have the debate.
Still, it still wasn't easy, was it?
But I think that that's, that's, that's all we've got.
We have to be grateful that our media is free and it's open and none of us are censored.
So that's, you know, there's law.
We've got to be concerned with law, but that's not being censored.
Well, maybe not quite.
I mean, when you're seeing, and, and take this, and I mean, this is necessarily what, but
you know, when you see the president of the United States.
Get taken off.
Amazing.
Tech platforms.
Now, you know, quite openly, I, the hair stands on the back of my neck when I hear the former
president Trump, but I find him very hard to, I have to turn off because I have such
a reaction to a lot of the things he says.
I almost find it impossible to listen.
Some of them are, yeah.
Get the Chinese planes to bomb the Russia.
I mean, how do you get, like, get away with it?
And I can sort of understand in some elements why he was, but that just happened in a, in
fact, I can really understand why he was banned from some of those platforms.
Because of what was going on.
But yeah, you said there's no censorship, but yeah, that's true.
I, I, you're right.
However, we also do need to, there is a higher order here and the higher order is protecting
democracy, right?
So if you're actually undermining our way of life, that is a problem.
And if you've got the power to remove, in this case, an individual that's undermining
democracy, that, that is actually, for me.
Over and above.
That's over and above.
That's there.
There's a higher order here.
Yeah.
And in the end, in the end, we need to, we, because everyone else can keep debating.
We've just taken that voice out because that voice is actually, the dissent is so powerful
that's been created.
That it's dangerous and it needs to be censored.
That's an interesting way to put it.
And I understand that.
We see great leaders in the 21st century now, Russ, really understand their communication
and how they do it.
You're an incredible communicator.
You always have.
What's been the way that you've gone about it?
Well.
You, I was going to say scarcity, but that's, it doesn't, it doesn't quite wash, does it?
Oh my God.
Uh, I, look, I, trying to stick, trying to stick to what I know, um, I think has been
what I've done mostly.
So I feel very comfortable talking about ideas and advertising and, you know, so the, my,
initially I'd be on the radio with Virginia Trioli and I'd talk about ads, you know, and
then Gruen, I'd talk about ads.
Mojo did a documentary that's about ads.
It's different what I'm doing now for sure, but maybe that's cause I've just got a bit
more comfortable with media.
So sticking to what I know though has been the, that's been the core.
Um, I, I think I've, see, I wouldn't urge caution, uh, talking to the media.
Um, and I think a lot of people, they're, they're cautious when speaking to the media.
And I don't think that that's a good thing.
Um, Americans aren't cautious.
When talking to the media, they just go for it, right.
And they, they very much see the media as just part of their big democratic world.
That is the States, you know, there's everything's up for debate.
Everything's up for argument and everyone's discussions is fair and reasonable, you know,
to a point everyone, everyone's, everyone's, um, everyone's an open book and as a result,
they all do really good media.
Don't they?
So I think it's hard.
I think it's hard for Australians.
I think, uh, we have a natural caution.
Um, we don't want to show off for one.
Yeah.
Um, and for two, we're cautious about what, how we might get tripped up or we might say
the wrong thing and, and then not sleep at night.
You know, I think a lot of us are like that.
I have been like that.
I still am a bit like that.
So, um, cautious and tried to stick to my knitting, but none of that makes any sense.
I wasn't like that.
I'm more like that now.
Right.
I think the, the sort of cancel culture part, I think is a real, a real thing and you can't
actually say, sorry, you can't make a mistake.
You can't have slipped up.
And because, you know, more than you're in front of the microphone, the odds are just
going to say, you're going to get something out there that you didn't mean to, but you
haven't got that luxury anymore.
I mean, 15 years ago you could be looser, you know, and I think it was healthier because,
you know, you want to hear people as close to their real self and not guarded.
I'm not sure where.
Yeah.
I think that's true.
And there is an issue in that Google, let's just say Google, but it's all digital.
Doesn't forget.
Yeah.
So, and I think that's, that is really, that's not good for any of us.
Um, you know, maybe it's not good for you or I, because we're talking and this is, you
know, it's a lot of what we do is public, but for people that are deeply private, it's
not good for them either because, you know, you might Google that particularly private
person and discover seven years ago, something happened that, you know, wasn't good.
It's, it's.
You've taken, been taken out of context as well and, you know, an imbalance version of
what happened as well.
Yeah.
I don't, I don't like that.
I, cause I think that's unfair on all of us cause all of us make mistakes.
Of course we all, we all do.
Um.
There's a lovely piece of legislation in Europe called the right to be forgotten.
And you can actually, you, you've got to go through a very, a very major process.
So you can't be a naughty person and then say, I want to be forgotten.
You got to be a fine, outstanding citizen and then go through the process of being forgotten.
Getting your digital history cleansed affectionately.
Yeah.
And I'm, I'm going to go off the grid.
You can, you can be officially off the grid.
Yeah.
Which who knows?
That might happen.
Uh, that might become more prevalent.
I do think there needs to be a, a rebalance with regard to the big tech behemoth businesses
and all of us individuals, cause us individuals provide them with the data that they make
the money.
Right.
So there isn't, there isn't a balance at the moment.
I could talk more about what should happen there.
Should I?
Well, you know what I was thinking, Russell, I was, my mind was going back to Shane Warne
again and I was thinking why we love Warne so much is that he owned all of his history
and we loved him for it.
And I think as we could see our own failings and our own mistakes in it, and that was a
great celebration.
You needed to be as charismatic as Warne and taking 700 test wickets probably gives you
a bit of credit, Russ.
It does.
Not many did.
So there's a book, there's a book that someone could write and it could be called media brave
because he was media brave.
All right.
So he wasn't intimidated by what might happen as a result of a headline.
I don't think he was intimidated.
He might've, he might've had sleepless nights, but I don't feel like I'd feel like he was
brave.
And I don't know.
There's many.
That's your next book, Russ, media brave, and you are an author of, uh, of great repute.
So I encourage you to look up Russ's work.
It's a, it's definitely worth the final dimension I want to ask you about is, uh, the idea of
collaboration as being something leaders really seek out proactively now, how do you think
about that?
It's the new thing, isn't it?
And maybe we've always tried to find partners that, that were, um, going to enhance our
offer.
You know, the old synergy one plus one equals three, right?
So it's, it's not new.
The, the notion of collaboration cooperation, what I think is new is actually trying to
seek out the collaborate or collaborations that are out of the box.
So unexpected collaborations.
I think that's where it's getting very interesting.
So in an advertising context, when Crocs does a collaboration with KFC, that's really interesting.
Yeah.
Or when North face does a collaboration with Gucci.
That's really interesting.
So if you, if you sort of put Gucci brand extreme left, they should be collaborating
with someone who's extreme, right?
Yeah.
So thinking really beyond expectation for collaboration, that's where you're going to
find something really interesting.
So that's sort of, I think the new, the new way to think about it, not, not the obvious
partnership version.
Which is a brilliant, um, not surprised for us, your brain's going there and it comes
back to your love of diversity.
Doesn't it?
Yeah.
So that in people, you know, often groups get together that look a bit the same, sound
a bit the same, feel a bit the same, and we're moving the same circles.
When you bring the positive collisions together from unlikely sources in different areas,
you know, we're saying that in, in the work we're doing has been brilliant.
Right.
You know, why can't someone who conducts an orchestra have a big influence on a senior
sporting coach?
How good is that?
I'm sure they can.
And that, that doesn't necessarily look like it should match up.
I love that.
It's happening, you know, and it's happening in such a powerful way.
Yeah.
It's happening in such a powerful way.
Creative brains like yours overlapping into different areas is, is, is fascinating.
Two final questions for us, and I've loved, I could spend hours with you as always, but,
uh, the final two questions, who, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Oh, there's, oh, you can edit out this pause.
We're keeping this pause in for sure, Russ.
I love the thing.
There's a lot.
I, I, I really admired, um, obviously I'm not a big fan of the, um, the, um, the, the,
the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the,
the, the, the responsibility.
I, um, obviously I admire Jim.
I really did admire Jim.
Great Jim Steines, though.
He, He I, I genuinely did because he came into
a boardroom totally naive.
Like, really, he had no idea how to run a board meeting to be the, the president.
And yet he was able to get in a powerful group of people who then all genuinely collaborated
and he found a way to lead and was outstanding.
I mean, I, I sort of the Jim Steines era, there's pre and post cancer.
Yeah.
cancer is the truth of it. Pre-cancer, just incredible. And then
it got tough, clearly, after that. There's a
fellow called Hamish McLennan, who I've worked with a lot. He's now
the chair of Magellan, for goodness sake. He's an ad guy.
How did you do that, Hamish? Unbelievable. Ran Channel
10 in your era there. So I reported to him at 10. And when I was the regional
CEO of Y&R, he was the global CEO of Y&R. And he
is someone that just—he
really knows how to make stuff happen. He's got a powerful way just to
get stuff done. So I always admired that, because
I don't lead like that. So there was a degree of, geez, that's
pretty impressive, and I don't think I'd be able to do it. So there was a bit of admiration
off the back of it. I've talked about Luke before,
no question. He is a very good leader, for sure. Luke says, yeah.
Ted Horton is a terrific leader. He's one of the
great ad guys in Australia.
Just recently turned 70, still runs an agency
with employing a lot of people.
Does very, very, very well for himself.
In the media world, you've got, you know,
you've got Gingell, he's a terrific leader.
I haven't seen him for a long time.
I don't even know him.
I haven't seen him, you know, watched him for a long time.
I think he's on-
Former CEO of Channel 9 for a long,
lives in Byron Bay now, I think.
Right.
He's joined the pub game with great success.
And then, you know, you've got footy club leaders.
Of course, we've discussed Max.
Jack Trengove was on his way to being a brilliant leader.
He got injured and that was it, you know, terrible, did his foot.
He would have been one of the great captains of an AFL club.
He had all the qualities that you would want.
So that's, you know, hello to Jack.
Who else?
Roos.
Paul Roos, very good at being the king.
You know, there's something about hierarchy,
which actually does work as well, you know.
Ultimately, you know, someone who sits on the throne
and then everyone just lines up behind them.
Yeah.
He definitely did that at the Melbourne Footy Club.
And, you know, and maybe it's a sport thing, Darce, I'm not sure,
but you sort of do need to line up.
You need to get everyone in line.
If you're not lined up, then you're in a bit of trouble.
Yeah.
And he definitely got everyone lined up.
He got everyone lined up, no question.
Which reminds me of when I saw Ewan McKenzie.
You know, Ewan McKenzie, a coach of rugby union.
Yeah.
I was at school with Ewan.
And the day I was appointed to the Melbourne board,
I saw him in the street.
G'day, Ewan.
And then, you know, what have you been up to, Ra?
I said, well, today I've had a great day today.
You know, joined the Melbourne Footy Club board.
And he just says, mate, there's only one thing that matters.
You've got to have absolute alignment from the president to the CEO
to the coach to the captain of the team.
If you don't have that, you're cactus.
Well, it's pretty true.
Never a truer word spoken, Russ.
And I had that said to me when I was captain of the Bulldogs.
I had great info.
I'm sure you won't mind.
He was the president.
At that time, it was, I think, David Smorgon was still in the chair.
Yes, lovely fella.
And Campbell Rose was the CEO.
Yep.
Peter Rowe was.
We had some challenges.
We had some real challenges.
And I was probably getting frustrated,
wanting to try and solve things that weren't really in my capacity.
And the great Barry Richardson was an advisor to the,
the coach.
He was the coach at the time.
He said, he said, listen, you know,
you need that sort of alignment in every area and it's not there.
And so you're going to do your heading and you need to focus on what you can
control.
And it really resonated with me because it felt selfish.
It felt like, hey, I want us to be successful.
We need to try and, you know, and he, he was just, you know,
he played in premierships, been a president of premierships,
coached premierships.
I think he's the only person in the industry that's ever done that.
So there was some wise words and, and, um.
That alignment, right?
Yeah.
And it's, you know,
you look at Richmond,
Richmond had brilliant alignment the last few years.
I'm sure they will again,
or I'm sure they haven't lost that alignment and clearly Footscray,
Bulldogs has got great alignment, Melbourne Footy Club,
great alignment.
Everyone's saying that Essendon's now got that great alignment and it does
sound really obvious, but it is, as you know,
and as I've experienced in darker times, it's really hard to do.
Without it, you're no chance.
With it, it's still incredibly hard, isn't it?
In a competitive industry like this.
Final question in the, in the spirit of collaboration,
uh,
Russ, if you could collaborate with one person on the planet,
it could be in any area of your life.
Is there a name that, that springs to mind?
Well, he's no longer alive.
Um, so that's a pity, but Picasso's a big, I'm a big, really?
Yeah.
I, I find him fascinating, genuinely fascinating.
Um, you know, he's criticized in his private life.
I understand that, but his, his creativity was absolutely
extraordinary.
Like he would make, you know, many pieces of art every single day.
Um, and it would of course get to the point where he'd have a meal and he would just paint
a fish on the plate and that paid for his meal.
So, you know,
So it was without ever knows Picasso, but I'm not a student far from it, but so was
he as big when it was alive and Kelly post that he's become, you know, he was, he was
commercially at his time.
Six.
Yeah.
So hugely successful as an artist and I like working with creative people.
So, um, so the idea that, you know, being the idea of working with, you know, the 20th
century's graders, you know, that's, that's what immediately came to mind.
But I love how you've gone there and his personal life.
What was so.
Well, he was sort of, he, he wasn't great.
He had women in his life, but he could be very cruel and, um, he was known to be very
cruel.
So that of course, you know, there's, that's not a great, that's not a tick in the right
box there.
Um, he, he, you know, he sort of, he sort of, he'd change around a fair bit.
He'd get himself a new partner quite often, you know, and at the time, I don't know whether
that was seen as a good or bad, but you know, he could be cruel.
I think that's probably the best summary.
Um, he, he, he lived a sort of a, what do you say?
I'd like to leave a peasant's existence and be very rich.
Yeah.
Which is basically what he did.
Um, you know, he was in bare feet, shorts and a t-shirt, but was really rich off the
back of just being a brilliant artist.
Russ, uh, I'm always inspired by being around you and your creativity and, uh, your positive
energy.
It just fills up your life when you're around people like you and, uh, been looking forward
to catching up and really appreciate your time.
Thanks again.
Good luck with the business.
Thanks, Russ.
Good on you, man.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me, Luke Darcy, produced by Matt Dwyer with audio production
by Darcy Thompson.
To start your leadership journey, I encourage you to go to elitacollective.com.
Take our Empowering Leaders Indicator Tool and understand the impact you have on your
environment.
Join us at Elida to learn, lead and collaborate.
www.elida.com.