Well, this week is a really special episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast for me.
I'm out of the studio and lucky enough to be in beautiful Bali talking to the principal
and head of teaching and learning at the famous green school in Bali, Sal Gordon.
The episode was recorded at the health retreat Sukhavati Bali.
You can check it out at Sukhavati Bali, spelt S-U-K-H-A-V-A-T-I, bali.com.
I'm fortunate enough to be one of the co-founders 11 years ago of this Butu Gay Vedic Health
Retreat.
The beautiful staff and people at Sukhavati Bali are so excited to be back open again
after a couple of years of the challenges of the pandemic.
It's a fantastic place to look after your health, all about preventative health and
the programs I couldn't speak more highly of.
It's been a great pleasure to be part of that.
So check out Sukhavati Bali and I love the opportunity to spend some time there and have
breakfast with Sal Gordon.
Sal Gordon, one of...
The great revolutionary educators in the 21st century.
Sal and the school are striving to champion the new model of education, one that nurtures
students and gives them agency in their own lives and their learning.
Education and changing our traditional thinking about the way we approach teaching our kids
is an incredibly meaningful conversation for me.
And this type of open and progressive communication is something that I love to explore in my
business, Alita, which was co-founded with my great friend, Matt Wadowitz.
It's a place where leaders can collaborate and learn from one another and have conversations
they probably can't have elsewhere.
And we have had the great privilege of working with remarkable people around the globe, including
Mike Dunlap, the assistant coach of the Milwaukee Bucks, Eddie Jones, the head coach of English
rugby, Andy Lee from Hamish and Andy, just to name a few.
It's something you can be part of as well.
And you don't have to be a world-leading comedian or a head coach to be part of Alita Connect.
Whatever you do, we all...
We value and love the idea of bringing what you have in your environment to Alita.
And you can find out more about it.
Go to alitacollective.com.
Encourage you to check out the signature Alita Connect program, which is talking about to
understand how people like Sal Gordon from the Green School World Leading Educator are
collaborating and leading and learning in their world.
Sal Gordon is the head of learning and principal of the famous Green School in Bali.
The Green School's mission is to create a global community of learners, making our world
sustainable.
The Green School Bali has supported a global movement in education with schools opening
in New Zealand, South Africa, and Tulum, Mexico.
The Green School's living curriculum educates for sustainability through community-integrated
entrepreneurial learning in a natural environment.
They strive to champion a new model of education that nurtures the whole child, giving them
agency in their own lives and learning so they can thrive with purpose in our ever-changing
world.
Sal Gordon, as the principal of the Green School, is a self-described education revolution.
Sal, it's great to be with you in Bali today.
Yeah, thanks very much, Luke.
Lots of people might know me as Bill Gordon.
You know, it's got a family history of craziness with names.
So, knowing that there's some people in Australia might be listening to this, it's Bill Gordon
and Sal Gordon all at once.
So, you grew up in country Victoria, correct?
And you were educated in South Australia?
Yeah, I was born in Nill, schooled in Caniva, and then moved to Adelaide, Pulteney Grammar
for the majority of high school.
And then a university degree there, too.
I want to talk about your tenure gap year in a moment, but it's extra special for me
today being here with you.
And I'm sitting with you at a place called Sukavati Bali, which has been fortunate enough
to open 11 years ago and so connected to the community here.
Our family's been so lucky to enjoy the beauty of the Balinese people and to have a place
of health and rejuvenation, to see it back open again.
It's been a tough time around the world, but you've lived through this in Bali.
Can I first ask you about how the Bali people have gone?
One of the most special things about the Balinese, I think, is their sense of community
and family.
Definitely very difficult times financially when you take away tourism, which is the majority
of the income for most of the families.
Really tough time for them, but in a way, it provided an opportunity for them to demonstrate
who they really are in terms of looking after each other, looking after the community, looking
after their family.
It's different when you're in Australia.
Yeah.
You're sort of living in, you're fenced in little sort of house in the suburbs to understand
that sort of communities can be completely different models.
And it was difficult for the Balinese, but they didn't look like it was that difficult
for them because they just look after each other.
So loving and caring and sharing.
Life just went on for them.
They have a sense of a greater good and that's family and community.
It's beautiful to watch.
It was beautiful too without the traffic.
I can imagine the island would have been incredible.
Oh, it's paradise.
Yeah.
Absolutely paradise.
Has it returned quickly?
Very quickly.
Like a switch.
And possibly with probably more people here in terms of tourists than previous because
I think everyone's been waiting two and a half years to go on their holiday and they've
all just come back at once.
So the island has inundated.
It's got really, really busy really quickly.
So it's a totally different country, different island.
Yeah.
We always feel so fortunate.
We always feel so fortunate when you spend some time here and to sit here at Sukavati
and be so connected to our local community here and just to see the nature.
And as you said, the way they support each other, we were checking in right throughout
the lockdown period.
It's like, you know, how much rice and vegetables can I eat was the answer that came back.
We're going to be fine.
So it's a powerful message.
You learn a lot every time you're here.
Yeah, totally.
Now I'm fascinated by your story, Sal.
As you said, you educated a private school, went to university.
But at the end of that, you know,
reading some of your backstory in preparation for this,
you felt like you weren't really adept at coping in the real world.
And you went on a gap year that turned into a gap decade,
gave yourself a whole heap of life experiences.
It's a condensed version of a big chapter of your life.
But can you describe how that experience brought you back to being an education revolutionary?
I suppose I had a mantra that was learn more.
As soon as I got out of university, I was planning to get into a postgrad medical course.
I wanted to...
I wanted to be like the next, you know, development world doctor.
I wanted to make a difference somehow.
But I also realised that my education had given me probably a couple of skills.
One is sort of how I learnt.
And it also just give me a couple of numbers on a piece of paper.
Going through all of that education, you know, private school education, then university,
it's taxing it for a while and putting myself four years of more of it.
I was like, I need it.
I need a chance.
Yeah.
I need to get out in the real world.
So I did.
I moved to India and worked with a health and development organisation there.
But as soon as I was sort of like, you know, out in the real world,
I realised that all of that education I'd been given hadn't really taught me anything.
It's funny to say that.
I felt really sort of, yeah, ill-equipped to cope.
I didn't think that skills had been something that I'd been taught.
The only skills I'd learnt, I'd sort of learnt on my own.
And I didn't think values were...
I didn't think values were anything that had been part of my education.
They were part of my upbringing from my family.
But, you know, when you get out in the real world and you realise that this certificate
that you've got is basically pointless and is not going to help you solve problems or
communicate or collaborate or think critically, it's not going to help you adapt.
It's not going to be able to help you think empathetically or with equity or act with integrity.
When you realise all these things that you're missing, you're like, well, okay, it's time
to give yourself a bit of an education.
And so, yeah, 10 years.
I spent jumping around the world and upskilling myself, learning with that mantra of learn
more, learn more, whether it be a language, a culture, people, places, jobs, different
jobs.
I really like sort of like getting a great job or, well, probably an ordinary job, starting
at the bottom, learning, learning, learning and climbing way up and then six months later
going, well, that's enough for me.
I think I've learnt everything here.
I've got a supervisor, a managerial role.
I'm out of here and I'll go travelling again.
So, the next step, I'd have to start at the bottom again.
It taught me a lot about probably what leadership is.
It taught me a lot of what real life learning needed to be and how that could look in a
school.
And then, you know, there was a time when you get married and you're starting to have
a family.
You're like, well, you know, what am I going to do for a job, a real job?
And I realised that I'd just been teaching and learning for 10 years all around the world.
And so, it was quite easy for me to jump into education.
I was a teacher.
And I was a learner.
I was really passionate about maths and science as well.
I saw them as explanations of life and of magic that this planet holds.
And so, yeah, I just got my degree at Melbourne Uni and jumped into education pretty easily.
And you ended up in a school in Orbost.
Yeah, I love Orbost Secondary College.
Incredible, isn't it?
That, you know, your life took you on that trajectory and you started integrating sustainability
through the curriculum, you know, in a meaningful way.
But you felt, from what I read, that you've always felt you're bumping your head against the wall.
You've always felt you're bumping your head against that system.
And the TED Talk from the founders of the Green School in Bali, that inspired you.
It was the thing that got me.
Yeah.
That's the thing that got me.
I wanted education to be different for my kids.
I wanted it to be different for all children.
I saw the opportunity of education that it wasn't taking, an opportunity for it to be
more than just a place where you get an exam result, for a school to be a part of a community,
a centre of community.
A school that can be a place where students love learning.
Do something with their learning now, rather than just maybe later, or just for an exam.
I thought that schools really had this opportunity that they weren't taking at all.
I saw education in a time capsule for the last hundred years, while the rest of the
world changes and is still changing, you know, societal change, technological change, environmental
change, which we should be a lot more concerned about.
But schools, this education process that we put in place, you know, it's not going to change.
It's not going to change.
And the money that we put our kids through for 13 plus years hasn't changed.
I mean, what's the purpose of school, Luke?
Is it just to get a mark, or is it to make the world a better place?
Because I think it's to make the world a better place.
And that's, you know, why I love having this opportunity to chat to you.
And it's something we just had breakfast, you and I, my wife, Bec, and we've got four
kids and, you know, educating private schools back in Melbourne.
And we're happy and connected kids, but I think as parents, we generally have this feeling,
have we given them what we actually wanted to do?
with this lifelong love of learning?
And I think the answer's no.
In fact, I'm sure the answer's no because, as you said,
you look at every other part of your life,
everything's been disrupted apart from education.
And you're doing that here at the Green School in Bali.
You guys are the template for what it can look like.
That's the mission to try and then take that to the world?
100%.
We've had an opportunity.
And I see, you know, I'm never dissing any other schools
and other teachers.
I think teachers are superheroes.
And I think there are a lot of schools doing a lot of good things.
Big systems, traditional systems are bigger
and more difficult to change.
They're like big ocean liners.
If you want to change course, it takes a long time.
But I see change in them.
I see change in the IB curriculum, the NYP.
And I've seen some change in the Australian curriculum from afar.
But we had an opportunity to create a whole new model of school
without any limitation.
So when we thought what could school be,
we thought, well, it could be a place,
a place where a whole community comes together.
Okay, our school is a community of learners.
When we realised that you could learn much more at school
than just knowledge and, in fact, just pick up your phone
and find out any piece of information you want now,
that skills and values are much more important to be educating,
we just did them.
We just did it.
When we realised that you didn't have to go to a geography class,
a history class, a maths class and stuff,
you could actually teach around a theme,
base it on something environmental or societal,
like, you know, you could teach around a theme,
access to education or women's rights or the oceans
and teach a thematic integrated unit
that combines literature, arts, science, maths,
dance, if you want, rap it.
You can rap your exam out if you really like.
When you think, well, learning doesn't have to be like it's always been.
School doesn't have to be like it's always been.
You can be creative and do something really cool.
We took that opportunity.
And there's been hundreds of educators go through there.
We've got our own curriculum.
It's internationally accredited.
Kids still can do calculus and organic chemistry.
If they really want, they learn their times tables
and learn how to read and write in the primary school,
just like any other school.
But we've created other opportunities,
other types of learning experiences that are real world,
that kids love, that are connected to their passions.
And now we want to share it.
Like, we've created a model that works.
Our kids go to university all around the world.
Our kids transition back into their home schools
when they go back to their home countries afterwards.
This model works.
School can be different.
We've proven it.
And now we really want to share it as much as possible.
And it's a brilliant story to tell, a brilliant story of leadership
and you following that sense of what made you want to continue
your learning journey.
Can you just describe it?
You've created an environment out there that is just next level
in terms of being connected to nature.
There are no walls at the green school.
It's a thing of beauty, that's all.
Yeah, well, there's not a lot of visual prompts in podcasts.
So I highly recommend anyone that's listening to this
to jump on the website or jump on YouTube.
And have a look at some of the imagery.
It is on a massive, massive jungle campus
with a river running through it, the Ayung River,
the biggest river in Bali.
Its classrooms are all wall-less, innovatively,
sustainably designed bamboo buildings.
There's gardens, vegetable gardens, medicinal plants.
I think there's over 140 plants that we garden and eat.
It's got solar, hydro power.
We're basically completely off the grid.
We've got an innovation hub.
We've got animals all through the campus from ducks and pigs and cows
and chickens and Bali dogs and the occasional snake.
And I've seen a couple of monkeys there too.
Bamboo is really important to us.
It's fast-growing.
It's sustainable.
The place is magic.
It's a place where people come and they love their school.
So how many people out there think back about their time at school
and go, well, I love that place?
Well, people come to green school and grow a love for a school
and grow a love for learning.
It's a beautiful place.
It's innovative.
It's creative.
You know, it is so cool that Dr. Jane Goodall comes to visit us
because she's heard of Green School Bali
or the Secretary General of the United Nations wants to come
and learn about how we've done education.
Alexandra Cousteau, Jacques Cousteau's granddaughter,
spent three months with us as an activist.
You know, we want education to be something like that,
not just a school where people drop their kids off to get a mark.
It should be a place that's special.
And Green School Bali is definitely a special place.
And you use the word fun a lot in all the stuff I hear.
It's fun.
I'm just talking to you over breakfast before.
You were saying on a Friday there could be a music band playing.
And how many people on campus?
You had over 500 students pre-COVID and coming back to that.
But tell me about a Friday at the Green School.
A Friday afternoon, Spirit Friday, we call it now.
We'll do a whole school assembly.
So if there was 530 kids before COVID, you double that with, you know,
everyone bringing at least one parent and then there'd be probably another 500,
sort of, guests and people just coming because we would.
We'd have a live band.
We'd have a big farmer's market.
We'd have the bar open.
Don't tell anyone.
Couldn't really have a bar.
But, yeah, we think that learning can be something that we celebrate,
share and have fun together,
and that a school can be that place in a community.
I love what you were talking about before, Sal,
around teaching, you know, 21st century lifestyle skills,
you know, adaptability, creativity, critical thinking.
And then teaching values, as you said,
they're the things that really set you apart in life as you go forward.
And to think that they're not part of mainstream Korean curriculum,
how do you go about doing that and how important has that been?
Yeah, I think values-based learning is probably the foundation
of all of those things.
You know, you've probably got some historical people that you could think of
in the past that were great communicators, that were very intelligent,
but without a good value set at the bottom,
they end up people like Hitler, for example.
Very smart, good communicator.
Right, but so values are as important really as anything, you know,
and I learnt my values from my parents and my grandparents and I've, you know,
I was lucky, but values-based learning is really sort of a new nut to crack
for education and I think a lot about it.
I've designed a whole way of thinking about values-based learning
where you provide an opportunity for someone to experience a value.
So, we have our early years to teach the community peace.
Here's a good one.
I just thought of it.
They do a peace parade.
So, our kindergarten students and our pre-K, they learn a few songs about peace
and they build certain, make some little gifts and things like that
and then they tour the school, like a lap of the school,
singing with a bit of a band that follows them and they bring peace to all
of the community around the school, end up in the high school.
We have a big party in that sort of high school area.
So, you provide an opportunity for someone to experience the value
and then a big part of it is reflective at the end of it,
where you ask specific questions and you prompt people to think about what did it feel
like to experience that value, you know.
What did it feel like to experience peace?
And then, you ask, what do you think other people felt like to experience that?
And then, you ask, well, how in the future could you create that same sort of experience?
And you're actually learning a value.
Values based learning isn't something that you can read about.
You can't learn empathy by reading about it.
You've got to practice it.
So, again, you think about it, provide an opportunity for someone to experience.
Thank you, Jack.
Thanks, Zach.
Thanks, Jules.
experience empathy and then do a reflective cycle on it. And you're building empathy because you
can't get a hundred percent on empathy. You can't, you know, sometimes I probably should be more
responsible, you know, on a Friday night, you know, playing pool with my friends. I probably
should be a little bit more responsible. So you can't, you know, you're never a hundred percent
perfect with your values, but you can always be learning them and you can always input values into
the learning program. And if you're not receiving empathy on the home front to be able to go to a
place where you spend that amount of time, as you said, over 13 years, you think the amount of time
we spend at school to not at least experience that, understand what it's like and to maybe
share that with equity, community, trust, responsibility, you know, the world would be
a different place if values were a part of school. And you're intimately integrated in the community
here in Bali. And you're telling me that there are over 30 scholarships for local academic.
There's some of your favorite stories of leadership you were telling me. Yeah. You know, well,
sitting here on the,
on the drive here, I was thinking, you know, I wonder if Luke's going to ask me what's my
definition or who's my favorite leader. And I thought, well, actually some of my favorite
leaders are our local scholars. There's, we do have a, an amazing school, but we don't want to
just lock it away in an international school bubble. So our scholar program's really big.
There's 32 this year that are just local Balinese. They can't, couldn't afford, you know, we're in
international school. It costs money to come here. Couldn't normally afford to. They provide us
an instant connection with the local community. And there's some of, yeah, those students, I'd say
Guste. Guste's in grade 11 now. He's created his own stair-step electricity generating system.
So that, you know, everywhere you walk is going to create power, electricity. Another, another
awesome leader, Dipta, is, he's gone all around Bali, developed a really cheap, easy water
filtration system and is digging recharge wells.
Another one of their friends, Terta, another Bali scholar student. She's really into women's
empowerment. And, and so she's developed the whole women's empowerment program that she's going
around the world, growing around Bali and, and upskilling and uplifting, empowering the women
in Bali. We've also got people like Melati Witson and her sister. They started the Bye Bye Plastic
Bags movement. She's well-famous, TED Talk, thousand millions of views. She and her sister
started the movement that banned single-use plastic bags. She's also a member of the
bags in bali um now like un speaker clover hogan an alumni she's um started a company called forces
of nature and is going into and lectures now at oxford and cambridge and at the un around
ecophilia and building a connection with nature so you can build a different model of school you
can also send kids off to a medical degree if you really want but you can't it's not really the the
answer for everyone we're creating a model for change makers rather than change takers i reckon
when you and i went to school we were just taught how to take change and we've built we've built a
model that actually creates change makers they can make a change in the world you know to their
own life to their community and and we're seeing it now in a global global setting as it turns out
you and i are going to school you know not that far apart at a pretty similar time yeah and i was
thinking back as we were talking then about it was a really memorable teaching moment that i
had
at school and i'm searching for one and i'm not trying to be too critical to my kids as well
you know i'm not being too critical there of mainstream they've had a great experience and
great connection great friendships but you know when you talk about single-use plastics being
eradicated off the island of bali coming out of students in real time because of the education
they're getting and creating change makers in the world i mean that that seems to me what the the
whole principle the bali green school is doing is that is you know i can't think of us i can't
hear a story that 100 percent that i had a chance to do that i can't think of a story that i had a
school that was even close to that or memorable i can't tell you a lesson that i can think of which
me neither yeah sad isn't me neither yeah i think there's again i said before there's an opportunity
we send our kids to school for a long time and with education being in that time capsule we've
lost the purpose we've forgotten the point or even the opportunity of what that could be for a human
i think the world's probably suffering a little bit you look around societal challenge cultural
challenges they're not going to be the same as they were in the past and i think that's a big
part of that and i think that's a big part of that and i think that's a big part of that and i think
we see it all around the world in terms of race and religion um we see it now in our relationship
to the natural environment there's things that our generation and generations have done before
in terms of pollution uh is just one example that they're irreversible um and i think that's
sort of an end product of an education system that's ignored its potential its purpose
and for me education's got to be to make the world a better place
and so i suppose you're um you know very keen to point out that it's not utopia going to school
but you still have the same same issues and behavioral issues possibly even more
so you don't want to create this false pretext you know and what about kids with learning
difficulties and and how does how do you cope with the things that happen at school on a day-to-day
basis yeah we've got like 40 different nationalities so that's a lot of different cultural
norms and cultural norms and cultural norms and cultural norms and cultural norms and cultural norms
and cultural expectations that make a lot of that even more difficult um with it's a school that has
80 retention so 20 of the community changes every year and so when you're talking about a school
we're talking about a culture and it's a continual annual rebuild of a culture and recreation of a
culture and that culture is foundational um we we're not the perfect school and i don't think
one exists um we and because of those different changes in culture i think some of the challenges
are even more than other schools um you know learnings i think we're all unique learners in
a way and that's the way we try and think about it at green school we don't put you know the naughty
kids or the add kids uh the dyslexic kids in sort of a box and say well you just learn wrong they
just everyone learns differently and uniquely um we we try and provide as much learning support
structured based mostly through our early years kindy program and our primary school
and then the
nature of the program itself in middle school which allows for students to
explore their own passions to demonstrate their learning in the way that they want to learn rather
than do this learn this way and show me if learned it in a test sort of thing where you can actually
say well let's learn about the oceans um you can learn about it in any way you like and you can
demonstrate your learning back to me any way you like so you don't have to just sit and write an
essay about it you could actually do a rap if you like or paint a painting or do an infographic
there's so many ways to demonstrate learning that said
um you know there's a place like green school where you get everyone's focus you know and i
taught there for a long time too you get everyone's focus and you're right in and then the chicken
runs through the classroom or there's a snake even worse you know um there are no walls so
you you remember when you're at school and you're always just staring out the window well there is
no windows it's bang right there there's a garden and you just it's quite a difficult place um for
students that are challenged in terms of maintaining sort of concentration because everything's sort of happening all the time
yeah
so it's not the perfect school it's not the perfect school for everyone but there's parts of the model
that could be replicated um whether it's thematic learning or skill-based learning or values or
just the concept of a school being a community that you could do in a square room well that was
my question to you to say you know not everyone you know can build an oasis uh in all wood like
the green school we know that's not going to happen you know expansion has happened in in a
different way new zealand looks incredible and tulum mexico i mentioned off the top in south
africa as well but for these people it's not going to happen you know it's not going to happen
in a different way new zealand looks incredible and tulum mexico i mentioned off the top in south
big ocean liners as you describe them that are hard to turn for a reason they and they're proud
institutions a lot of them and have great history and they've produced fine people over a long
period of time what what do they need to take out of of the the lessons of the green school in bali
i think yeah like some of the things we've talked about already i think um thinking more than just
knowledge-based learning systems uh skills and values are more important now like i said you
just look it up on your phone you know when have i ever used fourth grade and i've never used fourth grade
third's pi r cubed for the volume of a circle like when and if i did need i'd just you pick up
my phone and hit google you know hit google um so skills and values i think uh teaching real world
things teaching integrated real world things you can cover i taught i proved it in australia where
you can cover all of the learning outcomes for literacy maths and science for a term by teaching
about sustainability for example by teaching a unit about water um i think schools would be
better places and
places where people look back on in fondness uh not just for the school but with in terms of their
relationship with learning if they were probably more community-minded and were able to think of
themselves as centers of a community rather than just a place where parents drop their kids off
um it just any i think just that concept of uh student-centered learning is really important
you know we don't want to we i think education sometimes has the opposite effect to what it
what it's probably trying to do to get students to get back to school i think it's really important
i think education sometimes has the opposite effect to what it what it's probably trying to do to get
to do um you know if you go through school and you end up not loving learning um the the system's
failed the kid because life's a learning process as soon as you stop learning you die basically so
think about schools could just think about just igniting a natural love of learning why not
i love sitting down with different leaders from different backgrounds so seeing what leadership
looks like in different settings you know sitting here with you in bali today and your journey's
as unique as anyone's but it's a great story of leadership in my mind and and we see these
dimensions of leadership as being consistent with 21st century leaders like you and we think
self-leadership is one of the first dimensions where people who can have an impact like you are
i've got an acute sense of self-leadership does that make sense to you yeah totally i think there
was a time remember when i said um my mantra for a while was learn more as soon as i got into
education i wanted to do something with this opportunity and and found myself
wanting to move into leadership positions i changed that mantra mantra to be better and so i wanted to
do something more with that learning and to be better be better for my students be better for
a community be better for myself and how so then then you really sort of need to be self-aware so
be aware is one of our green school skills which is not really a normal uh life 21st century life
school but being aware and being aware of who you are and where you are and who you're with and
even
your relationship all of that and your potential impacts really important so i spend a fair bit of
time reflecting um day to day in a way of sort of how i can be better and not just be better for
myself but how can that be better for a greater good i suppose it's probably not the nicest way
to say but how can how can i have a positive impact on other people on the environment and
maybe hopefully with people listening about education changing on a global system
that needs to change so when you have that mantra be better is that something that you know you've
written down is that something yeah it's something i've written down and i'm and it's where i start
you know i've got a great coach um dave hayes in sydney hey mate um great coach he keeps me
centered and keeps me level but it's something that i you know i start most of my reflective
practice with of you know because you're not perfect people aren't perfect i'm not perfect
i don't try to be i'm very normal i you say these things about leadership and i just sit here going
well really i'm not i don't know is that really me i just want to be better i suppose it's a great
thing to have and and you know a personal mantra and it's you sum up self-leadership in
such a brilliant way can i ask you about about the coach you mentioned your coach dave dave hayes
dave hayes i mean i love hearing people talk about you know the analogy for me if roger federer needs
to coach we're naive to think we don't need a coach so 100 so so how did you come across
the coaching yeah he's an ex green school family uh
parent um and i got to know him like personally as a friend and he was a parent i was a teacher
of his kids um so he had this he's got a unique insight into the place that i work and the type
of challenges and he's back in sydney now so we all got used to doing things online on zoom and
um i think with him the one of the best things about coaching with him is that sometimes i'm
not sure whether i'm coaching him or he's coaching me um which is really good i find that it's just
a really sort of mutual uh respect and relationship but yeah he challenges me where through times
probably to be better um it just gives me that different view and and probably a really well
informed view of the challenges or who i am and who i can be i love the accountability that isn't
it when you actually get on the phone to someone that identifies as your coach you've got to be
accountable to the things that you do don't you even in that it's pretty profound thing to have
in your answer on self-leadership you mentioned a
about be better and wanting to have a positive impact on others and we see that as a genuine
dimension leaders now they are really conscious about the impact they have on others can you
delve into that a bit more on a daily basis how you go about having a positive impact
i think sort of one of those you know if you look back if i look back or if i had to define
leadership um which comes through me and my mantra i think that you know things like being
inspiring and empowering and enabling you know if i ask myself how can i be
better for my teachers well i need i can be better at enabling them or empowering them or upskilling
them um i can be better at just sitting and listening i think listening is probably one
of my superpowers even though it doesn't sound like it in this you do you normally talk more
in this and i love it it's brilliant i think you know those things those leadership qualities that
um that you have to work on that some people find probably more natural than others um
that allow me to you know i don't think there's one
definition of a leader and i think leaders have even in my role here there are different
aspects of leadership i have to demonstrate all the time to different people into different
circumstances and situations but most of the time it's it's around i think care care and
demonstrating love love something that's sort of coming back thank god into the world um empathy
um in you know i think if you can tap into someone's passion
whether it's a person or a person's passion it's a person's passion it's a person's passion
it's a student or a teacher or a parent within your community you're being better at providing
a service for them to for them to be better as well um yeah and i see that uh in you having
breakfast and you know you turn to a beautiful pudu who made our breakfast this morning and
and you speak balinese and you speak another local dialect here as well so you talk about
lifelong learning 100 you've uh you embody that yourself and that obviously flows through isn't
we love debunking the idea of leadership as well so in the terms of just it doesn't need title
does it and you'd see that from your students it can come in all shapes and sizes as well
yeah totally i think like a lot of things in life whether it's leadership or respect i suppose the
language thing for me is the way that i can be better as a person that's living in in bali and
indonesia rather than saying i respect you i will learn your language and communicate with you and
it's hard you know i never learned a language um at school so you know it's not hasn't come easy
to me but i think all these things are action-based maybe that's sort of something that yeah that we
talk about you know that uh empathy isn't something that you talk about it's something
that you demonstrate um respect isn't something that you can you know say i respect you it's you
you've got to demonstrate the things you've got to show this and i think that's probably good
leadership as well you know you can try and inspire people but maybe the biggest inspiration is you
know you know or empowering people but you know it comes from within as well so i think a lot of
these things are not things that you can just talk about you've actually got to do it um yeah well
said um creating and sharing a vision is something we see all leaders are really conscious of as well
and you know we've heard about you as a self-proclaimed education revolutionary this
idea of wanting to disrupt the education for the better globally i mean how have you thought about
that and how do you go about sharing and creating that vision
yeah well this is this is part of my job sitting and and sharing what we've done and not what i've
done but what we've done as a community at green school um i honestly believe that education
is a change mechanism tool for a better future a more sustainable future not just an environmental
sustainable but talking holistic we're talking societies and well-being um there's a lot of
there's a there's a lot of problems around the place sorry
i'm not i'm definitely not a negative person either if you look at the relationship with the
environment we look at societal problems look at mental health mental health for for kids youth
nowadays it's just should be really really scary we've got to do something you know we don't have
another earth to move to we've got this beautiful amazing planet that um with this beautiful human
species that is sort of thinks it's conquered the planet it's got an amazing advancements in
technologies it's got so much going for it
for it but sorry it's going down the tube education can be something that changes that education needs
to be something that changes that if we're waiting for governments to change we're waiting for big
global corporations to make those changes for a sustainable future just keep waiting we've got an
opportunity uh i think schools and and teachers themselves are superheroes because of their love
of teaching and learning that's the change mechanism tool we need to activate and i'm
passionate so passionate about it i can move forward i can actually take it and i can change my world and so will you
for it but sorry it's going down the tube education can be something that changes that education needs to be
can't think of anything more exciting than education changing around the world if small
changes in big systems big changes wherever they can happen where we provide a learning opportunity
for the youth that moves them into the future as change makers not change takers that we can
adapt in the future because some of these environmental changes are permanent now and
we can't change what's going to happen we need to be resilient we need to be problem solvers
communicators creative thinkers critical we need to think critically a lot more and that's got to
come from a different type of education system if you're sitting around learning stuff from a book
and then regurgitating it in exam so that you get a score if that's all school is i'm sorry i'm not
going to be a part of it i want to change it it needs to change this planet our kids my kids and
their kids they need it they need education to change yeah it's a profound way to sum it up and
i love those stories you shared of your local leaders at your school
doing incredible things you know based on the education that you've given them at the green
school barley curiosity is a where we hear a lot of dimensional leadership so and i'm sure your
brain will go there and through curiosity we see so much learning and development can you tell us
about what that means to you yeah well i think it's a it's a handy tool to have rather than
to be questioning things or fearful of things to be curious about them you know i'm curious about
what happens when sea level
rise by a meter or i'm curious about what we do when the next black lives matter thing happens
i'm curious to how afl clubs respond to the historical racial problems that that have been
in cultures and footy club i'm curious about the potential of humans to to be better um yeah i
suppose and i think you know when you rephrase uh things into a state of or a state of mind of
curiosity you're opening yourselves up in a much more level-headed and open-minded way of thinking
and an honest way to to solve a problem or to to address the issue yeah curiosity is something i
my coach hey dave talks about a lot yeah i could tell that was going to resonate with you
communicating the clarity is something you do extremely well and something we see as a common
dimension of leadership you you tell your story you know really profound way if you've consciously
thought about that is it just somehow your communication and to get this message out
how have you gone about that i'm always in my favorite
teacher at school is my english teacher and i went on to you know do a science degree so
um two and two together and you get five sometimes um i've always had a love of literature and i've
written a lot i used to tell you write a diary i think for 20 years i wrote every day as a story
as a chapter of my life um i never consciously worked on um communication in fact it was the
thing that scared me the most becoming a principal of you know getting up and talking
to in front of 500 people or sitting there with a microphone in my face i've got the world's best
school prize on tuesday next week it'll be a keynote online but there'll be thousands of people
can we just pause there and say congratulations marine school bali is internationally um you know
up for an award to recognize you as the most sustainable school globally it's a environmental
action so world's best school for environmental action brilliant so i was scared about it but i
suppose that's something that where the be better came into it
as well um knowing that i had a belief in something and knowing that i had an opportunity to
share that belief and share what we're doing meant that i had to start thinking about how i
communicate and plus i'm communicating to at school to 40 different countries the americans
still need a translator for me sometimes um yeah i'm talking to you leslie um so you know it's
something that i had to work on you know i'm if i really want to have an impact or if i really
want to share what collectively my community is doing then yeah i've had to get better at it i don't
know if i'm getting any better at it i think you've uh you've got a pretty good handle on that
how you get your message out you're you know jumping off there for a minute again you're 42
different nations represented at the green school bali at a point in time so it's a melting pot
isn't it of international um community coming together yeah yeah and they all come to green
school well they come to bali
for the school so there's that added sort of expectation pressure um they haven't just moved
to bali and then shopped around for a school they've picked up their whole life um some of
them it's financially a stress as well because it's it's an international school it's probably
only half the school fees for anyone going to a private school in australia right now so
if you're thinking about a change anyone australia the gates are open bali's lovely
can people literally if they're listening i mean are you taking registrations we're growing quite
quickly um
and part of sort of you know what i consider is a really important part of the schools out the
culture you know that culture is defined by the people in it um and so we don't want to grow
exponentially we'll probably cap out in a few years at about 600 i think that's a magic number
yep um but yeah it's a challenge but it's also one of you know we've got a real global community
um from people all over the world including our host nation people here um the balinese and
it's it's quite a unique place um but also with quite you know serious challenges we've got
ukrainians and russians in the school we've got chinese and americans in the school we've got you
know it's it's it's it's a beautiful place and we're all coming together though you mentioned
the mission um at the start when you did the intro you know we define our school as being a community
of learners making our world sustainable and everyone that signs up it's it's um we have quite
a thorough admissions process you know you've got to be the right type of family you've got to
you know want to make us an effort or even step up in terms of your life uh living sustainably and
and sort of ethically empathetically in terms of a cultural being as well so you know it's a little
bit of a family fit rather than just sign up we want my kid to go here we would like to talk to
you too luke about who you are and what you want in life um because you're a part of our our
community that sort of thing
yeah it's brilliant uh the final dimension is uh we see leaders are really passionate about
collaboration now as a as a dimension of their leadership what you're doing is an incredible
collaboration how do you go about that and how do you think about collaboration
i think i've learned really quick that i'm not right all the time in fact um it's much better
to think just to lose that attachment to being right as a leader is really enlightening and
refreshing and i think when
other people that you're working with um who who used to think that they were working for you
but when they start to realize that you we're just working together and they realize that this person
that they thought they were working for isn't doesn't want to always be right um is the first
step of good collaboration um a collaboration of course you know you've got your baselines of you
know um establishing sort of alignment in alignment in in a vision or a mission or that end project of
what you're trying to to agree on it's pretty hard to collaborate when everyone's trying to
get to a different place and so that my role is probably more uh helping a group of people
sort of be aligned with where we want to get to what's what are we trying to create and then
knowing that i'm not always right in fact sometimes it feels like i'm the least intelligent
person in the room but that's the way i want it you know i want that person who's great at
mindfulness and it's got a degree in something else and i want that person who's
got their phd in another part pedagogical design um and i want another person who's
a learning theory expert in there and let me be the person to bring all the great minds together
and then we get the best result and that's good effective collaboration for me yeah i've heard
that a lot from the different leaders i've spoken to that this practice um you know spoke to john
birch and the legend of australia too recently and he was talking about walking into a room
and having the mindset that he knows nothing yeah i know nothing and then i can
be in the presence of wanting to learn straight away not i'm going to share with you how much i
do know and i think it's a profound way to think yeah yeah um who's been the greatest leader in
your life so personally i was always big global citizen big global historical leaders um were
always the people that i had posters on the walls i suppose is that what you're looking for you know
cliche you know it's it's gandhi i've spent a long time in india i thought the way
of his mind and the peaceful the degree of difficulty of what he was trying to do it's
nelson mandela it's it's probably really cliche you're probably expecting something
probably more innovative not at all um you know i learn most from my kids i suppose and so in a way
they're leading me in terms of my learning journey through life my own children and that might be the
different way of thinking about who are my favorite leaders well i love it i'll let you
immediately go to to and we get i love you know you didn't hesitate because
you you know you thought about i mean i had i had a dream the big poster martin luther on my wall for
you know five years i used to stare at it as a kid that's unique isn't it well not cliche it is it
it's inspiring because you've gone and taken your life in that direction of inspiring others so i
mean that's unusual for a kid though to have martin luther king growing up in country victoria and
then going to popney grammar in adelaide there wouldn't have been too many others where did that
come from is that from your family or just the sense of purpose about who you were yeah i don't
know you know born and raised on a farm good christian upbringing um i don't know my parents
allowed me to think differently and always sort of fostered just my passions um you know it was
kind of hard for them they send you away to school they're farmers they send you away to
pulteney they pay a lot of money i go do one uni degree and then pull out of doing a medical degree
and go travel around the world for 10 years um but they trusted me and they'd always i suppose
that trust trust is a really important thing isn't it that trust is a really important thing
and knowing that you know the passions that i had probably i don't know where that came from
because it was pretty monocultural sort of upbringing um but i believe that you know that
we could be better as a species as a person and i believe that we could probably all have a dream
and i was always allowed to follow it and you're living it every day living the dream it's
brilliant literally living the dream speaking about cliche mate that's uh might get a tattoo
of that one uh on the back of that we're obsessed with collaboration if you could
collaborate with anyone i mean clearly the green school barley and and or anything in your life
any passion of yours is there is there someone that springs to mind that you might want to
collaborate with you know i'm 49 now and i wouldn't mind jumping back into australia in a
couple years time um 10 years at green school i've got another year next year that'll be 11
and if i could get some i don't know who they are but if i think the education system's right
to change and if i could help and collaborate with some
some of our government i'd love to be out of some of the leading schools in there i think
education in australia could be a frontier of change around the world um i want to look after
my home backyard a little bit a bit more than i have um but yeah i think i've got this i these
ideas and and a model now that i could share that could really change and so if you know i don't
want to keep this this these ideas in on a little island in bali you know it'd be it'd be
amazing to try and change the australian education system the way that i've seen it change here
well there's a call out to uh to anyone who's uh who's listening and i think all of us who
you know care about our kids in the future want to see uh the values-based 21st century learning
community i mean i don't think anyone would see overlaying that more into us not a babysitting
environment not just chasing you know i've got this feeling sal that perhaps the world's going
to disrupt education and i think that's going to be a big part of the future of education
in reverse where universities now don't care anywhere near as much about all the big tech
companies around them i don't care at all about the score at the end so perhaps that's going to
say if you come back the other way you know maybe we do need to learn more about the sort of learning
that you're talking about it's not a big shift you can still you can still study calculus you
can still you know your primary kids still learn their times tables um they still learn spelling
and grammar and things like that there are things you could do i could do it overnight
to see if i could do it overnight and i think that's going to be a big shift in the future
some of the australian system and the world would be a better place and learners our students
would be happier and our parents would be happier and i think australia would be a better place
just from making some tweaks to a pretty archaic old system look back at our schools with uh with
that sense of fun and that sense of um you know respect uh would be a brilliant change um it's
been a great uh pleasure to spend some time you're right here in bali and i know you've got a busy
day straight back out to the green school yeah um look forward to catching up with you
again thanks so much for your time oh thank you very much yeah it's been awesome yeah thanks
empowering leaders was presented by me luke darcy produced by ed gooden with sound design by matt
curry start your leadership journey i encourage you to go to a leader collective.com take our
empowering leaders indicator tool and understand the impact you have on your environment join us
at a leader to learn lead and collaborate listener