This week's guest on the Empowering Leaders podcast is Australian basketball legend Sandy
Brondello from her Manhattan apartment overlooking the New York skyline, where she is the current
coach of the New York Liberty in the WNBA.
You can hear Sandy talk about growing up in a sugar cane farm in Queensland and practicing
basketball for hours on end on a grass court with a backboard her dad had made for her,
handmade out of timber and painting it white.
An extraordinary story of her becoming one of the great shooters in women's basketball
history.
Sandy talks about the importance of teaching kids the fundamentals rather than overtraining
them, a great lesson to share.
Sandy also describes the loneliness of leadership and the great wisdom she's received from collaborating
in her Alita Connect group.
Sandy's bespoke Alita Connect team includes Justin Lepich, the three-time Brisbane Premiership
legend and current assistant coach of the Collingwood Football Club, John Bertram, Australian
Hall of Fame legend.
And one of Australia's greatest ever sporting success stories, Darrell Franklin, who is
the current head of staff, chief of staff at the Green Bay Packers.
Brad Fittler, rugby league legend from New South Wales, current state of origin coach
for New South Wales and an extraordinary person, Brad Fittler.
Pat Clifton is part of that group as well, the assistant vice president of player health
and performance at the NBA.
And Sandy talks openly about how that shared opportunity to learn and to connect and to
collaborate has been incredibly powerful for her.
And she has an amazing amount of wisdom to share as well.
If you want to find out more about Alita Connect, we'd love you to head to alitacollective.com
and book a discovery call.
Matt and I would love to get in touch with you.
You don't have to be an NBA winning coach to be involved.
We love connecting with different people from different backgrounds.
So go to alitacollective.com.
Huge thanks as always to Jason Nicholas and the team at Temper Australia, New Zealand.
Temper, a mattress like no other.
And many of the best athletes around the world.
We choose to sleep in temper bedding.
We spend a third of our life asleep.
So investing in a temper bed and bedding is a positive decision that I promise you will
change your life for the good.
Sandy Rondello is Australian basketball royalty, representing Australia at four Summer Olympic
Games, winning a bronze and two silver medals, playing over 300 games for her country.
She's a member of the Australian Basketball Hall of Fame, was awarded the MVP in 1995
as the most valuable player in the Australian League.
And in 1999, her first season.
As a player in the WNBA in the United States, was good enough to be an all-star in her debut season.
She also spent 10 years playing in Germany, winning 10 straight national championships.
Her WNBA three-point percentage of .41 has her placed fourth all-time in the world's best league.
Sandy's coaching career post-retirement from playing has been another remarkable success story.
In 2014, coaching the Phoenix Mercury to a championship win, as well as being awarded
the coach of the year.
She's currently the head coach.
She's also the head coach of the New York Liberty and the head coach of the Australian
national team.
The Opal of Sandy, it's a pretty extraordinary life of success.
Thanks for joining me today.
Oh, it's great to be here with you.
You grew up the daughter of sugarcane farmers from Mackay in Queensland, Sandy, and you
stand five feet, seven inches tall, if I'm correct.
It's an unlikely story to be one of Australia's greatest ever basketballers.
Yeah, look, really, to be quite honest, some days I just have to pinch myself, you know,
where I came from and where I am now.
But, you know, I think.
I took the opportunity with two hands.
I worked extremely hard and, you know, I think my parents, you know, instilled that in me
from a very young age.
So, you know, I'm living the dream.
Sandy, I understand your dad built a grass court basketball hoop and you grew up playing
on grass of all things.
So where did the love of the sport of basketball come from out of that part of the world?
To be quite honest, it was by chance.
My sister started to play basketball with some of her friends.
And there was a new country basketball club starting up close to where I live because
my mum couldn't drive and my dad being a sugarcane farmer is quite busy during the, you know,
the crushing time.
And, you know, I was just asked would like to come along and play and just fell in love
with the game straight away.
And I was playing with a lot of my friends that I went to school with.
I was a very shy girl growing up and, you know, I was in track and field.
I had a pretty good success at that, but just gravitated to basketball and, you know, started
at the age of nine.
And still have the same passion as I had when I was a nine-year-old.
And Sandy, millions of kids around the world, you know, dream of taking their sport to a
professional level.
Only a handful ever get to your level.
What do you think looking back with the traits that set you apart?
Yeah, I mean, hard work.
I think that helped.
And I think like obviously growing up in a sugarcane farm, I used to help out with my
dad.
So lifting pipes.
There was no big, you know, irrigation system or we didn't have any.
We'd be...
You know, lift the pipes in the mud and, you know, carry rocks and stuff like that.
And track and field certainly helped me in my basketball career in those early years.
Just, you know, I was quick, I was strong.
I loved the game.
I didn't work on the game a lot as a youngster, which I think helped prolong my career because
I lived in the country.
I talked about my mum not being able to drive.
So I couldn't get to practice in the city as much.
And that's why you spoke about the grass court that my dad did on the water tank.
And so I could really...
I learnt the craft of shooting, being a jump shooter.
Back in the early days, everyone used to say I shot like a man, but, you know, everyone
shoots like that now.
But it was a great skill for me.
I would go out and just shoot.
And a local guy, he played basketball, he taught me that.
And I just spent hours out there and I could only catch and shoot or one bounce because
it wasn't...
It was a grass field court, not a, you know, a bitumen.
So the ball would go everywhere.
It was two dribbles or more, plus I had the water tank, so I didn't want to run into that.
So I perfected the skill of shooting and that was one of my biggest strengths.
And, you know, I still had a lot to learn.
And when I went to the AIS, that really just opened up my world for a lot of different
opportunities.
So grateful for all the coaches that helped me to get where I was in my career and also
my coaching career.
Sam, my mind is going to two very famous Australian sporting stories and I hadn't, apart from doing
the research, to understand.
And you and Mackay Queensland on a grass court, and it makes sense, isn't it?
The ball's going to bounce everywhere and you pick it up and you shoot and that repetition.
And the great story of Don Bradman, who used to throw a golf ball at a water tank and hit
it with a stick, effectively, not even a cricket bat, and developed this incredible eye on
the back of that success.
And they talk about the Chappell brothers playing backyard cricket in South Australia.
And their mum had, I think, their favourite, it might have been some sort of fruit tree,
but it was at square leg.
And if you hit the fruit tree, mum was going to go ballistic.
And they developed this incredible technique to avoid hitting the fruit tree, which sort
of stood all the Chappell brothers apart, amongst everything else.
Does that sort of resonate with you to think, God, if you had have gone into town and trained
with everyone else, you might have just played a little bit like everyone else too?
Yeah, definitely.
I mean, when you're not getting those daily workouts, a lot of kids are, because I couldn't
get into the city.
The club I played for was just a country team and we used to work, practice on an outdoor
court at a nearby school, but you know, once a week.
So yeah, it's just, you know, my dad, he, and it wasn't a backboard that you buy from,
you know, we call it Dick's Sporting Goods here.
I'm not sure what's back home now.
Rebel Sport.
Okay, there you go.
Yeah.
He actually just got pieces of wood and he just nailed them together, painted it with
it white, put the square on and the only thing he bought was the basketball rim and you know,
I'm forever grateful for that because it allowed me just to hone my skills and I, you know,
one of my neighbors, Brian Swindles, he taught me how to do the jump shot and it was, you
know, it helped me to go to four Olympics because that was one of my biggest strengths.
I could certainly shoot the ball and off the dribble and, but you know, obviously to hone
your skill, a lot of hard work continues to go in it.
Not just in the beginning, but over the 18 years that I was a professional athlete and
then the other nine years that I was just a youngster trying to grow in the game.
Hey Sandy, do you think it's possible that we overcoach our young kids a little bit these
days?
You look back and understand the story of Roger Federer, his mum was a tennis coach,
but she felt like he didn't have the right temperament.
She wouldn't hit balls with him and because until he learned how to behave properly and
he went off and played soccer and all these other sports, table tennis and at the age
of 13, came back to tennis.
Yeah.
When his mum would finally hit the ball with him.
Do you feel like sometimes now, look at this sort of kids that are so drilled at seven
years of age in their chosen sport, they don't do other things because their sort of family
are on a mission to get them to be a world's greatest soccer player.
Is it possible we've maybe overdone it a little bit with the next generation?
Yeah.
Look, I'd probably say yes, we have, Dars, because they don't get to just be kids and
experience different sports and, you know, growing up, I talked about, I was in track
and field.
I was an Australian champion at the age of 12 in long jump
and, you know, played all my school sport.
But I never really loved it as much as basketball.
I started at nine, but at the age of 15 I chose,
I had to choose a sport because there was some, you know,
overlay in our schedules.
And I chose basketball and I talked about I didn't overtrain.
I overtrained when I got older and became a professional.
So that's another story there.
But you felt like you were playing catch up.
But I think a lot of kids today, you see it in America,
obviously we're on base now, that they're spending thousands
and thousands of dollars to try and develop their kids
with personal trainers and all the AAU basketball,
that's the club basketball that they have here,
and trying to get that college scholarship,
which obviously is a lot of money over here.
But I think kids don't get a well-balanced childhood
because they're staying so busy, whereas when they're young,
I think you just need to be kids.
But when they do do a sport, I think teaching
the fundamentals, that's important.
Yeah, beautifully said.
I agree.
It seems to be a bit of an arms race, junior sport,
and you're seeing not necessarily letting kids be kids
is an interesting discussion.
Very tiny percentage, Sandy, as I said, play at your level,
but even fewer then go on to be outstanding coaches.
And I mentioned in the opener your incredible success in 2004
and a head coach of the Phoenix Mercury in the WNBA.
You take them to a record-breaking 29-win, 5-loss season.
You go on to win the championship.
That year, I mean, again, what do you think have been the skills
for you as a coach?
Because not all players transition well into coaching.
What's helped you on that front?
Look, I think really it started just with the passion.
Like I knew I wasn't going to be able to play for the rest of my life,
and I retired at the age of 36 after the Athens Olympics,
and I just had injuries, and I felt like I had accomplished
anything that I had to, and I didn't have that same drive.
But I still loved the game.
You know, I felt like I could give back
to the next generation, and I wanted to coach
at the highest level.
And another thing that really helps me there is, you know,
my partner at the time, now my husband, was a professional coach,
so a head coach, and I got to see all the preparation
that he went into it, and, you know, it's not just like a player.
It's totally different.
Now, players don't understand how much a coach actually prepares
for a game until they do it themselves.
But it just fascinated me.
I just wanted to give back.
I wanted to stay in the game, and I wanted
to be a part of it.
I wanted to coach the very best, and I retired,
and the next year I was lucky enough to get an assistant coaching job
with the San Antonio Silver Stars under, you know,
a great coach in Dan Hughes and a mentor, and he helped.
That was the beginning, so forever grateful for that opportunity.
And, you know, the rest is history, but I've had a lot of highs,
but I've also had so many lows too, but I think that's a part
of the whole journey to get me to where I am now,
and I'm sure I'll continue to have those highs and lows because
that's about the journey, but that enables me
to continue to be the very best I can be because I'm not,
I keep telling my players, I'm not perfect,
so we can strive for perfection, but let's just make sure
we're putting in the work and trying to be the very best
we can on every given day.
And, Sandy, you mentioned your husband, Olaf,
who's got an extraordinary coaching career over many,
many years.
He's also now your assistant coach at the New York Liberty,
which is an amazing dynamic, isn't it, to have your husband
and partner working alongside you.
Can you tell us?
Can you tell us about how that works?
And I'm sure there's some moments and there's a lot of upside as well.
What's it like?
It is, it really is great.
You know, we haven't always had the opportunity to work together,
but our, you know, our connection went back when I was a player.
He was the coach in one of my teams over in Germany.
No one knew that we were actually together because that was our jobs
and it was not, you know, no one's business, to be quite honest,
and then, you know, we're passionate about what we're doing
and that was the most important.
But when I retired, we were assistant coaches together
in San Antonio Silver Stars as well and then, you know,
we went to coach in Russia and he was the head coach there
and I was his assistant.
So it's not a problem.
It kept our family together.
You know, once I retired, you know, we have two children,
Brody and Jada, and it's nice when you start a family.
I mean, being a mum and a dad is very important,
but if we could do it together, that was, you know, great,
especially in those early years.
But, yeah, Olaf kept coaching in Russia,
but I in the off-season would coach in Phoenix.
And so we were a little bit separate then,
but we've coached against each other in the WNBA.
He was with Chicago.
I lost to them in the 2021 WNBA Championship in the fourth game.
So that was heartbreaking, but most, you know, for me too,
but heartbreaking for my kids because they were crying more
about me losing than dad winning.
But he was assistant coach, so I think that was a little bit different.
But now, like, we're coaching with the New York Liberty,
and it's nice.
Even though we live half a year in Phoenix,
our kids are back in Phoenix going to school.
They spend as much time as they can with us during the season
and off the season.
We're with them the whole time.
But he's got a brilliant mind, Olaf.
He compliments me.
We're not the same.
He challenges me, which I think that's great.
That's great for my growth.
But he doesn't have a problem.
He loves what he does.
He could be a head coach.
We know that.
But, you know, for the best part of our family,
it's making sure that we stay together right now.
And I'm always interested when I sit down with people like you
who've had, you know, an incredible life of success.
And as you said, we focus on these conversations,
always on the achievements, but there's always plenty
of bumps along the way.
But, you know, to have two kids and have two high-performing coaches
for parents and an elite athlete for a mum,
I mean, how's the parenting leadership style on the home front?
How does that go?
Yeah, that is a great question.
I think, you know, there's a lot of laughter.
Yeah, I'm the fun mum.
Dad's the serious one and he's got a very dry wit.
He's German, so that's where that comes from.
But, look, we just try and help our kids.
We give them so many experiences.
You know, us being, them being on this journey with us coaching
all around the world, they had this unique opportunity
to be a part of it as well, you know, getting to visit
so many different countries, live in different countries,
but also be around.
Teams and interact with the players.
I thought it definitely has, you know, helped their, you know,
their development as well.
But as a coach, you know, obviously it's they both play basketball
and it's, you know, we want to help them as much.
And our daughter, she's like driven our son, you know, he's 16.
And sometimes I really just have to remember that I'm a mum first
and, you know, not a coach.
But even though like when he asks, I'm going to obviously give him
very honest opinion to both of them.
And Olaf does the same thing.
And, you know, we're there.
We don't force them into play basketball at all.
We want them to enjoy as many other sports as they can.
But, you know, our son in particular loves the game.
And, you know, and hopefully he can achieve, you know,
whatever he aspires to from the game.
And Sandy, we've had this great privilege of overlapping with you
in a space that we're really passionate about.
Elita Connect is a program that my great friend Matt Wadowitz,
and it's timely actually because he was just with you last night.
It's the New York Liberty game.
And I'm a little jealous.
I'm getting these great photos come back from New York
and he's sitting courtside watching you and your team perform.
But we're really passionate about these groups that are forming
around the globe of bringing together people like you
into bespoke groups of five or six people.
And it's a fascinating group that you connect with in Elita Connect
on a regular basis.
Justin Lepich, who's the triple premiership Brisbane Lion,
current assistant coach at Collingwood.
They're doing incredible.
They're doing incredible things at the moment.
John Bertram, the Hall of Fame legend of Australian sport.
His story is just remarkable.
John, Australia too, and winning the America's Cup
after 150 years of US dominance.
Daryl Franklin's based in the US.
He's the chief of staff at the Green Bay Packers.
Brad Fittler, legend of New South Wales Rugby League
and current coach of the State of Origin for New South Wales.
Pat Clifton, who's the assistant vice president
of player health and performance at the NBA
and Australian guy who's doing extraordinary things
on the globe.
Daryl, can you tell us a little bit about what that's meant
and how you've enjoyed that program, Elita Connect?
Look, Daz, I've actually loved it, every single moment of it.
And, you know, it's really great to be connected
with other leaders from different fields and just communicating.
And obviously we were led by Stacey Morling,
who is fantastic at facilitating.
And I've looked forward to every meeting that we've had.
It's just to share.
And you're building a community of trust within, you know,
some pretty amazing people and sharing ideas
and overcoming kind of hurdles that we all have
in our profession at any different time.
And, look, I've been a sponge.
I've really, really thoroughly enjoyed it
and always look forward to the next meeting.
And the meetings go for an hour and a quarter.
And given where everyone is located around the globe,
you're able to fit that in.
Everyone's got these incredibly busy schedules
in the world that you're running.
Yeah.
Has it helped you in your leadership style, do you think, Sandy?
Yeah, no, definitely it has.
I think when you start talking to other leaders,
you realise that you have very similar issues.
And we're not just coaches.
We're from different – we have a few coaches, different roles.
And it's just fascinating.
But we've learnt – like I've learnt a ton.
Like I felt like I've grown as a leader by just having this experience,
having a community because I always talk as a head coach, as a leader.
You know, it can be a little bit of a challenge,
but it can be lonely at the top at times.
And, you know, putting these groups together,
you feel like it's a group where you can be vulnerable
and ask for thoughts from, you know,
obviously these great people that I have on my group
and just get ideas how to handle different situations
that we've all come across at different times.
And, you know, obviously having John Bertrand,
who has so much wisdom, you know,
really just kind of like the icing on the cake.
But, yeah, no, thoroughly enjoyable.
It certainly has helped me become better.
And, really, I just aspire to actually do more now.
Yeah, it's beautiful to hear, Sandy.
And we're really passionate about that sort of community expanding
because you want to – as you said, someone like John at his stage of life
has got so much to share and you just feel like you want to capture that.
And, likewise, your world experience and everyone really brings to the table.
It doesn't matter what stage of life you're at.
And we love the idea of having younger people with people
of a different generation or female.
Leaders are doing extraordinary stuff like you are
with diverse leaders from different backgrounds.
Would you recommend it to other people?
Oh, yeah, without a doubt.
Look, I've – you know, obviously, Brianna Stewart,
she's one of my great players on the New York Liberty.
She's on a group and I've test-matched in the Captain of Australia.
I encourage a lot of the people.
I'm always saying, hey, you guys need to get in one of these groups
because it's just sharing and it's just the trust that you can build
and the similar experiences that you can go through.
But, for me,
it's just more that community feel.
And it's really special and it's obviously well-led.
You all do a fantastic job.
But, yeah, if anyone's interested in becoming better leaders,
they should certainly be a part of it.
Thanks, Sandy.
We really feel grateful to have the connection with you.
And, as you said, Stacey's doing an incredible job
as someone who started in one of our groups,
who's done an amazing job as a facilitator.
I'm interested in your perspective,
someone very passionate about playing for Australia.
I know you stood out of seasons in the WNBA
to represent Australia and make that a priority.
You've got a great perspective on American sport
and European sport as well.
But Australia and US sport, what's the difference in your mind?
Look, the WNBA for us, I'm just focused on women's basketball now.
I mean, it's the very best players in the world.
So, it's a global game here.
Yes, there's mostly Americans.
Australians are well-represented here in the WNBA.
But, you know, I have a French girl on my team,
a Chinese girl, someone from Bahamas.
And that's fantastic because everyone wants to play against the best,
you know, test themselves against the best.
But there's only 144 spots available in our league
because we only have 12 games because it is the elite of the elite.
But, you know, back in Australia, it's a very strong league as well.
I think it's very close to maybe being the second-best league
in the world behind maybe WNBA but maybe EuroLeague as well,
the best teams in Europe that play against each other.
And, you know, Australians, like we've – we're a world force, you know.
We've got these great individuals, you know, coming from the Penny Taylor
to the Lauren Jackson to Christy Harawa, you know, coming into the phase
that we have now with Kayla George, Mariana Tolo.
And we've got the newcomers coming in, Jade Melbourne, you know,
this 20-year-old playing with the Seattle Storm at the moment, you know,
taking them all by storm.
And we just got a lot of depth back in Australia.
I think Australians are really fundamentally strong.
They're fundamentally skilled.
And they know how to play the game in the right way.
And that's a credit to our grassroots and the coaches that we have back there.
And it's great that we have great success there as well.
But the biggest difference would be overall depth of talent between the two leagues,
you know, but Australia is certainly up there and it's a very competitive league.
You mentioned some incredible names, a lot of them are old teammates of yours.
You coached Penny Taylor in that championship win in 2014.
Lauren Jackson was the number one pick.
In her draft and has gone on to be, you know, one of the world's greatest ever players.
It's an incredible story, isn't it?
How well Australian women have done in basketball, winning Olympic medals consistently.
It's an over-representation for a country our size.
What do you put that down to?
Yeah, look, I wish our game was even bigger in Australia because of the success that we've had.
You know, I played, 1984 was the first Olympics.
The Opals have won.
I went through in LA and in 88 was my first Olympics in Seoul.
And we were the very first team to beat Russia.
We ultimately had a heartbreak against Yugoslavia in the semifinal game and lost the bronze medal to Russia in the last game of the tournament.
But, you know, we've had great success.
We won our first medal in 96 and continue to do that every year.
And we've had a few hiccups along the way in Tokyo.
I don't want to get too deep into that, but that was one of them.
But it's hard to win.
Players get better, but I think the depth of Australian talent continues to be constant.
I think that helps with the standard of the league that we have back in the WNBL, but also the players coming over to the WNBA and obviously improving their games by playing against the very best and getting that experience as well.
And a lot of it comes down to coaching, too.
You know, I think we invest in coaching development and ultimately that overhelps all of our players.
My biggest wish is that more people...
More of the NBA.
Yeah.
More of the Australian Opals players will household names.
So I think that's the thing.
We had a great World Cup last year, finishing with the bronze medal, and we have the Asia Cup coming up very soon at the end of this month.
But, you know, we had great support there.
But I think, you know, it's hard to be competitive in Australia with all the great sports that we have, but we want to make sure that we can continue to grow.
And Sandy, I love asking these set of questions because, you know, you learn so much from someone who's achieved what you have.
And your values and, you know, just hear about your passion for connecting with people and to hear the word community a lot in your language.
And I understand that's a great strength of yours and why you're so successful, your ability to build relationships with people.
But we feel success does leave clues, and these dimensions of leadership are part of that pattern for us, starting with self-leadership.
Sandy, what does that thought mean to you around leading others from starting with yourself?
Well, I think that's the most important thing.
I know.
People always ask me, I mean, what kind of leader am I?
Like I talk, I'm a servant leader because I want to help others to be the very best that they can be.
But self-leadership is making sure you're looking at yourself in the mirror and what are my strengths?
What are the areas I need to work on?
How can I impact people's lives?
Because that's what you're doing as a leader in a positive way.
And that doesn't mean it's always rosy, but you can still impact people's lives in a positive way.
And, you know, that's self-reflection.
It's always continued to grow, that self-leadership.
But I always say, don't be something that you're not when you take over a leadership role.
Because I tell my players, you will see consistency out of me every day, win, lose, whatever, because that's a part of the journey.
And I want them to make sure we're in this journey together.
And if we can stay together, great things can happen.
I love that term you use, a servant leader, and the idea of wanting to, you know, impact others.
That's the sort of title of this podcast.
The podcast effectively around empowering other people.
And that's what great leaders do.
And you went to the next dimension automatically almost, the idea of positively impacting people on a daily basis.
It sounds like that's a real focus of yours.
How have you gone about that?
Yeah, look, I think, you know, as a shy kid growing up, you know, sport was my haven.
I kind of became this, you know, very competitive person.
But it was more about having fun and doing the very best I could.
And I knew I grew, like, it wasn't always hard.
Coaches are different over the years than when I was coached.
Not as much feedback, you know, more yelling.
But I always feel like, you know, I know what got the best out of me.
You know, I always felt someone that believed in you, you know.
And that was Adrian Hurley when I first went to the AIS back in 1986.
I knew I was a great shooter and I was going to keep getting better and better.
And he believed in me.
He said, you're going to be an Australian player.
You're going to have this wonderful career.
And I'm like, really?
And just those.
Those words.
And he's still a mentor to this very day.
He doesn't, it was life changing.
And that's what I, you know, it's having someone that cares for you that much,
but believes in you that much more than that you did.
That's all I kind of needed as a kid.
And then that positivity.
I'm a very positive person.
You know, some players may not always like that.
Now I can be direct, but I'm always going to be constructive and positive
because I think if we can empower the players to believe,
they have this mass potential, then they will believe it.
And we can help them on that journey.
And I think that really goes a long way.
And Sandy, I'm fascinated hearing you say that.
I think we're of a similar generation and probably grew up with similar types of coaches,
but I feel like it spawned a generation of coaches exactly like you who went,
hey, you know, I can handle the yelling.
That wasn't a problem.
But what was the most effective?
And it feels like you're right when someone genuinely believes in you, gives you direct feedback,
but sees your ability.
And wants to nurture.
That's where you really see the great growth.
And I'm not surprised you're coaching that way as a whole generation now are.
It feels like a much healthier and smarter way to go about it.
We see people in your roles and leaders in different areas are really conscious about how they create and share their vision.
How have you gone about that in your world?
Yeah, look, I think, you know, it's an evolving vision because basketball is changing year by year.
And I think that's the part is being open to adapt to what the changes are.
Look, I feel like I love the game, like I'm always studying the game.
I'm a student of the game, but I love teaching the game to simplify it so everyone can understand it and helping the skill set what's required here.
And that's a part of my journey.
I mean, like, I don't stay stuck in what I've done 10 years ago.
It's my, I stay up with the trends, what are today.
But I'm making sure that I'm adapting to the players.
I'm adapting to the players that I have instead of them adapting to what I want to do.
And I think that's obviously really important.
And it makes me, you know, change and mold to be better.
And like I said, the game, like we obviously, a lot of us, we watch the game.
We're looking at the NBA.
That's what I do.
We have similar rules like the WNBA.
So I'm looking at what they do.
It's not a power game as much.
It's all about the spacing and how we can actually exploit all the defenses that are being played.
I think European.
Basketball, you know, we're all just stealing plays off each other.
That's part of the evolution and the vision.
And it's always, it's ongoing.
Now, I think my core values remain the same.
I think that's how I want to play the game.
Having, you know, being selfless on the offensive end and, you know, the spacing and making
sure we're taking great shots and, you know, not forcing action.
Whereas defensively, I have non-negotiables, which, you know, if we do this, we're going
to have success, but it's trying to get consistency with that.
But then obviously just molding.
How we can be the very best team by, you know, learning from others.
Yeah.
I love that combination of really strong values and consistency there, but openly wanting
to be better and evolve, isn't it?
You often see organizations that are trying to hang on to the past and the way things
are done and not, you know, as you said, it's constantly changing and moving forward.
And I can hear the curiosity in your tone.
It's that constantly learning and wanting to get better.
And I'm not surprised that Aleda Connect is something that you've loved through that curiosity.
And we see people really, through curiosity, that's how they want to get better and develop.
Does that resonate with you?
Yeah.
Without a doubt.
You know, I've spoken about this has been my passion since the age of nine.
You know, obviously starting to play basketball, learn basketball, seeing where basketball
has taken me, you know, going to the Olympic games.
I mean, who would have dreamt I went to one Olympic games?
Not everyone gets to do that.
I went to four and, you know, it's just blown away.
I love the competitiveness.
But I think you have to, it's like I said, the curiosity is more is continue to learn.
I always wanted to be the best player I could be, not be better than my teammate or someone
else, but trying to learn from others how they do things, you know, asking questions,
finding mentors.
I think that's critical for anyone's development at any level.
You know, I think mentors, they can help you along the way because it's not just a physical
thing that we do with basketball.
You know, there's the mental part.
There's the physical part.
There's the emotional part.
There's the physiological stuff that we all have to learn to be the very best that we
can be.
And, you know, I've got to know a lot of different people and the curiosity part comes from just
digging, asking them questions.
How?
And that's why I love the letter because it's fantastic just because we had so many different
leaders that you could just, you know, connect with.
And I've had Zooms, you know, I love just reaching out to them and just digging deeper
and how they do things.
And regardless of it.
It was in there.
It was in the NFL, the NRL, the AFL, just coaches.
And I love that we wanted to share and help each other, you know, because we can all learn
from each other because in business world too, I mean, because leadership is not just
in sports.
I mean, you see leaderships because it's all about developing a culture where you can actually
grow the most.
And I'm massive on that.
It's not just what you do in practice.
I'm really big on let's build the right culture.
What kind of team do we want to be and how are we going to get there?
Yeah.
I love hearing your passion.
I can see it come out on the screen and the positive energy that flows out of the smile
on your face.
Communicating with clarity is another dimension we see really consistently.
How have you gone about that in your world, Sandy?
I think communication is probably one of my biggest strengths because I was a player and
I played with, you know, so much, you know, so many different people all around the world.
I've played in Europe and, you know, obviously the Olympics.
Yeah.
And the WNBA.
And I always found getting to know the person on their personal level.
I think that's important because you know how everyone ticks and that's where you can
get the most chemistry.
You know, I know some players and coaches, mate, it doesn't matter what they do off the
court.
For me, I think it does matter.
I think you can build more connections and being very, having great communication and
honest communication.
I'm not talking about always just patting everyone on the back because there's sometimes, you
have to have hard communication, but that's a part of helping, you know, whoever it is
you're talking to, to be the best version that they can be.
But yeah, so building relationships, it's just something I've always tried to do and
I think I've grew as a player, especially when I was entering the end of my career and
then started mentoring the younger players because I went through what they did, you
know, and I didn't have as, you know, you had great players that were helping me, you
know.
When I first made the Australian team, I was a very shy and timid 18-year-old.
Yeah.
But driven and have the older players took me under their wing and, you know, I did that
at the end of my Opals career and even when I got into the coaching career, I had other
mentors that can obviously help me and it was all about connections, building relationships
with really healthy communication.
And you're right, isn't it, Sandy?
You go back to the playing days and the unspoken is where you start to question, don't you,
when your coach hasn't reached out and communicated with you or you feel like you're, even at the
end of your career, isn't it?
It just creates that uncertainty.
As you said, you're open to however direct the feedback, but at least you know where
you're sitting.
It sounds obvious, but it's often missed, isn't it?
In the busy world of leadership, people forget the obvious thing to just communicate consistently
and well.
It sounds like it's a huge part of the way you go about it.
How important has collaboration been for you?
Yeah.
I mean, very important.
It's not like, especially I'm in a team sport, basketball, it's not about me, it's about
us.
You know, doing it in the right way, doing it together, sharing ideas.
I love the part of collaboration, just coming together with the team and finding ways to
be the best that we could be as a team and to enjoy the journey.
Now as a coach now, I have a pretty big staff underneath me and I want to hear their ideas.
I'm all about like, throw them all at me because this is not about me.
You know, this is about us and I have my thoughts and I always tell them, I always want you
to have your honest opinion.
That doesn't mean I always agree, but I'm going to listen.
I don't want any like, yes people, like challenge me when you need to, but the collaboration
allows us to get to the destination that we want to get to.
And because we can all bring something to the table.
And so I try and, you know, give my staff the confidence to speak up, you know, and
if they don't like something, speak up, you know, and because then we can get to, like
I said, our end destination and hopefully that is winning championships.
But for me, I don't talk about championships once I start a season.
I talk about process.
I'm very process detailed, you know, we just come off a loss.
It's like, okay, what's the solution for us to be better because there's things that you
can touch.
Don't look at the end result.
Let's look about the step by step and that's win the day, you know, how can I be better
today individually and collectively.
Yeah.
And we know they're the best environments where everyone feels like they've got a voice,
isn't it?
Yeah.
And you can kind of have a sway of opinion your way, but at least you feel like that
open, you know, communications there and you can have a say in your environment.
Sandy, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
My parents, you know, I mean, I think everyone says that, but for me, it really is true.
And just the upbringing they gave me growing up on a sugar cane farm, it was very easy
going.
And it's funny, recently, you know, talk, I'm 55 this year, I talk about, well, you
know, my kids will, you know, graduate from school.
I love what I do.
I'm going to continue to coach as long as someone gives me a job.
I love being in a leadership role, but I always think about, okay, where do I want to live?
Well, lately, it's more back where I grew up and it's kind of weird, but it's more like,
well, my family's there and I feel it's my community.
And it's kind of unique, you know, that we can have that, but I'm enjoying this journey
that I'm on.
Sorry, I've totally lost the bloody question now.
Can we start?
Well, I love it actually.
Yeah.
You know, I'm looking at you, Sandy, and the backdrop is the Manhattan skyline.
You've just coached the New York Liberty and your mind's going to Mackay, Queensland again.
And as you said, you know, you said, I'm sure a lot of people say they're mum and dad.
And the short answer to that, Sandy, is that some people do who really have that connection
and a lot don't, you know, and I feel the same.
If someone asked me that, I would straight away feel as though the upbringing I got are
my mum and dad.
And as you get older, it's a gift, isn't it?
And I'm a bit the same.
Yeah.
It's the same.
As I've got older, I really appreciated where we grew up.
I was desperate to leave Adelaide as a kid.
But now I look back and think, God, that was a great upbringing, wasn't it?
So in your mind, you could end back in the sugarcane fields of Mackay.
Is that a possibility?
Yeah.
Well, I'd be more on the beach, Dast.
But I love the water.
You know, I grew up, like, my parents had a sugarcane farm, but we also had a holiday
house at Seaforth.
And I go back there every time I go back to Australia.
That's because that's where my parents have retired.
And I feel, it's just a weird feeling.
That's my haven.
Because I feel, this is, listen, I belong here and I can go back and nothing's changed,
which I love.
I still feel like I'm the kid that was there from the age of eight.
And I'm going back and I'm, you know, hanging out, you know, it's just a special feeling.
But I love the beach.
Initially, it was the Gold Coast, you know, I think now I can't live in a really small
town of Mackay.
Yeah.
But I know, you know, it's about family.
It's about those relationships that we have and spending quality time with the people
that you love.
But, you know, that's not for a few years off, but, you know, I want to keep hope doing
this and, you know, trying to keep improving as a coach for as many years as someone will
want me.
Where's Seaforth?
Seaforth is in between, it's about 40 minutes outside of Mackay.
Okay.
Yeah.
It's on the way going to Airlie Beach.
Ah, beautiful.
Beautiful.
Beautiful part of the world.
Yeah.
It's very nice.
I'm not surprised that your heart and your upbringing is dragging you back there at some
stage.
Sandy, if you can collaborate with anyone on anything, we're passionate about it at
Aleda and that sense of world of collaboration and what it looks like.
And you're involved in some great collaborations and it sounds like you've had great mentors
along the way.
Has there been someone you thought, God, that's the person I'd love to connect and collaborate
with?
Well, so many, really.
Yeah.
You know, really so many.
And I look at the, obviously I look at the basketball world and there's been some amazing
coaches and I've got to know Brian Gorgie and he's just a wealth of knowledge and just
how he's adapted over the years too.
I think it's always fascinating and got the best.
He's just a brilliant mind.
Steve Kerr, someone that would be, you know, someone I'd love to get to know and just the
success that he's had, but the culture that he built, because that's so important for
me.
I mean, because you've got star players and they've got to buy into playing the game in
the world.
They're playing the game in the right way and they do it beautifully.
And, you know, you have to have great players to play great too.
We understand that as well, but yeah, he just has a great demeanour and just how he connects
to his players.
I think that's important, but there's so many that I've got to see and, you know, I follow
a lot of sport.
I still read the Australian newspaper every day, even though I haven't lived in there
over two decades.
I'm more NRL and basketball, but I still follow the AFL and now that obviously I have a connection
to Justin Lepish.
Yeah.
I, you know, obviously follow his team and they're doing great and his coach is amazing
and he's got, you know, Craig McBride, you know, just hearing so many wonderful things
about him and I could probably go on and on.
I just, I could, yeah, and that's what I love about being part of this leadership group
is just to, you know, build connections and I just, I know that they're going to grow
in the future and hopefully in the end that, you know, I can be the best leader that I
can be.
But hopefully I'm giving some back from my experiences because I've certainly had a few.
They're not always, you know, you know, cherry on top, but I've learned along the way and
that's why I said, what do I need to do to be better?
And I'm always self-reflecting and I think that's been a strong part of my journey as
a player and a coach.
Sandy, it's been a great joy to spend some time with you today and I can feel the positive
energy that comes out of everything you say and I'm not surprised that you've had the
success right along the journey.
It's an amazing story.
For me, growing up in that part of Queensland to international sporting success and I love
that maybe one day it's going to come full circle and back home to Australia.
Thanks so much.
We're really privileged to connect with you and Alita Connect and thanks for taking the
time today.
No, I appreciate it, Dars.
Thanks for having me on.
Thank you for listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast, powered by Temper, a mattress
like no other.
And to make sure you don't miss an episode, click subscribe wherever you get your podcasts.