This week's guest on the Empowering Leaders podcast is Sarah Grinberg, the host of A Life
of Greatness podcast, which I encourage everyone to download and listen to.
Sarah has a brilliant story and she talks to me about how visualization has helped her
to create the life that she loves and leads now.
The kindness that Hamish and Annie, two of the legends of Australian entertainment and
media, showed her and how that has influenced Sarah in the way that she works with others
on a daily basis.
Sarah also talks about the really powerful daily routines and habits that keep her healthy
and successful and how the key to living a life of greatness for her is all about being
your authentic self.
Really enjoyed this chat with Sarah Grinberg.
I hope you do as much as I did.
To people like Sarah Grinberg who inspire the work we do at Alita, love you to have
a look at our signature program, Alita Connect.
Head to alitacollective.com.
We bring together diverse leaders from different backgrounds like Sarah in groups of five or
six.
To share and to learn and to connect in what we think is a really profound way.
We'd love to connect with you.
Book a discovery call now and head to alitacollective.com.
Big thanks as always to Jason Nicholas and his team at Temper Bedding.
We know that great leaders value sleep and you can hear Sarah talk about how important
sleep is in the people that she's spoken with.
Temper is a mattress like no other.
Investing in that, given we spend a third of our life in bed, is a decision that you
will not regret.
Sarah Grinberg.
Sarah was executive producer for arguably the most successful radio program in radio
history, The Hamish and Andy Show.
Her passion for living a life of true purpose, finding your own purpose, and not dying with
the music in you is the foundation for her brilliant podcast, A Life of Greatness.
Sarah has interviewed the likes of Deepak Chopra, Simon Sinek, Matthew McConaughey,
Rich Roll, Jay Shetty, Seth Godin, and many more.
And I highly recommend, like my wife Bec, Sarah does every single week, and I listen
to her podcast every single week.
So if you want to listen to her podcast every single week, you can download A Life of Greatness
and hear some of Sarah's outstanding work.
Great to see you, Sarah.
Thank you, Luke.
That's so nice.
Oh, I used to see you regularly in the corridors and walk past and say hello.
We were working different radio shows, but we crossed paths regularly.
Can you take us back to working on Hamish and Andy?
What did you learn from two of the nicest guys in the world, by the way?
Oh, two of the nicest guys in the world.
I want to actually start because it's just triggered in my mind.
And I first met you when I was starting to be a producer.
And I was interested.
And Jay Muller was producing the Triple M morning show that you were on.
And I came in and Sarah Fayol was the producer as well.
And they were like, you can come sit with us.
So before I started work every day doing like I was in the activations team, I would sit
with Jay and Sarah and I would watch your show.
And then they'd say like, do you have any questions or anything like that?
And they kind of saw a lot of the light in me and they were like, you'll be a really
good producer one day.
And that was like.
What I would come in early in the morning, unpaid, obviously I didn't do much, but watch.
But it kind of was the start of like producing, which then got into hosting and, you know.
Well, that's coming back to me now.
So I can picture that.
I've forgotten that.
And you're always very friendly.
Well, that's nice.
Because as you know, that time of morning has its moments.
I mean, I'll talk to you about that as well.
But Hamish and Andy are special people in their own way, but really the positive, brilliant
way that they've been able to help me.
Yeah.
They have their success.
Did that rub off on you?
Absolutely.
I think there was, you know, it's funny when you go into producing, like firstly, I think
it's Australia's biggest podcast and they just finished radio and they kind of had delved
into the podcast space a little bit before and then they were just starting up their
podcast and I got asked if I wanted to be their executive producer.
So there's this imposter syndrome that you get when you're about to work with two of
Australia's biggest names.
And, you know, their last producer, they're going to be their biggest producer.
producers, Sam Kavanagh, their last executive producer, who is, you know, one of Australia's
best producers. So then I'm going into this thinking, oh my God, how long am I going to
last in here? Like, how did I get this role? This is amazing. But, you know, am I good enough? That
kind of thought goes through your mind. Anyway, after a few months, I realised that they were
thinking that I was doing a really good job, but still the voices saying like, do they really think
you are? They're going to find you out. You know, you're not that good. And then, you know, I really
kind of learned from them that they wouldn't have anyone in their team that they didn't think was
brilliant. And as leaders, they are two of the, probably two of the best people I have ever worked
with in my life. Like there's some great people at Listener as well that I've learned a lot from, but
in particular them. And one of the things that sounds so basic, but it was something that I
really saw from them was how they
learned from them.
with kindness. They were, well, they are two of the kindest people and generous people. You can
find it was all about, you know, how they could get, how they could nurture their team. And then
in return, the team is obviously going to work hard for them because they adore them, which is
what's what happened. Everyone is so cohesive together, working so brilliantly. There's,
in the four years that I was their executive,
there was never dramas, no issues. And how you think like there was a team of nine of us,
everyone just works so well together because from the top, it was just led so beautifully. So
it really, when people started to work for me, I really was, you know, cause I had been in,
in jobs before where, you know, big leaders were managing through fear. And I had learned that too,
like, you've got to be hard on the person and, you know, they're not going to,
they're not going to do the job properly or they're slack off unless you're a certain way.
And then when I worked with two of Australia's most successful people, I realized that is not
true at all. And it, it really changed the way that I manage people. And it, you know,
they wouldn't have even realized like what an impact it had on me. Not only was it amazing
to work for them, but then yes, moving forward, I learned so much.
And talking to Andy about that in particular, they're really strategic with that, Sarah.
Like, as you know, from this world of media,
and radio and TV that, you know, you and I have been around for a long time now,
it can get incredibly toxic. And there are some horror stories out there of
just dysfunction and, and, you know, it's not unique to radio and media, but it's pretty
prevalent and, and, and, and been horrific. And in the building we're sitting in now,
there's some, there's some shocking stories and Hamish and Andy, they, they were set about one,
they wanted to make a great show, but they set about trying to change that by treating people
differently. And, and even talking to you about that, I think it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's,
and even talking to them both, they, they had some great rules where they were pushing the
envelope themselves. They never did anything nasty. I love their humor is always, uh, you know,
done in a way that's really positive, but if they had upset each other, uh, they'll tell me they
wouldn't go back on air in the next break unless they had a heart to heart and sorted it out. So
even if they had to play four songs in a row, they weren't going to start again until they'd
made sure that they were both on the right page again. So they had some discipline, didn't they?
They, they absolutely, like,
it, it's an, it really to watch two people who are so good at their craft, but then as so good
with people, like every meeting would have a planning meeting every week. And the first half
an hour was just made up of chatting. Like literally it was like, no one talks about work.
The half an hour, the nine of us would just chat about what's been going on. Like, and that was
done obviously. So everyone just loosens up a bit and we actually, you know, find out a bit about
what's happening with people and have a laugh as you do with those boys.
Absolutely. Like that even, that was such an interesting way I thought of starting like a
planning meeting is for like half an hour is a decent amount of time. We'd literally just talk.
Yeah. Smart, you know, Sarah, isn't it? We, we talk about that in, in the world we're in where,
you know, if you don't, then a lot of people in the meeting don't feel comfortable enough to speak.
And so you get people talking and we talk about like the opportunity to celebrate what's going
well for a start. Cause as you said, that old hierarchical model that you saw and leading
through fear, which has been a pattern in media.
Yeah.
Consistently, it just, it can ruin, generally ruins people's lives because you're unhappy at
work and it's a model that's just bankrupt really, isn't it? When you see the opposite of it, it's,
it's profound, isn't it?
And how effective the opposite is. Like so much more effective, not only for the team's mental
health, but how cohesive the team works because working under fear, you're never going to get the
best out of people. And then they're going to, you know, have some sort of breakdown or they're
going to leave eventually.
And say negative things about you and everyone around because you're breeding that kind of
horrible energy or you do it the complete opposite. And I think Hamish and Andy have
people that have worked for them for something like 15 years. You know, that, that is a long
time to work from, like they've come from their radio show onto their podcast and they do other
bits and pieces as well, but they would never leave the boys. It's interesting when I just,
when a life of greatness got to the stage where it,
it was, it needed, you know, me to put more energy into it and it was getting bigger.
I, after four years made up the decision that I was going to stop producing and I would move
into just hosting. And I thought to myself, and I knew I had to obviously talk to the boys about it,
but I thought to myself, I can't believe I started here thinking, when will they find me out and get
me out of here? Like, you know, full imposter syndrome to now being the one to make the decision
that I need to leave, not because I don't love it. Cause I did,
but because I have to, you know, nurture my podcast. And, you know, like I said,
I recalled a meeting with the two of them. I'll never forget. And I sat with them
and they're like brothers to me. Like they literally were, I would speak to Andy because
he does more of the business side of things like three times a week about stuff to do with the show.
And, um, I started to cry and I was like, you know, I do, you know, cause I also don't know
if I'm making the right decision. I'm like giving up the best EP job, probably in the country with
the best people to like some kind of take a leap of faith.
And I remember Hamish said to me, you know, Sarah, no leaps of faith ever don't work out.
You know, we're so proud of you and we wish you all the best and you have us, you know,
backing you all the way. And it's just, you know, to be nurtured like that and then to
exit in such a beautiful way as well. I mean, who could ask for anything more?
It's a great, uh, level of success, isn't it? When those that you work with are so happy for
your next chapter and then create successful people around them. It's probably the greatest
legacy you can have. I would have thought to do what you did. I mean, I want to ask you about,
you were producing Breakfast Radio for a while after you sat in on our show and I understand
you hated it. Yes, I did not like Breakfast Radio.
Didn't work for you. Why was that?
Well, firstly, it was, I didn't, I know that you did it for ages, but the hours were terrible.
So that was the first thing. And I think that's, I think at the time I had a two and a four year
old and not many Breakfast Radio people. And I think that's, I think at the time I had a two
radio producers have that. And I was the only producer cause it was going between Melbourne
and Sydney and I was the only producer in Melbourne. And then, um, there was digital
producers and stuff in the talent world in Melbourne. And it was just, just managing my
children and then work. And, you know, it was 24 seven working on any kind of breakfast show is 24
seven. So then, you know, I would kind of finish and then pick the kids up from like creation,
this and that, and then have to still be switched.
It just, it led to me like hardcore burning out really hardcore burning out. And I just thought
to myself, like, what quality of life is this? Like it really, and it's interesting. I'd love
to know how you kind of managed it, but I felt like I had jet lag permanently. And then come
the weekend, it wasn't like that was a savior that then it was like, you were kind of like
you'd sleep, but then you felt like your brain still felt kind of weird and fuzzy. And I just
realized that the stress plus the hours is not a good combination for anyone.
Yeah, no, it's, it's, it's true. I like getting up early. That's probably how I get out of bed,
still do. Uh, and I could get my head around it because I would be disciplined at the other end
of the day. And really without having an amazing wife, who's the superstar of our family, you know,
if I was juggling probably what you were, I would have, you know, blown up within a handful of
weeks as well. So I did it for 11 years and I look back.
And I think I never used to say to anyone, I was tired. I never once, because I thought if I
concede, then I'm going to leave that. So, so now I feel good. And then when you stop, you went,
no, you didn't. And I could never do it again. Once I'd stopped, there was no way in the world,
no amount of money could ever, ever drag you back to doing that.
And you don't look good either. Like if you look back at photos, I can't talk for you,
but I can talk for myself. You kind of don't, because you're eating at all different times.
You know, and you're kind of out of whack. So I feel like your mind and your body are not in sync.
Your metabolism isn't working properly. It's all, I'm sure if you did it properly and managed it
properly, you would be all right. But for me, I didn't really have the experience. I wasn't
into personal development like I am now. And it all kind of caved in, which was the catalyst
for me changing my life. So really it was like the dark night of the soul that led me to,
you know, I was like, I'm going to do this. I'm going to do this. I'm going to do this. I'm going to
do this. I'm going to do this. I'm going to do this. I'm going to do this. I'm going to do this.
You know, bigger and better things, which I would never take back for anything.
Yeah. There's a saying, isn't it? On the other side of pain is everything that you always wanted,
isn't it? If you can walk through it like you did. And I found that hard too. I love
exercising to start the day and it's almost impossible in breakfast radio.
No, no, no. You're not going in the tree.
The alarm's going off. Yeah. You've got to be pretty hardcore if you're doing that and
get to the life of greatness and how that did transform you from a challenging time. But I read
with interest as a 17 year old, you studied the spiritual side of Judaism. How profound
an impact did that have on you? Yeah. It's funny you say that. I was
telling someone about it today. It was interesting because I, you know, wasn't really into religion
and, you know, Judaism is my religion, but it wasn't something that was so, I didn't go to a
Jewish school or anything like that. It wasn't like so hardcore ingrained in me. But I thought
I always had this leaning towards spirituality.
And when I got to my later teen years, I thought, okay, well, Kabbalah was kind of making a comeback
because of Demi Moore and Madonna. And I thought, well, why wouldn't I study the Jewish mysticism?
Like it's a connection. And so then I tracked down, I asked a few people and I found out there
was this guy, Label Wolf, who is like the biggest, Rabbi Label Wolf, who's the biggest Kabbalah
teacher. Well, definitely in Australia and still like a big one in the, you know, the scheme of
the whole world. And I thought, well, why wouldn't I study the Jewish mysticism? And so then I
And I just said to him, like, would you be interested in kind of teaching me? And I think
he was really like, okay, who is this girl? She's really doesn't follow the normal Jewish traditions
and stuff, but not many teenage girls come to me and ask if they can do this one-on-one. So,
you know, it's so funny in hindsight, seeing where I am now, but for a year, every Sunday,
I used to sit with him, like in Balaclava at his kitchen table. And he would just like read
passages of different Kabbalistic texts. And then we would like, he would tell me about them and
we'd kind of break down the meanings. And it was like, I loved it. And I think that definitely
probably was the start of like putting a seed within me that lay dormant for a while, but kind
of was always there that then led me to do other personal development work after I had the dark
night of the soul in the radio job.
I think if you've had the dark night of the soul in radio, maybe I don't express it quite as
articulately.
As you do, but that's fascinating for someone who's not, you know, strict from the Jewish
tradition to sit down with a rabbi at 17, most 17 year olds are finding the nearest nightclub
that you can. I mean, that's unique. It must've been something deep within you.
Yeah. And it's funny because my parents are not like that either. So I don't know,
it's not like I was brought up in an environment that is like that. Like if my kids were like that
now, I could completely understand because they hear so much from me. The way that I speak is
very like that, but that, you know, dad's a doctor, like he was, he's all science and
genetics and all that, you know, only things that you can see are real, you know, all that kind of
stuff. So I think it's, you know, I think sometimes you just lean towards things that
interest you. And I think also, you know, when we're at school, sometimes I know we get to choose
our subjects in later years, but we're like, you have to do these certain subjects and you don't
like them. And then you kind of, well,
like lack interest in a lot of things. With this idea of like the Kabbalah, it was something that I
just became very interested in. And I think sometimes our kids don't have that, you know,
like even my son says to me, and he's only 10, like, oh, when I'm sometimes like just before
school, like I don't want to go to school and this and that, it's boring. And I know, you know,
what kid doesn't say that. And I was honest with him the other day. I said, look, I understand
it is boring. And there are subjects that you don't want to do because they're boring,
but when you get to the older years, you can actually choose some of your subjects.
It becomes really fun, but you don't know these subjects that you think are boring. You might need
them in later life. You may never need them again, but just know that it's like knowledge that's
going into your brain. That is a really good thing. And also it's illegal if you don't go to
school. So you have to go. Here's the boundary at the end. I hope you enjoy it, but bad luck if
you don't. I love the parenting on that. A life of greatness. It's a great
podcast. Congratulations on it. You ask other people, what does it mean to live a life of
greatness? It's what does that mean to you? Oh, I do ask other people that, but definitely,
you know, like we were just saying, compassionate, being compassionate towards people,
having a life of service. That's the biggest thing. And I, you know, I'm sure you feel it
in the work that you do that lights so many people up, even if it's just the commentary part of it,
like people like love that because they are listening to you and you're bringing them joy.
But I think service is a big part of that. Kindness is a big part of that.
Having that all in place and living an authentic life is the biggest thing. And something that like
I think nearly every single person who comes onto the podcast talks about is living a life that's
authentic to you is one that not only will be fulfilling for you, but for everyone around you,
because you're not trying to be someone that you're not. And they've done a lot of studies
now that, you know, people that don't live that authentic life and might follow a career because
their dad wanted them to follow it or their mom did, or they don't go and, you know, go to that
country that they wanted to because their husband didn't want to go or something like that. Like
a lot of that happening the whole time during your life can end up in disease at the end of the day,
because you're not living to who you truly are. So having the knowledge about that now,
I think it's so important for anyone that wants to live a life of greatness,
that they live authentically to them. Like even people, you know, someone said to me the other
day, they were complaining about a friend who's doesn't, you know, she's not a good listener and
she always kind of makes comments, you know, she has no filter on things. And I said, look,
she's always been like that. And my friend's like, yeah. And I'm like, well, she's living
her authentic truth. You know, she's not pretending to be someone that she's not.
Um, so, you know,
obviously lead with kindness, but I think all of those things encompassed together will lead you to
a life of greatness. I think, you know, really when you're with someone that is being the authentic
self, even if they are, as you said, sometimes annoying, I find those people so easy to deal
with because it's the person that's got the mask on trying to be something, but really they're,
you know, and you always find out they're doing different things. And it, yeah, I can imagine
it's incredibly tiring to keep that up all the time. And it sounds simple, doesn't it? I think
find out who you are. I mean, everyone else is taken, so you don't really want to try and, um,
be anyone else, do you? But it's, it's easier said than done. I mean, you, you speak to a lot of
people, uh, who, who live that authentic life. Is there a skill to it or is it something you
discover? Well, I think it's, I think it's something you discover along the way, but you
know, when we're young and I see it with my kids, especially my daughter, it's like, you just want
to be like everyone else. Like you, you know, when we're young, we just want that same top as that.
We want to do the same things.
It's like, well, what do you want to do? And they think they want to do with just what everyone
else is doing. And we're all like that as kids. We just want to fit in. And then when you're older,
you realize like, you know, why was I pretending for all these years to like football? I don't
like football. I was pretending to like football because everyone else liked football or something
like that. You know, you know, a lot of people have those realizations where they're like,
every week I was going to the games and I never liked it, you know? So what am I going to do
for myself that I actually really enjoy? And it might be something bizarre that not many other
people do, but you're filling your cup by doing that because you're living your authentic truth.
It's even standing up for things that you believe in. Yeah, they might not be something that everyone
believes in, but at least you're living your truth, you know?
Yeah. And as you said before, I think that, you know, as a parent, you're a mother of two. For us,
it's the thing of overlaying our world onto our kids. And this is what you need to do to be
successful. And this is...
This is what really is missing in my life. So I really want you to get 99 for your ATAR. And I'd
love you to go to university and study this because I didn't do it. And you see the pain
that causes, isn't it? Rather than just, we want to celebrate whatever you are and whatever you
turn out to be is enough. And I think, yeah, that's where a lot of pain comes from. And you're
really passionate, Sarah. I listened to you talk about your passion for meditation and visualization
and daily routines and habits. What does that look like for you?
Yeah. So visualization...
Visualization and meditation has been a big part of my life for a long time. And it really was a
game changer for me, like over a decade ago, because it was the first time that I realized
that, wow, I can actually create my desires and bring them into reality with this mental rehearsal
visualization. And as you would know from sport, it's done so often. People do that, like they
don't not train, but they do that in conjunction with training. And they've done so much research
to see that the athlete doesn't...
It's a lot better. Same with musicians. They also, they'll practice, but sometimes
to ensure that they weren't getting, you know, as many injuries, if they were like a violinist
or whatever, then they would do the mental rehearsal and they noticed that the person
was achieving the same things, doing the combination of both. And I obviously don't
do it for either of those reasons, but I do it in a sense because I want to create this reality in
my life. And it's...
It just works so unbelievably, like that I will go into meditation and most days, I mean,
I do meditation every day, but if I was to do one combined with a visualization,
I will literally in my mind think about something that I want to create. And when I'm doing that,
I raise my energy to... So when I'm visualizing, I'm actually in the scenario that I see myself in.
And then it draws those things to me. And I can't tell you the amount of things that
have come out of that.
into my life from doing things like that. And sometimes it takes a while. And sometimes it
will take months of doing, visualizing the same thing. And sometimes those things don't come,
but a lot of the time they do. And then I think, you know, not only does it work,
but it gives you that sense of hope, which I think we all need to know that you are kind
of creating what you want into your life. So obviously doing that, like I said, if you're
a sports person, you would obviously do the training.
But, you know, for me, if I need to know, I know that, you know, in my eyes open world,
I need to action things as well. So it's a combination of doing both of them that has
just worked so well for me.
There's a great study they did in the US with elite college basketball. And they trained them
for six weeks on free throws, you know, which is something they should shoot 90%, you know,
or thereabouts. And then the second control group, they didn't let them go on the court at all,
but they got a visualization coach to picture themselves,
shooting better free throws. And every time the group that didn't train outperformed the group
that was training. The power of, as you said, it's almost, you know, it's almost scary. And
then you gotta be careful what you wish for because, you know, what you put in there is
inevitably likely to come to fruition.
Yeah, absolutely. And like you said, it can happen with negative things as well.
I mean, the mind is so, it's like, you know, such a gift to us, but can also be such a burden. The
way we use it.
The way we use it is so important. And, you know, the amount, and I'm sure you would know this too,
of athletes that I've spoken to over the years, they say, yes, training is obviously unbelievably
important, having a passion for what you want to do and all that. But that's also using the mind
to be so laser focused that they know that nothing is going to get in their way for them to achieve
their dreams in their sporting careers. And it's the same with everything that we do. Our suffering,
as the Buddha would say, comes from the mind.
So how can we switch that? And it's interesting. I had this guy on my podcast just recently. His
name is Bruce Bryan, and he was falsely accused of a murder in America and put in prison for 29
years. He literally just got out in April and he's 50. So he was in jail for majority of his life.
And what he did in jail was he started to read all these texts, like he read The Secret.
And he got into, he wasn't a religious man before.
He went in there, but instead of joining a gang, he thought, well, I'm going to like read
scriptures. He said from the Bible, the Torah, the Quran, just everything to fill his mind with
good things. And he said that he would, when he was put in solitary confinement, which was
sometimes for three months, he would sit there and he would just visualize himself in a different
place. And he would just go and do it over and over again. And then some nights he thought,
you know, he learned this all in jail, that he read that the subconscious mind should be
filled with good things before you drift off to bed, not negative things, which I know through my
work as well. So he said he'd like maybe read a passage from The Secret or a scripture, and he
would be thinking about that before he went to bed. And then obviously he manifested getting out
because this guy that was going to be put in jail for life ended up, someone found out about his
case and, you know, got a great lawyer and they ended up getting him out recently. And now he's,
you know, about to tour the world. And he's going to be put in jail for life.
Speaking and his, you know, his life has changed in such an amazing way, but it was the power of
his mind that kept him sane. He said people were dying around him. They were taking their own life.
There were so many gangs in those American prisons, like they're horrendous. Yet he just
stuck to his guns and it, you know, has turned out brilliantly for him.
Some great people doing incredible things, isn't there, Sarah? It's the beauty of this
format, isn't it? There's stories around and that power, as you said, to,
and as we know ourselves, like you think something horrific that may have not even
happened. And most of the time it hasn't. And you can feel that in your body and that stress and
that sadness comes on immediately. And the reverse is there, isn't it too? As you said to,
I'm picturing a conversation I had with Steve Hooker, the Olympic gold medal pole vaulter. And
he said on that final jump, the biggest moment of his life was the easiest thing he'd done
because he'd seen it so many times that it just, it just happened because he could picture himself
going over the bar. And you're right. People say that in sport easily. They don't,
so much see it in life around, Hey, what is the life I want to live? And as you would describe
a life of greatness, you can create that if you understand the power of your mind as,
as you clearly have done in an amazing way. Well, I often use the term, Sarah, like success
leaves clues. And someone said that to me in this format, what are the patterns you've picked up?
You've spoken to some fantastic people. What are the synergies that you've picked up from
those people about a great life? Well, I think the biggest one, as we mentioned,
was this, the story of being authentic. And one thing I want to add on that, there was this
beautiful author, her name's Bronnie Ware. She's very well known. And she wrote the famous book,
The Five Regrets of the Dying. And the biggest regret of the dying was that I didn't lead a
life that was authentic to myself. So that, as we discussed is obviously a big one. You know,
the whole idea of kindness, I know that sounds like it's such a buzz. It's not even a buzzword,
but people think it's like,
a nothing thing, but it isn't a nothing thing. Like we touched on with Hamish and Andy, like
being kind can change lives and doing the opposite can also change lives. And you know,
kindness is a ripple effect. You're kind to someone, they become happy. They don't even
realize they're kind to the next person and then the next and then the next. And it's a ripple
effect because everyone gets those drops of kindness. But when you're also not nice to
someone because someone cut you off in the traffic, you know, you're rude then to the
shop assistant who gets upset, who's then rude to her kids when they,
get home, who's then, you know, that also is a cycle as well. So, you know, I think that's a big
one and, you know, having purpose and meaning in your life is huge. Like, you know, I always knew
that I wanted to be in media and I, you know, kind of started out there and then did marketing
for a period of time and then moved back into media. And I remember when I started working for
SEA and it was like, this is, it was like one of the, at that time was one of the best moments.
Like I've just come back to like what I feel like is home. And I'm like so passionate about
the media industry and entertainment. And I just felt like me after spending years in corporates,
in marketing, it just didn't feel quite right. And then, you know, that even though it was like,
you know, jobs doing activations, I just got so much joy out of that. And it just gave me this
sense of like, I woke up in the morning feeling like, wow, like I've got me,
and purpose in the world. Like this is, it just is such a different feeling than walking through
life feeling like you just, you know, you're not happy with where everything's gone or your job or
anything like that. That I think is just a huge, huge thing as well. So, you know, having all those
things, I think creates a really great life. We were talking, Sarah, before we started about
Bali, you've been up there recently and we've been lucky enough to spend a lot of time up there at
the North retreat at Sukhavati Bali. And you always, I always feel like it's a life lesson
when I'm around the Balinese. You walk amongst them and they're laughing constantly and they're
smiling. And I was watching them when I was up there a couple of weeks ago and some of the guys
were putting together this bed and one of them sort of picked up a plank of wood and it hit the
other one in the head. Now you'd be, you know, right to sort of turn around and give a, like,
he laughed immediately and they all laughed because it was an accident, you know, whereas
on a work site here, you could imagine that would.
It'd be a tense five minutes and you mightn't speak to someone. And one of our guests that was
checking in on the way in the car, she'd said, seen, you know, you, you, you watch families
for on a motorbike and there was a husband and wife clearly, and they had these crates
of like teacups or a stack, like six high. She was driving to our retreat. Someone cut
the motorbike off, the crates fell and they smashed on the ground. And she did that. How bad,
you know, like, and she stopped and waiting, you know, and they got,
and they laughed and they laughed and like, and she was like, it's smashed. Like you can't do
anything about it, you know, and you could go and, you know, have road rage here in Australia
or they realize that that person didn't really mean to do anything bad to them. It was an accident
that happened. And, but it's hard to live that in the moment, isn't it?
It's the interpretation of our environment is huge. Like at the end of the day,
things can happen. Like if there's war in a country and you're in that country, of course,
you're going, that's horrendous. Your external world is controlling,
what's going on to an extent, but we have control over our mind. Only we do. And that
Bruce Bryan is like the guy in jail. That is a perfect example of that. And what you'd said
before about in Bali, like how they interpreted those accidents was up to them. They decided
they're going to interpret it in a positive way. I mean, how much better is that than if it's all
just like, oh my God, I can't believe this. And, you know, it's a, we're in control of that. No
one else, like someone can be mean to you, but it's your interpretation of that and how you let
it affect you that then rules. They can't affect you. They can say things, but you can be like
Teflon and it just, you know, wipes off. So I think that that has just been a big learning that
we have the power to control how we perceive or envisage the world and, you know, the people that
come into it. Do you believe in luck? No.
You don't?
No. I believe that we, well, I don't know. Cause I think we create it all. So I don't believe like,
you know, you know, if someone was to say like, oh, you're so lucky you get to work at this great
media company. I would think like, oh no, I created that for myself. You know? So I think
like luck is like things just happen randomly. And I don't think that things do.
Yeah. I understand. I slightly differ from you on that. I feel like being born in this country in
Australia.
There's enormous luck. And I don't think I played any role in that or having the mom and dad that I
was lucky enough to be born into that family. I feel like, but I'm with you on the opportunity
to take what those moments are and turn them into something greater. But yeah, I think you've
articulated that ability better than almost anyone. We see these patterns around what great
leadership Sarah is, what I'm really passionate about, what it looks like in different standing.
I love your story. Having seen you in the early days, you've been a great leader. You've been a
to creating this beautiful life, which is an amazing story. But we think one of the dimensions
is the idea of self-leadership. That it's really hard to lead anyone else without the sense for
yourself. I imagine that's pretty clear for you. Yes. So for me, it comes back to what we've been
speaking about. The kindness thing is obviously a big deal, but then it's not just in the workplace.
It's the way that I live my life normally. But setting myself up to do that every day,
like the meditation that we talked about, the visualization, the gratitude. I will take time
out of my day to think about what I'm grateful for. People can easily write that down, but I just
kind of put my hand on my heart sometimes or lie there after my meditation thinking about what I'm
grateful for. And all those things give me energy as well as things like sport and stuff like that
and making sure I eat well.
Because I think people think, oh, eat well, sport, sleep, that's important. But those are
crucial elements to living a great life and being a great leader. Because if you're not doing those
sort of things and you're not fueling the body in the right way, you're not allowing the body and
mind to rest overnight for eight hours, then you'll see cracks in the way that you go about
your leadership for yourself and for other people as well.
Sleep is an unbelievable one. Because I know for myself, when I don't get enough of that,
I can start to really feel that my emotions start taking over in a way that they wouldn't usually.
And they now know that we sleep things like Alzheimer's disease and heart disease. A lot
of the triggers for those are coming from people who are lacking in sleep. So I think all those
things set me up to lead people well.
And to be a good, you know, lead people well, lead myself well, which then flows through to them as
well.
Yeah, talk about people who, you know, don't get enough sleep. It's sort of akin to, you know,
almost worse than being an alcoholic or some forms of cancer. That's how important that part of your
life is, isn't it? To be able to understand. There's very few that can get away with the
decent amount of sleep that we know. Positively impacting people in their environment.
Sarah, we see a really common pattern around people have great lives, and I'm sure that
resonates with you. How would you describe having an impact in a positive way?
Well, you know, especially with the people that, you know, are in my team, I, you know, again,
I think I got this from Hamish and Andy, and it's so basic, but when they're doing good work,
I tell them that they're doing good work. I tell them that I appreciate them. I don't do the
opposite, thinking like, oh, if I appreciate them too much, then maybe they're going to be
they'll, um, you know, I don't know. You can't over-appreciate, can you?
Exactly. Exactly. You know, it's, it's little things like that. Um, again, something I learned
from the boys, like actually at Christmas time, buying them something nice. It's their birthday,
celebrating their birthday. These are all such little things, but they all make such a big
difference. Being an ear for them if they need to talk. I mean, there was someone that was,
that works for me that was really having a hard time the other day and called me and said,
and we just chatted about their personal life and I gave them any help that I could and any
resources that I thought would help them along the way. Like you have to lead with compassion
and you have to be real when you lead too. Like I, I don't, you know, you don't want to be a
bumbling mess. You obviously, but at the same time, I think when you're a leader and you do
show that you're a human and, and you have emotions, that is a big thing too, because it
allows them to realize that they too can change. And I think that's a big thing too, because it
allows them to show that. And I remember years ago, I interviewed Simon Sinek and he was very,
he's obviously a leadership expert. And he was saying like during COVID, he's not going to
pretend that he's not suffering to his team. He was suffering. And people would reach out to ask
him if he was okay, the same way that he would do the same. So I think it's that whole idea of
realizing that you're all human, you're not robots and that you need to treat people in a respectful
manner and be a human. And I think that's a big thing too. And I think that's a big thing too.
Be compassionate and know that sometimes they are doing long hours and maybe that means that
they don't work the next day or they start later. It's just little things like that. So they don't
feel like they're a number rather than a person. Yeah. And people pick fake too, don't they?
They pick when you're, you know, dialing in and not really mean it. It's, you know,
authentic's a word you've used more than any other word, I think in this podcast and it certainly
resonates. And I think you can't fake it. People genuinely understand whether you really care or
you don't. Creating and sharing a vision is something we talk about a lot and you've had a
really clear vision, it seems Sarah, for this life you've created. And I love it. It's such a great
story. How have you gone about that? Well, I think, you know, basically I had the idea for
the podcast after I had the dark night of the soul in the radio job. Well, I didn't, I actually,
that's when I got into personal development work. I started working for the boys and then I
was engrossing myself in personal development work.
I started doing a lot of writing and I thought, why wouldn't I just do a podcast about this? And
it was six years ago nearly. And I thought like, I'm so well versed in this area. I can just
interview people who, you know, I've been teaching people how to interview for many years now.
Why wouldn't I just start something? And that's how that kind of took off. And then from there,
it's like, you know, courses and, you know, supplementary podcasts and doing speaking and
keynote talk.
And, um, you know, live shows and things like that. It just, one thing I'm sure you have these
two, you'll do one thing and that will give you an idea for something else that will give you an
idea for something else. And then it, it goes forward from there. But I think one thing is,
is, is how can I help others has been one of the biggest mantras and how can I be of service that
I say every morning, every morning I say, how can you know, use me for service, use me for service.
And how can I,
within my writing, within the conversations I'm having, how can I help other people?
Cause I find when you do that, um, not only do you feel good, you know, that you're helping them,
they feel good. And, you know, that comes straight back to you. It's this like beautiful,
like synergy and that kind of spurs on more work. And, um, it's this beautiful cycle. So
everything I do, I lead with, you know, how can I serve? How can I help others? How can I educate
more people?
So that they can live the greatest life.
Yeah. Beautifully said. They talk about that. The highest form of living, isn't it? Being in
service to others. And that is really, uh, when people are at their peak, when you're genuinely
giving, not because you're wanting it back, but because you, that's, that's what your purpose is
in life.
Like nothing for me is more important than getting those like emails from people or,
um, you know, messages on social media or things like that, where you know that you've made a
difference in someone's life. Like I find, I don't think I'll ever get sick of that. Like,
that fills my cup up more than anything else.
Yeah. Well done. Curiosity is where we hear a lot of in, in this space and through being curious,
that's how people get their learning and development and that constant sense of
self-improvement. Does curiosity ring true with you?
Yeah. I've always been curious about everything in life. And I also, you know, that I think the
podcast was good for this. I was always like, I'm not just going to follow one, like, you know,
sometimes people follow just like one lead or one thought leader or something like that.
Or one author. And I always thought, you know, I just want to get a bit of everything and then
make up my own mind because no one's way is better than the next person's way. So having that
curiosity to always seek out new thought leaders, read new books, um, I'm constantly doing those
things. And I feel that that's really enriched me. It's given me the knowledge about different
areas, but it's also allowed me to just stay curious about life because things evolve as
well.
Like, you know, the ancient scriptures usually have it right and things always relate back to
them. But at the same time, when you're talking about neuroscience and, um, the way the brain
works, like we're just finding out new things every day about that. And so like, okay, how can
we use that in a way that allows us to live a better life? And I think we know always need to
be curious, um, and always question things as well. Like, you know, it just because someone
said it doesn't always mean that it's right. Or maybe there's another avenue.
That's always been something that I've really, really been big on, you know?
You're not being rigid, rigid in your thinking and being open-minded. And sometimes you can
change the thought, can't you? Because you hear it in a different way. And, uh, yeah,
putting your, uh, your mind into that space is, is interesting. Communicating with clarity.
And that's, you know, pretty much what you do, Sarah, very clear about living this life of
greatness and you work with great communicators and this has been the world you wanted in media.
Have you thought really strongly about the way that you've been communicating with people?
Well, it's funny because over the years in different, like, you know, in the,
in the radio roles I've had, or in the producing roles I've had, people always said,
you're very matter of fact. And I, and I, it's always, it's my authentic self. So I think my
mom is quite matter of fact as well, but I've never noticed it until other people were saying
that. So, you know, obviously I'm being authentic. Um, you know, I don't bullshit. That's the
biggest thing, clearly. But what I've learned over the years is to make sure that like, I don't,
I'm not too matter of fact. Um, cause you know, there's a lot of people, they do it in such a
nice way with all these pleasantries. And then it's like, get to the point of where are we going
whilst I'm straight to the point. And that's what Hamish and Andy loved about me. They were like,
you're so matter of fact, like we just know, know how it is. Um, but I have been working on
thinking about that before, you know,
I say something to deliver information or all that kind of stuff. Cause you matter of fact is
good because it's authentic and you're not, people don't walk away thinking like, I don't know what
they're talking about, or I'm really confused, but at the same way, you need to do it with kindness.
Well, I love the self-reflection, isn't it? It's not understanding yourself, isn't it? And then
you can maybe add a bit of nuance to, to the way you communicate. How important has collaboration
been for you, Sarah? Oh, it's so important. And you know, it's a, it's a funny thing. Cause I
think in our world, sometimes people get scared to collaborate.
Like not just having a guest on a podcast, but you know, maybe doing courses together or
sharing information or I don't know, um, doing events together or something like that. And
it's interesting cause they're like, this is my patch. And, um, you know, I, if we bring the
worlds together, God forbid your audience would know about my stuff or something like that.
But you realize that that's not the way. And being in that scarcity mindset is only going to give you
more of that within your life.
And I think collaborations are the most beautiful thing. Like being able to expose
your knowledge to more people and their knowledge to your audience. And it really like lifts the
both of you up. And it really, it's an audience thing. Like you just get out to so many more
people. It's, it's wonderful. Like, you know, if you're collaborating with the right people
who, um, you know, you believe in their work and all that kind of stuff. And you think that they
could be, um, helpful to the people that, that, you know,
you are your audience too, then I think it's a wonderful thing.
Yeah. If there's shared values, isn't there? And you, and that abundance mindset is,
is such a healthier way again, isn't it? That there is enough, there is enough going on.
There's always enough.
In whatever area you're in. It's, uh, yeah, I think people have that, uh,
fear all the time, isn't it? Someone's opening up a restaurant next to mine. Well,
perhaps that just brings more people.
Exactly. Exactly. It's the interpretation.
Yeah. Always. Who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Who's been the greatest leader?
Look, I think, you know, I, I think, you know, the, my dad is someone who I've always like
looked up to. I mentioned that he's a doctor, but he was always, you know, he's a very kind man.
Um, and he's, he always looking at him, you know, he never will say a bad word about anyone.
He's very funny as well. Uh, but he's very caring too. And so, you know, I grew up
seeing that. And I think that's, I think that's, I think that's, I think that's, I think that's,
and my mother is exactly the same. She also is like that, but it was nice to be nurtured by people
that, you know, were their authentic selves and were kind and led in a way, you know,
they led the family in a way that allowed us to blossom. I mean, you know, I don't know if dad's
listened to one episode of my podcast, but mom listens to every single episode. Um, but that's
okay. He doesn't need to be on the same wavelength as I am. Cause we're not, we're very different.
But, you know, it's just seeing the way that he's led his life, um, and being very successful at what
he does has made me realize again, similar to Hamish and Andy, that you can lead like that
and be able to, you know, have abundance and love around you.
But you know, he's there and you know,
Absolutely. So proud.
Yeah. So he should, so he should be. I mean, you've had some great collaborations and it's
a great achievement on your podcast.
It's turned up in different lights, but you know, we mentioned Simon Sinek and, um, Deepak Chopra
was brilliant. Incredible. Jay Shetty, you've collaborated with great people on your podcast.
Is there one person that you've thought that's the person I'd love to, not necessarily on your
podcast, but in life in general, I'd love to collaborate with one person in general. Is there,
is there a name that springs to mind?
To be like, I've had so many of them. Like it was, it would have been Deepak a few months ago.
And then I had him and it was, it was, he was amazing.
Um, you know, there's always, it's funny, but I have had a few musicians on,
and I know this is a completely different area. I love people that have really good life stories
and I've followed Bruce Springsteen for a long time. And then, you know, he's done podcasts
with Obama and I remember listening to them a while ago, especially when I was starting a
podcast with Josh Frydenberg, when he was the treasurer, I listened to that cause he did it
with Obama and I thought, Oh, it'd be good to hear kind of like what they bantered about and stuff.
And he is such a super interesting guy. Um, all these songs come from, you know,
deep meaning within his life. You know, I'd love to collaborate with someone like him.
Um, there's, I think in the personal development world, I think I've nearly ticked everyone off.
Um, there's always people that come up, but I think the people that I've wanted the most
have been on. So, you know, there's always interesting people within the entertainment
space or the sports space, um, that,
you know, you think, Oh God, that would be good. You know, it'd be interesting to get into their
mind and, and, um, see how they tick. But Bruce Springsteen, Eddie Vedder, people like that. I
mean, I love them. I reckon the boss that jumps out, doesn't it? Love to see you sitting down
from the boss and I would not back against you making that happen. I can see that in your
visualization coming to fruition. Congratulations. I love your story. It's, um, you can see living a
life of purpose and greatness, which as I said at the start, uh, if you haven't listened to Sarah's
work, I encourage you to do it. And the wisdom you're passing on to others is an incredible
contribution. Thanks for taking the time. Thank you so much. Thank you for listening to the
empowering leaders podcast powered by temper, a mattress like no other. And to make sure you
don't miss an episode, click subscribe wherever you get your podcasts.