I was fortunate enough to be joined by Scott Pape on an earlier episode of the podcast,
which we'll link to in the show notes. So after you've listened to Scotty Pape's take on the
current situation Australians are facing in their financial lives, I highly recommend you go back
to the first conversation we had with Scott, where he tells the story of his journey to become the
barefoot investor and his impact on personal finance in Australia. It's a remarkable story.
He talks about the importance of teaching financial literacy in schools and where the
Department of Education has got it wrong. His decision to give away his business and instead
provide financial education for free as a TAFE-trained financial counsellor is an incredible
contribution. His passion for supporting and training small businesses, he refers to small
businesses as the backbone of the country. So I encourage you to go back and listen to the
original episode with Scott Pape, the barefoot investor. But first, I know you're going to get
so much out of this update with Scotty Pape, where he talks about his work, again, as a financial
counsellor for Australians who are struggling with financial difficulties. So I encourage you to go
find a way to put a roof over their family's head and to get healthy meals on the table. He also
addresses the sneaky tactics of superannuation funds and tells us what we need to do to stay
in control of our own super. And he puts forward his unique approach for how best to talk to kids
about the household budget. It's incredible people like Scott Pape, the barefoot investor,
who inspire our work at Alita. I'd love you to check out our signature program, Alita Connect.
Go to alitacollective.com and have a look at our program. We curate groups of five,
six leaders around the globe to come together, to learn, to share and connect. We'd love to
get you involved in one of our programs. Book a discovery call today. Big thanks as always to
Temper and Jason Nicholas, their team at Temper Australia New Zealand for supporting conversations
like this with Scotty Pape. If you haven't invested in a mattress like Temper, it's a
mattress like no other. I encourage you to check it out today. Scott Pape, the barefoot investor,
is a great champion for helping Australians manage their financial well-being. He
tears his time to support Australians in financial distress, lobbies governments to support better
financial literacy for our kids. He's a very passionate and proud father of four who lives
on his farm in country Victoria, where I'm talking to him from today. Pape, thanks for joining me for
a second time. It's the first time I've circled back around to a guest on this podcast for a
second time. I love catching up with you. I really appreciate you joining me today.
Thanks, Gus. Good to be here.
Now, the cost of living crisis, I want to start there, Pape. It's real. Can you give a sense of
just how it works?
How tough it is out there for the average person today?
Well, that's a really interesting point. What is the average Australian? I mean,
we saw with the phase three tax cuts, people on $200,000 a year are saying,
we're doing it tough. Everyone's doing it tough. I think that the problem is that most people hang
around with people on the same income as them. I've got a bit of a unique insight because I
actually help people who are really struggling. So single parents, you're in lots of debt.
And often I'll sit there and talk to them about a budget where we're trying to make
$10 stretch. We're talking about putting food on the table for their kids. So I guess the insight
for me is when I hear about the word cost of living, what I think of is housing, right?
That is the number one thing that is the issue in Australia right now. If you've owned your house
for about five years, generally speaking, you're doing okay because the housing prices, as we all
know, have gone up. You've built up a bit of equity. That's not to say that you're not struggling
day to day.
We know most Australians are struggling day to day, especially if you've got kids in private
school and all those sorts of things. But generally speaking, that big block of owning
your own home and having some equity there, you're doing okay. It's the people that have
just bought their home in the last, say, three to five years that have caught those 13 rate rises
that we were never supposed to get. And it's those people, especially who are renting that
are really struggling right now.
I mean, rental affordability is the worst on record. They say it's at a crisis when it's
one, one and a half percent vacancy rate. We're at 0.8 of a percent right now. So if you're a single
parent or if you're earning the average income, what we are finding, I was reading a report that
basically said there's almost zero properties that are considered affordable for the lowest
income, the lowest 30% income.
Well, if you're in that situation, that is where cost of living is really biting. If you're a single
mum and you've just been told that your rent's going up 200 bucks a month, that is a crisis.
That is what we're seeing. Yeah. So for me, if I'm looking at the cost of living, I think housing.
And I don't think either political party really has an answer to that. And if they don't have
an answer to that, it means it's just going to keep going the way it's going. They won't look
at tax breaks.
Negative gearing and the capital gains tax discount, which favours rich people like you
and me, Das. So I'm talking against my own book here, but I find it strange that we are basically
favouring investors versus young people getting to their first home. I think there's a lack of
supply. And I also think that bringing 500,000 new migrants to Australia, when you've got a rental
crisis, there's a lack of supply. And I also think that bringing 500,000 new migrants to Australia,
there's not enough rental properties. And it's basically the whole market is cooked. I don't
see how that's helping things. And Pepe, you look at coming out of
COVID, for me, the divide has never been bigger. The top 1% of wealth in the world now own more
than the next 50%. And if you had money going into COVID, you've made more money. And just
seeing that that has got bigger and bigger, as you said, someone who's now
not got a possibility to rent a house and has got no margin for error. And then you've got the elite
wealth that have got this obscene amount of wealth. I mean, how big a problem is that in your mind?
We are the 1%. Australia, according to Credit Suisse, is the wealthiest nation on earth.
We are the lucky country, but we're also the lucky country where 3.7 million households
don't have enough money for food on the table. We are also the country where you've got anyone
under the age of...
30 and living in a capital city is basically giving up trying to buy a house, especially if
you live in Sydney. We live in a country where probably the most important workers, so teachers,
nurses, police, fireys, they can't afford a home in a capital city without overextending
themselves and really stressing themselves out. Some of the toughest emails I get are from people
who did the right thing. They saved, they bought a house, they bought a house, they bought a house,
and now they've just copped these rate rises, and they're really struggling. As you and I talk
about, Das, for many, many years, you buy a house, you get married, and you have kids. It's a very
expensive time. It's a very stressful time in your life. So I just kind of feel it's not really the
1% because by living in Australia, owning a home, you are in the 1% anyway. It's really that
generational divide of people that are priced out of the property market or are priced out of the
property market right now and are overextended. That's, for me, where the divide happens. I think
Australia is becoming a very uneven country, and I don't think this is going to bode well for this
country going forward. I think it is good context to have that perspective of being in the 1% and
being in that fortunate position, but wanting to have this conversation, maybe a sense of empathy
that is out there at the moment. I know this is a hard question to answer, but I like asking,
of you, and I'm not sure there's an easy answer to it, but how much is enough money? You've got
access to do things that could make you five times as wealthy if you really wanted to be,
but you make choices to live a balanced life. I like talking to you about that. How much do you
think is enough money for someone to live a healthy and happy life? Well, generally, it comes
back to what I said. Most people only hang out with people who earn the same amount of money as
them or more. There's a saying that if Bill Gates woke up and
only had Oprah's wealth, he'd jump out the window. It's all relative. It's the people
that you hang out with. I'm kind of lucky in that I live on this farm. A lot of my work deals with
people who are really struggling. For me, it's a real reality check and a gratitude check of just
how lucky I am because I am dealing with people who are really struggling. I think it's different
for everyone. I think it's a lot less than you think. However, that whole money doesn't buy
happiness.
It's true beyond a certain level, but I can tell you the people that I deal with that are
being necked with a couple of hundred bucks extra rent from their landlord, that's miserable.
That is misery. If you're a young couple and you're going to auctions every weekend and you're
seeing prices just bit out of your control, that's miserable. The idea for me of the lucky country is
that I can buy a house that I can afford, that I don't have to get myself into a house that I can
into serious debt for, and that I can live a good life and contribute to society. That figure is
going to be different. It's said that beyond $70,000, it doesn't increase your happiness.
For me, it's about security. If I've got a house that I like, it may not be the biggest house,
it may not be the Kardashians, you name it, but if it's my little house and I can afford it and I
can afford to take time off work and if I can choose to do a job that I enjoy doing and I have
time to do it, I can afford it. I can afford to take time off work and if I can choose to do a job that I enjoy doing and I have time to do it, I can afford to do it.
I can afford to go to my kid's footy game and all those sorts of things. Any money beyond that,
as you and I know, isn't going to make you any happier. You and I both know people that are
very wealthy that aren't the happiest. For me, it's all about financial security.
At that end of the scale, there's an enormous amount of greed in the world. I think I've said
this to you before, some of the unhappiest people I've met are the kids of the super wealthy that
inherited too much money and haven't ever had to think about working. I think Warren Buffett's
a great person in your life. I know you're a devotee of his thinking and I think he is famous
for paying for his kids' education and almost nothing else. I think the quote is,
I want to leave my kids enough they can do anything, but not enough that they can do
nothing. You choose to take your kids on caravan trips and you go to Europe in a caravan. You
could take them on six-star trips if you wanted to. Why is that so important for you?
Well, it's just that whole thing. I was very lucky to… Warren Buffett, for those who don't know,
is one of the wealthiest people in the world.
He generally has been number one.
He's sort of in the top five.
He's sort of like the Melbourne demons of the wealth group.
And I actually was fortunate enough to spend five –
He's worth $100 billion plus, Pape, isn't he, for some perspective, isn't it?
More than $100 billion.
I was lucky enough to spend time with his son.
My thing is that you can – if you're a rich dude, if you're mega rich,
you can spin a line and the media will eat it up.
You've got enough money to basically create your own image in the media.
But you can't fudge your kids, right?
And I spent a day with Peter, his son.
What I found to him to be was just a really humble guy.
He grew up in a house that was a suburban house in Omaha.
He walked to school.
He went to a public school.
He was just a genuinely lovely, very centred guy.
And as you and I both know, I've dealt with a lot of –
trust fund kids and they are some of the most screwed up people you know.
So for me, I kind of looked at it and went, I want my kids to be like that.
It's important for me that my kids are hardworking and that they're generous
and a farm here is a really great place for kids to grow up.
But again, you know, I'm the first to say that I'm very privileged as well.
You know, I've been able to give my kids experiences that other kids can't.
For me, it's really important.
It's probably the most important thing that I'm doing.
You're hugely passionate about basic financial literacy and not being taught in schools.
You wrote a brilliant book about this specifically for families.
So what's the best message you give to support families to enable us to help
with a better financial wellbeing future for our kids?
You know what I think is really interesting?
And I've been reflecting on this.
As we are coming – as those rate rises have gone up, you can –
I get hundreds if not thousands of letters from people.
And I can –
I can feel the stress that people have because we all know that, you know,
the Reserve Bank said, just go out and borrow.
It's fine.
Rates aren't going up.
And then bang, bang, bang, bang, all these rate rises came up
and no one was expecting it.
And so there's a lot of stress in households right now.
And so the thing that I have been reflecting on is often what we want
to do is hide our kids from those stresses.
We don't want them to know that mum and dad are worried
about money or are anxious.
And, of course, you know, it's got to be age appropriate.
But I think having those real conversations with your kids
is actually really important.
You know, once they sort of – older primary school,
but certainly high school, talking about what's going on,
letting them see how you are going, you are resilient
and how you're overcoming them.
Because the thing is you can't hide it from the kids.
They know when things are tough.
So for me it's having those conversations.
You may not want to bust out your credit card bill and show them
or anything, but just giving them an understanding of what it's like
to live through this period of time where arguably we've got some
of the most indebted households in the world.
We're really struggling, a lot of families.
I think that is something that will stick through with kids.
That's something that they're going to learn.
But again, for me, just in those sort of younger years
where the concrete's still sitting on their –
on their personality, that idea of working hard, doing jobs and giving, understanding that they're
doing pretty well. And that's why that sort of that food bank thing that I spoke about,
I love giving the food bank because it's really tangible for kids. They know what it's like when
they haven't eaten, when they've missed breakfast, they get a rumbly tummy. And, you know, the
chances are that a couple of kids in their classroom haven't had breakfast. You know,
if we've got 3.7 million households that are kind of struggling to put food in the fridge,
there's a fairly good chance, my kids go to a local public school, that there's a couple of
kids there. And they really understand that. So just building that empathy and that hard work,
that's all we want. We just want our kids to be hardworking and generous.
I love how you simplify that. And it's true, isn't it? Putting that into practice and
trying to teach empathy is something that we can
think about.
I think about the share market as a pretty complex thing at times,
Papi. It's your world, you know it really well. For a lot of us, it's hard. How do you start?
Where do you get the knowledge to even, I suppose, start investing? Should everyone in your mind
that can save a few dollars be investing in the share market in some way?
Well, Darcy, I think I'll backtrack there and say that I think it's deliberately confusing.
And I think it serves an industry.
An entire industry called the superannuation industry for you to think that and to not think
about your super fund and not even think about it until you're 55 or 60. You know, they would
really like it that if you just paid no attention to it. So they could just, you know, they could
charge you as much as they can. They don't want it. They don't want you turning up to the meetings
and asking why you're spending money on this, that and the other thing. You know, so for me,
the first question is,
is you are already an investor. If you've got superannuation, you're already an investor,
whether you like it or not. If you're working, you've got super. Now, one of the things that
you find that I, a lot of the stuff you read in the newspapers and on TV are from financial advisors
or wealth companies. And they'll say, you're going to have a million bucks to invest. You're
going to have 2 million bucks, you know, to retire, or you're going to end up, you know,
chomping grass out here like a sheep.
I had a look at it.
Right. And I did the figures. And what I found was the average retirement balance for a man in
Australia. So the median, which is the midpoint is $211,000. That median retirement balance for
a woman is about $158,000. So that is middle Australia, right? But here's the thing. Those
people don't get to spend that $211,000 or $158,000. They don't get to spend that $211,000.
Because the majority of them have still got debt. So they've got to take that money. And they've got
to pay down their debt, which we know is quadrupled over the last, you know, 20 years,
household debts have. So for me, I'm just focusing on the young people who are going into work now,
saying, you really need to pay some attention to your super and to your
savings. Because a little bit of effort there can literally change your life as you get older.
Again, I love the simplicity of the message. And you teach families a lot about that, isn't it?
Spending less than you earn and living within your means and a happiness that comes with
not necessarily having to keep up with the neighbours as we talk about a lot. Do we need
to teach governments the same paper? You and I live in a city called Melbourne. You're slightly
out of town.
On the farm, but you look at the debt levels that Victoria has accumulated,
record numbers, the combined totals of other states combined, I'll get the number wrong,
but $370 billion worth of debt. I think last time I had a look or thereabouts,
as someone who knows this space well, should we be alarmed that our governments have borrowed
at that level? Or is it okay? Look, I try not to get into politics. So for me, I guess that
the best analogy I can give is that I'm not a politician. I'm not a politician. I'm not a
politician. I'm not a politician. I'm not a politician. I'm not a politician. I'm not
a politician. I can have, I don't know, let's say that's 20 acres behind me, right? I can
have 20 sheep in there and do pretty well. And I can keep putting sheep in there and
earn more and more money. But the problem is, is eventually I'm going to have not enough
grass there and people are going to be unhappy. It's a similar thing with what's going on
with government debts and the population growth that we're having right now.
For me, though, what I focus on is the things that I can control.
I can't control the Victorian state debt, which does worry me.
I can't control what politicians do.
I will say that the difference between, say, America and, you know,
TikTok, Instagram, we all get all these gurus from America
and we often don't see the difference between Australia and America.
The big difference with Australia is in America,
the government's got all the debt.
In Australia, we have all the debt.
It's our households that have all the debt.
So for me, I'm just focusing on the things that I can control,
and that is I have no control over the government.
They do some pretty silly things, but for me,
it's more about what can I do for my family to make sure
that we've got enough.
And, Poppy, I'll go back to the social divide.
Again, for me, which I find sort of scary,
that if people have next to nothing, you do become desperate.
And if you have no sense that there's hope to find your way out of it
and the numbers you just articulated, 3.7 million households
who are struggling with their food bill, that's a crisis on every level
in a population size of the country that we live in in Australia.
I mean, if you could wave a magic wand to get more equality,
is there a fix?
Is there something that you would do?
If you could just, as I said, find a way to influence it?
I mean, I've looked at a couple of things.
I mean, I think the first thing is that we need to have more housing
for single parents and people who are vulnerable.
And there are people that that doesn't fit their political ideology.
But for me, it's not just about those parents.
It's about the kids coming through.
And so what I've tried to focus on is kind of three things.
So the first one is finance.
Financial education.
Because we all know that financial education is that one thing
that changes your behaviour.
So we expect a lot from people.
We know that probably half of Australia, thereabouts,
don't have the basic financial skills to operate in life.
They can't work out percentages.
They don't really understand super.
They've got no idea about private health cover, none of that.
So we expect young people to actually understand this stuff.
And so I think financial education,
is one thing.
The second one is you've got to help the battlers.
You've got to help the people who are harder.
And if you don't, if you want to see what that looks like,
if you don't go to America, see how well that's working out for them
by treating those really poor people like they're just a piece of dirt, basically.
And then the third thing that I've done is I have this thing.
I'm going to give you a plug.
It's the Small Business Debt Helpline.
So I helped set this up coming out of just before COVID.
It's specifically for small businesses that are struggling, that have got debts.
We all know, you and I are both small business owners, hardworking people.
They're not doing it to earn millions of bucks.
They're doing it because they're passionate.
It's generally a family business.
Generally, banks don't lend to small businesses.
What they'll do is they'll just say, well, we'll borrow against the house.
We'll borrow against your assets.
And so they end up getting into a lot of trouble.
So if there are people that are struggling,
that are struggling, that are watching or listening right now,
that are small business owners that are feeling the pinch,
there is help at hand.
It's called the Small Business Debt Helpline,
something that I'm really proud of that we helped set up.
It's 1-800-413-828.
That's 1-800-413-828.
And again, I'm a financial counsellor.
Anyone who's struggling with their debts, feeling out of control,
don't do it alone.
Call 1-800-007-007.
You'll meet up with a financial counsellor.
It's a free service.
It's independent.
And it'll help you get back on your feet.
That's why I admire you, Papy, as much as anyone.
I think you've got integrity that other people haven't even thought of before.
We could spend this time plugging the book that sold more copies
than any other book in Australian history.
But you're always thinking about giving back and helping small businesses.
We'll make sure we put those numbers in all of the show notes post this.
And there are people there that can help.
It is an incredibly tough time.
But I love the fact that you've got someone like you, Papy,
who's a voice for people.
That haven't got a voice in this space.
So I really appreciate you jumping on again, mate.
I know there's a lot happening in your world.
But I appreciate the update and some sound advice, as always,
for people who are doing it particularly tough at the moment.
Thanks again, mate.
Thanks, Darce.
Thanks for listening to another episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Huge thanks, as always, to our great friends at Tempa.
And we encourage you to check out our Leader Connect program.
New episodes are out every Wednesday morning at 6 a.m.