How does a humble country boy become the face of finance in Australia?
And how do you stay true to yourself on the back of life-changing success?
G'day, it's Luke Darson.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership both on and off the field
has been a lifelong passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective
and have had the privilege of working with thousands of leaders
in education, sport, industry and the arts
that have helped shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership
where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
Scotty Pape, known as the Barefoot Investor,
has changed the paradigm completely for how millions of Australians think
and manage their personal finances.
His book, The Barefoot Investor,
the only money guide you'll ever need,
is the highest ever selling book in Australian history
with over 2 million copies sold.
His follow-up book, The Barefoot Investor,
for families, is also a number one bestseller.
Scott's leadership in lobbying state and federal MPs
to overhaul financial literacy in schools
has put that issue firmly on the agenda.
Scotty Pape's positive contribution
to the financial health and education of millions of Australians
is a great story of passion and leadership.
Welcome to the Empowering Leadership Podcast, Pape.
Thanks for joining me.
Thank you, Dars.
Now, I've got to say, I'm not sure why I'm here.
First point, I rarely do,
I don't do podcast interviews.
I rarely do radio interviews anymore.
I don't do television interviews.
And this is a show about leadership.
And I've got to tell you, I know nothing about leadership.
I'm going to put it right there.
The only reason I'm here is because you are one of the most genuinely lovely people
that I've worked with throughout my career.
And I mean that.
We've worked together for nearly a decade.
So I'm here for you, buddy,
but I'm a little concerned because I could stuff this up for you.
Well, very kind of you.
I'll say that, mate,
because I see your life story as ultimate leadership
in the world that you operate in.
And as I'm talking to you and answering that comment,
and very nice of you to say it,
but I'm thinking about an interview we did on this podcast
with Brian McNamee, who was the CEO of CSL.
Great story, I'm sure you're aware of,
transforming that company into Australia's largest company.
And he spoke about on the podcast, Pape,
that everyone gets a couple of cards in life,
and it's how you play those cards
that determines you a lot.
I reckon you got your cards,
you know them well,
and you play them well.
Is that a fair assessment?
Yeah, I think so.
I mean, one of the things,
one of the sort of the turning points for me,
there's a couple,
but the main one was when I started,
I started on a little student radio station
trying to make money sort of interesting for young people
about 20 years ago.
Because everything from that point
was actually written for older people.
And I remember, you know, getting really excited
and I went back to, went back home and dad said,
you know, no matter what you do, don't be a wanker.
Look after the battlers.
You know, I'm a kid from Oyen.
You know, no one ever came to Oyen.
So he's like, you know, just make sure that, you know,
you don't get too ahead of yourself
and write for those people.
And I guess that's kind of one of the things
that I've tried to do.
Great advice that is from,
man, you're always on, mate.
The phone's going.
I like that.
And I might've had a family call.
So let me know if we need to pause and sort that out.
But mate, from there, from community radio,
effectively into selling the highest ever selling book
in Australian history,
passing 50 Shades of Grey and Harry Potter.
It's an extraordinary story of success.
So what do you think about that success
when you're sitting here now?
It's a little overwhelming, to be honest.
I mean, I sat there when I first wrote the book.
I thought to myself,
no one really,
buys books anymore.
No one reads books.
We're all online.
So I wrote this book.
I thought if I'm going to do it,
I'm going to write this book
like I would be sitting at the bar with my mate,
just telling him exactly, you know, what I do.
You know, so sketching out on the back of a coaster.
Here are the buckets that I use.
You know, here's the accounts that I use.
Here is the pillows that I buy.
All these random stuff.
So I wrote it.
And then I sent it off to the publisher.
And they're like,
this is actually pretty good.
They didn't think because I'd written for the newspaper
for like 15 years,
they sort of thought,
oh, you know, you've got a bit of a following.
Let's just throw out a book.
But when they read it,
they're like, you know,
this probably could sell 20,000 copies.
Like this could be really good.
And then I remember the first week it sold,
like we had a pre-order thing and it had like 80,000
copies in the weekend.
And I'm like, wow, this is big.
And then it just became a,
uh,
I think they've called it Australia's largest finance cult
or something.
And it grew into something pretty crazy.
Where did those,
you know,
I suppose to me,
the thing I've always noticed and loved about you,
Papi,
is that your values are really strong.
You could have commercialized so many aspects of what you
do,
but being fiercely independent has always been that part of
you.
Where did that value come from?
Yeah,
I do think it came back to sort of mum and dad
saying,
you know,
that,
you've got to look after,
you know,
just,
tread your own path.
Sort of thing.
Yeah.
And so for me,
I distinctly remember,
um,
we'd sold it.
It just cracked over a million copies and I went for
dinner with my wife and we had it got a babysitter
and it was like a celebration because we never thought I
never thought I would sell a million copies.
And she said,
you know,
what's next.
And at that time that was right at the peak of it.
Right.
So I had,
you know,
people wanting me to do,
um,
uh,
managed funds,
hedge funds,
um,
financial planning.
The whole range of things that I could do.
Like people were,
we just had a list of people wanting to offer me stuff.
And,
and this serious commercial opportunities,
like millions and millions of dollars.
And like an estimate.
I mean,
if you went down that path,
you're talking tens and tens of millions.
Yeah.
It could have been very,
it could have been really,
really lucrative.
Um,
for me,
did you think about it for a moment?
No,
I did not.
I actually didn't.
Um,
because I didn't realize that the book was going to become this big.
And it was almost like,
when it did,
it was,
um,
a little bit,
I'm pretty humble,
sort of a dude,
you know,
I just live on a farm and it was a little overwhelming to be honest,
to be sort of a household name.
It was quite overwhelming.
Um,
but you know,
I,
so I sat down with my wife and she's like,
what are you going to do?
And I said,
you know,
I think I'm going to go to TAFE and I think I'm going to do,
um,
uh,
become a financial counselor.
So basically a social worker who helps people that don't have any money,
um,
manage their money.
And,
and she's like,
um,
do you get paid for that?
And I'm like,
fair question.
No,
no,
you don't.
But we've earned a lot of money through the books,
so we probably don't need to.
And so,
yeah,
at the,
at the height of it,
I,
I handed back my Australian financial services license.
Um,
I went to TAFE.
I did this course as a,
as a student,
I learned to become a,
what is basically a social worker,
like a financial counselor.
So if you are in trouble,
uh,
you've,
you know,
you don't have enough money to,
to pay,
to pay your bills,
you can ring up the National Debt Helpline on 1-800-007-007.
You talk to someone like me and I'll sit down and try and talk to your bank.
Um,
it could be a farmer who's struggling.
It could be somebody who's got a terminal illness.
It could be someone that's been caught up in a scam,
or it could just be someone who's a single mom.
Who's just had a re who's those cards didn't fall the right way.
And so what I do,
um,
is sit down and help them get themselves out of debt.
And so for me,
you know,
I thought that that was a good use of my,
my time and I've sort of tried to promote that service because you know,
as we've spoken about before,
we live in a day in an age where we have some of the highest household debts in
the world.
So for me,
that was really important to try and help those people who have really been
left behind with this current boom that we've had.
And you started this podcast saying,
I'm not sure why I'm here.
I don't see myself as a leader.
And what you just said is,
as I said to you as the ultimate leadership,
isn't it?
Where you could really go on a path.
And,
uh,
and make as much money as you wanted to with your reputation.
And you've decided to go down the full time social worker path.
I mean,
I don't think you can get more leadership than that paper.
And it's an industry,
your industry,
the finance industry that's littered with kickbacks littered with people giving
advice who are maybe not upfront.
Is that something you realized at a young age as well when you were entering
this space?
Not really,
because I was always really interested in,
uh,
like my old man,
um,
quit school when he's 14 or 15.
And he,
I think if he had it,
if he,
if the cards had been dealt differently for him,
he would have done what I've done.
Like he always wanted to go into finance,
but he never really,
uh,
never really got that opportunity as a country boy.
So for me,
he was always like,
I had mates whose dads would get him up out of bed on a Sunday
and tinker with a car.
And he became a mechanic.
My dad was always getting me to learn about shares.
He was,
you know,
paying me in shares,
one little BHP share.
So he sort of fostered that,
um,
that sort of,
uh,
idea in my head.
So I was always really interested,
but kind of in a way of demystifying it for the everyday person.
So that community radio show that I did was like,
hang on,
everything's for older people.
Nothing's for younger people.
I'm going to try and do it.
But what I worked out quite early on was that the parents of the kids were listening because they're like,
actually,
I understand what this guy's talking about.
It actually makes sense.
And so what I've tried to do in my career,
same with the book is just to pitch,
uh,
my mate,
sitting next to me,
who's a smart dude,
really smart dude.
He just doesn't know anything about finance.
He just doesn't have all the,
the terms and try and explain it to him in a way that makes sense.
And I'm not going to do something dodgy to my mate.
You know,
I'm not going to give him crap information.
I'm just going to tell him what I do.
And that's something that I've tried to do in my career.
Because a lot of us aren't born with the finance cards.
We do other things.
And so to have that trusted provider,
and I think it's one of the great assets in life.
When you find someone I ultimately trust,
everything Scott Pape does.
And I think that maybe is,
you know,
your plain language and your point of difference,
isn't it?
Is that trust is there really,
uh,
really intensely.
So you,
you,
you mentioned your dad,
you're probably living what he wanted to do.
You're a father of four now,
uh,
Papey.
They're going to have a different upbringing than you had now,
given the success that you had.
How do you teach those values to them now with you,
you are a household name and you've been an extraordinary success.
I know you've just gone on a trip around Australia.
I'd love to talk to you about that.
Yeah.
How do you teach those values?
Well,
I mean,
you know,
part of,
I live on a farm in Romsey,
um,
and,
you know,
really,
um,
like we've seen it in,
in working together,
you know,
a couple of years ago,
I really made the decision to pull back on a lot of the media that I do.
Um,
you know,
in the,
in the newspapers,
I take the holidays,
school holidays off.
Um,
and,
you know,
for me,
the kids growing up on a big farm,
there's always something to do.
There's always,
it's cheap that,
um,
that need to be looked after.
There's like,
just like a million jobs.
So for them,
you know,
they understand what I do,
but,
you know,
even,
um,
before Christmas,
they were at the agency that I work at and they were packing up food hampers for people,
for families that,
that didn't have enough food for Christmas.
So for me,
it's really important that they understand that,
you know,
too much is given,
much is expected.
And so,
yeah,
they're,
you know,
uh,
having to do,
you know,
a lot of the,
the jobs and things because they got the barefoot investor for a dad.
I gotta ask you a question.
You might find this hard to answer.
There's so many.
I want,
I want to go back to the trip around Australia and your timing in lockdown in Melbourne to get away with the family.
It was a,
it was a great story.
But is there a net worth amount that equals happiness for a family?
Can you actually give a number on that,
that you went,
if you,
if you've got beyond $3 million or $10 million or 15 million,
can you,
can you have a guess at that?
Well,
there was a,
there was a news.com,
um,
article,
that,
that looked at a survey and it said,
how much do you need to be financially well off?
And I think the figure was about 360 grand a year.
That's five times the average income of,
and so,
you know,
what I would say to that is we are completely and utterly out of whack.
You know,
we are judging our values.
When I grew up,
I was judging my values of people who lived in Oyen in the country.
Now,
our kids judge their values.
Uh,
and,
and there's a lot in life by what they see online.
Yeah.
So it's completely warped.
So for me again,
and just to tie into,
to going around Australia,
you know,
we were living basically,
we were free camping a lot of the time,
you know,
we were,
just eating,
um,
you know,
on,
on the,
on the Barbie,
um,
spending very little money.
And that was the most,
that was the best trip of our lives.
How much that's cost?
Not that much.
I mean,
I didn't have,
I,
I didn't work for four and a half months.
So there's a,
there's a,
um,
there's a cost there,
but just that idea that I don't know if I could give you a figure,
because I think it's different for a lot of people,
but I think there are a lot of people that I meet that think they need to earn more.
Yeah.
And the definition of wealth is someone who's wealthier than you.
And that can be a real trap because what really matters,
I think is the time that you spend with your family ultimately.
I mean,
you can do a lot of things in your life and make a lot of money,
but I met a lot of very wealthy people whose kids don't really,
really like them.
Yeah.
You know,
so for me,
once you have a roof over your head and you know,
you pretty much paid it off,
um,
you got a decent car,
you know,
everything else is gravy,
money's not going to make you any happier.
It's a great line,
isn't it?
From someone who spent their life in that space and you've lived it because the opportunity for you,
you know,
to,
to make,
uh,
extraordinary amounts of money have been open and,
you've made decisions along the way,
which I really admire.
Around family and around your values and about around where you live.
Um,
Steve Biddulph,
who's the legendary author of kids books.
Yeah.
And he talked about,
interestingly,
so one thing you should try and do with your family is go and take off and,
and spend some time and,
and do what you did.
Uh,
one of my great mates,
uh,
for 30 years has talked about his family trip around Australia.
Was it,
was it as good as it,
as it sounded?
It was challenging.
I'll be honest.
It was really challenging.
We got four kids,
um,
in an RV.
Um,
it was challenging,
but,
um,
it was the,
yeah,
it was the best trip I've ever had because number one,
it was COVID.
So Melbourne was basically in lockdown.
New South Wales was in lockdown and there was a lot of fear and a lot of stress.
And to be on the open road with the kids,
um,
you know,
pulling off to the side of the road,
having a little campfire,
just drinking in the amount of time that I got to spend with them.
Like literally I would have with my daughter,
who's three,
we'd have a,
a daddy daughter date,
a three day every day.
And we go for walks and I would just get on her level.
And I think there's something about getting out of your routine and actually just,
I see it as an investment,
really investing your time there.
I've never been closer to my kids.
And what was hard was we got home and we got this big house,
right?
So one went one way,
one went the other way and it's like,
oh,
we're back to normal.
But prior to that,
you know,
we're all in this little,
this little RV and we just lived with each other and it was fine.
So yeah,
it was great.
You got to share a story.
It's been a crazy time around the world,
but Australia particularly,
and you were trying to win your RV cross from Northern Territory into Western Australia.
Explain what happened to you if you,
if you don't mind.
Yeah.
So,
I mean,
we'd heard as we were driving,
so we went up from Victoria up to,
skipped over New South Wales because they were going through their really bad lockdown.
Queensland to the Northern Territory.
And the Northern Territory WA border is in the Kimberley's and it's at the middle of nowhere,
like literally out the middle of nowhere.
And we'd,
we'd heard that they were really tough in WA.
So my wife had done all the right things.
She'd got this G2G app,
which basically asked you for all your information.
We got approved.
Everything was fine.
Rolled up to the,
to the border and we were met by a Western Australian police officer and I went down the window.
It was so hot.
It was like 40 degrees.
Kids are narky.
You know,
I'm just hot.
Gave her the app and she said,
I don't,
we don't,
we don't want that.
And I said,
well,
but that's what we have to do.
And she's like,
no,
that could be,
that could be faked.
And I'm like,
but it's your app and you scan it and it goes to your computer.
And she said,
basically,
don't be smart.
Hand me your phone,
open up your,
your private bank,
your,
your bank accounts,
open up your personal photos and hand me your phone.
And I looked at Liz and my wife and went,
and she's like,
just do it.
And so she took the phone and she walked away.
And your bank accounts open,
your personal photos open.
Looking through my bank accounts,
looking through my photos.
And it was really invasive.
And what they were doing was you had to be at that time,
you had to be in Northern Territory for 14 days before you could move over to WA.
And so what they were doing was trying to look at where we'd spent our money to try and,
basically say no.
Anyway,
she came back to me with this kind of twinkle in her eye cause she had the mask on and stuff.
And she's like,
what's this photo?
And Google had,
she'd be looking at the metadata on my photos and Google had incorrectly stated that I was in WA when it was really Northern Territory.
I explained it to her and she seemed genuinely annoyed that she had to pass us through.
The other interesting thing was they,
you had to be 14 days,
right?
So there were people who said,
well,
I got to the NT on day one and they went,
ah,
that's day zero.
You have another 24 hours.
So they're sitting up,
these poor bastards are sitting on the side of the road for 24 hours.
So then that I could get through.
So it was,
it was kind of surreal,
a surreal time.
But again,
I was really,
when you got to WA,
it was like,
wow,
COVID doesn't even really exist.
Like don't worry about masks.
Everything's fine.
My friends overseas bring me in and they say,
what is going on?
And that is a crazy country that has unfolded in the last two years.
You live on this little island down there.
It was actually quite a big island.
And there's an imaginary border that you can't cross and you might have loved ones.
Or you try to tell my friends in America,
you know,
the 52,
you just can't believe that that has happened.
And people argue and say it was justified.
Probably don't want to get into that debate because it's not really what we're on about.
But you know,
there's a lot of,
of things we accepted and gave up that I was puzzled by really in the last two years.
Even the city we live in,
9pm curfews,
5k radius,
you couldn't move out from.
It was an extraordinary time.
It was.
And it was,
and you know,
again,
to be,
you know,
I felt,
never felt more wealthy because I was able to take those four and a half months off with the kids,
knowing that there's a lot of angst and stress and stuff all around us.
But to be,
to be on the open road,
and be able to spend time with,
with the kids and,
and take what is,
what was a very stressful time for a lot of people to,
to invest that in the kids was great.
But we're living in a time as well of 0% interest rates.
And there are people saying,
this is utopia opportunity to make money.
Like you've never made money before.
You think this is a disaster.
No,
I would agree.
I think it is a time to make a lot of money because what happens when you keep interest rates low,
is people like you and me,
who have assets,
who have shares get rich and those people that don't have assets get left behind.
And,
you know,
I've been really strong on this for a long time that I think we will look back on this and say,
what did we let these central banks do this for?
Like what,
whose idea was this that you could have the lowest interest rates in 5,000 years,
you know,
and be pumping money in as a consequence of COVID.
Now,
you know,
JobKeeper,
there was a,
there's a fair bit of spillage there,
but I understand that because I'm a financial counselor.
I help people who are in financial struggles.
I think that helped out a lot of people.
But,
you know,
as we sit here,
now in 2022 that they're still pumping a lot of money into the economy and interest rates are still basically zero.
I think we will look back on this in a generation and say,
why did,
you know,
we really income inequality in this country,
I think is one of the biggest issues.
That we're going to face.
If you have a young nurse and a police officer,
they can't afford to live in their community.
Or if they do,
they get saddled with debt.
That is just so high that changes things for them and puts them under financial stress.
I just think that I don't think anything good comes from it.
And I say that as a guy who's been cheering on the share market,
who thinks,
you know,
I've been loving the returns,
but you know,
at what cost?
And so,
yeah,
I just,
I look at it and think the other thing is that interest rates are starting to go up.
We have been through the average 40 year old has never seen a recession in their adult life.
And I just think that interest rates are going to start to go up.
And we,
as my hero,
Warren Buffett says,
we get to find out who's naked when the tide happens.
So the social divide,
I have to get back to you on Warren Buffett is,
as you said,
we'll talk about mentors in a moment.
I'm sure he's going to come up as people who've inspired you,
but this just creates greater divide in wealth.
And,
and we might touch on this because I know most of you get thousands and thousands of people write to you and seek financial counseling and want advice from you,
which you,
which you freely offer incredibly.
Um,
but there's a crypto comes up a lot in your world.
It comes up a lot,
Darcy.
Were you saying that you had a bit of a tickle?
You had a bit of a,
bit of a,
yeah,
look,
I am.
I,
I'm,
uh,
I'm a,
how have you gone?
Well,
you know,
probably been early enough to be okay.
Pay.
Really?
And what have you,
what have you invested in?
Well,
started with a bit of a Bitcoin.
I like in the Doge coin,
not in the Doge coin.
Okay.
Um,
and I,
and I get your world and I understand where you're going to go with this,
but,
but I also think,
you know,
part of the story for me was the US government printed a third of us dollars last year,
equivalent to all of the money that had been produced in history.
And so the idea that there is digital currency coming,
I,
someone like you will say,
which horse do you back?
And Bitcoin,
it could be back to zero at some point in time,
or Ripple who are solving the blockchain technology to,
uh,
to actually solve eventually the financial institutions are going to come on board with that technology.
So you're right.
It's,
but it's same as picking a stock,
isn't it?
And saying a stock and you say,
no,
am I,
it's not because they don't make money.
And then when you're picking a stock,
you're buying,
you're becoming a part owner in a business.
And if you're a part owner in a business and that business generates stable profits,
you get any,
have you ever invested in gold before or silver?
You wouldn't do that.
Wouldn't touch it.
No,
I mean,
I,
the only thing that,
you know,
for me,
it's,
it's a very simple,
um,
idea is that I only invest in things to make money.
Um,
so gold looks pretty,
um,
but it,
there,
there is no income.
Yeah.
And so therefore you can't really value that.
But again,
I agree with you.
Um,
I do think that it's a fascinating thing.
I just wouldn't be investing.
Oh,
well,
and tread your own path is your line.
I'm going to use it.
I think,
uh,
you do that well.
And I think,
you know,
others,
uh,
I mean,
I'm not going to debate crypto with you.
Cause I don't think it's one that I'm going to end well for,
for me,
you know,
and I'm certainly not an ambassador for it,
but it,
there's a percentage of you.
Do you ever bet?
Do you ever,
I'm not a punter.
I'm not a gamble.
You never have never had anything not for fun.
Oh,
I mean,
I haven't,
yeah,
I have in the,
in the past,
but,
but now I,
I don't.
And I just think,
um,
yeah,
for me,
it's that people say,
you know,
put 1% in,
uh,
in Bitcoin just as a hedge.
I'm like,
well,
it's just like saying,
put 1% in the pokies just in case you're in the jackpot.
Like,
but you know,
I do,
I do understand where it,
where,
where it's coming from.
I just,
and I don't really mind what people do.
I,
I don't,
I find it all really interesting.
So I want to come back to leadership because,
uh,
that was where we started.
That's what the essence of what we're talking about.
You're a humble country boy,
as you said,
from,
from onion,
but,
and,
and humble enough to not see yourself in a little bit,
but you also intelligent enough to understand that you are in a serious
leadership position because so many people look to you,
and the words that you say resonate,
they,
they move the needle in finance in a way that hasn't happened in this country
before.
So have you thought more about that now,
uh,
as,
as a leader,
you know,
and the way that you deal with that?
Yeah.
I mean,
I think one of the things,
so I went and did financial counseling because I really,
it was maybe the old man saying,
look after the battlers.
And I really wanted to see,
you know,
um,
to try and help people that,
you know,
single parents and,
and people that have,
um,
the cards of,
uh,
have been dealt wrong to them.
But one of the things that,
um,
that I came back from after doing that was,
I would help the parents,
right.
I would help them,
you know,
try and get their debts waived or,
try and get them back on,
on track.
But there would be a kid while I was meeting with parents that was sitting
there and I'm like,
I want to help that kid.
I want to make sure that that kid doesn't,
um,
fall into the same trap that the parents did.
And so for me it was like,
um,
what I really want to do and what I'm really passionate about is helping the
next generation.
And so for me,
you know,
we've had conversations about this forever,
but you know,
the idea that really you can go through 18 years of school or,
you know,
um,
12 years of school and not really learn anything about financial education.
And,
and,
you know,
it's the one test that every kid's going to be.
It's the one exam.
Every kid's going to be tested on it every day of their lives.
And yet we don't really teach it that well.
It's kind of something that some schools do and others don't.
And that to me in this day and age,
when we're talking about Bitcoin and,
and all sorts of things that are happening,
the fact that we don't do that really upset me.
And so for me,
I'm like,
if there's one thing that I can do,
given that I bought,
I've got this platform,
it's to try and make change there.
And it's an amazing story.
Your Foxtel show,
you know,
was great.
It got up and running just at the start of COVID.
And I'm sure,
there's more to come on that front.
And I love the courage.
You've really,
you know,
pushed back at the big banks who had themselves entrenched in schools,
the Commonwealth Bank Dolomites account.
My friends in advertising will say that was the greatest advertising.
Some might say the most evil.
Most lucrative.
I mean,
it's made them billions because they signed up kids straight out of school,
who then graduated to credit cards and,
you know,
but they're now gone.
And collected their data along the way and had enormous information on kids,
under the guise of here's your,
your Dolomite account.
So many,
you know,
customers would be sitting here listening to this and saying,
that was me as a kid.
We all remember it,
but you've pushed really hard.
And so we need to get the vested interest out of schools and we need to get the education back.
Can you sum it up?
What are the things that kids need to know?
What are the basics they need to know coming in and out of school?
Well,
I mean,
I think in a primary school level,
my view is that you need to understand,
it sounds really basic,
but I,
you need to understand it's fun to work.
It's good to work.
Um,
um,
it's good to spend money.
No one wants a tight ass,
you know,
it's good to spend money,
but I'm,
I'm careful about the money that I spend.
And I'm,
I'm kind of,
I understand that I'm going to be manipulated by marketers to,
to,
to want certain things,
especially on social media and influences and stuff.
Um,
uh,
it's good to invest.
That's how you get rich,
right?
So your money grows while you don't have to work.
Uh,
and it's good to give,
you know,
it's,
it's the givers in this world are the people that are the,
are the happiest.
So they are re they're,
they're behaviors,
right?
That's not tech.
That's not getting too technical,
but if you can teach a kid that it's good to get up and work,
I know 35 year olds that haven't got that lesson,
you know,
that they had,
that just hasn't computed for them.
So they're those basic lessons that you can,
if you can instill them in your kids,
right?
The thing I say is that with no one wants to raise a spoiled brat,
it just happens,
right?
And the way it happens is you give kids money for doing nothing,
And you don't have,
a focus on giving.
Yeah.
So if you,
if you get kids to,
to do some sort of giving within their community or they,
some of their money has to go to giving someone other than them and working
hard,
I think that's important.
Um,
for the high school kids,
um,
I created a program,
uh,
and,
and the,
the book barefoot families,
um,
as around this idea of the barefoot 10,
these 10 things that you can get your kids to do,
you know,
having your kids,
um,
be able to cook a delicious,
nutritious meal,
right?
Rather than getting Uber eats,
um,
having them apply for a job.
So they actually have to go and sell themselves when they're teenagers and they,
you know,
grumbly and stuff.
Um,
you know,
having them hopefully getting a bad boss that,
rides them a bit,
you know,
so that they actually have to work out,
that whole power dynamic and relationship,
um,
learning to invest,
you know,
or just these little learning lessons that you can do with your kids that while they're still under your roof,
they can,
they can make those mistakes.
But they just have that ability because what I find is I will meet 23,
24 year olds who say when they 16,
I'm not really good with maths.
I'm not a really not a good numbers person.
And so what happens is they turn 18,
they get a credit card,
they get after pay debt,
and then they wind up in my office saying,
see,
I'm,
I told you I was no good with money and I've got the credit card balance to prove it.
And so for me,
what's important is trying to get kids,
to learn that life skills before they graduate,
because as soon as they do,
they are the most heavily marketed to generation in history.
And all,
as you said,
all the financial institutions have been doing AB split tests.
They know exactly how to get you to spend their money.
Um,
and so I just think that the banks have become very good at selling money.
We need to get better at helping our kids,
um,
resist that.
I want to go back to something.
It's,
and I love your language because it makes sense and it's always clear.
And it's something that has,
uh,
resulted in so many people hanging off every word you say in this space,
because it does make sense.
But you said something earlier saying some of the rich people,
you know,
some of the unhappiest people,
and we understand financial hardship is terrible as well.
It is.
But I think very few people understand,
and you and I would have been exposed to people who inherited a lot of money from really wealthy families.
Some of the saddest people you ever meet because exactly what you said,
they've never really had to think about work and never had a meaningful job.
It's all been there for them.
And you can't have too much money,
can't you?
It's the paradox of choice.
Like I've,
I've worked with,
um,
very wealthy,
uh,
families,
um,
that have family offices and things.
And,
and,
uh,
that is something that I would never want for my children.
Um,
the idea,
you know,
it's that again,
the Warren Buffett thing of give your kids enough that they can do anything,
but not enough.
They can do nothing.
And that idea of actually saying,
you've got all the money,
you don't have to work.
It blunts your ambition.
Um,
and it's just something that I,
I wouldn't do that idea of the work ethic,
whether that is,
um,
you know,
building a business or doing something that you're passionate about to help people.
I think that's the,
that's really the essence of it.
One of the great Warren Buffett lines,
isn't it?
Who's worth over a hundred billion dollars.
Yes.
Father of three.
I think he might've paid their college fees,
maybe,
or maybe not.
Actually,
you know,
I met his son,
Peter.
Really?
And what was,
what was interesting,
I spent some time with him.
And he told me that in his thirties,
there were times where he was struggling to pay his mortgage.
But just to pause for a sec,
for those that aren't,
you know,
Warren Buffett,
the greatest investor of all time,
you know,
has been the richest or in the top five with net worth of over a hundred billion dollars.
You met one of the three sons.
He would be the richest person on earth,
but he's given away most of his money and he's still one of the,
you know,
in the top three,
top five.
So his son inherited almost,
and at times was struggling to pay his mortgage.
Yeah,
he was,
um,
I sat down and spent some time with him.
He was a really quietly spoken,
humble guy.
He said that he didn't know that his father was,
um,
you know,
one of the world's richest men while he was at school.
Um,
his father was just a finance nerd.
They went to the local,
um,
the local Omaha schools.
Um,
and his dad still lives in that same house that he bought.
Still,
still lives there.
Incredible.
Um,
and he said that,
um,
yeah,
he,
he remembers being in his,
I think his twenties or thirties,
he had a mortgage and he was struggling.
Um,
and,
uh,
but you know,
he,
he again learned from his father that,
uh,
he was passionate.
His father was passionate about investing.
He's passionate about music.
He won an Emmy,
I believe for a screenplay that he wrote with,
uh,
dances with wolves.
So he's very passionate about what he's doing.
So you meet this guy and go,
yeah,
you may not have got the money,
but you've got something.
Equally as important,
which is a passion for what you do.
And I've got this view.
You can't manufacture passion in your kids.
Well,
yeah,
no,
no.
Yeah.
That was the thing that,
you know,
you,
I meet you and I would meet a lot of,
uh,
wealthy people,
a lot of successful people who talk a big game.
And,
and when you're really rich,
you have the ability to market yourself,
um,
to create a facade.
But my view was the one thing that you can't do.
You can't fake is your kids.
You can't fake them.
And so when I met him,
I'm like,
you are just a cool dude and you've been raised the right way.
So,
and to me,
that is like the ultimate success,
you know,
that's right.
If your kids are happy and the ultimate regret,
if they're not correct,
you didn't invest the time.
So I'll get to the questions I asked at the end,
but one estate planning for Scotty Pope,
then what do you leave your full kids?
Well,
I mean,
I've been,
I've always been very,
um,
uh,
open with this.
So,
um,
I,
my kids aren't going to get anything.
Um,
I mean,
they'll pay for,
I'll pay for their education,
which is like a huge thing and absolutely huge thing.
Um,
but I don't think you'll leave them nothing.
No,
I mean,
I'll,
so I'll leave them,
um,
the,
the farm.
They'll all have the farm that we currently live on.
And I'm,
you know,
again,
I'm a,
I'm a longterm dude.
So what you'll find me doing a lot is I'm planning a lot of chestnut trees and oak trees.
These things.
Don't really,
they say you,
you know,
you plant a nut trees for your grandkids.
So they're there.
They will get this amazing farm that they'll all use,
but they're not getting to farm chestnuts and to farm.
No,
no,
just because they'll be beautiful in,
in 50 years time.
Yeah.
Not,
not as a commercial aspect of that.
I mean,
farmers markets and all that sort of stuff.
But you know,
the idea that my kids,
um,
will,
always,
they will grow up in that home or on that farm.
Um,
and it will always be theirs and it will be a place where hopefully as the kids get older and they have their own families that draws them back.
Yeah.
You know,
we've got a big,
you know,
damn,
um,
we've,
we've got,
you know,
it's,
it's a,
it's a kid's paradise,
you know?
So for the grandkids,
hopefully it'll be a place where they all go back to.
Um,
but as far as leaving them a large amount of money to not do anything with or to bank on or to fight with,
I mean,
I have sat in rooms with.
Household name families that have hundreds of millions of dollars and that has scared me when you look at the way that wealth has played out.
Yeah.
It's been really debilitating for most of those people that I've met and I would not want that for my kids.
It's a powerful thing to say.
Yeah.
Family breakdown that comes with often that amount of money is,
uh,
is extraordinary.
So,
um,
yeah,
I will just say that I'm going to,
my wife and I are going to,
we don't have huge amounts of money,
but,
um,
you know,
on a global scale,
we are very wealthy as,
as you are,
as anyone listening to this is,
but,
you know,
my thing is I've sort of turned,
I'm very much into my not for profit stuff.
So we'll create a foundation at some point and the kids will end up managing that.
What a great story and a great story of leadership,
Poby.
I love it.
And I think,
um,
you know,
true to yourself,
treading your own path,
you couldn't leave your values any more than,
than anyone I think I've ever met.
So we ask these questions,
Poby,
because we're into leadership and I say,
we,
uh,
passion we've got,
and I've spoken to you about,
what we're doing in education ourselves with the leader.
And we're seeing these common traits of leaders as I see you and self leadership.
What,
what,
what does that mean to you when I talk about self leadership?
Well,
I mean,
yeah,
again,
I don't really see myself as a leader.
Um,
one of the things I've tried to do is every column for nearly 19 years,
the,
I don't know why I started doing this from the very first column.
It was that my sign off is true drone path.
And to me,
that has been what I,
I try and kind of my North star in that,
um,
I wrote a book,
I did very well.
Um,
and then I looked at it and thought,
what am I really interested in?
I'm interested in people who've,
who,
who struggle,
or I'm interested in making sure that their kids and all kids learn this stuff.
And I'm interested in my kids and spending more time with them and less time,
you know,
running around promoting myself.
So I guess for me,
it is the whole treasure and path ethos and not buying into more money.
It is better because I've,
I've learned enough through meeting other people who have become very,
very wealthy,
that you can't buy back the time that you can spend with your family and your
kids.
Yeah.
Beautiful message,
mate,
that you've articulated so well,
positively impacting others in your environment.
I suppose a lot of your work has been a solo.
You haven't,
um,
necessarily worked in big teams.
Is that fair to say or not?
Yeah,
no,
that is fair to say.
I mean,
one of the things that I've,
um,
that I've tried to do,
is,
um,
with Barefoot Investor,
it became a huge and is a huge community.
Um,
and so what I try and do each week in the newspaper and on my email,
it goes to like half a million people is to,
I try and tell people stories.
Um,
and there's a lot of family violence of people that have escaped in the middle
of the night and who have been able to rebuild themselves or,
um,
about little kids that have started a lemonade stand,
or stories of people that have been able to rise up,
um,
through either Barefoot Investor or just because of them drawing a line in the sand and saying,
this is what I want to do.
So for me,
um,
I sort of see the community that I've built,
even though it's really big now,
as highlighting those stories and,
and,
and celebrating them.
Not sure you could positively impact people more than that.
And if you,
if you think Scotty Pope doesn't live his values,
he had a subscription,
uh,
business,
every business wants a subscription model and you shut it down and he said,
I mean,
it's extraordinary and I'm going to do this all for free.
I'm going to get my newsletter out there and that's the way.
So if you want to get weekly communication,
how do we get that with Scotty Pope?
Uh,
well,
uh,
either in the,
in the newspapers,
the Herald Sun or,
um,
go to barefootinvestor.com and you'll get the,
the email.
We see leaders who are really clear on creating and sharing their vision and your
vision now to improve the financial,
uh,
literacy and education of kids in schools and,
and to help those that need it,
the most is an extraordinary vision.
Do you give a lot of thought to how you share that and create it?
Yeah,
it's,
um,
it has been dust.
It's been really interesting because again,
as you said,
I haven't really had a big team around me.
It's just sort of been me.
Um,
and I had this idea of the money movement where I was going to try and,
um,
get financial education in schools.
It actually worked out to be really tough.
Um,
because I mean,
I think one barrier is you've got to teach the teachers.
Who maybe didn't learn about this in school and,
and,
and are already overrun and may have their own financial issues.
Um,
and it became,
it is a really hard endeavor and I think where I'm at at the moment with it is
that I'm writing another book as we speak sort of barefoot investor for kids
where I'm talking directly to the kid.
Yeah.
Um,
and sort of that's where I've really had the most success is in writing
something super engaging.
It's really challenging because I'm writing to kids.
It's with very limited attention spans,
but yeah,
that's,
that's sort of the next project is to try and write a book,
um,
that,
that really hits sort of primary school kids,
um,
and that they get and that they learn from doing.
So that's the next thing.
And it's a fair point.
You may have,
we've found in the way that we've been doing teachers themselves are under
enormous amount of stress more than I understood.
And a lot of their work from what we're here is social work.
They're getting kids to come to school that really trying to get them healthy enough to be able to participate.
The start is a huge challenge.
And then we're laying all these things on one of our passions is about teaching mindfulness and meditation to teachers.
And we're,
we're launching a social venture in that space,
but we actually worked at,
we really got to sort of look after teachers first and their wellbeing so they can pass that wellbeing onto the kids.
And it's a,
it is an issue in Australia.
I feel like we value our teachers anywhere near pay them enough or,
or revere them enough.
Other parts of the world do it a lot better than we do.
Yeah.
And,
and that was one of the things that I,
when I,
when I first went in,
it was like,
we need to teach the teachers.
Like if you are going in,
maybe when we were younger,
it was like,
Oh,
be the,
be a teacher.
You get all the holidays and all the rest of it.
I would not,
I couldn't hack being a teacher.
Like it is really hard.
They don't get paid enough.
As you said,
there's a lot of social work and stuff going on.
There's a lot of regulatory stuff now.
Um,
and,
uh,
one of the things that I found was,
um,
if I could spend time with young teachers,
just starting out a lot of them,
their first four or five years,
they're on contract.
So they really don't have the job security.
They don't get paid a lot of money.
They're,
you know,
in the deep end,
they're dealing with parents,
they're dealing with all sorts of things.
And,
you know,
in the current environment,
if you are in Melbourne or any of the capital cities,
the chances of you buying a home is next to nothing on that wage,
you know?
So it's,
it's incredibly tough for them.
So for me,
again,
part of the thing I learned was that,
yes,
I want to get to the kids,
but being able to talk to those teachers,
and help them,
because if they get excited about it,
they are the advocates and the gatekeepers for the kids like that.
You know,
what I've found is the politicians,
the education boards and stuff,
I can say things,
but if you get a teacher that cares about your kids or their kids,
that's what you need.
Well,
thinking of a time I was away with my wife,
we weren't married at this time,
and her brother was living in Switzerland and he had a Swiss girlfriend,
two highly intelligent people.
She's one of the smartest people.
And,
uh,
and my,
my brother-in-law is as well.
And,
and she just got news the day we landed there,
I'd only just met her,
and she could do anything she wanted at university.
And the word came through that she was accepted to be a teacher and the family celebration.
Wow.
And the benefits and the,
the kudos that was given that she was,
uh,
you know,
respected enough to be accepted as a teacher.
I thought,
God,
you,
you put that overlay on Australia.
We don't have anywhere near,
probably the most important thing is who's in front of our kids.
Pepe,
we talk to leaders who really have curiosity as a common trait,
and we see,
they approach their learning and development through this sort of curious mindset.
Does that resonate with you and your own development?
Oh,
absolutely.
I mean,
I think part of the reason,
you know,
I wrote the book and I've been doing barefoot,
but one of the things that was sort of foreign to me a little bit was,
you know,
I,
I have a very privileged upbringing.
You know,
I had,
I had two parents that loved me.
Um,
I lived in a stable home in,
in the country,
and I had really no context of family,
violence and mental health issues and all the things that,
that affect a large,
um,
proportion of Australians.
So for me,
the idea of actually going back to TAFE and kind of learning to be a social worker and actually doing,
I,
I've worked in prisons.
Um,
I,
I've worked in juvenile,
uh,
juvenile,
detention centers,
um,
and just to learn,
other people's,
um,
paths.
And,
and really how those choices have led them to where they are and to help them try and communicate,
get them on a level that can help lift them out of that and their kids.
That to me is what is really fascinating.
That's what I find really,
really interesting and being able to communicate in a way that actually meets them.
Whereas a lot of the finance stuff is sort of aimed at people who are already wealthy or people who are already going to sit and,
you know,
input things into a spreadsheet.
I want to try and get people that have never thought that,
or who have,
you know,
one of my proudest stories is like,
help the kid get a part-time job.
His parents had never had a job.
His grandparents had never had a job.
Now that one thing.
Yeah.
He then,
so then we picked out a savings account for him.
We've got a super fund,
you know,
that is the start of something for him.
So yeah,
that the curiosity is,
is what I,
that's,
that's what drives me.
Yeah.
It's brilliant,
uh,
way to describe it.
And I,
and I think when you're talking paper,
I think someone like me,
financial acumen is a blind spot.
And,
and,
you know,
I've been fortunate in my life to do things.
I love that have come from a small business family though.
Yeah,
correct.
But,
but just that understanding day to day,
isn't a natural thing,
not something I enjoy.
Yeah.
It's a chore.
And then you're looking then for trusted support to collaborate with.
And so when you hear someone like you,
that that just is in your DNA and what you do every day,
but for people to try and find that,
or to pass that onto their kids is such a powerful thing.
And,
you know,
we're talking about communication and,
and you've got,
you've got this very clear way.
You mentioned before we worked together doing radio in Melbourne for 10 years.
I almost need to apologize because we would hijack your segment and somehow try and turn it from finance into talking about,
you know,
strippers somehow.
I mentioned Nick Malloy there.
I'm blaming Malloy more than my good self,
but I did play along.
You did.
So,
but you've had a very clear way of getting a message.
Was that something that you had naturally,
or have you worked really hard on how you communicate with clarity?
Yeah.
I mean,
I,
I do,
I work hard.
It's hard to do it.
It was something that I think you play to your strengths and I've always had this.
I think that was something that I learned early on,
but yeah,
it's a lot of hard work.
You know,
the book was,
um,
was,
it was hard work.
Every line,
I sweated over every line.
Really?
Yeah.
And,
you know,
the funny thing was,
um,
after I wrote it,
I would have people that would come to me and go,
I saw what you did there.
I'm going to write that.
I'm going to write a book like that.
That's easy.
I'm like,
sure.
Go,
go and do it.
I'm not,
I'm not saying that I'm,
I'm,
you know,
I'm gifted or anything,
but I'm just like,
you should try and do it because it's actually a lot harder than you think.
Like trying to make things really simple.
It's a really,
it can be really difficult to try and get some support with that.
Or did you just work it out?
You just trial and error.
Something about writing for,
you know,
the Herald Sun,
back in the early days before blogs and all that,
cause it was probably pre that.
There's nothing like getting brutal feedback.
From tabloid newspaper readers that toughens you up.
So I've been called everything under the sun and,
and stuff.
And,
and that sort of,
I learned,
it was a really great training ground for me to learn how to craft my message.
I find it hard to think a news limited executive would be brutal.
Pay me.
That's a,
that's a stretch,
uh,
um,
tongue firmly in cheek clearly on that one.
A collaboration is a,
is a trait.
We're saying modern leaders are great collaborators and they seek out,
uh,
collaboration regularly.
And,
you know,
I mentioned a lot of your stuff has been you,
the barefoot.
How do you approach collaboration?
Well,
um,
with great difficulty,
actually,
I'll be really honest with you.
I mean,
I,
again,
I'm a solo machine.
I've been able to basically,
um,
uh,
sit at my farm and do what I do.
Um,
and so therefore it was a real fish out of water thing of actually having to
engage every state education minister and the various education bodies.
Um,
and it was,
it was in some instances quite frustrating,
because I'm like,
I'm no good at most things.
I am literally hopeless at most things.
But one thing I kind of do know is how to communicate financial education.
I had all these people telling me like ripping my stuff to shreds.
And,
um,
it was quite difficult,
to try and collaborate with not just one education,
uh,
department,
but you know,
all around the country.
So your solution to that is now bypass them,
the middleman go direct to kids.
And is that,
is that what you,
you say the best path forward for you to,
to,
to get your message?
Yeah.
I mean,
what I,
what I said to them was,
um,
I don't need this to be about my name.
I'm happy.
I don't,
I don't need to be paid.
I just think this is really important.
And I gave them my materials.
Some of them were a little risky,
um,
because for the teenagers,
I had Nazeem Hussein,
the comedian and I,
we had lots of fun,
but I think you have to push the boundaries in order to,
to sort of engage teenagers.
So I've given them all,
all my content.
Um,
I've said that I'll help in any way that I can because I'm really passionate about it.
But just having that time for reflection,
I'm like,
you know,
you got to play to your strengths.
And I think for me,
my strength is actually writing or communicating in a way that someone opens a book and,
and I'm talking directly to you.
And if I can hold your attention,
which is a really hard thing to do,
and I don't always succeed,
but if I can do that,
I can really help lots of kids.
Well,
we'll watch and read with interest the new book.
It'll be brilliant as always with what you do.
And we started talking about the cards you've got and you know yours as well as anyone else.
We've been asking these two questions of all the great leaders and I see you as a great leader in your space.
Who has been the greatest leader in your life?
I think the greatest leader in my life.
Um,
well,
I would say my parents,
obviously,
my dad sat me down and,
and,
and paid me,
in one BHP share,
which blew my mind as a little kid,
you know,
in and,
just having as I get older and deal with different people,
having two parents that loved each other and that loved me is such a huge step up in life.
Um,
because not everyone gets it.
Warren Buffett,
uh,
the,
who we've just spoken about,
um,
I've met a couple of times.
How much time have you had with,
uh,
not,
not enough.
Yeah,
The time is,
is very valuable.
But you,
you're a regular pilgrim to,
uh,
Omaha.
We're not going through pandemics.
Um,
and do you,
do you enjoy that as much as for you?
That that's your grand final,
isn't it?
My grand final mate.
You love it,
don't you?
Yeah.
And,
and,
and is the wisdom still,
is he's over 90 now?
Yeah,
he's,
what it is about him is that he has lived a very authentic life.
You know,
he,
um,
he has become the richest person on earth.
He still lives in the same house that he,
that,
um,
that he bought when he was a young person,
loves his kids.
And it has given all the money away.
And I think that is something,
you know,
I,
you don't learn anything from,
from me now.
I don't learn anything,
but it's that re it's like going to church,
just reinforces that this is a guy who is the real deal.
Money has not tainted him.
Um,
and he's made all this money,
he's given it all away.
And,
and so that legacy I think is really interesting.
And then the other one would be my wife who has supported me through deciding to go back to TAFE to be a mature age student and,
you know,
drinking beer on a Thursday in the college,
uh,
lawns when she's at home with the kids and stuff and supporting me with all the stuff that I've done.
And,
and yeah,
it's been good.
So we are into the world of collaboration.
I love that you are honest enough to say that it's hard for you and that's what,
you know,
tread your own path authentically yourself.
But if you could collaborate with anyone,
is it in anything?
And it mightn't be finance.
It might be you've wanted to write a song with someone or is there any collaboration that,
that would jump out at you?
Well,
I mean,
I think that the thing that I'm always interested in is,
um,
you know,
the space that I'm in.
And one of the things that I would like to do that I haven't done yet,
but I,
but I'm interested in is I do believe that small business is the backbone of our country.
And the one area that I haven't really focused on is that I think that there's not enough training and help for our small businesses.
Anyone can set up a small business and you give it a go.
And we all know that the majority of them fail and you learn by trial and error.
But I do think,
that there could be something that you could do that I would like to collaborate with,
with somebody who has been very successful,
that you could create something for small businesses.
What I do is,
um,
uh,
as part of my financial counseling is,
um,
there's a small business debt helpline.
A lot of small businesses get in trouble and I see the pain that that inflicts on not only the business owners,
but the family and the kids.
So there's something there I'd like to collaborate there to try and help,
um,
help those small businesses.
Because they do it bloody tough and they work incredibly hard.
You and I are both from small business families.
You know how hard it is.
That's something that I would like to do.
But, you know,
I'm just going to focus on the kids.
Well, I'd love to see that happen,
uh,
Pepe,
because it's,
uh,
it is close to my heart as well.
Grew up in the hospitality industry,
still,
uh,
actively,
involved in the hospitality industry.
Hasn't made a lot of fun in Melbourne,
you'd imagine,
for the last couple of years.
And,
and,
and you're right.
It's one of those things.
There's no playbook really hard to get,
um,
other people sharing their IP,
hoping there's going to be a better sharing economy in that space.
And there's a,
there's a lot,
we inflict a,
it's sort of like finance.
We,
we suppose,
presuppose a lot of knowledge.
So,
you know,
that you got these kids coming out,
they're 18,
they're,
they've got a,
supposed to know what health insurance is and super and all this stuff.
And with employees,
we expect them,
you've got to have all these regulations,
the pay grades,
all these things.
And you're trying to make a buck and you've got all these other regulations.
Something that actually mentors and helps those people.
I know there are programs,
programs around,
but I would just like to try and work with someone who really has a deep knowledge and skill in that.
And that's not me,
but to try and create something that can give value because I think small business owners are the,
are the backbone of our community.
What a great idea.
And I'm sure knowing you,
that is only a matter of time before you make a big impact in that space.
And as I said,
off the top,
I see your leadership is extraordinary in what you're doing and what you continue to do to change the literacy and education for,
for so many people in this part of the world.
It's a,
it's a great story.
Always enjoyed catching up with you.
And I really appreciate your time,
Scotty.
Thanks a lot.
Thanks,
Darcy.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me,
Luke Darcy,
produced by Matt Dwyer with audio production by Darcy Thompson.
Start your leadership journey.
I encourage you to go to elitacollective.com.
Take our Empowering Leaders Indicator Tool and understand the impact you have on your environment.
Join us at Elida to learn,
lead,
and collaborate.