A Listener Production.
G'day, it's Luke Darcy.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership both on and off the field
has been a lifelong passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective
and have had the privilege of working with thousands of leaders
in education, sport, industry and the arts
that have helped shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership
where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
Shane Dillier is one of the most recognisable faces
in the Australian food and hospitality scene.
He is best known as the director of the Dillier Group
which encompasses restaurants Maha, Maha East, Maha Bar, Biggie Smalls
and Middle Ground.
The hospitality industry in Melbourne, Shane's hometown,
faced an unprecedented level of distress through the COVID period,
essentially being locked down without meaningful trade
for the best part of two years.
Shane's creative response in founding food delivery marketplace Provador
is a game changer for the industry.
Bringing top tier restaurants to doorsteps across the country.
Provador's ready to finish meals are shaping the future
of how the hospitality industry will thrive into the future.
Shane has an extensive media presence as a television presenter,
print contributor, author, charity and brand ambassador.
It's always great to catch up with you, Shane.
Thanks for joining me, mate.
I like that intro.
I've got to put some time into it, mate, because you are a bit of a machine.
It's an expanding empire and it's a great story of success.
When you reflect back on it, what do you think?
I think I'm pretty lucky.
I think about even sitting here with you, mate.
I remember going on the footy and watching you take big grabs and kick goals
and bust your way through packs.
To be able to sit here and share a desk with you and have a relationship
and a friendship is really important.
I didn't think I'd achieve half the things I've achieved.
I didn't really have many goals, to be honest.
I just kept pushing through every day and things have eventuated.
You're a boy from the western suburbs of Melbourne and, as I said,
it's an incredible success.
When I think of you, Shane, the word grit comes to mind.
I think I'd back you to find a way, no matter what was thrown at you.
Can you describe where does that resilience and determination come from?
I think it comes from family.
I think it comes from the environment that you brought up in.
I think it comes from the stories of the people that you respect and trust.
My dad, I think, is a big inspiration in that.
He came to Australia, turned 18 on the boat coming over from Malta
to settle in a new country and then bring the rest of his family,
his brothers and sisters.
His parents over.
Then he was a very resourceful person, but he was always about giving.
He never worried about what he had or what he needed.
It was always about giving for everybody else.
I feel that weight on my shoulders.
I feel that everybody's given a lot.
My grandparents have given a lot.
My dad's given a lot for me to have some great opportunities.
I can't just go in half-assed.
If I'm going to go in, I have to go in and I have to make it work
because a lot of people sacrifice a lot to give me chances.
I want to make the most.
They're great migrant stories, aren't they?
I love that you've got that consciousness around the fact that those before you
did it really hard for you to have the life and your kids now.
You grew up in a pretty tough environment.
I've spoken to you about this before, Shane.
Some of your mates were getting into some pretty serious trouble
and there was a few sliding door moments in your life.
What was the influence, when you look back,
that got you onto the path that you are?
I think knowing that I had a community of people
that cared for me, around me.
I think that a lot of my other friends maybe didn't have that,
didn't have that support, didn't know that there was a line.
I pushed the line a few times and a couple of times
I stepped over the line, but I knew that if I did cross that line,
that I was impacting more than just me.
I was letting people down and it kept me on the straight and narrows.
I think a tough upbringing is important.
I think that people that whine on about it and say,
oh, it was tough for me, I'm like, yeah, well,
it's tough for a lot of people in a lot of different ways.
What do you learn from it?
How do you build resilience and then how do you carry that fuel,
whether it's negative energy or if it's positivity
or if it's just grit, as you say,
how do you actually use what you've learned through that adversity
to push forward?
I've tried to harness that.
Yeah, I'm big on that circle of influence in your life, Shane.
As you said, there was some opportunities to go one way
and a few of your mates did and ended up in some challenging situations,
but you always felt like,
the people close to you, you didn't want to let them down.
So even in that teenage space where you're taking a few risks,
you always had that sense that it was bigger than just you?
Yeah, I thought I was going to embarrass people.
I knew, look, my grandfather was the sergeant of the local police force
back home.
He was a man of pride and respect and I didn't want to bring any shame
onto our family's name.
I think that everybody sacrificed a lot to build that
and I didn't want to be that guy.
I didn't want to have to go home and look at my parents in the eye
and know that I've let them down.
And a few times I've had to face that and I still probably do.
But at the end of the day, that's a line I wasn't really willing to cross.
I think they'd be pretty proud of where life's ended up.
You find your way into the hospitality business.
It's a brutal industry.
A lot of people try, a lot of people fail.
What's been the secret to your success?
I think in the beginning, it was just, I didn't set huge goals for myself.
I just wanted to get in.
Do the best I could in that day.
I didn't have goals of like, as a young chef of owning a restaurant
or becoming the best in the world.
I wanted to compete every day amongst the team that I was in,
whether it was my guys working on the bench next to me or the opposition
that was thrown in front of me.
I just wanted to compete that day and win that day.
And then the next day I looked at the next day, like I didn't really aim too far ahead.
But once I started to get into a bigger market and started to have an opportunity
to open a restaurant, I went in not pretending to know anything.
Like I really did, I was a sponge and I still today try to think I'm a sponge.
And even though now I've got a few more scars and I know a little bit more,
I don't think to know it all, you know, and I'm always ready to learn.
So I think that's kind of been something I've, one of the reasons I've succeeded.
But also I don't stay within my own industry.
I think the problem within the hospitality industry and other industries
is it just become really insular.
You just stay in your industry and the people that are around you
facing the same issues become your community.
And that's a small pond attitude, you know, I want to live in the sea.
So I try to surround myself with people outside of my industry
to gain more knowledge, to learn what they've learned,
to see what they're facing, because then it can change my perception
and the way I approach business.
You're a great connector.
And I want to come back to that because, you know, when you catch up with you,
it's such an interesting experience because there's people from all walks of life
and you collect people, it seems, from sport, from, you know, industry.
And I mentioned about some of the brands that you've been an ambassador for.
I'll come back to that.
Because I think it's fascinating.
That's a real key, I think, to how you really do set yourself apart from others.
I look at you now, you start off in the kitchen.
You said you didn't have these huge goals, but it's turned up into a big empire.
You manage lots of people now.
How would you describe yourself as a leader?
I think I'm different in my two businesses.
You know, we talk a thing about the restaurant business.
I'm very connected to that business and I bleed for hospitality and I understand it.
And so in that type of business, I suppose, as a leader, I'm all in.
You know, I'm really all in.
I try not to lead.
In the earlier days, maybe through being a bit naive, I led through with a bit of intimidation.
And that comes from a low self-esteem, I think.
And that's become a negative now because I think that persona still lingers within, you know,
within, you know, the hospitality business.
I don't piss off Shane, you're going to get, well, that's not the way to lead.
You know, I try to use a lot more empathy now.
Try to deal with our people.
As people, as individuals, try to connect with them and just show some interest.
And I think that if you show interest in people, you show that you're actually invested in their
success and genuinely invested in their success, not just because you want something out of it,
people will go to war for you.
In my other business, in Provador, I'm learning how to be a leader in that business.
And I struggle with it every day.
And it's probably one of the things that really I'm battling with because it's a different type
of business.
It's different people.
I mean, you know, Darce, I mean, hospitality is about passion,
the high of being involved.
I'm involved in hospitality and it's addictive.
But in the different business like Provador, where I'm still unbelievably engaged in,
I'm dealing with a whole different demographic of people who don't respond in the same way
and it's challenging me.
So I'm still trying to work that one out.
Yeah, I'm interested in going there as well.
So many places to jump off with you, as you said, from the hospitality sector,
effectively to a food tech startup business, which is, we'll talk about that in a moment.
But I wanted to pick up on something you said because I love how open you are.
And any time I've been around you, that has been the case.
But talking about you as a young leader and maybe using some intimidation,
that's been a bit of the history of hospitality, hasn't it?
I mean, this shows Gordon Ramsay's got this reputation, whether that's true or not,
around the kitchen space being a pretty brutal environment where, you know,
young apprentices have been, you know, sort of targeted a little bit.
Hasn't always been a great part of the hospitality.
Do you reckon that was part of what you saw as a young chef coming through and maybe,
you know, learning that was what you felt?
You passed on and it's taken you a while to maybe find a different way?
Yeah, to be honest, it's probably one of the things that attracted me to the industry
because I knew that market.
Like, I know that that's the ring.
And I grew up in the ring.
You know, like we grew up in, like you said, in hard times in the Western suburbs.
And, you know, you either could battle with your intellect, which wasn't really well respected,
or you could battle with what you had.
And I was always a pretty bulky guy and I looked mean.
I wasn't really tough.
But I just, I knew how to fight in that ring.
And so when I saw that hospitality was competitive,
competitive and quite masculine, and, you know, your skills will take you a long way,
but you also had to have a persona of aggression to push your way through at those times.
It really did attract me to them.
But it's not, there's no longevity in that.
And it doesn't actually get you where you want to be.
You just end up an old grumpy man that nobody respects and nobody loves and nobody actually
cares about.
And it's a quick road to the end.
So I had to leave that behind.
But I love your evolution, Shane, because some people can never change that.
It's hard to shift paradigms as a person when that's all you've known.
In fact, most people can never do that.
So for you to understand that, you know, and we talk about this a lot, Shane.
In fact, this whole podcast is based on exactly that, this new generation of leadership, which
is more self-reflective and more collaborative.
And you've found that shift.
Was there someone that really inspired you?
Or was it just that you came to that realization yourself?
You know, I think there's a lot of people.
There's a lot of people that helped me get through that.
But I think the biggest thing that I learned was just through some personal issues that
I had.
You know, from the outside, you can look at everything and go, wow, he's got a great life.
It looks good.
Instagram looks good.
Nice cars, pretty wife.
Kids are good.
You know, good football team.
But the reality is that everyone goes through a ton of battles in the dark, you know, and
personal issues, self-esteem issues, relationship issues.
And that's the real core of someone.
It's not what's on the outside.
It's what's happening.
It's what's happening at home, behind the scenes.
Forget about the leadership and the business stuff.
If you can't fix yourself, you're never going to be a good leader because you're just, you're
talking shit, you know, because you don't actually know how to fix yourself.
How are you going to fix somebody else?
And essentially, as a leader, you're fixing people and you're helping them, right?
So I was lucky.
First, I suppose I was lucky the person that helped me the most was my wife.
Because if I was her, I probably would have walked away a long time ago.
And she didn't.
You know, she stuck beside me, invested in our family, invested in our values.
And really, probably the biggest thing that I learned from her was that she was a great
The easier thing for her would have been to say, you're too hard, I'm out.
So her and I resolving our issues, resolving, you know, helping me get strong again.
And then me knowing, again, falling in that position that I suppose I felt with my father
and everybody else, I can't let this person down now.
You know, I actually have to, she invested so much in me, I have to get better.
So I changed my mentality.
I started training better.
I started eating better, surrounding myself with more positive people, shed a couple of
the bit of the dead weight that was holding me back.
And being honest.
And being honest enough to reflect and seek help.
You know, I spoke to psychologists.
I spoke to someone to help me sort of meditate and try to center myself and understand why
are you being like this?
You know, and not just flipping the script and becoming Gandhi overnight.
But just, you know, because you don't have to be, you know, suddenly I'm, you know, drinking
my coffee out of Keep Cups and, you know, driving an electric car.
But just understanding why do you do this stuff?
And if you want to decide to keep going that track, fine.
Own it.
There's nothing wrong with that.
That's who you want to be.
Be it.
But I don't want to be that person.
I love how brutally honest you are, mate.
And, you know, your beautiful wife, Maha.
Maha is the name of your wife and your businesses.
And obviously, you know, your dedication to understand.
And let's be honest, you draw back the curtain for everyone.
Below it, we've all got the same challenges.
Everyone faces them.
Some people just can never get a handle on it or really understand themselves well enough
to say, actually, I do want to live a better life than that.
And, you know, for you to go and find that way is a great credit.
It must be, as you said, everyone's a work in progress.
But it feels like you've come a long way down that path.
Yeah.
And I'm not good, you know, but I'm trying.
And I actually understand when I fall off and when I mess up, why,
and then how to resolve it.
And I think that you can't just sweep it under the carpet, address things,
call it out, fix it, move on.
You know, but my strength has always been my community, mate.
Like, I've got great friends that I can call on, whether it's I need advice,
you know, I need help.
And someone to pull me in line.
Or if it's just someone to just to blow some steam off with.
I know that I've got really good people from a good cross-section who are invested in me
and my happiness.
So that's it.
I want to go back to and head towards Provador and what you've created, mate,
because it is one of the great success stories in recent times.
But firstly, can I just go back to you're running your business successfully.
Suddenly COVID hits.
Melbourne holds the record for the longest lockdown city in the world by the end of that period.
How stressful did that get when you couldn't,
when you couldn't literally open the doors?
Yeah.
The stress, the stress wasn't because I couldn't open the doors.
The stress was from the pressure that I put on myself to find a way.
And I felt immense pressure, you know, immense pressure to find a way out of this.
Like it wasn't, oh my God, my life's turned to shit.
I never really came to that point or maybe briefly in the beginning.
But as soon as I'm pushed past that, I went, well, you can't just dwell on it.
You have to find a way.
That pressure was huge.
And it almost broke me.
I remember.
I remember when just before we launched Provador, um, I mean like hours before we launched
Provador, cause it was so many moving parts to get it ready on time.
I mean, we took a six month launch strategy and compressed into like six weeks.
Um, like it almost broke me.
Like I, the day we went live, I remember sitting in our little private room at the front of
Maha and it was like an out of body experience.
I remember sitting myself, sitting down in that room with the small team that we had
and we were, they were all sort of celebrating that it's actually live.
And I can just remember myself standing up, walking up.
I should have probably, shouldn't have probably drove home.
But the next thing I remember was walking up, waking up in bed at home, like a day later.
And Maha was saying to me that I walked inside, opened the door and like collapsed on the
stairs.
I just, it like broke me, but I had to push myself that hard to know that I could, cause
it was a big deal, mate.
This was something that could actually destroy everything I built.
Um, so I had to find a way, but it's, um, it was pretty scary.
I mentioned grit and that's a great example.
I mean, a lot of people went to online who'd never thought about doing food delivery in
the past in restaurants.
Yeah.
But for you to take it to that next level and essentially create a platform for, for
all these iconic businesses and, and that's what Provador is in the middle of the most
stressful time is such a unique, you know, and not only that, it was the, the execution
and the speed with which you did it with.
And then I suppose Shane, you know, in the hospitality sector, you've got enormous amounts
of friends, but everyone's competitive as well.
So you had to get the trust of these iconic restaurants to say, I can handle this part
for you.
How was that?
And, and what were those conversations like?
Um, surprisingly that part was, wasn't the hardest part, um, friendship is important.
And obviously in a, in a normal world, it would be increasingly hard to get restaurants
to come on and do that.
And we're finding that now, I mean, Provador is still, you know, it's a, still a successful
business and, and growing, just invested a lot of money, raise some capital.
Um, and we're, and we're finding that those conversations harder now when you're moving
to new markets.
We're in Sydney, we're in Brisbane, we're going to launch in Perth, Perth and Adelaide.
By the end of the year, um, but I think that I was really genuine.
I just approached the conversations.
I spoke to like Andrew McConnell, you know, you know, he has restaurants, he's a great
Melbourne entity, um, identity.
Um, and I just spoke to him via zoom and said, Andy, I'll, I will be the custodian of your
brand.
Like I'm putting my brands on this thing.
I will look after your brand.
I won't put it in any danger.
You have to trust me.
Yeah.
You know, and, and I do that with like most of our guys, like I'll sit down and I'm honest
with that.
I do not want to jeopardize I'm, I'm their brand.
I'm firmly invested in the industry and I don't look at this as a, as a short stop,
you know, and I did in the beginning, I thought this is just something to help us get us through.
But the more I time I spent in Provido, I realized that this is the way for us to break
out of this prison that we have and, and, and, and finally find a way to make this into a
real business.
So this is what I love about this Shane, because you know, you, you walk into Maha, such a
brilliant restaurant, iconic restaurant, but there's millions of dollars worth of fit out
that goes into dragging people into the city.
It's so easy in Melbourne to come in and have that experience.
And so there's always been this mindset, I can't just give the Maha experience to people
who take away at home or, you know, you think of the flower drum who were using Provido
or these incredible restaurants that have got these great brands.
So the, the shift is to sort of say, Hey, only, you know, a hundred people can, you
know, however many it is in Maha at one period of time, but at the same time we can fill
that up several times over.
Is that the shift in mentality that Provido is providing for the hospitality industry?
Yeah.
That's the fundamental revenue part, which is I think important.
And that's the thing that everybody looks at the end of the day, how much money does
it make me?
But how do you measure how much money it makes you?
I said, it's about new eyeballs and hospitality is really hard to market a hospitality business.
There's so many, so many great restaurants, only so many customers, how do you get their
attention?
Um, so really now what Provido has developed to is where we're a strategic marketing partner
for our restaurants.
Um, it's how do we not just drive sales online?
I want to make sure we can drive bums on seats.
Yeah.
We want to get new customers into those restaurants, you know, 70% of customers that come to the
platform experience a restaurant for the first time through the platform.
So that's a lot of customers.
So the proposition I go to the restaurants is great, look, we can provide you with revenue
and there'll be some revenue and there'll be probably significant revenue, but look
at how many new customers across the state we're going to put you in front of, you know,
and we can share that data with you and we can help drive revenue into your restaurants
and we can grow your market, um, and evolve your, your, your market.
So it's not just, you know, your traditional restaurant customer you have.
Look at how many new demographics we can bring you.
And that's the exciting bit.
Yeah.
And maybe the next generation as well, where you maybe wouldn't have been able to take
the whole family into Maha or one of those restaurants, but now you can have a little
sample of that at home and then, and then the ambition to go, I'll go back to the leadership
part because as you said, the hospitality world is you and you know how to connect in
that space.
Now you're building an online tech platform.
You're into a different, different sphere.
And you said it's a, it's a work in progress as a leader in that space.
What, what have been some of the challenges?
Uh, fighting.
Fighting my place.
Um, I'm, I don't know at all, you know, I don't know it all in hospitality.
I definitely don't know it all in e-commerce.
Um, I've employed, well, I've employed a partner with a great CEO, um, who's comes from eBay.
He's got a ton of experience, 10 years plus in there.
And we're building a new team, a new structure that I don't understand.
I know in a restaurant with a front of house, back of house, we've got the head office team.
I know how to manage that.
Um, but this is a totally new team.
You know, we've got developers, we've got marketers, all flavors of marketers, you
know, flavors, you know, people that I didn't even know, retention marketer, frequency marketers,
acquisition marketers, conversion marketers, and, and, and, and, and people with different
experiences, um, different way of doing business, a different, a different upbringing, um, culturally
different, you know, values different and, and, and, and, and spread across the country,
um, where we're doing, you know, two days in the office, if maybe two days in the office,
uh, most of your meetings are done online.
How do you build that connectivity, that trust, that loyalty?
Um, how do you even gauge who, who's doing what, when, you know, it's always in the restaurant,
you can see who's chopping the veg and like, I don't know who's working and what they're
actually getting done, but also I suppose not running, not being the main guy, you know,
like, um, at, at, in the restaurants, even though we've got leaders in every department,
um, I'm still the main guy, um, in Provador, yeah, I'm still the main guy, but really Tim's
the CEO and he runs it.
So working out how we work together, um, and also trying to balance out my time, mate,
because both businesses are really, really busy.
Yeah.
I want to stay true to my other values and, and make sure I'm looking after myself and
looking after the family and then doing the media stuff as well.
So, um, I'm learning and I haven't got it right and, and it's, it's the thing I'm struggling
with the most is how do I get more out of myself to contribute more into that business
because it needs me the most.
With the, with the sense of values and family balance as well, which everyone is striving,
uh, Shane, and you, you have an incredible capacity, but I love that your values are
right out in front.
We can come back to the connection, uh, piece because I said, I mean, you are a, a, a, a,
a great connector of people.
I've had the privilege of occasionally dropping into your world and it's a lot of fun.
There's an annual dinner that you hold, uh, that is great fun and you look around the
room and there's, there's a young boxer that you've supported.
There's the head of Mercedes who's a great friend.
You bring people together.
I mean, that in itself is a great story.
You're, you're ambassador for the Bulldogs, a great supporter of the club that we both,
both love, but you're also, you're a great connector that brought Mercedes Benz to the
Western Bulldogs.
No one would have thought that was a partner.
Yeah.
A partnership that was even possible, but that, that to me is, is Shane Delia and, and
is that always been the way as a, as a kid, were you a connector of people or is that
something that you've developed?
No, definitely wasn't as a kid.
Um, very, I had a very small, I hate the word network cause it's so transactional, like
a very small community of people as a kid.
And I thought everybody in Australia was Maltese until I left foreign school.
You know, I lived in Deer Park.
But it's, um, it really didn't, to be honest, I didn't really understand the power of a
community.
And the value, not, and I think sometimes when you talk about power, it's about the,
you know, the, the value to yourself and how much you can get out of it.
There's so much more.
I, I didn't realize the value of a good community until probably about three or four years into
owning my own business when I started to see different people in my venue.
Um, I mean, the first time I went past, the first time I went out to Kew was when we bought
a restaurant out there.
I didn't even know that side of town was, was, was around like, so it's, um, it, it
is, it is a, it is something that I really value.
And it's my strength.
Um, but I, as a kid, I wasn't, I wasn't great at it.
I've had, I've had to develop it.
Um, and now I've got great friends and I take, you know, I don't look, I don't seek them
out based on their title or based on who they are.
We're just drawn to each other.
Um, I've been asked a ton of times to join networking communities and, um, we won't single
any one of them out, but I don't, I don't know.
I haven't, I haven't needed to, I've, I've finally just met people along the way and
it just happens.
And.
Yeah, it's a great gift.
I mean, last time I, I did catch up with you at Maha.
Um.
I don't know what experience that was with another interesting group of people, but we're
talking about part of what we've through the leadership space is actually connecting different
people, but on the same values you're talking about, not about how do we grow our commerce
to that might be a byproduct of what happens of it, but how do you get diverse people together
just because you share the same values you want to learn, you want to grow and you want
to learn.
And that's, that's part of what we've been doing through our work at Alita.
And I love the fact that that's something that's been created just by youth organically
in it.
I said, based on values, not just, can I get the next most influential person in my life?
Because being around you, that's, that's just not the case.
Yeah.
I think that I've, I've tried to invest in people for people as that, who they are and
what they need.
And sometimes they just need somebody that's just down to earth that's not going to try
to get something out of them.
Yeah.
Like I don't try to get things out of people.
Don't be wrong.
If I need something, I'll ask.
Yeah.
A hundred percent I'll ask.
And I expect the same in return.
And I, and I'll always deliver.
Like if someone asks me for something, I don't deliver expecting to receive something back
later.
I'll just deliver.
I can get them where they need to be.
Um, and generally that's enough.
You know, like if it's, if, if you ever, if, if, if, if their favor ever comes back, great.
If it doesn't and you achieved your goal, amazing.
That's all I want to do.
And I'm lucky to be surrounded by people who've got the same values and you know, you can
have transactional relationships too, then it's not a bad thing.
Um, but once you've brought people into Enid Sanctum, I feel that they're there for life
and um, true testament of that was the speed we got Provador together.
I mean, that was our Bulldogs community, you know, Jason White and Sam Salter, the guys
that are marketplacer.
They turned that around for me in a second and I met those guys through the club.
They, uh, they created bike exchange initially, another brilliant, brilliant story and, and
that, that was the community and they were the ones that had the tech skills to support
you with Provador.
Yeah.
And I met them through the club.
Um, Chris Nolan, you know, sits on our border.
You know, you know, he helped me with all of our marketing and, and our procurement
of media.
Um, you know, Peter Gordon and Lev Shevky, you know, from Gordon's and, and Cornwall's
that, you know, those guys turned around in a second and helped me.
Yeah.
And it really was our, our Bulldogs community.
And I'm not just doing that to say, you know, Bulldogs to me, it was a community that just
went, I'm putting down everything, this bloke needs us right now, let's just jump in and
do it.
And that's, that, that's, that's your strength.
Yeah.
It's not about money in the bank or maybe name out in lights.
It's what people will lay down to get you where you need to be and everybody was there
for me.
Yeah.
And I love that, you know, authentically, you, you as a person have always been there
for other, but without expecting that in return, I think it's a great lesson out of this conversation
with you is that when that happens naturally, you don't expect something, but it comes back.
Yeah.
Always with that, with more interest.
Now before, there's a range of leadership questions I want to ask you Shane, but I can't
help, uh, sitting alongside somebody who loves food all their life and, and you can see it
when you're around you, what, what's been, what have been some of the great food experiences
of your life or some of the great meals or where, where, where do you go?
It's probably a hard question to ask.
Oh, no, not really.
Um, there's been tons and I, and I like simple stuff, mate.
Like I, I could, I could talk about the top end and I could talk about chicken nuggets,
mate.
Cause I like, I'm, I'm a big fan of chicken nuggets.
Yeah.
Um, but look, I've, I've, oh, geez, um, uh, a little, a little restaurant, um, a little
restaurant in, in Paris.
Um, and I know it sounds really extravagant, but we'll start from the top end, a two Michelin
star restaurant, um, that a friend of mine told me about, never heard much about it.
My, my heart and I were in there at the year of the world cup.
So 2018, I think, um, we'd left my family in Malta with my mom and dad.
So it was just her and I, no kids.
And we belted in and we sat in this restaurant.
And I was blown away just with the bread that came out and then, of course, you were
in for a good feed here.
Um, and that, that was like a, a really, really, really good experience.
I mean, um, so what makes that is, what's the secret is people walk into a restaurant
and there is a feel about it that, that changes your whole experience.
I think in that scenario, you walk in and I, I, I'm, I'm a lover of hospitality.
All right.
So, and, and I, I can't help it, but I just automatically go into this like terminator
scanning mode of a restaurant.
When I walk in, I can see every floor, everything and it's okay.
I can accept them, but I'm just trying to get a lay of the land, but I walked into this
venue and I've just gone like, I've scanned the rooms, got, oh shit, we're in, we're,
this is serious.
You know, the way that the waiter walked in the, the attitude of the, you know, of their,
you know, their persona was amazing.
The way they were dressed, the, the way they connected, you know, the kitchen was like
in unisync and no noise.
No, it was just getting done.
You're like, wow.
You look at the architecture, you look at the roof, you look at the table, you sit down
there.
It just feels right.
The table feels right.
The cutlery weight is right.
It's just like, you're going, wow, this is really good.
You look around the rest of the dining room and you can see the ways the waiters are interacting
with tables.
It's just everything had been thought through and it was an art.
And then when you get the plate and it looks like a work of art and it tastes exceptional,
you're like, oh my God, you're blown away.
Like this is just, the price people always thought, oh, but it would have been expensive.
It gives a shit.
Like, honestly, like it is, who cares?
This is a once in a lifetime opportunity.
And it doesn't even matter what it costs.
And I was blown away.
But then I've had great meals, like in a shelled out building in Tripoli, sitting in an alley
eating hummus on a milk crate.
It's the same experience, exactly the same experience.
You look around, the environment, really authentic, thousands of years.
You look around and you immerse yourself in the environment.
You think about the happiness, the pain, the sorrow that's happened just here.
The people that have come through, the love that's in that.
One dish and how many stories have connected through that one dish.
And you just immerse yourself in that environment.
And that's the value.
You know, like that meal cost a dollar.
The other one cost a couple grand.
Yeah.
But the value was the same.
The value is totally the same.
You're taking me back to as a son of a Republican and growing up in the pub space and going out with my dad always.
It's exactly you.
It's the side scandal.
Is the music up too loud?
Is the waiter paying attention?
The guy who poured the beer, how much did he waste?
I don't know.
You know, that's straight to the bottom, straight to the bottom line.
I love hearing those experiences.
You just hear passion come through when you talk about food.
Hey, Shane, we're talking to leaders from a vast array of backgrounds in different areas,
but we're identifying what we think are these common traits around leadership.
And it comes through in your language big time.
Self-leadership, I've heard you talk about it already,
but we see that as almost being the first quality of a leader.
What does that mean to you?
For me,
it means doing the most I can out of each day.
I think to be a leader who sits there and says,
oh, you know, not I want more, but we need to do more.
We need to do this.
We need to do that.
And then you sit on your ass and you're just getting through the day.
That's not a leader.
I don't think you have to belt yourself and push yourself against the wall.
You have to achieve something.
But I know every night when I put my head on my bed,
like hand on my heart,
I know that I might not be the best,
might not got the most done,
but I have given my all that day.
And if I wasn't enough,
it's because I wasn't good enough.
And that's fine.
It wasn't because I didn't try hard enough.
I gave my all.
Whether it's conversations I've had,
you know,
the way I engage with someone
or the opportunity I've given to somebody else
or the time that I've taken out
just to walk around the city and look up,
it's the most I could do.
And I'm content with that.
So being a leader who leads by example.
Yeah.
And you spoke about,
you know,
your change in diet,
your access to improving yourself,
was a person as well,
really resonated for me.
Starting,
I think you used the term at the start of this podcast,
you know,
if I can't lead myself,
then how am I going to lead a big team,
which you clearly do with great skill.
We see leaders are really conscious now,
Shane,
of how they positively impact others in the environment.
You've mentioned this already,
you know,
from you maybe being an intimidating leader
to really being a more caring and empathetic leader.
Have you consciously thought about that
and the impact you have on others?
Yeah.
Yeah,
I definitely have.
And it's hard
because your body language says a lot,
right?
And especially when people,
people perceive you being a certain way.
So say you're in a meeting
and something's not going the way you want it to go.
And people,
whether they want,
they start like,
their eyes start shifting towards you
to see how you're reacting.
Now,
if you react in a way that they expect,
the whole room,
your energy changes,
you know,
and to sort of hold yourself back
and try to not have that face that they want you to see,
that's even worse.
You have to honestly let go,
like,
and not be that
and find a new way to connect.
And I think something that I've struggled with in the past
in confronting situations
where people are getting a reaction that they expect
is that I don't listen.
You know,
I'll just react.
I'll just talk.
And then,
just to say to listen more
and to listen more.
And you may have something you want to say,
but actually listen to what's actually happening.
Take it in,
digest it.
And you don't even have to give your opinion then and there.
I think that the best thing you can do is take time,
you know,
suck it in.
Yeah,
look,
and admit when you don't have the answer.
And sometimes buy yourself some time,
come back and address it later.
Yeah.
It actually has more impact than just losing your shit.
Or,
talking for the sake of talking.
Yeah.
To look like you've got an answer.
Yeah,
it's a great lesson.
We see leaders have got a really interesting process
around how they create and share their vision.
The vision for Provador is an enormous,
as I described it in the opener,
is a game changer for the industry.
And it has the potential and it has already done that.
I mean,
how have you gone about creating and sharing the vision
in the world that you create?
With Provador,
is he talking about me specifically?
Yeah,
just your world and how you go.
I mean,
Maha's a vision that you've created.
is there a system that you've put behind that?
Or is it just you and-
I think that I'm quite reactive.
So if I've got something I'm passionate about,
I have to talk about it.
You know,
because I can't just internalize it and start to work it out
and come with a finished vision of where we're going.
I'm not that guy.
I have to talk about it.
I have to talk about it a lot.
Talk about it a lot with different people.
And during that time,
I'm sitting there,
I'm digesting it,
I'm processing it,
I'm building it.
And it'll change a million times,
right?
Whether it's the Provador story or a restaurant story,
or,
you know,
I spoke to you before about,
we're about to open a little cocktail lounge.
Like,
I've been talking about that for a while
and trying to understand it.
And once I visualize it,
then I need to get everyone on the journey with me.
Yeah.
I'm like,
all right,
this is where I think we should go.
Present it.
Are we in?
Let people pick at it.
Because then you can learn some stuff.
Make sure everyone's aligned.
And let's go together.
Because then when we're all on the same boat,
we're going,
we're going.
And that's exciting.
Yeah.
You know,
it's really exciting.
We've done a great job of explaining that,
your process,
you know,
exactly how it is.
And I suppose Provador,
then I'm interested to delve into that a little bit more
because everyone through that period of time,
the restaurant industry was facing extreme stress.
But then I'm assuming there's some risk attached.
You've got to build some software.
You've got to employ some people.
I mean,
how about,
how about that one?
Was that,
as you said,
I suppose you collapsed afterwards,
but did you take your,
you know,
more time than you thought to get that,
to go on?
It's getting harder now.
Now we're in the fight.
All right.
Like,
so Provador in the beginning,
there was no other real choice.
We had,
we,
we did the best we could and we built a,
a marketplace that worked,
not the best marketplace to work,
but it worked.
And,
but now it,
you know,
the market's equalizing a little bit.
People have got choice again.
They can go in restaurant,
then go out and getting the attention of our restaurant partners is,
is,
is a challenge because you go back to what you know,
right?
You go back to what you know,
you do your traditional thing.
You can,
you can use a heap of analogies,
right?
If you kick the ball wrong forever,
you kick the ball wrong,
unless you actually straightened up,
you always go back to sort of what you know.
It takes a long time to correct that.
And restaurants going back to what they know and not,
not believing in the future.
Now that we're back open and people forget,
don't they?
Yeah.
But we're taking a lot of risk.
Like,
you know,
we've,
like I said,
we've raised a heap of money.
We're building new tech.
We've employed a bucket load of people,
building a brand,
spending on ads.
Because I really do believe,
not in myself and,
and,
and this is going to make me a buck.
Cause believe me,
it's not making a buck at the moment.
But this is the way of the future for restaurants.
I don't want to move restaurants online.
No.
Restaurants need to be,
we need to be there gritty,
you know,
in the restaurant,
building relationships,
creating experiences.
But this is definitely the way for us to have,
you know,
two markets to connect to more people.
And there's a ton of risk and a,
and a ton of work in connecting with our restaurant partners.
And,
and that's,
that's the big challenge at the moment.
It's,
it's show,
opening the,
some get it straight away.
They're like,
yeah,
we see this.
It's definitely not even about the revenue.
It's about,
this is the future.
Because,
you know,
think about my kids,
your kids,
they live on their phone now.
Yeah.
They consume on their phone.
They,
they get their information.
They buy,
they live,
they communicate through their phone.
Yeah.
The person in the future is going to buy your restaurant through their phone.
So,
you know.
If you're not there,
then you're going to miss out on that generation of,
have to be there.
Yeah.
It makes,
it makes sense.
We,
we see leaders,
Shane,
curiosity is a common word that comes up.
Just these days.
And often they approach their learning and their improvement through the lens of curiosity.
Does,
does that resonate with you?
Yeah,
it does.
And it's probably one of my,
my,
my flaws.
I don't feel like,
I feel like better myself in so many verticals,
right?
Like,
like you said,
you know,
personally,
professionally,
mentally,
physically,
where I don't grow myself enough is,
is,
is probably knowledge.
And,
and,
and I suppose learned knowledge as opposed to just from like,
you know,
experience-based knowledge,
ton of experience,
right?
I'll chuck myself,
I'll chuck myself in situations and I've always learned well like that.
Yeah.
Put myself in a situation,
learn from that experience and then that's my learning.
But there's a ton of learning out there through podcasts,
through reading,
seminars,
courses,
and I don't invest myself in those enough.
And I know why I've got ADHD.
I've had it my whole life and I've been treated for it and I've,
the whole lot.
But it's a thing.
I can say,
yeah,
I've got it and I acknowledge it.
It doesn't mean it goes away.
Yeah.
I find it really hard to learn in that environment.
I've always learned really well in,
getting my hands dirty.
But just because it's there,
I shouldn't just dismiss it.
I do need to better myself in that area.
So I am extremely curious.
And I think I could be a much better leader and a lot more successful if I
applied myself a little bit more and actually did the hard things.
And the hard things for me are go learn some stuff.
It's fascinating because the first part of that is actually understanding
yourself well enough,
which most people don't get to there and then identifying that.
And as you've done all your life,
you then find a way to make that happen.
So I wouldn't back against you,
in that space or any other spot.
I was thinking as you were talking,
and one of the things is being less involved in the hospitality industry,
but growing up,
we lived upstairs in pubs and venues and it's not the same passion for me
that it clearly is for you,
but my family have been involved.
I didn't think there was a great sharing economy where everyone was so busy
doing their own world,
trying to survive that,
you know,
the lessons that you've got from a lot,
are they shared enough?
Have you gone to other great restauranteurs and hospitality experts?
Have you found that you're,
you've learned through that lens or is that not happen?
Um,
you know,
yes,
I think there is a restaurant tours do create their own little communities
within the industry and share knowledge.
Um,
and I have learned from those things and I do dip my toe in
that every now and then,
because I think it's nice to have a finger on the pulse and
understand what other people are going through.
But I think the issues that are,
they're not unique to hospitality,
you know,
the issues are issues across every business.
And I've always had a re I've never been a,
like I love sport,
but I've never been lucky enough to play as team sport my whole life,
not even in school.
Never.
The connection I've got through sport is through people like yourself and the
clubs.
But I see the faces we fight that the issues we face in
hospitality and sporting clubs,
very similar.
You know,
we go into battle every day,
you know,
in an AFL,
they play a game once a week.
We play a game twice or twice a day.
Yeah.
Um,
but very,
very similar.
It's about team.
It's about building people.
Um,
the same thing as leadership succession planning,
ins outs the executive,
we've got it all.
Yeah.
Um,
and I tried to learn from my community rather than just from my internal
hospitality community.
Um,
but I'm always,
and I like to listen to the struggles that my other people are having
because I learned,
I learned a ton.
And that's what we love is that,
you know,
exactly what we're doing.
Hopefully this podcast is,
is that it's,
it's,
it's about different people from vast variety of backgrounds that are
coming together,
but there are these shared traits that come through and you're picking them
up,
uh,
listening to Shane right now and he's incredible,
um,
life story so far.
We're communicating with clarity.
I mean,
you're a natural communicator.
You present incredibly well,
but have you thought really about your communication and how you go about
it?
Yeah,
it could be better.
Um,
I think it could be better.
and again,
it comes down to,
uh,
um,
education.
I think as well,
you know,
my vocabulary could be better.
I think that,
you know,
you can,
you can use the skills you have and the tools you have.
And we have English as a language master that to be able to connect
better to people,
not to,
not to elevate yourself.
And put yourself in an elitist position where people don't want to
connect with you.
I think you,
but you need to have more strings to your bow.
Um,
and,
and I need to grow,
grow myself,
grow,
grow that part of my communication.
But I think also learning how to actually be in a room with someone
and look them in the eye and use the tools you have,
you know,
you,
I'm a,
I'm a wog.
I can't help it.
I use my hands too much,
but,
but I think,
you know,
smiling and,
and connecting and,
and,
you know,
the,
the aura that you present,
um,
and,
and that,
that,
that you push onto people means a lot.
I think communication is,
is really important.
And,
and I like to think that when I'm speaking to someone,
I'm,
I'm connecting with them.
Um,
if I'm investing in them and I care for them,
then I'll show that,
you know,
whether it's,
whether it's happiness,
whether it's anger,
whether it's,
you know,
sadness,
whatever.
Um,
I think you need to really leave an impression on someone.
So,
um,
but it could always be a bit better.
I hope you don't mind sharing this story.
Um,
we were talking just before we started recording and I was saying,
um,
my 15 year old,
my third eldest,
uh,
working as a glassy,
in one of our venues,
uh,
Melbourne public at the moment and teenage boys,
you know,
they're not full of words as a rule,
uh,
but seeing him outside of the family,
having learned to smile to customers,
having learned,
and he's practicing his three plate carry Shane and he's,
he's out,
you know,
pubs are interesting spaces.
You know,
people are looking at him.
How old are you?
How come you're here?
He's having to communicate in ways.
And you were saying the same,
you've got your young daughter now on the floor at Maha,
and it's been a positive experience for her as well.
Unbelievable.
And,
and like,
we all love our kids.
That's right.
I mean,
that's at the end of the day,
that that's your core drive.
You have to look after your kids and give them the tools they need to
succeed.
You know,
and,
and I felt I'd been given that,
um,
as,
as a child.
Um,
my daughter,
I mean,
like you said that,
you know,
we look about the hospitality industry cup of beating.
What about all these students?
You know,
in all like my daughter's last full year of school was grade five,
um,
grade six in year seven,
she was in lockdown.
So now she's in year eight.
She went from a Catholic primary school into a private secondary school,
went through puberty in between,
um,
lost all her mates.
Hasn't had any time to,
I suppose,
sign off from grade six and then get inducted into year seven.
And her self-esteem went to shit.
Yeah.
You know,
like,
you know,
didn't know how to communicate.
Everything's on an iPad,
felt really introverted,
you know,
didn't want to go outside,
didn't want to do anything.
And my wife and I were really concerned,
you know,
like,
cause she's such a smart,
beautiful person.
You can't start like that.
You know,
like you need to actually,
you have some confidence.
So I just said,
do you need to get into like coming to the restaurant?
And she's like,
what do you mean?
I'm like,
you need to get into the restaurant.
You need to,
you need to,
you need to be around other people.
You need to see how adults engage and see how young people engage.
You need to feel that energy in a room and that power when there's people around you.
And,
and you're either going to thrive from it,
but you,
or not,
but you're going to learn.
Um,
and she's jumped in and just made,
I hate it.
Cause she's a natural at hospitality.
And I'm sorry,
I don't want her to be in hospitality.
she's got,
she's got it.
And I'm like,
she's like,
dad,
maybe I could just do this.
I'm like,
no chance.
You're going to school.
It's in the DNA,
mate,
isn't it?
And it's brilliant,
That,
that shared passion.
And I,
I can feel the pride in,
in,
in your conversation.
And also it's an important story to tell.
I mean,
people around the country,
maybe not understanding as you explained it for kids that missed two years,
effectively,
there's a whole heap of challenges out there.
And,
and maybe things like getting a job and the way it's unfolded for your daughter.
And my,
my third eldest is,
is a brilliant story.
We,
we,
we see leaders are really passionate about how they collaborate.
You,
you don't create profitable without some serious collaboration.
You don't create Maha and your food empire,
that collaboration.
How do you value collaboration and how have you gone about it?
Uh,
yeah,
more so now.
Um,
and it's hard cause you get burnt too,
right?
I mean,
not everything's going to be rosy.
And I think that's,
that's a,
that's a key part about valuing good collaboration,
you know,
getting burnt in,
in,
in relationships that don't work out.
Yeah.
It doesn't have to be a negative experience.
I mean,
you can learn a lot from that and it doesn't have to be resentment that you
learn,
but you learn the value of a good partnership.
Um,
but good partnerships are built through trust and,
and,
and just being transparent,
you know,
collaboration can be really good,
but if you know exactly what you're getting,
yeah,
what you sign up for is what you're going to get fine.
Um,
but collaboration is important cause you can only do so much on your own,
whether it's your team and the people that you employ.
Um,
if you look at them as employees and I hate it when people say I work for,
no,
it works for me.
Everyone works with me.
Now we work together to get something done and we have to make sure that we're,
we're totally aligned and where we want to achieve or it's an external party
that we're bringing in or it's a partner,
you know,
someone that we're actually physically partnering with and financially
partnering with to achieve a goal.
We all have to be on the same page.
Um,
we have to be invested and we have to make sure that we're very transparent
about where we want to be.
Um,
because if we're saying we want to end up in a spot where we're going to sell
for X,
let's do that.
But if one person doesn't actually really,
believe that it's never going to work.
So it's,
it's,
you have to be transparent.
Well,
it's a great point to make a shame because you can talk about collaboration,
but it is important to talk about the other side of it.
and,
and I've certainly,
I think you're not trying if you're not going to come across,
uh,
relationships that don't work in partnership and in collaboration.
Someone in this podcast,
and I can't think of who it was.
This is what great partnerships look like.
You've got to have shared vision without that,
you know,
chance shared values and then complimentary capabilities.
You don't have to be able to do the same thing to get in fact,
it's better.
If you,
you don't,
you bring different skillset,
but if you don't cross the first two,
it's never going to work.
And does that make sense to you?
Is it?
I think it's exactly what I was saying.
I think,
you know,
um,
I think something else as well in a,
in a partnership and partnership sometimes,
uh,
sometimes can be slave and master.
Um,
just be careful of that,
you know,
cause if I've been in negotiations with partners before where you really need
them,
right.
And you're in a partnership because you need the other person.
They need their skills.
Cause if you had those skills,
you probably wouldn't be in partnership and,
and they may,
they may overflex or,
um,
their position in those times when you need them,
that's toxic.
Um,
because all you're doing in that position is actually showing your true card
and your true hand and that you don't actually give a shit about this
partnership.
It's transactional.
Um,
and especially you've been led to believe that it's not transactional.
It's a partnership.
Um,
once that trust has been broken,
um,
it's never going to work.
Um,
because there's always going to be that little bit of doubt,
um,
sometimes resentment,
and the trust is broken.
I mean,
trust is really important.
It doesn't have to be in any type of partnership.
It doesn't have to be respect.
Trust and respect are two very different things.
Um,
I think that if you trust that they're going to do the right thing by it,
get it done.
Great life lesson,
uh,
in that one,
no doubt that Shane,
for me,
we've been asking all the inspirational leaders,
which you firmly fit in that category.
These two final questions,
who has been the greatest leader in your life?
Ooh.
Uh,
wow.
Um,
the greatest,
I mean,
I,
uh,
I always,
and I,
I don't know what other people say.
I don't really care to be honest.
I always look back at,
at my father.
Um,
I think that,
um,
you know,
he's not a born leader.
You know,
he's not a leader of men.
He doesn't surround himself with a lot of people.
Wouldn't profess to having hundreds of friends,
you know,
not the most vocal person in a room.
Um,
but he just does what it needs to get done.
You know,
he,
he does what he needs to do.
He's selfless.
Um,
he's honorable and vulnerable,
you know,
and I think that they're really,
they're really key characteristics.
Um,
and I also have seen his four flaws and he admits them.
And I've seen his evolution,
you know,
from being that,
young,
hardworking father who may be insecure and,
um,
carrying his own demons,
just pushing through and trying to get it done and burying his head in the sand and sticking to what he knows.
So now seeing a guy who's,
you know,
older,
wiser,
um,
less armed,
more,
more respected to himself,
probably carrying less baggage,
um,
and probably a better person now than he's ever been,
and more vulnerable.
And I think that's vulnerable leadership.
So important,
um,
being able to admit when things aren't right and,
and,
and say it openly.
Um,
I think having those leaders around you is something that's really valuable.
Yeah.
What a brilliant answer.
And,
you know,
the people that have been lucky enough to have a great parental influence,
they often go right there because,
and it's not for everyone because we realize that's pretty special and it's obviously been a massive part of,
of your life.
Um,
I love that that generation now,
as you're saying vulnerable has been sort of the,
the,
the catchphrase for leadership in the last four or five years.
But for that generation,
that wasn't an option at all.
So for him,
as you said,
to evolve into that space now is,
is pretty special,
isn't it?
Yeah,
no,
it is.
It is a lot.
It is real.
But I think to be honest,
it's something that he probably always longed for.
Um,
and,
but,
you know,
it wasn't,
you can't,
we couldn't say that,
you know,
big men don't cry,
and,
um,
I think for him,
even understanding that he could be that as a man,
as a leader,
as a father,
um,
was something that wasn't even on,
on,
on the cards.
Um,
so yeah,
I think it's,
it's,
it's a big credit to him.
And it's redefining leadership too,
Shane.
We,
we're really passionate.
You don't need a title.
You don't have to have had a massive business.
You don't have to have had 50 people in your team.
The impact that he's had on you is incredible leadership.
And you don't need a title is,
is what we're passionate about.
We love the idea of collaboration,
Shane.
If,
if you could collaborate,
collaborate with anyone in the world on anything,
any part of your life,
uh,
what,
who would it be?
And if it,
is there someone that springs to mind?
Uh,
um,
oh,
maybe with you,
Dars.
I'm always,
always like pubs.
Mate,
I'd love to do that,
mate.
That would be a,
yeah.
I'm not sure what I bring to the table though,
Shane,
but,
uh,
oh,
you,
you got a few inches on me.
Oh,
look,
I,
I don't know,
mate.
I'm not the,
um,
I,
I really,
and,
and this is another flaw,
I'm not tuned in to a lot of things.
Um,
I don't,
I'm not a,
a fanboy.
Like,
I don't look up to a lot of people.
Yeah.
Um,
I,
I really value the people I've surrounded myself with,
but there's no one that I'll look,
like,
I don't even know what's happening in my,
you know,
globally,
I,
I haven't got time,
you know,
I look at my own world.
Um,
so I don't look at,
you know,
like what's happening with,
um,
the Musk guy,
Elon Musk and all these guys.
The Musk guy.
Yeah,
like,
I don't know.
I,
I think I've got a great opportunity to sit down
and talk with people like yourself and like Ed
and,
um,
you know,
Bart and Dave Elliott and all these guys and,
all my friends,
you know,
like I've got so many great friends that we can talk
to and they're the guys that I want to collaborate
with and they're the guys we do collaborate with,
you know,
so I'm,
I'm lucky.
Shane has just mentioned a few names that people
who,
you know,
in his humble way,
but he's talking about Ed McGuire who,
you know,
he's had a long relationship.
Bart Campbell's a great leader in our space.
David Elliott is the,
the,
the CEO host plus.
So Shane's just quietly,
uh,
as connected to anyone,
but in that same humble way,
they're not transactional relationships,
uh,
Shane,
you,
you give and don't expect in return.
I think,
you know,
I've loved this,
this medium cause I've been able to,
you know,
know you for a long period of time,
but I feel like I get your essence even more.
Uh,
it's an incredible success story,
um,
and open and you're,
you're full of owning your own mistakes,
mate,
which we all need to do and learn more from.
So thanks,
mate.
I really appreciate you taking the time today.
No,
it's been good.
Good to see you mate.
Empowering leaders was presented by me,
Luke Darcy,
produced by Matt Dwyer with audio production by Darcy Thompson.
Start your leadership journey.
I encourage you to go to a leader collective.com.
Take our empowering leaders indicator tool and understand the impact you have on your environment.
Join us at a leader to learn,
lead and collaborate.