Well I think the search for the truth is always the most important piece of the jigsaw and too
often you have your facts and I have mine and we're not prepared to debate in a Socratic way.
People confuse opinions with facts and of course we're all entitled to our own opinions
but we should at least be able to agree on the facts and fake news is the real problem.
This week's guest on the Empowering Leaders podcast is Sir Rod Eddington. From the humble
beginnings of growing up in country Western Australia to being one of the most respected
business leaders in the world. Sir Rod talks about the four basic questions he asks of everyone
to understand a business, build connection with people and listening before implementing anything.
Just trying to build up a mental picture of how people saw British Airways,
what they believed the challenges were, what do you think's broken and how would you fix it?
Sir Rod also talks about his lifelong friendship and connection to Rupert Murdoch
and his unique understanding of media having spent a couple of decades
on the Global News Limited board.
Rupert's always been passionate about getting to the bottom of stuff,
the facts, what are the facts and to be relentlessly curious to find new ways of doing things
and not to be a prisoner of the past. That takes some doing. You can't spend too much
time looking in the rear vision mirror Luke. It's people like Sir Rod Eddington who inspire
the work we do at Alita. Check out our Alita Connect program where we bring together leaders
from around the globe. We'd love to have a discovery call with you. Head to our website
and book a call today.
Big thanks as always to Jason Nicholas and his team from Temper Bedding.
Great leaders understand the importance of sleep. Temper is a mattress like no other.
NASA approved. Invest in Temper Bed today. It'll change your life.
Sir Rod Eddington AO is a highly distinguished Australian businessman and community leader.
Sir Rod was the Managing Director of Cathay Pacific, Chair of Ansett Australia,
Deputy Chair of News Limited and Chief Executive of British Airways before
retiring from executive duties. He holds first class honours degree in engineering,
a Master of Engineering and a PhD in the Department of Engineering Science at the
University of Oxford where he also played first class cricket for Oxford University Cricket Club.
In 1974 Sir Rod was the Rhodes Scholar from Western Australia. Sir Rod has received a
British Knighthood in 2005 for services to the aviation industry, was appointed the Officer
of the Order of Australia in 2012 for distinguished service to business and commerce through roles
with a range of national and international economic trade,
infrastructure development and transport organisations and was awarded the Grand
Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun by the Japanese government in 2015 for his contribution
to strengthening the economic relations between Australia and Japan. Sir Rod, it's an incredible
life of success. At 74 years of age, I'm reading your history back to you. What's the thing that
gives you the most pride? That I'm still going, Luke. That I get up in the morning and I really
look forward to that. That I get up in the morning and I really look forward to that. That I get up in the morning and I really look forward to that. That I get up in the morning and I really look forward to that.
That I get up in the morning and I really look forward to that. That's the thing that gives me a real kick.
Right now you're about to head into the city and there's so many more exciting things to do. Is that
constant never-ending self-improvement journey? That's it. Absolutely part of it. I learned
something yesterday. I learned something today. I learned something tomorrow and I love being in the
swim. And you don't look back too often. There's some serious achievement there, Rod. Is there one
that you think, God, that was a great chapter in particular? When I retired from British Airways,
I'd had the better part of 30 years in aviation. Someone said to me, what were you most proud of?
And pride's a sort of a mixed emotion for me. The thing I think I got the most satisfaction out of
was that in all my time in aviation, we never lost an aeroplane. And that wasn't about me.
That was about the people who put safety and security first in the business. So I get a kick
out of that. You can never take safety for granted in aviation. Passengers can take it for granted.
But the people who work and run airlines can't. So that was the thing I got the biggest kick out of.
Rod, not many Rhodes scholars can play first class cricket. You grew up in country Western
Australia and played cricket alongside the great Rod Marsh. John Inverarity is a name that people
will know really well and legends of WA cricket. If you had your time and you could maybe give back
a bit of business success to play more cricket, would you do that?
No, I got the balance right. I was a journeyman. I loved playing. I loved playing with,
people who were better than me. And I learned a lot from people like Bacchus, Rod Marsh and from
John Inverarity. Bacchus sadly no more. Inver's still in great shape. I learned a lot and sport,
I think, teaches you a lot. There are very few things in life where you get direct feedback,
Luke. You get it in sport. It's called the scoreboard. At the end of the game, you look up
at the scoreboard and you've either won or lost and you've either had a good day personally or a
bad day. It's feedback. It's feedback. It's feedback. It's feedback. It's feedback. It's feedback.
It's feedback. It's feedback. It's feedback. It's feedback. It's feedback. It's feedback. It's feedback.
It's feedback. It's feedback. It's feedback. It's feedback. It's feedback. It's feedback.
And I think that makes you stronger.
The Rhodes Scholarship is regarded as the world's most prestigious academic program in the world.
And to attend the world-renowned Oxford University, they identify young leaders from around the
globe they believe can make a difference in the world. 1974, you're the Rhodes Scholar from Western
Australia. Tell me about that experience. Well, I arrived at Oxford never really having
been outside Australia before, wondering what to make of it. Loved every minute of it. It was a
different world in many ways. Lots of really capable people. You know, I grew up in WA and
went to school and university with some really good people, but you get to Oxford and you're
surrounded by people who are really smart and clever and many of them good people. So for me,
that was a complete eye-opener. I think Winston Churchill said that the Americans and the British
were two peoples separated by a common language. I think that's true of Australia and Britain.
I'd grown up in a household where...
My father had been a pilot in Britain during the war and lived to tell the tale and always
thought the Brits were good sorts, apart from when the Ashes series was on. And so I got there
sort of with a positive mindset. Getting a Rhodes Scholarship changed my life, really.
And I loved every minute of it.
Well, I heard a story that you're sitting around at Oxford and the crew that founded
antibiotics are in your sphere. Can you share with us a bit of that story?
So Luke, I was a graduate student at Lincoln,
at Oxford. Everyone who's in the university is also a member of a college. And I was a member
of Lincoln College, Oxford during my postgraduate days. And Howard Florey, Lord Florey, a South
Australian Rhodes Scholar, had been at Lincoln College, Oxford. And Florey had been responsible
for taking the bug that was penicillin, the fungus, I think it was, and turning it into
the world's most famous biotic, antibiotic.
And so I was privileged enough to sit and listen to them talk about the penicillin journey,
how they took what was seen initially as an obscure fungus that killed bugs in a Petri dish
and turned it into something that saved countless lives. And understanding how they'd got from
that, and how they'd got from that, and how they'd got from that, and how they'd got from that,
and how they'd got from that, and how they'd got from that, and how they'd got from that,
to that point of a Petri dish to a world-class global antibiotic was remarkable. And they'd
done it on the smell of an oily rag.
It's an incredible story, isn't it?
It's extraordinary.
Is it true they literally use themselves as guinea pigs?
Well, indeed, what they did was they had to develop this, and they had very limited resources.
They had some help from America, but having developed the drug and knowing that it could
kill bacteria, they had to work on it.
They had to work out how much to give people, how often to give it to people, all of these things.
And it was wartime, and there was really no time to have a great series of trials with laboratory mice.
So they literally used it to treat people who were probably going to die anyway of things like
septicemia, blood poisoning, and they effectively trialed it on people. And those sort of things
happen in wartime, I think. And they did remarkable work, but they
did it literally on the smell of an oily rag. And they produced, one of them who was still
an academic at Lincoln when I was there, Norman Heatley, who was a wonderful man. I remember him
saying to me that their goal was to produce enough penicillin so that when the invasion of Europe
took place, as it did in 1944, they had enough penicillin to treat the wounded. Now, that's a
pretty big goal.
Yeah.
And they were able to deliver it. They were remarkable people, and they didn't have all the
laboratory space and infrastructure that people have today.
So how inspiring is that for a young boy who loves his cricket and did well academically
from Western Australia, grew up in the country, your dad was a banker, you moved country town,
suddenly you're sitting in the most prestigious university in the world, arguably.
That's it.
Was that something that you thought, wow, I can make a difference? Did that happen?
Well, it is the art of the possible, Luke, I think. It's up to you at the end of the day.
But you're in a place with people who have achieved extraordinary things, miracles almost.
You know, I would argue that Howard Florey, for instance, was probably the most famous
South Australian in many ways. There's a walk in Adelaide of, on the footpath, famous South
Australians, and I think Florey's at the beginning of it, and I reckon that's about right. But it
tells you that if you work hard, you absolutely commit yourself to what you do. There's no prize
for not doing what you do. There's no prize for not doing what you do. There's no prize for not
giving it your best shot. And this group did.
And so did you. You go on to be knighted for your services to the aviation industry, and
in particular for your role as the CEO of British Airways. What type of leader were you? A famous
organisation like British Airways. What type of leader were you in that role?
Well, I think because I'd worked in the aviation industry, Luke,
for Cathay Pacific and Ansett before I went to British Airways, I'd been in the industry for,
for quite a while. But I think it's a great mistake to think that because you know a
particular problem, let's say in Cathay Pacific or Ansett, that the same problem
in British Airways has the same solution, different time, different place. I arrived
there in early 2000, and I always try and spend the first few weeks listening to frontline staff,
to customers, to my fellow managers, shareholders, suppliers. You want to know about an airline,
go talk to Boeing or Rolls Royce, because they sell aeroplanes or engines to everybody.
Just trying to build up a mental picture of how people saw British Airways,
what they believed the challenges were. I always had
sort of three or four questions. What do you like about what we do? What don't you like about what
we do? What do you think is broken and how would you fix it? So you build up a picture of how
the people who you're going to be working with see the entity you're in. And having done that, you can
then get about trying to make it better.
And I had five and a half years of doing that.
You made the, I'm assuming, tough decision to retire the famous Concorde.
Can you give those listening that maybe don't understand the nostalgia around the Concorde,
what it did and its place in aviation?
That must have been a big call.
Can you talk us through that?
Yeah, well, Concorde was, and is still today, it no longer flies, of course.
It retired in October, 2003, but it was the only commercial aeroplane that flew supersonically.
So it would take off from Heathrow for New York about 11 o'clock in the morning, and
it would get to New York just after nine o'clock the same morning, two hours before, quote
unquote.
And a standard commercial flight is taking how long from Heathrow?
It'd take about seven hours.
Concorde took less than half that.
So it would take off, go due west, and it couldn't go supersonically
to London.
So it went over the sea because of the sonic boom.
So it would get out over the Irish Sea, and the skipper would stick the throttles forward,
and it would crank pretty quickly up to twice the speed of sound.
What experience was that like flying in it?
It was a remarkable aeroplane, obviously.
And the men and women who operated and maintained it were fantastic with it, because it was
so different to every other aeroplane.
It was tiny.
It was a bullet, basically.
So it was tiny.
How many seats?
100 seats, 25 rows, two on each side of the aisle.
And as it left Heathrow and headed to JFK Airport in New York, as it burnt fuel, it
would climb.
Most commercial aeroplanes maybe get up to 39,000 feet.
This aeroplane would get to 60,000 feet.
The sky wasn't blue, it was indigo.
And the horizon wasn't flat, it was curved.
So you could see the curvature of the earth in the car.
You could see the curvature of the earth.
Wow.
Yeah.
It was a remarkable aeroplane, and it was a smooth flight.
It was a privilege to fly it, and privilege to know the men and women who operated it.
And I still see some of them when I go to the UK.
Captain Mike Bannister, who was the fleet captain when we retired it in 2003, still
going strong.
And although the aeroplane's retired, I think the simulator's still there, and Mike flies
the simulator from time to time, he tells me.
So was it just not commercial?
Was it as simple as that?
Yes.
It was an extraordinary aeroplane.
But for a manufacturer of aeroplanes to have a program that's commercially viable, a new
aeroplane type, a 777 or an Airbus A350, Boeing and Airbus, the two big manufacturers, you
normally need to make and sell about 1,000 before you get your development costs back.
They made it and sold less than 20 Concords.
It was at the heart of British Airways.
But the aeroplane itself was never able to sort of get the broad coverage it would need
to be a commercial success for the manufacturers.
Is there a place again for supersonic flight in the future?
I hope so.
It's going to take a while.
You've got to resolve two problems.
The first is the sonic boom, because most countries won't let you fly supersonically
over land because of the sonic boom.
So tell me if a sonic boom over land, you're breaking glass and...
Yeah.
You're probably...
It's bang, bang.
You hear the shock waves that come off the aeroplane sort of come down to the ground.
So you hear it quite clearly.
But the other thing, Luke, is that it was twice the speed of sound, which is where it
flew, is an inefficient speed to fly at.
So it burnt as much fuel going from London to New York as a 747 and carried about a quarter
the number of passengers.
So the two issues you need to resolve.
You need to find a way to diminish the sonic boom and you need for it to happen efficiently.
It was designed and built before the first oil shock.
So fuel was very cheap when it was designed and built.
So I hope there'll be a replacement and there's quite a bit of work going on at the moment,
trying to find a way to make supersonic travel viable again.
You spent more than 20 years on Rupert Murdoch's News Corporation board and locally on the
Herald and Weekly Times board.
And you've got an incredibly unique position of understanding global mainstream media.
My perception, Rod, is that it feels like we've never been more divided around the globe
and that even understanding truth, this concept of fake news now is something that is real.
We saw an assassination attempt days ago of the US president and half the people don't
think that's real.
What's the answer?
What do you make of it?
It feels that it's never been more hostile.
What do you think in terms of mainstream media's role in all that?
How do we fix that?
Well, I think the search for the truth is always the most important piece of the jigsaw.
And I think that's something that's always driven Rupert and Lachlan, who now runs the
business day to day.
Having grown up through science and engineering, the pursuit of the facts have always been
at the heart of scientific endeavor, engineering endeavor.
And too often you have your facts and I have mine, and we're not prepared to debate in
a Socratic way.
Yeah.
I think the evidence, where does it come from?
Is it viable?
Is it relevant?
People confuse opinions with facts.
And of course, we're all entitled to our own opinions, but we should at least be able to
agree on the facts.
And fake news is a real problem.
And my understanding was that that was journalism, was that you report on the facts.
Correct.
And you let the viewer have an opinion and form that opinion.
And I think, and I do this from time to time, a story can come out in the US and you can
put CNN on.
Yes.
You could put Fox News on.
And you could be living in two separate places.
You could be living in two separate planets on what is being reported factually.
That to me seems, and then what's happening is that that feels like that's dividing people.
As you said, we're not coming together then to try and find solutions.
Yeah.
But I think good journalists pursue the facts still today.
They follow up.
If you have a, and sort of jobs I've done over the years, you find yourself talking
to journalists or not, and the good ones, and there are many good ones come well prepared
and they'll follow up on things you say.
Yeah.
So be clear about your facts if you don't know say so.
I think journalism is about a facts-based activity.
That doesn't mean that you can't have commentary alongside the facts.
Commentary's a view about how I see the world.
And as long as you're clear about what is a story and what are the facts and what is
commentary, my interpretation of where we are, I think good journalists understand the
difference massively between the two.
Yeah.
And today I think we confuse opinions with facts and that skews the way in which we
view the world.
And Rob, big tech has come in, Facebook and Meta, 135 billion US dollars a year out of
the advertising market now heads towards the Mark Zuckerberg entity.
We know those algorithms work in ways that have made mainstream media poised in a delicate
space.
You'd have to say, free-to-air television and newspaper journalism is, as you would
know, much better than me.
A challenging space forever.
What do you think about big tech's role?
We know unavoidably the evidence is saying that those algorithms are doing huge harm
to our kids.
We talk a lot about what social media has done in that space.
What's your view on that?
It's a real challenge.
I grew up in a much simpler world.
So did you.
You know, I grew up in a world in the bush in Western Australia before television.
So you listen to the radio and you read the newspapers and it was, the facts were the
facts and it was pretty clear.
It's a much more complicated world now.
Of course, it's a world of greater opportunity.
As we sit here, it's the 60th anniversary of the Australian newspaper.
And I read The Australian and The Fin Review every day and The Herald and The Weekly Times
obviously too.
You know, I think there's still a real place for good journalism, facts-based focus on
what really happened.
There is commentary around that, but I think our kids live in a much more complicated world.
And we still don't fully understand.
We don't fully understand the impact of social media on young lives.
We know it's an opportunity for kids, gives them access to a much broader range of views,
but it's also a challenge because they have to sort out fact from fiction.
And that's increasingly difficult for the reasons you've said.
Another one of your great legacies I wanted to ask you about, Infrastructure Australia
in 2008.
You created that.
You're the inaugural chairman.
I assume that was about priorities.
It was around privatising these billion dollar projects and saying, we need to keep them
separate from politics.
Correct me if I'm wrong on that, you know, bipartisan support for that amount of money
to be spent.
Would make sense to have a committee and it's, it's a great concept.
I can't help it.
In a city here in Melbourne, you know, the East-West Project was one that you wrote a
paper on, and we saw that contract torn up to the tune of hundreds of millions of dollars.
We've got a suburban rail project.
That could be a hundred billion dollar project.
at least that hasn't gone through the normal channels. What do you think in the city of
Melbourne, with your experience, what does that bring up for you?
So Infrastructure Australia was set up in 2008 and Anthony Albanese, the current Prime Minister,
was Infrastructure Minister. We set up Infrastructure Australia to take an evidence-based
approach to infrastructure projects because everybody's got their pet projects. The challenge
is to look at what problem they're solving and can they do it efficiently and is that the best
use of the money. If you don't have some discipline around that, you can end up building
infrastructure that has limited value. I describe it as building bridges over puddles and roads to
nowhere. The whole idea of Infrastructure Australia was to take the projects that were put forward
at both federal and state level and evaluate them.
Now,
not just in economic terms, cost-benefit analysis is something that's been around for a while,
but also look at the impact that projects have on the environment and community
and then publish a list of projects that we believe to be viable and sensible and appropriate
so that political leaders, when they come to choose projects, can do so
from a list of sensible projects. What often happens is that politicians,
like other folks, have their own pet projects and they often are keen to pursue them without,
I think, the necessary rigour into them. And we've seen examples of that all around the country.
We've seen some good projects, projects that make a real difference. The East-West report that I did
in 2008, which Steve Brax was Premier when we started that project, and when I delivered the
report, John Brumby was Premier. And the East-West report that I did in 2008, which Steve Brax was
Premier when we started that project, and when I delivered the report, John Brumby was Premier. And the East-West report that I did in 2008,
and when I delivered the report, John Brumby was Premier. And the East-West report that I did in 2008,
there were a series of recommendations in that. There were three really big projects.
Two of them were rail projects, improved connectivity to Ballarat, Geelong and Bendigo from Melbourne,
the beginning of an urban rail network in Melbourne, the Underground.
Both those things have either happened or are happening. And then the tunnel that would have
linked the Eastern Freeway with the Tullamarine in the Westgate, which was torn up at a minute to midnight.
At a cost of a billion dollars. My own view has been and remains that one day that'll have to be
built because it'll take all that traffic that runs through the north of the city,
underground, like the Burnley and Domain tunnels, take the traffic south of the city underground
and improve the livability. My view, Luke, about those things is that's an advisory role.
Advisors advise and governments decide, right? And sometimes they decide wisely. And in my view,
sometimes they don't. But you have to, no one elected me to office. I was asked to make a
contribution to the policy debate. I've always been happy to contribute to policy, try and stay
out of the politics, but contribute to policy. But government has to make the right calls and
we see it all around the country. And sometimes in my view, they choose wisely and sometimes they
don't. A very pragmatic approach. And I appreciate that.
And it makes a lot of sense. But I think people with your wisdom and experience and business
history have a voice. And Generation Young, it feels like we, and I'm going to be a bit local
here in Victoria. I'm fascinated. We're approaching $200 billion worth of debt as a state.
That's it.
Feels like we've got some unique problems coming our way.
Yes.
Do we need people like you to be out there beating the drum a bit? Is that a concern? I mean,
should we be concerned about that level of debt?
You should be concerned.
Yeah.
I think $200 million.
$200 billion.
$200 billion is a lot of money and that's where we're headed. And we're going to get there quite
quickly.
$26 million a day of interest we pay.
That's it. And if, heaven forbid, we were to lose our credit rating, then the interest bill would
go up. So it's a real issue. And you need to use bodies like Infrastructure Australia and
Infrastructure Victoria, because there's a state body. And some of the big projects,
they've never been near either of those bodies. And that's a real concern. Because if they're
good projects, then they'll pass muster. And you shouldn't push them through on the fly,
in my view. Because at the end of the day, governments have decisions to make about what
they spend on infrastructure. We've talked about some of that. But on hospitals, on education,
on the police force, on all the things that make our community and our society function
properly. And money spent often in one area means there's less money to be spent in another.
So you need to be very disciplined about where you spend and how you spend it. Because if not,
then your children and your grandchildren end up paying the bill.
And you've been another great champion for major events. And the benefit of that bringing
the Grand Prix and the Australian Open Tennis and these projects that make a state like Victoria
what it is. Can you tell us about why that's been so important for you?
So I did that. Steve Brax, when he was Premier, asked me to take it over,
which I did at the end of 2005, beginning of 2006. Ron Walker had really worked so hard to
make it work with Geoff Kennett. And I stood on their shoulders, really. And I did it for
a dozen or so years and loved it. In part because it's Melbourne's and Victoria's sweet spot.
We don't have iron ore. We don't have coal. We're not like Queensland and Western Australia.
Where there are large revenue streams that come from the resource industry.
And for Melbourne, particularly with the great facilities, we've got the MCG, the Rod Laver Arena,
Amy Stadium now, National Gallery of Victoria, the museum, the state library. We've got great
venues that are very centrally located. And Victoria, and remember it was initially called
Melbourne Major Events by the time I got there.
It was Victoria Major Events. So it wasn't just Melbourne. But Melbourne is blessed with
infrastructure that's been built over a long period of time. So we've got the venues to
host these things. And we have the people who know how to make it work. So you can go to a
football game or rugby game or a cricket game at the MCG. And you can be there with close to
100,000 people. You can arrive by tram. You can walk from the CBD. You can,
catch the train. And 30 minutes after the game finishes, the place is empty.
Now, there are not many places in the world where that's true. So we have the venues,
we have the people. And over a long period of time, Victoria built a reputation for being
not only the sporting capital of the world, but the events capital of the world.
And we've got to keep that.
It's a great way to describe it, isn't it? You take that for granted, don't you? 100,000 people
enter the MCG and within 30 minutes, you're in a restaurant in the city or you've gone home on the
train.
Absolutely.
It is unique, isn't it, to other cities in the world and something we should celebrate. I love,
I'm fascinated by your story. So many passions and different streams. And I mentioned in the
introduction, Sir Rod, your commendation, the highest civil commendation you can get from the
Japanese government, which is a great legacy. And you've been a huge champion of Asia-Australian
relationships and the business connection in that. Tell us why that was so important to you.
Well, Australia's three major trading partners, Luke,
China, Japan, and Korea in that order, South Korea. And although we are culturally sort of
halfway between here and London, I would describe us, something like a third of Australians weren't
born in Australia. You know, in my household, I'm the only one who was born here. My wife's
Korean. Our two children were born in Hong Kong. So Australia is a really sort of wonderful
polyglot place in many ways. But our culture still owes a lot to the Western civilization,
as well as indigenous civilization. But our economy is firmly part of Asia. Our biggest trading
partners are in Asia. And in talking about China, Japan, and Korea, let's not forget ASEAN too,
Indonesia, Singapore, Malaysia, the Philippines. So our economic well-being is very dependent upon
our Asian links. And I worked in Asia for 20 years, Korea, Japan, and Hong Kong,
and learned so much doing it. But our focus,
on Asia, is so important to us. And I think we often forget how important those Asia links are.
So I'm always keen to remind people that we depend on the well-being of our Asian neighbors,
and we should make the most of the relationship. Do you think Australians understand that?
No, I think they're beginning to. I think it was Paul Keating who said many years ago that
the closest most people get to Indonesia is they fly over the top of it on their way to Hong Kong
or Singapore or whatever, which is true.
I think we're beginning to understand how important Asia is. For me, the understanding
came as a student at University of Western Australia, because there were students who
came from South Asia particularly under something called the Colombo Plan, and the Australian
government paid for their education here. So in my class were young men and women from Malaysia,
from Singapore, from Indonesia, who came to study here.
Many of whom became lifelong friends of Australia. And many years later, when I would go to Asia on
business when I worked there, I'd bump into people who had been to University of Western Australia.
I mean, those links are very important. Hi, I love asking these series of questions,
and I'm fascinated by your take on it. I write on what different leadership looks like in different
settings. And your story is a fascinating and unique one. And we feel like the ability to lead
someone else means you've got to have an understanding of yourself. And we talk about
this idea of self-leadership before you lead someone else. Does that ring true to you, the
idea of self-leadership? Yes, you have to understand yourself,
but you also have to understand them. That's why it's important to ask questions. Because when you
ask questions of people, you begin to understand them as well as the issues. But I think leaders
need to be comfortable in their own skin in many ways. And for someone like me,
that came from sport as well as the classroom. You know, I think I learned more about leadership
on the sporting field than I did in the classroom, probably. And I think I'm not unusual in that
sense. So the other thing you have to, if you're going to lead in a business sense or in a sporting
sense, you better really understand the industry or the game you're involved in. I think the best
leaders are passionate about leadership. And I think that's one of the things that I've learned
about the business they're in or the sport they're in or the business of sport. They're
passionate about it. They think about it in the shower in the morning. They don't sort of pick it
up at nine o'clock and put it down at five. And they're constantly curious about understanding
the new things that are coming in. So, you know, aviation when I retired was very different to
aviation when I joined. Technology had changed, aeroplanes had changed, but the way in which we
did it remarkably, you know, we'd gone from people booking a flight on the telephone to doing it
online. I mean, there were, it was constantly changing and you've got to stay abreast of those
changes. Yeah. I loved your four questions before when you were at British Airways, you know, what
do you like about the organisation? What would you like to change? You know, what's broken and
how would you fix it? They're simple questions, aren't they? But you learn a lot. Well, you learn
about how people see your business, but you also learn about them and you get some great insights.
You know, if you want to know about an airline, go talk to the people who touch the customers
every day. You know, as chief executive, I sat in an office, I was often out and about in the
business. But if you talk to someone at the check-in counter or a pilot or a cabin crew member
who deal with customers day in, day out, not in ones and twos, but in hundreds, their insights
into what works and what doesn't, it's very, very, very useful. It's a great point and often
overlooked in the television industry. Not many people ask that question. I mean,
it's the cameramen who know everything. Correct.
And sit there and understand the industry maybe better than anyone else, but often rarely asked.
We see leaders who have great success like you, Rod, are really conscious of the impact they have
on others in a positive way every day. I understand you go back to London and the British Airways,
people that work with you, there's many friends and you catch up with lots of people. Were you
conscious of that, that positive impact you had on other people in your environment?
Well, you try and do the best job you can do.
That's the first thing you do. But in a complicated industry like aviation,
which is technology and marketing and sales, customer service, logistics, by definition,
you need a team of people. You're a big employer, so human resources are really important. Employing
good people and helping them grows important. So you can't run a business like that yourself,
by yourself. You've got to do it with a team of really good people who've got some real
clients. You've got to do it with a team of really good people who've got some real
clarity about what needs to be done and feel they can work together to do it. So I always took
the view that my job in the leadership sense was to create that sort of environment. And when you
do that and you work with people and you see people grow and improve, because we all have
speed bumps at different times in our lives, you get a kick out of seeing their success.
So I get a kick out of seeing
Cathay Pacific, British Airways, the two airlines where I spent most of my working life,
seeing people today who are running those businesses, who were there in a much more
junior capacity when I was there. And I get a kick out of that. And I like to,
from time to time, I bump into them and I like to celebrate their journey with them.
I get a kick out of that too.
You mentioned the clarity and the idea of coming in with a vision and being able to
share that with your team. How do you do that?
How did you do that? I'm assuming you came in with, once you worked out the path,
you've got to then be able to get, as you said, that team on board. How did you go about sharing
that vision?
Well, it's got to be a shared vision, Luke. You can't be something that you carve in tablets
of stone by yourself and sort of arrive to your team and say, Eureka, here it is.
I think you work out the path. You have your own views. And if you've got a good team around you,
those views can be crystallized and the best parts of them take,
going forward. But unless there's shared ownership about the journey,
and that's true all the way down the business. So one of the roles I think good chief executives
take upon themselves is they're not only the chief executive officer, but they've also got
to be the chief communications officer. You've got to be able to talk to people
anywhere in your business about where the business is headed and why. And you've also
got to understand how the work that they do day to day contributes to that success.
And once people can see what they do day to day and how that helps the business be successful,
that's really energizing for them. They see a focus. They understand what they can do
and how they can make things better. That's very powerful.
We see curiosity as a word that comes up a lot for different leaders who have sustained success.
And you sat down and I said, we looked back and you said, no, I'm happy to be here. And I've,
can't wait for today. And it sounds like you've got that curiosity. Does that ring true for you?
Oh, absolutely. I was asked a couple of years ago in my office in JP Morgan here in Melbourne,
what I fear losing most. And I think they thought I'd probably say hearing or sight or whatever. I
said the gift of curiosity. I think curiosity is a really important piece to be genuinely curious
and to know that every day you're going to learn something new, um, is really,
really powerful and very motivating. So just when you think, you know, the answer to a problem,
the problem changes. And if you think I know the answer to that problem, because I worked it out
a year ago or a week ago or a day ago, you've got to be open to the idea that the nature of the
problem may have changed and you better rethink what the solution is.
Well, how important is collaboration been for you in all of your different endeavors?
Well, collaboration matters because, um, I mean, clearly it does in sport,
but it matters in business too. So if you are in the airline business, then you're buying
airplanes from Boeing and Airbus. You're buying engines from Rolls Royce and General Electric.
You're buying wine, wine glasses, seats, galleys. You're buying computer systems, software.
You know, you don't make any of these things yourself. You're constantly buying.
And in today's world, if you are buying, you have to collaborate. And, um, a good example of
that for me was Boeing, who have got their challenges at the moment. But if you go back
to the Boeing 777 program, which was sort of early nineties, um, the project manager was a guy called
Alan Mullally. And Alan went on to be sort of head of commercial at Boeing and then effectively
rebuilt Ford Motor Car Company. Terrific guy. But Alan did something that Boeing hadn't done before.
Before they,
settled on the design of the Boeing 777. In the nineties, he got half a dozen of his best
customers together and said, what are you looking for? You know, what sort of airplane,
what sort of characteristics, what's, what are you looking for on the maintenance front?
So he looked at all the elements of, that airlines would think about before they buy airplanes.
And he worked with his customers. Cathay Pacific was one, British Airways was another.
I think United was one.
Japan Airlines. These were big buyers of Boeing airplanes. They operated wide-bodied airplanes.
Um, and they knew the good things and the not so good things about, about airplanes.
And Alan, instead of building an airplane and then selling it, decided to get customers on board on day one.
And that's been an extremely successful program for Boeing, the 777 program.
And that's a good example of collaboration.
And did you find you actually bringing competitors together too, as customers?
Yeah.
And the idea that that opportunity is there, obviously there's anti-competitive issues,
but when there is common interest and safety into something like an airline industry, did you,
did competitors find that was a reasonable thing to do?
Yeah. So there are clearly some things you can't talk about because it's anti-competitive behavior,
but everyone in aviation has an interest in safety. So you want Boeing to build the
safest airplanes possible. You also have a joint vested interest in, um, having an airplane that's
easy to maintain.
Where are the access panels? Where's the technology? How easy is it to maintain that?
And that's something that's not an issue of competition between airlines.
You wouldn't talk about things that were competition.
We never got into seats. Boeing don't make seats anyway.
Separate companies make the seats.
There are some areas where the airlines work together quite properly and quite legitimately.
And it was about sharing those thoughts, that thinking.
So Rod, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Lots of them. Mum and dad, probably. You grow up at your parents' knee. They sort of shape you,
really. And I was lucky. I love both my parents. Um, and then along the way, sporting people who
my captain's coach, we talked about two of them, Rod Marsh and John Inverarity. Um,
when I played football at university, it was a guy called Peter Tannick, who was captain coach,
who played for East Perth and who was tough. It was terrific. Um, and then there were people in
the classroom, people who inspire you. And I was always science focused, some great teachers at
school and some good teachers at university. So those sorts of people inspire you on your journey
and they really shape you. I think later in life, you, you meet other people who, who, um, who you
admire, but, um, it's the earlier, earliest part of the journey that determines who you are.
And for me, it was those sorts of people.
Okay.
And then of course, particularly doing the aviation job, you get to meet interesting
people and some of those inspire you too.
It's a great answer, Rod.
And it's such a diverse life that you've had.
And my final question too, we are a bit obsessed with this idea of collaboration and you've,
as you said, from Rupert Murdoch to a whole range of fascinating people.
We could spend another four hours.
I'd like to do that on the different people.
But in terms of collaborating into a project or you thought, God, I'd love to collaborate
with that particular person.
It might be an interest of sporting or any of your other passions.
Is there someone that you've been curious to collaborate with?
Well, I think serving on boards, you get to see a broad church.
And for me in a business sense, I think Rupert Murdoch is the most outstanding business leader
I've met.
Someone who could turn a single newspaper in Adelaide into a global media empire.
And, you know.
You know, in his early 90s, still clear thinking and fascinated by future opportunity.
And we grew up with printers ink in his veins, really, which he got from his father, who's
Sir Keith Murdoch, who was also a journalist and a newspaper proprietor.
But Rupert was able to move without giving up on newspapers, quite the opposite.
He's still a champion of them, was able to move into the electronic business system,
to television.
He's still a champion of television, to movies, and is still fascinated by new opportunities.
So being able to sit and be part of the conversations and what those sorts of people do, one of
the things it tells me, if Rupert can still be going at 93, mind you, he's got pretty
good genes.
His mother, who was a saint, lived to be well over 100.
Then there's hope for you and me, Luke.
We can keep going too.
Is it a misunderstood story?
People think that Rupert inherited the keys to the world.
But he literally got left the Adelaide newspaper, and the most successful media business ever
in history, arguably one of the most successful people ever on the planet, comes with, when
you're in that industry, your fair share of critics, and obviously people would understand
that.
But you've been up close and personal to see, and even in early 90s, what's next?
And that curiosity.
The business nearly collapsed in the early 90s when there was an economic downturn.
Rupert came through it and was rebuilt stronger and better than ever.
We talked earlier about the importance of facts, right?
Rupert's always been passionate about getting to the bottom of stuff, the facts.
What are the facts?
And he's always had a, you know, in a business sense, a capacity to look beyond the here
and now.
So to look at the iPad when it first popped up, instead of thinking, this may be the best
means of death of newspapers, thinking here's yet another way to get great content to
customers, including customers who probably don't currently read newspapers, and that
capacity to look beyond the here and now, and to be relentlessly curious, to find new
ways of doing things, and not to be a prisoner of the past.
That takes some doing.
And in order to be successful, you just have to keep looking forward.
You can't spend too much time looking in the rear vision mirror, Luke.
You mentioned as a CEO, you're the chief communication officer at the same time.
Can you give us a little bit on that?
How did you communicate?
How do you still go about communicating with a range of different people?
Well, I think when you're in a leadership position in the business, there are formal
channels of communication.
You know, businesses today have newsletters, newspapers, videos, podcasts to talk to their
people.
Which is really important.
But of course, if you're the CEO and you're talking to the press about, you know, and
if you're in a public company, as British Airways was, Cathay was too, Cathay Pacific
was too, then interim results, full year results, you're in front of the media as well as the
analysts.
And the people who, in my experience, who read with the greatest interest what the newspapers
and televisions focus on.
And you see what those folks have to say are your own stuff, your shareholders too, obviously,
but your own stuff.
And there's got to be real consistency in messages.
It's got to be true.
But if they read something in the newspapers that's different to what they hear from you
directly, then your credibility evaporates quite quickly.
So whenever you're communicating, you have to be clear about what the narrative is and
it's got to be consistent.
So, Rod Eddy, it's been a great pleasure to spend some time with you.
I appreciate it.
Yeah, for sure.
time and it's an amazing life feels like there's plenty more years and lots of great stories to
come and thanks for your time i really appreciate it thanks luke it's been good fun thanks for
listening to another episode of the empowering leaders podcast huge thanks as always to our
great friends at temper and we encourage you to check out our leader connect program
new episodes are out every wednesday morning at 6 a.m