A Listener Production.
Stacey Moorlank-Sullivan is an Australian lacrosse legend.
She graduated from Loyola University, Maryland in 2002,
based in Baltimore in the United States as a three-time All-American
and still holds the NCAA Division I record for the most goals in a game,
which, by the way, was 12 versus American in her senior season.
She's a business owner, the co-founder of Show & Tell Online,
a women's lifestyle brand, co-host of her own brilliant podcast
of the same name, Show & Tell Online, with her great friends Monty and Mel.
She's married to Mike Sullivan himself, by the way, an All-American lacrosse player.
They have three young boys, Raph, Jarvie and Mac.
Stacey came out of retirement to represent Australia at her fourth World Cup
as a mother of three, having previously won a World Cup gold medal in 2005
and twice been captain of Australia.
In recent times, Stacey has joined our team at Alita
as a brilliant leadership facilitator in our signature Alita Connect program.
Stacey.
Stacey, I look at you and I think you're a bit of a freak of nature for me.
Mother of three, business owner, I mentioned it all there,
come out of retirement to play for Australia.
Most people, when you do it all with good humour and great care for people,
how do you do it all?
Oh, God, that's a million-dollar question, isn't it, Darce?
And thanks for having me.
I'm excited to chat with you.
We're never short of a word, are we?
But how do we do it all?
I get asked that quite a lot, actually,
and it's that ever-elusive question of balance.
And the answer is there is no real answer.
I just know that I'm better when I'm busy
and I'm a more effective mother and person
and happier when I've got a bit of purpose.
And then I'm working towards something.
So I kind of live in a constant state of that,
even though sometimes I wish I didn't.
Most of the time I'm better off there.
So you need to have that real sense of achievement and purpose.
And even if it means there's a lot going on,
because I think anyone would appreciate what I just said.
To manage all that takes enormous skill,
but you know yourself well enough to think,
unless that's going, I'm not going to be the best version of myself.
Is that right?
Yeah, absolutely.
And I think it's when you're used to achieving,
I think it becomes quite addictive in a way,
which is not necessarily a good thing.
But I think once you know that you're capable of doing hard things,
nothing's too daunting.
So then I became quite relentless in always trying to learn
and push the boundaries and achieve.
Yeah.
Something different than what I was used to.
But I think I am better in that space.
I am more productive, more helpful for other people
and happier in myself if I am always on the pathway to something.
Yeah.
I've seen that with you and I'll come back and talk about this
in a bit more detail later.
But, you know, taking on something new and a challenge
and just to see your focus, but also just your capacity to learn
and want to keep self-improving is incredibly impressive to watch.
So I'll come back and talk about that in the context of the work at a leader.
But, you know, reading your story in preparation, Stace, I know it,
but I'm reading it again.
I think 17 years of age, you grew up in Newport,
you get picked out to go on a US college scholarship, you know,
and you're captain of Australia at a really young age.
So, you know, I see the work you're doing as a leader now as a brilliant job.
Have you always seen yourself in a leadership role?
Because it seems as though that's been the whole context of your life.
Yeah.
It's an interesting question.
When I was mentally preparing for this chat today,
I thought about that, about how young I was,
finding myself in those positions.
And I think I just, I did naturally gravitate towards, you know,
it sounds cliche, but the wee before me,
I was quite young when that developed for me.
I think just from the type of parents I had, you know, I was 17,
I was 14 playing with the best players in Australia at my club.
And they knew the lingo.
They knew what it looked like because they were older.
Some of them were 35 or plus.
And I was in an environment all the time where that was expected.
It wasn't about you.
It was about everybody else.
How can you serve the group?
So I think I started quite young in that area.
And I obviously just grabbed onto it.
And I did have that innate ability to connect with people quite easily.
And I was very much aware of how I affected people.
Like as a young child, like my mum and dad said that too,
I had a lot of empathy and compassion.
But just knew how to weave my way through people to make everybody feel quite comfortable
and serve them in a way.
So I think from a young age, I probably was, it was pretty innate in a way.
But I did often find myself in those positions,
mostly because I think I could play at a high level and serve people at the same time.
Yeah, it's a brilliant way to describe it.
And I love the language you use there, Stace,
it feels like that's where we've crossed over in that sense of we,
you know, coming out of such an individualized world.
And people listening to this will hear me talk about that a lot,
that, you know, there's so much research now,
how hyper-individualized the world's got.
And that's what I loved about team sport.
That was the first, second, and third thing, more than anything else,
was you worked out really quickly that you're only going to be good
if your mate next to you was good.
You're only going to have success if you could influence others to have good success.
And that just happened, you know, as a parent,
whatever layer,
you want to, you know, overlay that is,
it's just a healthier, happier way, isn't it?
But you obviously got that at a really young age,
as you said, 14 or 15.
Yeah, really young.
I was really young.
And then my first experience as a captain was
the under-19 Australian team when I was 18.
Then at Loyola for a couple of seasons.
And then it just kind of kept going.
But I was also really comfortable being in a capacity like that without a title
and making sure that everyone was galvanized
and together and working towards something that was bigger than themselves.
And not everyone gets that Tuesday.
So I'm playing team sport with you,
a smile on your face, isn't it?
And it takes all types.
And so you're not necessarily being judgmental there.
But, you know, certainly people I gravitated to were the ones that got that
and still do.
And I think that's part of that community you and I, you know, building.
And as I said, we'll talk about that, you know,
in a moment around that community of people that do look out for other people
is something that...
feel like the world needs if we're going to the high level.
You come out of retirement, your mother is free.
You've done it all at that stage.
I mean, there's not a lot to prove.
So what was going on there?
What made you want to come back and push yourself at this stage of your life?
Yeah, that's a good question.
There was a few things going on.
I think I was happily retired.
I had achieved everything I wanted to achieve.
And I retired in the first place because I remember that last World Cup I did.
I think I was 32.
I felt just a tiny bit.
I was off my top speed.
And it was really uncomfortable for me because I relied on it so heavily.
So as soon as I felt like I was 5% or 10% slower than I used to be,
I was like, I'm out.
Which in hindsight was a bit weak, I think,
because there was other things I had to offer.
But I was also really happily retired.
And I had one kid already on my last one.
And then my second one was rather challenging.
So he needed a lot more parenting than the first.
And then I think what happened was one of my...
One of the most important people in my life who was my mentor,
but also who I played with growing up,
who moved into coaching me probably for 80% of my career,
who passed away suddenly a couple of years ago.
She was the general manager of the last Australian team.
She came to me and said, we need you to try to come back.
And I said, well, look, you're going to have to be really clear about what this is
because this is an epic task for me.
She said, we just, we need...
Someone to come in and lead a young group
and try to show them what it takes so that we can build it for the future.
And I had a specific skill set that they also needed,
which was senatorial possession technique and skill
that I had developed over years to create an edge that,
you know, made me indispensable in a way.
So there was a few things working there.
And then I said, look, I'll give it a go.
But if it doesn't work, though,
Merky, you'll switch over to the coaching side.
And I said, that's fine.
Totally fine.
So we started that process.
It was hectic.
It was eight years of not being at a high level.
Eight year gap, was it?
Eight year gap of international elite play.
Wow.
And my body didn't like it.
I mean, after three C-sections and just, you know, it was a mission.
And it was probably the most challenging World Cup I'd ever done,
mentally and physically.
I learned more about myself.
I learned more about myself in this process than any World Cup before it.
It was the relentlessness of training a completely different way
and asking my mind to do things that was really uncomfortable.
But I think the reason why I came back was to serve the sport.
I had genuinely given away the need to perform
and had surrendered to the fact that I was doing this for Australian lacrosse
and for the players that were coming after.
And it was a really interesting process
and incredibly empowering in some ways
and also felt really vulnerable through the process as well.
Getting to know you in recent times and having heard you tell that story,
I'm not surprised by the person that you are,
that you would go and do that in such a selfless way.
And I can also relate to when you know what you like at your absolute best
and you lose, you know, people would say 5% of speed.
Why?
That's everything, isn't it?
At the top level, that's everything.
And that's the thing that made you obviously unbelievable at what you do.
So to get over that mental hurdle to say,
I'm going to come back but for a higher purpose
and knowing that you can still play clearly at the Australian level
but, you know, to overcome all that for a selfless purpose,
I think that probably sums you up.
And, you know, I mean, you won World Cup gold medals.
You've achieved how much enjoyment?
You look back to have gone, you know, you finished fourth in the World Cup in 2022.
You know, great achievement, great effort.
Do you look back with great satisfaction just because of what you went through?
Yeah, I look back with great satisfaction of it was the worst result I'd obviously had
and we've ever had in Australian women's lacrosse is fourth.
But I do look back on it in a very different way than the others.
I had a lot of support in the other World Cups with my peers
and some of the best players in the world at the time were playing in the same era as me.
So,
when I look back on this one, I think,
God, the challenge was so massive.
But like I said before,
I learned so much about myself that it was almost the most profound one for me,
even though the result wasn't what we wanted.
But I always do, you know,
one of the skills I have, I think,
in reflection for preparation for this too,
and just I've spent a lot of time trying to understand the difference between good and great
and what that space is in between.
And I think one of the things that I did have that lives in that space is,
is the ability to move through thoughts really quickly.
You know, my friends joke about it all the time,
that they're my memory bank of every World Cup.
They'll say, oh my God, remember we did this?
And I'd say, I've got no idea.
I don't remember any of it.
But even in games, it would be seconds.
They'd be like, you've missed the same shot 10 times.
I don't remember.
I just go back and keep trying.
So, when I finish World Cups, regardless of the result,
any game I've ever had,
I do have the ability to switch off it.
Like, it hurts for a minute,
but then, because I work so hard,
prepare so hard,
do everything I can,
I am content with the fact that I'd done everything I could.
And I think that's the gift you've got to give yourself,
is losing shit, yeah.
No one wants to lose.
But I don't leave anything,
no stone unturned,
so that when it's over, it's over.
And then I need to let it go.
Such a great life lesson, that one, Stace, isn't it?
It just takes the air out of all the pressure of sport, doesn't it?
To say, if you compete,
and prepare with everything you've got,
the end part actually doesn't really matter in the end, does it?
And it's easy to say that, harder to live it,
but clearly, you know, and that's the same in life, isn't it?
So, it's always, you know, you can't predict the results.
You can only control the amount of effort, your time you put in.
When you do, it sort of takes the pressure away from life and sport, isn't it?
It's such a profound way to approach it.
I'm not surprised.
And I pick up on what you said, too.
I can speak to people I play with.
You could go around six, 2001, and we played Essendon.
I could not have any idea of any moment at all,
and surprised that I was actually there when someone brings it back to me.
Yeah, maybe, not as, I suppose, can't articulate the way you did,
but probably something similar there as well.
Stace, you know, it's been great connecting and collaborating with you in recent times.
And I'm looking forward to telling the story,
because post the World Cup, around that time,
with you and you joined one of our Leader Connect groups.
And if you don't mind, I want to do this,
because often on this podcast, I'm talking about these, you know,
incredible people that connect with us, but I love the diversity of it as well.
And so, the group that you started with, if you don't mind me mentioning,
you know, Stacey Moreland, fresh from coming back into the World Cup of Lacrosse,
with a guy called Paul Daly from Gemtree Wines, who's, you know, great story.
They've had their own challenges, the wine industry, in recent times.
Greg Box from the...
Bass Coast Council, manager of people and culture down there.
Samantha Nanny does some amazing work in Life Education Victoria.
Bryce Middleton is packet and race course here in Victoria.
Bryce, you know, runs that world.
Simon Naismith is the director of coaching Australian Volleyball.
Bringing together these people, different backgrounds, people that you hadn't known before.
And for you to start there and then join us full-time, Stace, has just been such a...
Can you explain better than I do?
I never do.
Great job of explaining what it is a Leader Connect is all about.
What does it look like from your point of view?
Well, I think originally I was searching for something that was different than
everything else there for leadership that was out there.
And I'd done a lot of leadership courses in the past where it was a lecturer
and you did small group work.
And I just never felt like I walked away with stuff I could necessarily use in real life.
So, when I had stumbled upon a leader, I decided to do the program.
Mostly to meet new people of different backgrounds, to get insights and inspiration and collaboration
from people that had a different background than I did, to help me gain more tools to
obviously then deliver to the team I was leading and in business as well.
So, the original premise of joining a leader was that, is that I wanted something different.
I wanted to talk to real humans about what they were going through in their life and
ask them how they tackled things.
And their strategies for doing that.
So, that was sort of how it originally started for me.
And it was a really stimulating process to have real authentic conversations in a really
trusting environment.
And it brought me a lot of joy, like sitting in those sessions for an hour and 15 minutes
and learning about leadership dimensions, but also just, like I said, sitting there
and having real conversations with people about things that were challenges for them
and vice versa to support me.
And so, that was sort of how it started for me through some big parts of that campaign.
And then to flip over to the other side of being a fly on the wall in the same environment
almost in facilitating them, it's like the gift that keeps on giving.
You're just watching people talk about things that you don't often get to talk about in
real life.
And it is, it does still bring me so much joy and stimulation and challenge and all
of the things that you want out of almost small groups of people that are building a
small culture within themselves that become so connected that they've got these new connections
and networks that they can lean on forever.
Because all the groups, for the most part, have stuck together for years to come because
they've become close friends by sharing personal information.
They're very vulnerable.
So, for me, it's been that beautiful space to be inspired, to connect, to collaborate
and to learn from other people.
In real life, to attribute it to your own situation.
And we loved you so much, Stace.
We said, please come and join us.
Come and be part of the team.
That's just been incredible.
Anyone listening to this first part of the conversation will pick up on, you know, Stace's
empathy and her care for people.
But there's a fairly big resilience gene that comes with you as well and not afraid of any
challenge that comes your way and, you know, to see the way that you're just connecting
people in such a profound way, as you said.
And you humbly call it being a fly on the wall.
But you're doing an amazing job of bringing those groups together.
I'm bad at talking about the mechanics of it.
It sounds, to have you sitting here today, I feel like that's worthwhile for people listening
sometimes.
Like, what does that actually mean?
Could you drill into that a little bit around, you know, what eight sessions look like?
You talked about, which is the beauty of it.
We feel like, you know, this is a connection for life that happens when you form an Elite
Connect group.
And the evidence is showing that's the case, that this community is growing and they stay
together.
But can you just drill into a bit of how it works when you're hosting and facilitating
a group?
Yeah, certainly.
So there is eight sessions in the program and we meet fortnightly.
And each session is about an hour.
Well, it is an hour and 15 minutes.
And each week we dive into one of six leadership dimensions that you and Matt obviously developed
within the Elite Connect program.
So we dive into that.
But for the most part, that is a guided question.
For example, if you're talking...
If you're talking about collaboration, the question might be what has been a really great
example of collaboration in your environment and a specific hack or strategy you can share.
And then we'll share within the group anything that comes to mind that they can share with
each other that they can then take away and use in their own environments.
And it's incredible what people come up with, particularly when they're really diverse groups
from all different backgrounds.
And then typically the second half of that session is diving into someone's challenge
or hurdle that they're facing.
And we...
We do coaching around helping them serve each other and give them ideas and strategies
for thinking about it differently, where they can challenge each other's thoughts,
offer some more possibilities of ways that they could tackle it.
And the whole course does start with a empowering leader indicator report where they take it
to the team they're leading currently and find some feedback that will help them find
factors that they probably need to put a little bit more time into in terms of opportunities.
And then we use that as a way to guide them through the program, but mostly they're leaning
on each other to tackle challenges, hurdles, as well as really start to use some self-reflection
in what works for them and what doesn't, to share it, to help people either use what they've
done or stay away from what they've done that didn't work for them either.
I need you here every podcast day.
Because you sum it up in such a better way than I ever are able to do.
And I love what you said.
It feels like there is a bit of a shift in learning for a lot of people.
We know that doing MBAs or long studies is a brilliant thing.
And looking back at case studies is clearly a pathway, so no judgment there.
But the idea in real time that you've got people with real problems...
And real life is always more fascinating to me than anything you can think of in the past
because life throws...
All of us have these challenges.
So to have that group of people, as you just described, Stace, that are in your corner,
understanding, you're totally trusting, totally confidential environment, but can offer a
different way of thinking.
And that's the beauty of diversity, isn't it?
It's the beauty of you and I come from completely different backgrounds, so you're naturally
going to think about things in a different way.
So it's pretty special.
And you're not emotionally connected to your problem.
Yeah.
People that are outside your sphere that aren't connected to the outcome.
It doesn't affect them.
So it's a genuine space.
It's a genuine space for them to give you some feedback that's not going to serve them
in the long term.
So there's no bias.
It's just pure helping, serving each other to be better.
Such a great point to make, Stace.
And I love it because you're right, isn't it?
That unconscious bias.
You might have the best boss in the world who really wants to help you, but they've
got a vested interest in you.
They are there with good reason for wanting you to stay or whatever that bias may be.
Yeah.
Just in your corner.
And I do this a lot, probably to our own detriment sometimes, but I love it because I like throwing
the names out there because hopefully people can see themselves in some of the groups that
you're hosting and facilitating now.
And they are just bright and confidential, so I have no idea of the content.
But Sandy Brondello, the Opals head coach, New York Liberty head coach, seeing her connect
with John Bertrand, who's been on this podcast, who's a legend, Brad Fittler, NRL legend,
Daryl Franklin, who's the chief of staff at Green Bay, Pat Clifton, who's an Australian
guy doing amazing stuff in the NBA.
So it must be fascinating for you, Stace, when you're hosting those groups and seeing some
of the life learnings and hacks that come out of it.
I can see the smile on your face.
It sounds like you just love the wisdom that's shared.
Oh, it is.
It's like when you are a curious person and want to learn all the time, you're in an environment
where you're constantly exposed to high-level thinkers.
And no matter what level they are or what they've achieved, the people that come into
the program want to be better.
And they are high achievers in some form, because they're there to be better leaders
for the people they're leading.
So for me, I mean, what's cooler than sitting in a room listening to people talk about leadership
and what they've done in the past and things that have worked for them and watching people
lean on each other for support?
There's just nothing cooler.
And I mentioned this a little bit before, I'm a bit obsessed with the book I'm reading
at the moment.
One of the surveys that has come out of it.
It's progressed so far, there's a survey in America, that the most responded answer
around the people that you can connect with is Joanne Hari's book, Lost Connections.
And I'm looking forward to reading his next book at the moment, Stolen Focus, which has
been out for a while.
But he talks about most people now say they haven't got one trusted, confident in their
life.
And just how sad that is.
Even historically, the average was three.
And so to not have anyone that you can turn to.
Yeah.
It's sort of diminished in such a way that our whole purpose is about inspiring connections
and creating that world of collaboration and I'm incredibly grateful, Stace, that that's
what you're doing.
Head to elitacollective.com if you want to connect with Stace, book a call with us and
we can tell you more about it.
I want to talk about your business, your own business, Show and Tell Online.
And in preparation for this, I was telling you before we started, I've been listening
to your podcast, Show and Tell Online with Monty, Mel and Stacey.
That is hilarious.
I was laughing all night last night and I said to you before I started, I'm pretty sure
I'm not your target demographic, Stace, but you can see just this incredible bond, you
three great friends of God.
And I said, you're loose.
You say stuff that we could never get away with, but it's a great connection.
Tell us about the passion behind that.
Yeah, really cool.
We started it probably 10, it was 10 years ago with my best mate, Monty.
We've been best friends since we were 14.
And Brooke Campbell-Bays actually, who left the business a few years ago.
We started it 10 years ago as a way to connect women through conversation, organic, raw conversation.
So they felt like they were listening to their girlfriend sitting in a room, talking and-
I felt like I shouldn't have been in that room, by the way.
Yeah.
That was so funny.
But we did it so, parenting young kids is quite lonely too.
And we started it when we first had our children.
So we wanted to give women a way to have those needs met, a friendship, you know, females
need females.
They need that conversation and rawness and honesty.
So that's how it started.
And it's morphed over the years, obviously.
It was originally us having conversations with well-known Australian women on video,
and then it moved into a lot of social media and all these parts, and now it's a thriving
podcast of just sitting.
I'm sitting there waffling on basically, but it is very funny.
We have a really engaged, authentic audience, which is very cool.
It's been an amazing process to learn small business along the way, but to do it with
your best mates is incredible.
And it's brilliant.
I encourage you to check it out.
And that's what I love about, you know, if it's not your world, when you see people connecting
properly and the humor that comes out of it, I was listening to my, she was doing an interview
with Ursula Kahn.
Ursula Carlson, who's a brilliant South African-born comedian, and I'm like, you can't say that.
You cannot actually say that, apparently you can, but it's genius.
It's outstanding.
And then as that led into, so the business part of it is, you know, clearly a lot of,
as you said, you know, loneliness of, you know, watching Beck in our world, you come
home with four kids, more people around you than ever before, but you're more isolated
than ever.
And that need for that sort of connection and then sharing it, it's a brilliant space
and it's been something you've enjoyed.
I've loved it.
Look, it's given me a beautiful platform to learn a lot about small business and how to
do certain things that I never would have learned to do, and to do it when I had small
children at home.
While I was still in an elite environment in sports, I had switched over to coaching.
So I was still coaching Australian teams and doing that in between my retirement.
So to be able to, to work and be stimulated and still learning in small business and
doing things we're really passionate about while also being able to fulfill the sports
side of things and have young children, but to be home with them, to do all the drop offs
and pickups to, you know, yeah, it was hard.
I had to work at nighttime and on weekends when my husband was home, but it was, it was
a beautiful way for me to be present with my children and still be stimulated and create
a business that we were making a difference in people's lives.
We catch up.
And you know, often the parents, you know, they're like, you know, what's going on?
You know, what's going on?
And it's just, it's just a really exciting conversation to start straight away.
And I love it.
And it happens on this podcast all the time as well.
I think a lot of us are united by that.
I mentioned in the, in the opening, you've got three young boys, your leadership as a,
as a mum, I can see the great empathy and care that you've got, but you're pretty tough
too.
How would you describe the parenting style that you bring?
Yeah, it's interesting.
I think I'm probably the most hard on myself in this area because I want them to be, I
just really want them to be happy.
Like I want them to have the skills to be resilient enough to know they can do hard
things and to have the courage to be themselves.
But obviously I, you know, I'm very conscious of always putting him in an environment where
they're proving to themselves, they can do hard things so that as they grow, they're
not afraid of failing and trying things and thinking outside the box and being who they
are.
Um, you know, the day, the days are hard like this.
There's certainly no easy way to parent and three boys are hectic, but I have just sent
my last one to school, which is, you know, a little bit sad, but also liberating at the
same time.
But I have built, structured a life where I have been with them the whole way through,
which I'm incredibly grateful for.
And obviously, you know, my husband and I are a great team and we've, we've built a
life that we intended to.
And we've built a life that we've been with them the whole way through.
Yeah.
And we've been able to do that, which is great.
But you know, parenting has brought to, brought things out in me that I never actually knew
I had.
Like I didn't realize that I was actually quite impatient and quite irritable.
And I do have that, like all of the vices, all of the great things about me are also
my vices, you know, that I want to be achieving all the time.
And you can't, you can't do things when you want to do things when you've got little kids,
like it's.
I don't want to serve them first and then things get cut off and I don't like to start
a task that I can't finish.
So it's all these little things that parenting brings up, but it's probably been the biggest
learning of who I am since I've become a parent has been crazy.
Like I would never have told, I would have said I was someone completely different before
I had kids.
Yeah.
I'm not surprised.
It's, it's the ultimate mirror up, isn't it?
It just, and it's confronting, isn't it?
Yeah.
And I think that's what's brought out that all the time, isn't it?
And it's like, that's brought out something and I'm often going, you know, I'm going to
have to claim that behavioral trait.
That one's probably come from me.
I think, geez, you know, when it comes back at you and you hear it.
But I love these conversations because I still feel like we don't have them enough.
You know, as a father talking to a mother and sharing, it's the sharing economy, which
is again, you know, part of the huge passion for what we're doing with Leader and Leader
Connect is just have more of these conversations because you know, I often think the fact that
you care.
You and Mike are so invested, you know, and they won the lottery, those three boys, they're
just going to have them.
Well, soon find out, won't we?
Well, that's the confronting part, isn't it?
But I know that, you know, all the evidence is in it.
You're going to have your moments, but when you sort of invested as much as that, that's
about as good as you can do, isn't it?
There's going to be all the bumps and challenges along the way, but by being there and as you
said, intentionally carving out your life to make sure you're there, the fact that you
are, I hope because that's been it.
We've tried to do it.
Yeah.
And we've tried to do it.
We've tried to do it.
It's a lot of pressure, isn't it?
Yeah.
Which occasionally go wrong horribly.
We've all been there before.
I didn't know you're a marriage celebrant.
Oh yeah, I am.
Geez, God, I do too many things, don't I?
I, yes, I am.
I, one of my best mates that I grew up with actually asked me to marry them and classic
me thought, well, you know, I'll just do the course.
It's not that simple.
Like it's a full year.
It's legal stuff.
It's all this.
It was ridiculous.
And I abused her for about 12 months through the process of it, but, and yes, ended up
doing it, which has been really great.
And now I mostly do it to, for people that I know and, you know, want it to be a relaxed
environment or, you know, have someone I'm marrying them that they're really comfortable
with.
But that's been really cool too, but it's probably going to slip to the side.
I think, I think I've bitten off more than I can chew.
Well, I can imagine you, you know, being brilliant a lot of things, but particularly that, because
that is an important day and everyone's been.
Yeah.
I've been to the ceremony where the, you know, the priest goes rogue, you know, don't, you
know, I've been to many of those weddings, not the day to talk about footy today.
I know there's a lot of footy people, please don't, but they can't help themselves.
And that, you know, the emotional day, I've seen that nearly spill over from time to time.
You would be absolutely perfect for that.
I'm looking forward to your answer to these questions, Stace, because you're so invested
in, and we are so grateful to, to, to be working with you day to day.
So, you know, these topics really well, but you know, I often think to myself, geez, I'd
find them hard to answer.
So I'm looking forward to hearing what your thoughts are.
Self-leadership, Stace, I can see that written all over you.
What does that mean to you?
Look, I think it means a few things when I think about it.
I think mostly everybody has a set of values that they live by and they can change over
time, I think, depending on what stage of life you're in.
But for me, it's being consistently disciplined in what I put out.
What I put into the world and what values that I attribute to being how I want people
to see me move through the world.
So that's probably one thing.
I think one of the biggest things for self-leadership for me is self-awareness and understanding
how you make people feel is a big one.
And just, you know, whether you're adding value to their lives and value to your own.
And there is something to be said for, you know, having to serve yourself before you
can serve others.
Which is not that easy, like I struggle with that as well, but I think if we, you know,
if I exhibit accountability for the things that I believe in most over time and I'm consistent
with it, then my relationships are really trusted, healthy relationships because people
know what they're going to get.
And I know what I'm going to give.
So for me, I think self-leadership is probably focusing on the things that you value most
and living them every day.
And being self-aware of when you're not.
Yeah.
It's such a brilliant answer, Stacey, and that's what I love about these conversations
because I just learn so much and reflect, so do I, and again, it comes back to so much
of your essence.
And, and one of the things we are trying to spread through this world is that thought
about how do we impact others positively?
Feels like a shift, doesn't it?
Feels like we were taught when we grew up about what you need to do around self-help,
all about self and everything was all about, I need this to have a better life and I need
more.
And I think that as soon as you put your focus a little bit elsewhere on to helping someone
else as you do instinct, you know, from the age of the youngest possible age, there's
a lot more joy in that, isn't there?
It's a stick and it's a learnt skill too, isn't it?
It's something you can learn.
It is a learnt skill, but I think people are happier when they're serving other people.
I do think it's a part of how to be happy in life is to make sure that you're adding
value to other people's lives, even in the smallest of interactions.
And that leads to, you know, you're going to be involved in a lot of different things.
that leads to you know what you do positively impacting others and you know i loved uh you
know listening and doing some homework before today and you could just see the photos of you
with your teammates or with your friends or on the podcast or every environment you're in we see it
every day with you at a leader as well that you live and breathe those values is that what you
think about about the impact you have on others oh darce i think it's probably the thing i think
about the most i think i live in a constant inner dialogue of how do i make them feel then how can i
make sure i'm adding value here and look i i was really lucky that i grew up a lot of things went
right for me i had two very invested parents that basically growth coached me through life
trusted my opinion on pretty much anything i had a coach susa farness who coached me probably 80
in my career
a college coach as well that was really fundamental in in the growth of me as a person but
susa farness in particular had a motto she lived by that is very easy to use as a filter and it's
that nobody cares how much you know until they know how much you care you you can't have a
positive impact on people if they don't think you care about them so for me a lot of the things i
filter through are i just want people to know i actually care about them even if it's in a five
minute conversation i don't care about them i just want people to know i actually care about
them even if it's in a five minute conversation but i think it's also the the importance of
building relationships so strong that they can bear the truth is part of that and to have a
positive impact on people particularly if i'm coaching or leading them is really important that
that foundation is really strong so that we they can be pushed to meet their potential
and that's being able to tell the truth like honesty is having a positive impact particularly
i wouldn't have a positive impact on people if i didn't have a positive impact on them
honest conversation with someone if i hadn't created a foundation though either
but there was also the cost of that is time though to be able to be a great leader and
have a foundation of a strong relationship to have a positive impact the cost of great
leadership is time and it is it's the text it's the check-ins it's all the things that go in
creating that foundation there was also a book i read about 20 years ago and i flipped from
playing in college to coaching and i wasn't ready to flip but my coach was
dying of a brain tumor and had asked me to stay on and coach straight after college so i did
but i did i did a disservice to myself and to the players i think because i was very much in that
state of just do it like as a player i was like what are you doing just go and do the job i don't
get why you can't do it but i was too immature to do it at the time but i read a really great
book from donnie tony di cecco who was the usa women's soccer coach through the mia ham era when
they were changing the face of female sports and the title of the book was the USA women's soccer coach
still what i live by it's called catch them being good and it was just the simple act of
just catch people doing the good things more than what you want them to stop doing so now
if i'm giving feedback or coaching or trying to have an impact on people around me i focus on
telling them what i want to see more of rather than what i want them to stop doing so catch
them being good has been such a huge phrase in my life
but you know one of the things to having a positive impact impact i find myself having
incessant conversations with people about and particularly players about i don't feel
confident right now that's such a funny statement to me but i realized the reason why i never
struggled with that was because i was always in an environment where forgiveness was
around me and i was really cutthroat like to be fair i was a player that was
a see ball get ball didn't matter how i was going to get it i was going to get the ball from
someone but it put my team in at risk sometimes of fouls and situations and but i 95 percent of
my career i was in an environment where forgiveness was instant move on to the next one move on to
next one so it created a space of bravery for me and and forgiveness does create bravery it gives
people the ability to move through something so quickly that they're brave enough to do it again
so i think those few
pillars for me is what i try to stick with when i'm trying to have a positive impact on people
amazing wisdom there stace and i you know i love writing stuff down i love that you know from your
your coach you clearly had a massive impact such a brilliant line that isn't it no one cares how
much you know until they know how much you care it's just such a shift in sport around that you
know i've talked a lot about the era we played in there's none of that it's hierarchical and
you're the weaker where you're strong and you can cope where you can't and you know i think that's
a lot of us saw a bit of craziness in that and so it's such a healthier for you to have that
environment as you said that's there's a bit of good fortune in that isn't it having someone who
whole career college was a lot of discipline but it was a it was family as well but i i was always
in an environment where it was collaborating and care and there was a really strong foundation
underneath and clearly that shaped you and you pass it on and i love that you know catch them
being great it's such a brilliant thought isn't it and and i
see that you know i spent so much time in junior sport with the four kids and
it drives me insane is that the the negative coaching and and people don't know in fairness
they just you know some poor little you know kid misses a kick it's nine and the coach screams at
him and gets him off it's like no that's not you know as you said the celebration of the stuff
that's good but to to sum it up so clearly like that catch them being great celebrate the good
stuff focus less on the mistakes don't matter the snakes don't count at all it's uh
no brilliant um for you to share that i i really appreciate it curiosity is a word that
uh in fact i jumped forward um creating and sharing a vision i want to ask you about stace and
you clearly done that in so many areas of your life how have you gone about that
i've always thought of vision as creating a collective heartbeat within a group
because it's seems like a better foundation for me to work with and i think that's a few
ways you can create a vision but i think
before you can share one you need to co-create one because i've never been able to create a
strong vision or culture without co-creating with the people who are going to action it
so for me it's spending that time to understand why people are there and i think the challenge
of great leadership is everybody's why might be different but you've got to create a purpose and
passion that's quite similar in a way so sitting down and co-creating
a vision that can be seen i think is is one of those things whether it's the values of your team
and what that you want that to look like to the outside world but i think it needs to be a two-way
collaborative experience when you're sharing a vision for it to be actually powerful and actionable
and like i said i think the challenge is creating a cohesive set with people who are there for
different reasons and often it sounds crazy but you could be going to a world cup and my purpose
i could be i want to win a gold medal someone else's might be oh i just like to play with my
mates i don't really care if we win like it's it's bringing those few things together to create
a vision that's people can all live within is the challenge but i think doing that two ways
is the most important way to to bring that to life in in my experience
but and and that's just been us sitting with groups of people and asking them
who they are and why they're doing it and i think that's the challenge
why they're there and what their purpose and passion is and building it together
and as you said before you know showing that you care first regardless of um you know how
different your purpose might be and and and that's been the joy of one of the many joys of
working with you stace is just that you know you get that and you bring that to the table and
you know we've loved uh trying to create and share that vision with you around a leader as we said
before about inspiring those connections and creating a world of collaboration and you know
you're setting a high bar
so i hope we're doing it well enough to to not drive you mad at some uh at some point in time
um curiosity is a common word that we see stace and and it sort of defines a lot of leaders in
the way they think about their learning what does that mean to you oh god sometimes i wish i wasn't
so curious sometimes i fry myself wanting to learn stuff all the time but through through curiosity
and learning i think we give ourselves the capacity to create more and to kind of recreate ourselves
over time as well
but i also think it's really hard for me to be interesting and passionate and empowering and
um without constantly learning like to be able to have more conversations i mean i know when me and
you get together we have quite deep conversations like we go straight to things because we're always
living in a space where we're learning and wanting to what do you think about this what do you think
about that but i think stimulating my own growth allows me a greater opportunity to be able to be
a better opportunity to add value to people's lives and i i do live in a constant state where
i want to learn um and like i said before i have lived in a like i almost do research projects
through the learning sometimes about you know what the difference between good and great is and
what all those little obstacles are that people face but i think without it i would be really
boring i doubt it stay so i think that would be a good thing to do but i think it's a good thing to
be a very hard thing to call you boring at any point in time but no i love how you you frame
that again i had this conversation with someone yesterday and i talk about you know just how
privileged it is to sit down and talk to to you and and everyone in this format i've loved every
bit of it so what do you do with all those notes and i had to say quite often nothing but it's
shaping it's shaping and reinforcing you go your language today reinforces so many things that you
and i want to do better and i think that's an interesting conversation because you can jump
around with curiosity can't i'm all in on whatever it is you know i'm going to change tomorrow and i'm
going to do another course and you can hop from one thing to the next and and you know curiosity
is brilliant but do you sort of i think you get at world states where you know your foundations
are who you are and the curiosity layers and and you're open to it but there is a gap between that
and not really knowing who you are at the same time is that is that fair yeah i think it's fair
i do think it's fair but i think the most important thing is grabbing onto the things
that you connect with the most that are actually able you're able to bring to life and not everyone
can do everything they read even if they connect to it and not everyone has a platform to do it
either but i think it's it is important to be curious about things because there's a lot of
great stuff out there to be curious about for sure communicating uh with clarity and you do that
incredibly well and and as i said i you know i found myself um flying the wall on the podcast
last night watching that and and just seeing you with your mates uh you know made me smile because
you know you've got your own language which is brilliant is that you always do when you have
those close friendships but is it something that you've thought about in your sporting world your
business world communicating with clarity all the time particularly when you're coaching i think
in in sports and in other areas as well i think
important thing for me is getting to know people well enough to know how they like to be
communicated with because people are different now like it's not on a phone or face to face
some people don't like that it might be you know i remember you know leading players in this team
that needed me to go straight at them between the eyes just be better this isn't good enough
but then another person might need a different form of communication of let me give a positivity
first and then so it's i think it's about knowing how people want to receive communication
and make sure that's two-way i don't i don't think it can't it can't be one way um so learning
about the language they respond to best i think is important there but for me it's i just lean
on the truth always i always lean on the truth because if i would never want someone to wonder
if what i said was true or not or if i was just saying it to make them feel good but that goes
back to building relationships so strong they can bear the truth i think
that that's one of the most important things i lean on is truth i think for probably two hacks i've
had that i use on the daily almost is or particularly when i was doing you know
pre-game speech half-time you know even in meetings delivering things in meetings whatever
it was is delivery over content i used to spend so much time on the content i was delivering to
the team like my half-time speech my pre-game speech my this my that instead of
how i was delivering it to them and that's like passion body language all those things that go
into it is the cell i was watching literally darcy yesterday watching kevin hart talk about green
super powder but he was so um in great like i was so engrossed in what he was saying because of the
way he was telling the story yeah that i was like i need to buy that i didn't even hear what it was
about yeah it was just so captivating and i think we i i know i have spent way too much time on the
content and not enough time on delivery so when when i heard that i was like oh this is this is
what i need obviously the content needs to be good still but people are watching how you're giving it
to them more than what you're saying and look you know there's the little things like i don't give
more than three things in a half time or you know i don't give my kids more than one thing to do at
a time you know there's little ways to be clear and it's by not over speaking not over coaching
but also you know to just deliver something with a little bit of gusto and it kind of goes a long way
great advice all around um collaboration how important has that been for you oh god i think
collaboration is everything i think about getting my kids to school in the morning with collaboration
like well they're probably not collaborating but i think to be a great collaborator you need to be
self-aware and and it goes back to being aware of what if you're adding value to someone and one of
the one of the key mantras i live by in this space is to be self-aware and to be self-aware
is do i need to add value to that person's thought or do i need to shut up and that's
collaborating it's me understanding if i keep adding to someone's thought i'm going to steal
their thoughts not their thought anymore that's not collaborating so one of those that's one of
the the things um that i cling to for sure when i'm trying to collaborate with people
but i i do everything's a dance isn't it like us right now everything every conversation
is reading the room trying to collaborate in a way that make people feel really good
i know at a leader we use a quote in our collaboration
um dimension when we're talking about it and it's a benjamin franklin quote and matt
wadowitz actually uses it all the time too and it's called tell me and i forget teach me and i
remember involve me and i learn and it's a really great reminder of involving people in the process
and collaborating with them is how people learn best rather than just being told what to do and
we often skip those steps i think so there's some obviously some really great
um ways to collaborate but i think it is just god for me it's just knowing when to add value and
when to shut up i think you've got a great balance and a great perspective and a great way of um
of expressing exactly what you mean states it's uh it's great listening to it again who's been
the greatest leader in your life geez this is a loaded question actually um i think i've grabbed
from a million different places darth yeah i think you know my dad was the one who started
the it's just a game get over it so he gave me that message very young it's just a game no one
didn't die just play the game go home forget about it yeah and it was a massive gift to be able to
go hard walk off the pitch and be done to be able to switch off um and he he's a he's a unit like he
was rough you know he he played lacrosse too he played lacrosse and dirt biking footy got injured
you know he was an animal
he's very injured very young but built like a very you know i was i'm built like him the
physicality of being able to put your body through a lot comes from your dad yeah but he gave you
that gift of perspective as well yeah he just never understood why people were just hanging
on to stuff it's just a game you know and it served me through my whole life yeah my mom was
probably the relationship she grew up with disability she was born with spina bifida
she had the ability to build relationships and you know have conversations and she's a beautiful
friend and um she made me uh appreciate my body i was you know built like a boy in a way i was
didn't want to wear singlets because my muscles were out i didn't and she was always the one that
was like what do you want your body in your body's performing for you yeah so just just the great
messaging from someone who couldn't do what i could do um and then i think probably another
one's my husband he's i've never met anyone that's got less ego than him everything's factored out
everything's perspective he sees a situation reads a situation just for what it is yeah
without any emotional connection to it which is an interesting skill so probably him and then
susa farness was probably my next most profound one we call her mally um she died obviously like
i said before two two years ago suddenly during a campaign but you know she she was the glue that
held australian lacrosse together the most decorated player and coach of all time and
she relentlessly
gave herself to the sport and i think she taught me what culture was how to build culture and what
it took and how much effort and how much time so she's the gift that keeps on giving i still go
back to jesus what would she do here what would she say there and all those things an epic
storyteller um and we're now living through her you know keeping her legacy alive with the suze
safanas foundation which her her got her dream was to not ever have finances involved in bringing
the best team together for australian women's lacrosse
and that foundation was um for the first time in the last world cup was fully funded because of her
foundation and her family's done a beautiful job of doing that so we're keeping that alive that way
as best we can yeah what a brilliant yeah amazing stuff isn't it to have that in your life isn't to
have a mum and dad i love people who reference their parents who are lucky enough to and i feel
exactly the same way and then as you said before to have that influence in your life and uh and a
partner mike is uh you know as um as brilliant as it's been and i think it's going to be a great
sounds as well is a real gift so people that want to support sport and and women's lacrosse how do
you get involved in the foundation oh the foundation is obviously you can google suze
foundation to to um do it in any way you can whether it's just sharing or um donating whatever
that is i think lacrosse in general the exciting thing is where june july we'll find out for certain
if it's in the 2028 olympics in la which is pretty massive pretty massive and looking pretty good
massive game yeah com games 2030 is pretty much locked in yeah uh so i think for us it's just that
putting that time into the grassroots of getting it in schools and getting in front of people
there is clubs around the country obviously but it's um we're in the process of building to
now get into the it's a different format the games are different at olympics they've moved
it into more of a basketball style bit smaller a bit faster um so so that's interesting but we're
heading for big things in the future so i think it's a great thing to do and i think it's a great
i think so there's and there's a lot of opportunity in lacrosse with you know overseas scholarships
and you know you get country state trips all those sorts of things so it's an exciting time for the
sports are in a pretty pretty big building phase not beyond you to come out and play in los angeles
in 2028 the one thing you haven't done playing olympics um how good for for lacrosse and
there's going to be a massive result all around if you collaborate with anyone stays in
diverse areas of your life and we love we're so uh
uh rap that we get to collaborate with you but is there any one or anything that springs to mind
god this is a really hard question i didn't prepare for i do think i get to like collaborating
with you guys at elita has been an incredibly enriching experience for me there's probably a
few i'd be really interested to sit in a room with george mumford have you heard of george
i don't know george mumford he he wrote a book called the mindful athlete he was the right-hand
man to phil jackson in the era oh yes sorry yes yes and
was probably the first one to introduce mindfulness and you know how to create how to
develop your mind to be strong enough to withstand high performance challenge and all the critical
thoughts that come through so i'd be i wouldn't even need to talk to him i think i'd just like
to sit in the room and watch him actually interact with people to see how he gets them to perform in
a different way so probably him oh god there's a million to ask i couldn't even come up with him
all but i do think about him and his influence on on phil jackson as well and a lot of people around
the world have clearly watched the last dance and you got a look at phil jackson in that era and
one of my kids um young will was watching again i sat down the couch and i you know i don't normally
watch things twice too often but just taken by phil jackson and clearly um george mumford was
had a huge impact and he was big into spirituality phil jackson just the way that he was
and you know robin's going off the reservation mid you know playoffs you know doing world
wrestling you know events and coaches in that era just wouldn't they would have exploded and
and the press were like you know he's ruining your playoff series he's disrupting and phil
jackson just calmly said no he's not but i feel like he's ruining yours you know and i was like
it just took the air out of the well don't worry about it he's doing his role like
so ahead of uh ahead of their time in in every sense stay so i
when we catch up because these conversations are pretty much where we go to straight away
but to sit down and do it formally and you know matt and i eight years ago um you know to work
you know with my oldest friend uh matt is just an incredible person and then to have you on board
every day matt and i just think how lucky we are to have found you our big fear is that you know
we're gonna we're gonna cook you with so many things that we we want to do with you so let us
know um you know later connect something that we're really sort of passionate about what it's
and you're right at the forefront of that and you know i will go the gratuitous plug again if you
want to connect with stacy connect with us at the leader check us out we're really passionate about
it doesn't matter what your background what you're doing you know we know that there's a space that's
um you know we're really passionate about finding that for everyone that is out there it's really
exciting and uh great to sit down with you and spend some time thanks again you too darce thanks
for having me empowering leaders was presented by me luke darcy produced by ed gooden the sound
design by matt curry
start your leadership journey i encourage you to go to elitacollective.com
take our empowering leaders indicator tool and understand the impact you have
on your environment join us at elita to learn lead and collaborate