Being a leader for your children is one of the most important things we can do in life.
But how do you know if you're doing a good job and what values are we imparting on them?
G'day, it's Luke Darcy.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership both on and off the field has been a lifelong passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective.
And I've had the privilege of working with thousands of leaders in education, sport, industry and the arts
that have helped shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
I was joined by Steve Bidulph, the author of many amazing books, including Raising Boys and his latest Fully Human,
to discuss how we can learn self-awareness, not missing out on opportunities and looking at masculinity
from then to now.
So Steve is one of the world's best-known parent educators, a psychologist for over 30 years
and the best-selling author of many books, including The Secret of Happy Children, Raising Boys,
The New Manhood, 10 Things Girls Need Most, amongst many others.
His latest book, Fully Human, of Using Your Mind, is like his other books, simply brilliant.
Couldn't recommend it more highly.
Steve's books are in over 4 million homes and have been translated in 31 languages.
Steve also has led and funded a five-year human rights initiative.
The CivX Memorial Project, Taking a Stand Against the Treatment of Asylum Seekers, Seekers Arriving by Sea.
He's also a patron of the Australian Religious Response to Climate Change.
And on any measure, it is an extraordinary life of leadership.
And Steve Bidulph joins me.
Great to catch up with you, Steve.
Thanks for your time.
Hi, Luke, and hello to everybody listening.
Steve, I probably wanted to start at the beginning for you.
And I have heard you talk about this, but you were born in Yorkshire in the 1950s.
And I've heard you describe that a few times as, well, potentially the capital of bad parenting.
Can I ask why?
Yes, well, the world capital of negative parenting, I think, was what it was.
And yeah, I mean, Yorkshire is a really, people are lovely and very warm-hearted.
But in those days, kids just got clobbered for everything.
And also, it was normal to tell you that you were no use.
And so my dad would call me.
Which I thought was some kind of monkey.
But it was actually a halfpennyworth or something.
And even when I came to live in Launceston in Tassie, where I live now, it was very familiar because it was a blue-collar town.
Everyone worked in the mill.
And people loved their kids, but they just called them, you know, you waste of space, you know, you're a piece of shit, you're no use.
That was how people talked to, like, two-year-olds.
And they didn't mean it.
Kids didn't know.
And so we got a bit interested in maybe we could change that.
Maybe it could go a bit better than that.
Did you look back, Steve, and think that that maybe inspired your life in this space?
Because you are credited rightly with changing the language of parenting for certainly many millions in Australia and around the world.
Do you think your reflection on your own upbringing had a bit to do with that?
Look, it might have.
You never really know what's going to work out.
But I had a really nice dad.
And my dad could, he would play with us kids.
And he was part of this thing where you call the football pools, where you would take these football kind of predicting gambling sort of thing around.
And he would take them out for our whole neighbourhood.
And so I'd walk with him at night time while he's delivering all these footy forms to people's houses.
And he'd hold my hand.
And he was a huge guy, Luke.
He was 6 foot 11 tall.
Wow.
Picture that.
So I could barely reach his hand.
You know, I had to kind of lean up.
And I'm 6 foot 4.
But he was the sort of dad that gets you on his knee and, you know, bounce you up and down.
Whereas my mum was a bit more posh and she was a bit more, she was, you know, kind.
But she wasn't into cuddles.
We had to teach her how to, you know, when we were growing up, we had to teach her how to do a hug.
She finally got to like it and relax a bit.
But in those days, people didn't cuddle kids very much.
It's amazing how far we've come.
But yeah.
And so I hope I've helped that recovery.
Yeah.
Well, I really want to delve into that certainly across the course of this chat about parenting and your influence on that.
I've just got this picture of a 6 foot 11 door-to-door salesman effectively in Yorkshire in the 1950s.
I mean, that is an enormous height in 2021.
But he must have been a literal giant.
Yes.
And he was a very shy man.
And when he was in his last couple of years, he was a very shy man.
A couple of weeks of his life, I remember he was in hospital and I was able to stay in the hospital with him, which was really great.
And one day he told me this story.
He said, two days after you were born, he said, when we got home, I put you in the pram.
I thought your mum looked a bit tired and exhausted.
I'll put you in the pram and I'll take you for a walk down the street.
And so little sort of three-day-old Steve bit off in the pram and this huge guy.
And he went around the corner into the high street where all the shops and everything were in this little rough little town in Yorkshire.
And he said, little kids started running behind him and calling names, calling out stuff.
And even the adults were looking at him like, looking like scowling.
They were scowling at him.
And dad was on a lot of morphine when he told me this story and he was a little bit out of it.
And he just sort of went quiet.
And I thought, oh, he's just kind of.
You know, going back into the morphine.
And, but just to check, I said, dad, what, what were the kids, what were the kids calling out?
What were they saying?
And he said, your dad's your mum.
And so they were kind of jeering at him for pushing a pram.
And it was just unknown in the 1950s for guys to do anything to do with babies.
And because he was very shy, he told me he just ducked down a little alleyway.
And he took a.
He took a shortcut and got, just went straight home again.
He just couldn't, couldn't hack it being out there.
And this was one of the last things that he ever told me.
And I sort of took on that.
He was kind of saying, look, as dads in the 20th century, we, we really wanted to be hands-on dads.
You know, we really wanted to have be with our kids, but it kind of wasn't, he wasn't allowed.
And today, Luke, your generation of dads, you go down the street, we're pushing the stroller.
Nobody even turns a hair.
Um, so we, we, that's a revolution.
We we've changed that and it's just, just one of the best things.
Yeah.
Amazing story, isn't it?
Again, you know, to confront a six foot 11 father and, uh, even a shy man to, to have that.
I'm gonna find that just a, just a stunning, isn't as a, as a, probably a 21st century dad, you think of, you know, we've, uh, carried the kids everywhere and, and benefited from this change that you've had an enormous amount to, to do.
I want to jump from there, Steve, and talk about one of your latest themes.
And, and, and the term you use is super sense.
And on this podcast, we've been talking to a lot of leaders and it is a common theme that is coming up.
I, I think of Kylie Watson Wheeler who runs Disney, and she spoke a lot about her best decisions have always come when she's tapped into that intuition or that gut instinct.
And you, you take that theme a little bit further and you say super sense is actually a little bit more than that.
And, you know, I love the story that you used to, to describe it with, uh, the story of, uh, of Andy Llewellyn.
You, you're able to share that with us.
Yes.
Um, for sure.
And just so for your listeners to understand super sense is, is the name that I use for what psychologists and cognitive, whatever cognitive science calls parallel processing.
And it's the other side of your brain, which, um, doesn't talk.
We think with a little bit at the front of our left side of our brain, but the right side of our brain is a big silent computer.
And it, what it does is it takes in everything around us and it looks for what doesn't fit.
And Andy was a patient of mine long ago in the 1980s.
And she was a young mom and she was also a GP doctor, and she was.
In a car park in the middle of the day and a young man called out to her.
And she was by herself just coming back from having lunch with friends and, and he was well dressed the head of suit on, and he was a fair way away still.
And he was, she couldn't hear what he was calling them, but he, he sort of like, he wanted help with something.
He lost his.
phone or something like that and she was just on the brink of like putting her bags down and going
across to see what what he needed when she got this little kind of clinch in the bottom of her
belly in a bit of her stomach and and she just kind of had like a little mini panic attack
within like a microsecond she just jumped in her car locked the doors and skidded out of there
just got out of there thinking to herself you know what's what was that about you know the
poor guy she could see the guy in her rearview mirror you know so just standing there looking
kind of stunned and she got home she put it out of her mind that night the kids are in bed she
turned on the nine o'clock news a woman had been assaulted in the car park of her train station
by that young man and luckily he'd been interrupted and caught but it had happened
minutes after she'd been there and her husband
found her sobbing on the couch because she just realized she almost could have been killed and also
the complicated thing that your listeners will understand that because she didn't someone else did
um so it's called survivor guilt and but putting back her mental health she came she had a lot of
post-traumatic stress kind of things and she didn't just get back to normal she got past normal
what we realized was she'd been she was had an acutely aware of um intuitive gut feelings
that were able to literally save her life and the thing is that why i wrote about this and i gave it
the name super sense in the book is that everyone's got this and it's going all the time and so it
doesn't have to be a big dramatic emergency it's going in everyone listening to this right now it's
um giving you an emotional response to what i'm saying and what's going on it's not always
correct it's not always right but it's always got something to say and whenever you're faced
with a decision or a choice it's like this there's a whole supercomputer just sitting there
willing to give you a bit of a kick along if you want to have a listen you don't have to
take it on but if why waste that you know does that make sense luke it does yeah absolutely
resonates with me i think all the best decisions i've ever made in my life
and have always been on this deeper sense isn't it you don't know why but when you're
compelled to do something or the best work choices or you know desperate as a young
kid growing up to play sport for a living and you really could feel that you know tapping in and
then you know likewise the work in the media was coming from a really place i couldn't even
describe that i wanted to do it you know there was some links to my dad and and the work that
he did as well but you're right i think it feels like a lost art though steve i feel like there's
now and so much distraction from our phones and so much direct distraction from content we've
it's a timely reminder that that's there and it's not always right but it's not a bad place to start
yes and you're right it does you do have to kind of go quiet for a minute or so just to listen to
it and and if people are listening it the way you do it is you just go down the middle of your body
and it's it's it's it's kind of it's quite amazing it's called the vegas nerve and it goes right down
from your brain down the front of your body it wraps around your
lungs and your heart and down into your intestines and it's very important in sports people as well
to have this awareness they're coming back and so so if you go down in your gut there's kind of like
little movements and twitches and maybe it's contracting a little bit or it's opening up a
little bit it's a bit like the weather there's always some weather down there and if you just
listen to it you think oh you know i'm just talking to this person who's got this business
um something in my stomach just turned over sideways down there and i don't know what that
is but i don't think i'm going to sign on this dotted line right now you know and and you go
away and you have a think about it and after a couple of hours it just comes to you you know
this doesn't add up you know if i look at this and this but the thing is your super sense is already
there it knows it and and and then you you know like when you chose to move into doing media work
you go and you do your homework and you go and you get the information um but in your heart you
already knew that was what you were going to do and and the two things together is what makes you
strong yeah and i love the link to something else that you've also uh written in the book
there's a line that really jumped out at me and it's i'll read it back the idea that a lack of
self-awareness is the most crippling disability a human can have and i the question for me
on the back of that is can you learn self-awareness oh yes
um i mean it's it put it bluntly if assholes just don't know that they're assholes you know
otherwise they just wouldn't be and um um and we've done a lot of work in men's groups and um
and this idea when i wrote a book called manhood about maybe nearly 20 years ago now but still
around and one of the ideas in the book was you need a men's group um and it's not um you it might
include your regular mates but um it's kind of a it's a it's a it's a it's a it's a it's a it's a
a place where you just talk honestly about your life and you talk from the heart and after some of
the men's groups that started from a result of that book are still going now people have been
meeting like once a week or once a fortnight with the same guys for for 20 years and so given how
busy we all are they must be getting something out of it and i think what it is is that people
talk straight and they'll say things to you and and and you'll just kind of like
burn with you know that's not true you know and they'll sort of sit and wait until you say is it
you know am i am i that bad and they'll say well you look you're on your fourth marriage you know
we we've met several of those wives they seem pretty all right to us you know maybe the problem
is you mervin you know and um and we can of course we can we can learn and otherwise where would you
be and and i'm i was lucky i i was quite socially challenged as a
as a kid i i'm quite a long way along the autism spectrum and i'm i married someone who was very
warm-hearted and if if if you're a bit autistic not very good in the heart department and you
marry someone who's very kind and and emotionally intelligent so it's a great team and and now
my wife's name is sharon and it's like she's in my head the whole time and even if i go against
what she would recommend i'm acutely aware you know i'm on my
own you know i'm out on the on thin ice and um and so i learned early on that i was quite often
my judgment as a dad was often wrong um and she would tell me as soon as we got home or we got to
somewhere you know she didn't embarrass me in the middle of it all but she'd say you know you really
got that wrong you know you were you were talking too loud you know and it wasn't their fault or
something like that and i just decided not to bother with being an ego you know part of
jumps up to say you know that's not true they just you know don't give me that i just learned
to not do that because i'd rather be a happy idiot than a one that just stuffs up all the time
and it is a bit hard to take feedback but it's just so much easier and then you know this is
this podcast is about leadership and if you're a good leader you'll listen to your team you know
and and you you hire the best people you hire people smarter than you and and then you listen
to them so much for me to jump into there steven i want to come back to uh to the autism spectrum
with you in a moment and and also you know your 42 year i think plus relationship with uh with
sharon and and that conversation has come up a lot a lot of the ladies we speak to talk about
feedback as a gift you know and giving and receiving feedback as a gift sally cap the lord
mayor of melbourne i think that was exactly her quote you know to give it as a gift to receive
it is a gift even though we often squirm and don't like it but i think just picking up on part of what
you said and on the book manhood and the influence that had on men's groups what a great legacy for a
start but also i think part of your life work feels have been around the topic of of getting
masculinity right and and you know there's another great line that you have for the world to survive
we need to get masculinity right and uh you also you know shared a really another personal story
that i thought was irrelevant of a friend growing up who who took their own life can you can you
speak about that in the context of masculinity and what you feel we need to do i've had a
a very useful kind of life experience because i work with large groups of people nearly all the
time so i would often find myself with about 200 mums for the day running a seminar with 200 women
and there was a thing i would do i'd ask them to um design the perfect man and usually i do
this straight after lunch and and they'd be a bit sort of sort of buzzy and and um and and i say
got a big whiteboard here you call out the qualities of the perfect man and there'd be the
couple of ribald comments to start with you have to get those out of the way um but then they would
get very earnest and and they start calling out things like you know kind and loving and open
hearted and reliable and trustworthy and strong and you could tell in look in the way that they
were speaking out
and looking at people's faces that they were describing some of the things that they didn't
have in the men in their life you know a woman says reliable you know like that's an issue for
her and i'd cover the board with these and then i'd do this trick which i was they were the words
were coming i was putting some on the left and some on the right side of the board without
explaining why and what it was was that actually there are two completely separate groups
qualities so loving and kind and patient and fun those are kind of what you could call heart
qualities um it definitely you know everyone wants the men around them to have a good heart
but that isn't enough you also need the backbone qualities and by backbone you mean true to their
word they'll hang in when it gets tough you know if the wife gets gets sick and struggles with
health for a year you know if the wife gets sick and struggles with health for a year you know
or so he doesn't just bugger off with somebody else and if they say they'll do something they do
it and so you have to have a heart and backbone and if you if people listening to this um if you
think of the men you know you'll know some men who've got loads of heart really warm really
affectionate just can't count on them you know maybe it's a problem with alcohol or something
but they just they're not staunch and and there'll be men who are very strong and very trustworthy
but they're just boring as whatever because they can't talk about their feelings and and
they don't kind of get close to their kids and things like that and so it's the combination
that works i was always warm but i had to learn backbone 1950 style of man which is still around
um often running large organizations emotionally their wives would tell me this and she said he's
a good man you know but you can hear in that tone he was a good man
but you know it's like being married to a log of wood he's got no spark and um you know it's going
to bed with a log of wood it's not much fun and so the kind of masculinity that we're wanting to build
today and which is you know i can see in you and in your generation there's no doubt of this
um you're affectionate if you if you're sad you'll say i'm sad if you're scared you say
jeez i was scared you know remember that that surfer that was nearly
shark a couple of years ago forget his name mick fanning yeah i mean that's right mick and
um and his mates were like running into the water and they interviewed one of his when
he finally came into view again and he was still on his board his best friend said oh you know
jeez i was just i was scared witless you know i've lost my mate yeah and he just said that
straight to camera 30 years ago he wouldn't have done that he wouldn't have admitted that he had
you know that he loved his his best mate and what you know was scared for him
and so that kind of man is the reason that's good is that the feelings are out there and they're
gone and this is one of the things in the new book that emotions are meant to be out there and they
go um if they don't you know and this is why we hate it when people used to get redeployed to
afghanistan and things like that is it adds up and you get this cumulative backlog of emotion
and that's the kind of man who who one day
just just explodes and there'll be people listening to this who had a dad like that he would
he would build up over weeks and weeks and weeks of frustration with things and then he would just
blow and we know punch walls and hit people and and and it's just terrifying and so the reason
we want open-heartedness is so that you know where you stand and it's no big drama you know
everyone's sad because grandma died and everyone's just sad and gradually come out of that and it's
not it's just normal it's does that make sense yeah absolutely it's a great story of of backbone
and heart isn't it the mick fanning story as you said it's your mates jumping in and swing towards
a shark to save your mate without even thinking about it but at the same time being able to say
i was terrified you know and and you're right it's it was when you think of it in that way it uh it
is a great story and and and you're right i'm
i think our generation have learned that not small part to some of your thoughts i think as
well and now it's expected steve now that the the landscapes change you know for males and area it's
it's uh if you're not hands-on and you're not you know maybe i'm being a bit naive in the circles
that perhaps i talk about and perhaps it is naive because i did maybe want to jump from there
to another incredible study that that really had a profound effect on me when i when i read it
steve and and you talked about a study in the 1990s from u.s health insurer and and an amazing
way of doing that and and and and and and and and and and and and and and and and and and and and
link between adverse child experiences which i think you probably need to explain just how
significant they are at some level and then health outcomes for life and look i was shocked
really to to hear that sort of evidence it's uh a profound uh a profound study can you share it
with us yes this is something that i was blown away by when i came across it it's now quite
well known in psychology that the kaiser health insurance company is an enormous health insurance
company in this i think it's probably the biggest and they set up some some weight loss programs
across the country because they want if people lose weight they stay fit and then they don't
need healthy they don't need all these health bills and so they enrolled tens of thousands of
people and then about half the people had dropped out of the program after about a month and so it
was a multi-million dollar program and it looked like it was failing nobody was staying the distance
and so they did a survey of
the people who dropped out and because it was anonymous and just maybe because the people
doing the study just thought let's have a go at this they asked them a lot of questions like
um were you ever sexually abused as a child and and and things like that or did you know did you
have a parent who died or a dad did you know did anyone drink did anyone commit suicide in your
family pretty personal questions they discovered a very high correlation of child sexual abuse
i forget the exact incidence but in that population it was something like 60 of the people
and now about this time i was working training psychologists uh here in tasmania in the in the
1980s and 90s and we were discovering the same thing that amongst our trainees probably two
thirds of the women and maybe a quarter of the men had been and these were people who were
qualified social workers and psychiatrists and things like that had been sexually abused
as children and so this very widespread thing and and so they created this scale there's these 10
questions and they're in the book and it's really good to go through the scale did people hit you
when you were growing up um were you were you ever neglected like you didn't have enough to eat or
warm clothes and things did anyone go to prison in your family um and so pretty severe things
and 60 of everyone in the normal population
is one of those um and something like 38 has got two of those now those are quite severe things
and so what we say in the book is basically being having a traumatic childhood
is normal and we were so bad at parenting in the 20th century families were so hammered by all the
wars and everything a normal happy relaxed childhood is really unusual and my wife sharon
had four
had four of those 10 items in her family and um and what they were interested in was of course
there was terrible health consequences of that people tended to get cancer three times more
likely in that category um now some of that was smoking and drinking but even when they
controlled for that it was just the sheer kind of long-term stress that was written into their
bodies yeah what what uh you know horrific data to extract and i suppose uh as you said the lifelong
health consequences of that were terrible health consequences of that people tended to get cancer
and again it leads to me using that lens through through parenting and you know you've written
you know so many books about raising boys raising girls i suppose it's a it's a simple question that
may not be that easy to answer on the back of last time i spoke to you i spoke to you about
parenting guilt for me which is trying to get the balance right wanting to be around and maybe being
at work longer than you expected and you missed the kids one night and you said let yourself off
the hook you know that the fact that you care and think about that is actually you know a positive
you know you're saying that's actually uncommon in some ways in the in the past what is the art of
being a good parent then in your mind the one that that we've already been talking about which is
kids have this built-in thing that the the right side of their brain is organized to read facial
expressions and even a little baby newborn prem baby in a in a humidity crib they study a little
premature baby mom and dad come to look in through the window and they're like oh my god i'm going to
the glass you can picture that moment they're like this fish tank with a little kitty in the
middle and mom and dad looking either side they and they track the baby's eye movements
the baby looks from mom's face to dad's face back to mom's face again what's it doing it's
picking up the emotional tone of the of the adults you know we say a baby doesn't care if
they're born in a a mansion or in a tin hut they don't care about that but they really care about
is mom and dad love each other and mom and dad love me because that's what their survival depends
on and so so they read our faces and if if we're my daughter used to say my daughter's a young
professional now but when she was a teenager she would say where are you you know you you your
body's here where's your brain because she was very sensitive to the fact that i i was a stressed
out you know rush about sort of guy and and so i'd be you know it's kind of you're right quality
time with kids you know this terrible illusion we have this you're right we'll do quality time now
you know um my brain's sort of caught back with something that went wrong earlier in the day and
something someone said on social media or something i had to do in a couple of days time and i wasn't
present and present you know you didn't this is how
this is what love is you know you know someone loves you when you have their absolute full
attention and the trick of this is very interesting this is why i wrote fully human all around this
topic that you can't be present with someone else unless you're present with yourself and so the
first step is going down the middle of your body checking out where am i at you know and what that
will do is it'll come
you down or or it'll make you notice how you're not calm like we have a a reflex um luke that was
comes from when the from the stone age which was our main enemies when we were kind of big apes
getting around was animals that would go for the jugular you know there would be tiger cats and
whatever and they would always go for the neck because that's the best place you're going to
bring down a prey animal you grab them by the by the
neck so we have a reflex where our shoulders come up around our side of our neck people
this thing can't see this but your picture your shoulders come up around your ears like that and
that's a stress reaction and so if if you're stressed you're most often you'll feel it in
your shoulders and in fact your shoulders will start to ride higher and higher up
sort of like you're going to try and block your ears with your shoulders and if you if you check
out your body you know say you get home and you're sitting down with your kids you go
down in your body even in the car just walking up the driveway and you'll notice wow you know
my shoulders are really uptight and and my my breathing's really fast and and as you notice
that this is the beautiful thing about it will automatically start to self-regulate
and even hear me then just do a breath as i thought about it you know like ah
and and you'll start to calm down and so when you look in your kids eyes they'll see dad's really in
there you know and and and and and and and and and and and and and and and and and and and and
the lights are on the occupant is home and so they'll feel calmed down by your presence and
that you that they're a priority for you that's all you have to do you know and the next thing
they'll be wanting to play in the backyard or they'll be wanting to tell you that something
happened at school but you're already there they feel loved they feel attended to um and we're in
society that wants to steal our time
to get you know we don't have to fight tiger cats anymore we got to get our sword or our spear and
fight off time thieves yeah so many great stories to tell us thinking of a study quite another quite
horrific state i think in the 1920s in an orphanage where they did that experiment with
babies that they hugged and cared for and looked in the eyes and gave attention to and the other
group they literally didn't look at they fed them they kept them warm and they put them back
down and they were able to get them back and they were able to get them back and they were able to
but gave no attention and no and those babies literally started to die within a within a few
years it was that dramatic that clearly they had to stop the experiment but it was weeks before
you know as you said the survival depends on on that that love and that attention which we all
get distracted from don't we in our lives we're there but we're sitting on our phone or we're
sitting next to one of our kids but we're not you know being present as you said it was a
great way to break it down there's another passage that i
i loved and i just loved but also wanted to get your thoughts on and i might read it back to you
if that's okay um to look at the basic facts you're right the 40 rate of marriage breakdowns
the seemingly intractable problem of family violence the recent epidemic of anxiety in young
people growing suicide problem even among prosperous and successful people all these
things shout to us that something is amiss if only one in 50 people had a psychiatric illness
it would be plausible to blame your brain or a chemical imbalance balance but the figure is one
in five or more
we have to look at other explanations that the problem is not with our brain or our bodies but
the way we live so what is the problem steve with the way that we live okay well i think
there's a couple of things and and this is on my website i put this like a banner across the top
this quote that um that hurry is the enemy of love and that when we're rushing say if you're
in a family or if you're in a family and you're in a family and you're in a family and you're
working as a team or even if it's an organization and people working as a team
if you're in a hurry then the little fine-tuned connections don't quite work um you but if it's
a family say anyone of your kids says something and and there isn't really time to pick up on
what they said it sets off a little something ticking in your body but you there wasn't time
to follow it up you know and then next time you see them it's you know it's not quite the
opportunity and and then six months down the track there's this
huge problem that happens with them because let's say they've punched somebody at school
or stolen something or um in trouble with with the police or something like that and
it turns out that that's made up of you know 20 little missed opportunities and so you know the
big nightmare for corporate parents and a lot of parents listening to this is is very high
incidence of drug addiction and drug abuse in affluent um kids um and there's only one
of um drug addiction that we know of one one risk factor that holds up and it's got nothing to do
with income nothing to do with which suburb you live in or who your friends are it's lack of
parental time and so we work hard you know to send our kids to good schools or to to have
opportunities and take them on fantastic holidays and get them good teeth you know and things like
that um if that all doesn't really stand up very well if they end up in a in a
house somewhere or or taking heroin down the cross or something and so in term in sheer investment
terms it is better if you know once a week you take your teenage daughter out for a coffee
and you know on a sunday morning and have have pancakes and coffee and have a chat to her
that you and your son go camping or vice versa these and and um and have the time to unpack
um how are we going husbands and wives have these conversations how are we going that is is is our
life the way we planned it now there's a single example of this i really love because i always
i was aware of the brevity of time which is that tens of thousands of people read in one of my
books the idea of taking a year off and going around australia in a four-wheel drive that
the middle part of high school is a complete waste of time
kids and i have this on on the authority of seriously important school principals
mid-secondary school is a waste of time but even if they're in primary it's it's um take a year
off as a family and go and do something so you have so you and you'll put your family back
together again that will become the year that everyone looks back on as being magic when we
went to the you know we went to ningaloo you know and we
um we got bogged at uluru and and you know we went to tassie and nearly froze to death and
and the kids will just they just love that stuff no structure mom and dad hanging about you know
reading harry potter to each other in the by a candlelight um this is what families are made for
we're not made for we're not a money-making house building machine we're we're there to create
memories of absolute joy and we're not made for we're not made for we're not made for
and so so when we're gone i mean you're one of the fittest men in australia luke so this isn't
and you're in you've got probably 60 years ahead of you um but but i'm i'm getting on a bit and so
i'm thinking you know when i'm gone i want my kids to smile when they remember me big smile you know
and and have really specific memories when we and dad did this and me and dad did that
and that they feel deep down this sense of peace when they think of of
me and their mom and so we can we can give them that is in their muscles and nerves of their body
the feeling of being peaceful and content even in you know hardship and struggle um yeah so
thanks that's a great question thank you well it's a great answer and i was thinking of uh
one of my really close friends who actually interviewed in the podcast uh craig ellis who's
gone on to found the extraordinary business circle
triangle but uh him and i were great mates from sport from the age of eight and his family did
that year you talked about they him and his two brothers and they went around australia as both
his parents were school teachers i think i heard every i felt like i did that year he spoke about
it so often all the way through to this day it had that big an impact on him and he's got this
great sense of curiosity and adventure and travel all built on the back of uh you know that brilliant
experience as you said so you might have inspired uh that family as well i think uh from times go
past i heard you pick up and and in the book also you talk about you identifying as being on the
autism spectrum and it seems to me steve to be something that i hear that a lot more i've got
lots of people around me uh it's a word we know a lot more about now and it is a broad spectrum i
think sometimes severely misunderstood steve you think of and and clearly at the at the really
traumatic end there's there's families that have kids to function daily is a real challenge but a
lot of the families and the kids and that i've been talking to for a long time have been
growing up seem to have a part of their brain turned on a bit like you in a really unique way
that has this incredible empathy and this incredible caring nature i mean at what age did
you realize that that you were on the spectrum somewhere and can you relate to what i'm saying
i know it's harder than just that but it feels as though we've misunderstood this thing called
the autism spectrum and if we do more there's a genius there as well is that is that a fair thing
yes it is to answer that
i was i wasn't diagnosed till i was in my mid-50s and um and it was just like a like a whoa
that explains everything you know from um being a little kid in school to um just because what it
was was just not knowing how to read the signals and i joke about i said there was a lot of really
nice girls who went unkissed because because i just didn't i just wasn't reading the signs you
know and um um and my wife says that's
it's a very good thing um but it's hard and it's it was tough and and the human race felt like it
was a place where you didn't belong and so it's brilliant that this is now recognized um people
come up to me after talks and say i'm so thankful that you that you'd said you know kind of
identified as autistic because we've got a kid and you know we worry about them and so on and
the good thing about it is that i think the human race is diverse for a reason that we had to you
know the stone age was a tough place and we and we were there for half a million years and we were
actually very good at surviving and working in teams um human human beings lived in groups of
about 25 people who all loved each other and someone who's on the spectrum is very useful
because they they they don't have a herd instinct
and so everyone else will just go along with something because kind of it's a bit of a herd
thing and the person who's autistic will say wait a minute is that even a good idea um
um the famous um autistic woman whose name eludes me she said if it wasn't for
us aspies human beings would still be living in caves talking about their feelings
it's it's a hospital who said you know what about disease you know what about now why don't we build
a shelter here you know and there's other ways to do it and so um i like neurotypical people
and um and i've learned to join in i can be in front of 800 people in a room and i know everyone
in the room is that emotionally i can do that you know i've jumped over normal but i still take me
out of my comfort zone and i'm very awkward if i'm at a party i have to go and have a little
quiet lie down after about 20 minutes it's just too much you know um
i can do it but it's hard work and i think my kids would have often said i just i wish we had
a normal dad sometimes because i you know i was just learning as i went the gift in that
was i was writing books as i went you know when i figured something out i'd write it down i'd put
it into a framework and and the new book the fully human book is really my life framework
for the whole business of being a human being and i had to do that because i needed a manual myself
lots of people go pretty well but if they suddenly lose the plot they're at they're
completely at sea and that's where we whereas aspies can maybe be of help yeah before i uh i
go through um some questions that i've been wanting to ask and have been asking a range of
leaders and and your leadership in the in the space of of parenting in the space of raising
children is worldwide uh legacy that i'm sure you're incredibly proud of and i want to get
to that but just
something you said before you've jumped over normal in a room of 800 you just said that you
can pick up the feelings of almost all those people individually what what did you mean by
that did i get that right yes i well doing shows became very organized i had the best i had the
best sound engineer in australia um helping me to with my with the sound equipment of my shows and
things like that and we would always set up the theater with the lighting so that i could see
every face in the room and we would never go over 800 people because that was my
maximum um you can't see you can't see further than that um without binoculars or something
and so i could i just would notice who was struggling um in in the the raising boys talk
which we still now do online and people um schools get it online instead as a recording
there's always one or two people crying in the room and the stories are powerful and um people
used to get up and leave from that talk and
i think oh and it was always men and i think oh they're just sick of it or they've you know got a
meeting or their phones rung um but i talked to the ushers at the back of the theater afterwards
and saying you know the three guys left you know what was going on and say they say yeah he was
he was bawling and and i thought well that's you want to touch people but you don't want them have
to leave the show you know that's not a very good result so we put a lot more jokes in and a lot
more you know a lot more jokes in and a lot more jokes in and a lot more jokes in and a lot more
you know you get to a tough spot we just turn it around make it funny again um so that people
could handle it but you're doing group therapy with 800 people and you have to look after them
and i learned from people who are wonderful at that and they and they they it's it's about caring
you care about everyone in the room um and you try you know with eye contact and just like a
tilt of the head in their direction to say is this making sense to you you know and and um and you
an audience home and I know people listening who lead us I don't know how to lead a big
organization but I'm just wondering if that's possible that you if how would every person
there feel like you cared about them and that you saw them you know that you literally saw them
yeah that's a it's an interesting thing you say Steve we we hear from a lot of the sporting
coaches that that is a language that the the 21st century coaches are using now to say
I ought to find something in these players who can frustrate me and let me down sometimes
something in them all that I love literally that wasn't a language our coaches used in the era that
I played they were a touch more direct than that so they're talking and some of the coaches go
around at the start of the day and make sure they physically make physical contact with everyone in
the organization I know that's one of your passions as well Steve is that idea of touch
means an enormous amount to the health and particularly when you've got alpha males in
sporting environments going around doing it it's a great
you
new chapter of new of new leadership so Steve what I wanted to ask you we've we've got this
thought some of the work we're doing in business I'm in and passionate about and we teach school
teachers around collaboration and connection and leadership and we're seeing through the work at
Aleda a lot of consistencies in what makes great leadership and to have someone like you who's
spent his life in this space of parenting and raising children specifically and other areas
as well combined with other people in sport and corporate so
you know take as much time and I want to ask a range of questions on leadership and I'm
interested to get your thoughts and the first one is around self-leadership what do you think of when
I ask you about self-leadership yeah I think that there's a concept in the in the fully human book
of what's called the four-story mansion and in a absolute brief form it's the fact that
human beings have got levels to them or layers to them we've got our body we've got our emotions
got our thoughts, we've got our kind of antenna out into the cosmos. And those layers are very
often at odds with each other so that what we're doing isn't what we really think we want to be
doing or we really feel right about. We teach people in the book to just shuttle between the
levels, you know, go down in your body, check it out, come up to your feelings and check it out,
go up to your thinking and so on. And what you'll notice when you do that, it's like you've
suddenly turned on all the lights inside the building of your mind. And the disconnections
will start to be kind of glaring. And so, I'll ask my audiences, I'll say, you know,
does your life stack up? You know, do these layers stack up? And they'll start to realize, look,
you know, there's a whole thing I'm doing, which I don't want to do anymore.
A friend I've got who's not a friend, or I'm never going to take my child to that carer again.
And it comes from turning the lights on. And so, after a while, you know, there are people who
every layer of them stacks up. They're doing what they feel like, think is right, and sits
comfortably in their skin, and even spiritually kind of fits with their view of why we're in this
world.
People are outstanding. If that person walks into a room, everyone on some level is aware of them.
They stack up. And they don't have to lead in a sense of motivating people, because people just
want to be like them. You know, it's like, can I hang around with you? And you'll hear that about
some teachers and some school principals, people, you know, and some matrons of hospitals, people,
they want to work in your hospital.
You know, how do I do it? I want to teach in your school. We have an automatic radar. A little
one-year-old child can tell a person with integrity. A dog can tell. And so, it's, yeah,
stack yourself up.
Brilliant analogy, Steve. I love the idea of the four-story mansion. I'm glad you brought it up.
And it is the two key ideas you touch on. We touched on super sense and the four-story
mansion.
I think to use your own words again, just to briefly describe the way you gave it in the
book, an easily grasped way of navigating the multiple levels of your mind, getting the work
together instead of, as they often do, tearing you apart. The idea is so simple. It can be learned
by a five-year-old, so profound that it can help even the most damaged adult. And you really do
need to purchase the four-story mansion and, sorry, purchase a fully human, understand the
four-story mansion, because it is, it's a profound way of thinking in a really crystal,
clear way. And it certainly resonated with me in a profound way on self-leadership. It does feel
like the combination of your life's work. The second part for me was about your thoughts on
positively impacting others in your environment. How do you go about doing that, Steve?
Gosh, I think, again, it's like your attention is the most valuable thing you can give.
Everyone's struggling. People get really shocked, you know, when I wrote in the book about the
struggles that I'd had, you know, when my friend committed suicide and that you've referred to
before and things like that. Assume that everyone around you is struggling and that they would
benefit from some quiet time and some attention. And even on a non-verbal level, the fact that
you check in with them, that at least you're not causing any problems to them, you know.
So you can ask that question. You can say, look, am I doing,
am I doing what you need me to do as a boss? Am I the kind of dad you need me to be? You know,
you have a teenage daughter and she's doing a few things you're not happy with.
You know, choose your moment. It's a lot to do with the timing. Choose a moment where if this
is deep water, you can go to deep water, you know, so you don't ask it as you go out the door.
You know, you and her sitting in the rain because the game's been cancelled or something like that.
And say to her, I'm not sure that I'm being the kind of father you need me to be.
And she'd probably be really shocked. And it might take her a while to come back to that.
Or she might have a list. Yeah, you're right. I've got a list. And then it's like,
you better be ready to hear it. And yeah, we had a story of a girl who went on a holiday with her
dad. And this girl had slept with seven or eight different boys.
She's still in high school. She was in terrible shape. And we went on a holiday together. Her dad
had enough sense to know, you know, we've got to get away together, have some time. And she just,
something came up like a little trigger and she just blew him out of the water with all the times
he had failed her, you know, promising to show up for a concert and not showing up and, you know,
being rude and getting drunk at a party. And she had a list and there was nothing he could do except
um,
to it, you know, and say, you know, you're right. You know, you're, you're, I'm, I'm ashamed and
you're right. And I failed you and I want to do better. Um, and kids are very forgiving. People
are forgiving. They can handle imperfection. They, they, they know what it's like to be,
to struggle so they can handle that. Yeah. What a, what a profound story. I think,
you know, with my three boys, I've got three boys and, uh, the oldest is 18, uh, a couple of weeks
ago. My daughter's 16. So she's the one girl in the family and it's a, you know, completely
different experience as you know, and I've written about and, and you're right. I get direct feedback
from Sienna and in a profound way, she knows exactly what she wants and can articulate that.
But those moments when you do get her one-on-one and like, and she's driving at the moment,
it's a great chance to be in the car with her because it's just the two of us. And,
and you often find that there's an opportunity to have those profound, I can't say I've had that
one quite, but, uh, but that's inspiring.
That is a profound way to impact others in your environment. We talk a lot in the leadership
space about creating and sharing a vision. Have you got some thoughts on how you've gone about
that? I think this is, um, perhaps the only thing that, um, that's your responsibility as a leader
is, is I know when we built the, when we built the refugee Memorial in Canberra, uh, it took about
five years and it was, uh, um, seven or eight people who worked on it that whole time.
And, and we, Sharon and I funded it. And so we had one staff person, um, and they're everyone
else's volunteers and they were, they're all wonderful. And, and as I said, they were all
smarter than me in different ways, but my job was to, to remember why we were doing it. Um,
which was to, um, to honor the lives of 350 people who drowned in a boat and the boat,
it was 20 years ago that this boat set sail.
Mostly women and children. And they were on the boat because we had their husbands
in Australia and we wouldn't let them reunite their very cruel policy about that. And I wanted
Australia to see what 350 lives look like, because if they died in a jumbo jet crash,
that would have been a big deal. But anonymous refugees in a boat sailing to Australia was not
much news after a couple of days. And I, I would, I was really angry about that. I wasn't going to
let that go by.
And so the vision was we are going to make an honoring of those lives. And so when we had to
fight the government over building this memorial, I said, I don't care. You know, if we fight the
government, we'll be in the headlines and the people will be remembered. You know, if John
Howard doesn't let us do it, um, that'll be that memorial. You know, the government was too ashamed
for us to, to, to honor those names. Um, and by holding the kind of true North,
perhaps a small, you might say,
It doesn't even matter if we fail miserably.
And sometimes I really thought we would.
You know, it was a long struggle.
We gave it our best shot.
You know, it's like Bilbo Baggins in Lord of the Rings.
You know, you just did what you could, you know.
Yeah, an amazing legacy.
164 children drowned in that tragedy, mainly Iraqi and Afghani refugees.
And as you said, unfortunately, the news cycle, you move on.
And for you not to allow that to be the case, you know,
you're living a great life and you've got many things you could do.
It's an incredible piece of leadership that I know you must have put an
enormous amount of not only your own money but your own reputation
and effort behind.
So what a profound thing to do, to have that memorial now permanently done.
I know you had to fight for it to be a permanent legacy,
but congratulations.
Yes, it's right there on the lake shore.
If you go to Canberra, go and visit.
It's a very inspiring place.
It's a 300-metre long memorial.
It's just beautiful, yeah.
Curiosity is something, another dimension of leadership we talk about, Stephen.
I feel like your mind is incredibly curious.
Do you think about that?
And is that in terms of your own learning and your own development,
how do you approach that?
Now, these questions assume that I've really sorted out Luke
and I don't even know about that except I get this kind
of little boy excitement about stuff.
I've been learning about the brainwaves.
I've been learning about the brain just lately
and how it's got two completely separate halves
and one half focuses on the worm that you want to eat
if you're a blackbird or something and the other half
of the brain is thinking, yeah, but what if there's a cat
in the bushes, you know?
And so I find this fascinating and so I'm reading all these neuroscience books
which are pretty hard to read, but I just want to get
to the bottom of this.
And so that's, I think, something that is just a little kid digging
in the garden for worms, you know?
It's the same little kid that I was in Yorkshire, you know, in 1953.
I'm just playing in the mud and feeling just really happy
and looking up at the clouds every now and then.
And, yeah, so maybe the message is just enjoy yourself, you know.
Bill Gates and Steve Jobs, those guys, they were just mucking about,
you know, let's see what we can do and look how well it brought us.
Yeah.
Well said.
And they are questions without notice, Steve, so your answers are profound.
You know, clearly we talk about communication with clarity as well.
Is that something that resonates with you?
Clearly through your work you've communicated with millions of people.
Is that the way that you communicate effectively?
There's a thing I do with writing.
If someone in the street comes up to me and says one of the books
has helped them, which is one of the nice parts of my work,
people come up and they say, you know, your book really helped my husband
or something like that.
And the second thing they say is it's a really easy read.
And the way I write is a bit like if you're making a table
and you're planing the table.
You just keep planing until it's smooth, you know.
You just keep sanding until it's smooth and until it's just effortless.
But there's another thing, which is I have a pretty ordinary brain
and so I can't do complicated.
You know.
You know, if I could do complicated, I could impress all the academics
and, you know, make a fortune and everything.
But it's not.
I'm simple because I'm simple.
And the brilliance is in the simplicity, Stephen.
It's a great compliment, I think, isn't it, to say maybe it sounds
like a backhanded compliment.
It's a great read and I got it and I understood it because that's how I felt.
So many things I wrote down from Reading Fully Human,
it's exactly how it felt, you know, the way you described it,
which was great.
It's brilliant stuff that you could practically apply to your life.
So it's a great school that you've got.
I don't think it's  the genius is in the simplicity for me.
The final dimension we talk about is collaboration.
And without answering it for you, I'm thinking of
it seems like an incredible partnership, you and your wife, Sharon.
You know, 42 years, I think, I read you've been married.
It seems like that collaboration at home is big.
But do you think about collaboration extensively?
Yeah, I think.
I think what characterises it with Sharon is we still sometimes
get completely lost and I just don't understand where she's coming from
or she thinks I'm completely out of my tree.
And the only way we know to deal with that is one way is to take a break
if we're like just can't get it right, have a bit of space.
But the other way is to kind of come back and just keep talking.
And sometimes we often drive to Hobart.
We're in Launceston.
We drive to Hobart.
So it's nearly three hours from where we are.
Most of our great conversations have been on that journey
because three hours is about what it takes to really get down
to the bedrock of something.
That's where we decided to go live in England.
That's where we decided to have a second child.
You know, that's where we decided to, you know, that I could use our money
to do different things.
And so collaboration.
It feels like hard work.
It's much easier to just look, I'll do it my way.
You know, it's easier.
But if you want results, two brains are better than one every time.
And so you put the time, you know, teaching, you want to teach your kid
to fasten their laces or how to do the dishes.
That's going to take some time.
You know, it's quicker to just do them for them.
But.
Get a kid that can cook, you know, you're, that's a lifetime, you know,
so it's, it's worth a bit of effort early on.
Yeah.
And I will said, you know, think about my own home front again,
when you say that, you know, the 14 year olds say he's got this passion
for, for cooking and self, you know, he's quite amazing and it's,
it's great to see maybe, you know, first, second, third, we start getting
it right, maybe by the third or fourth time, but a final question that I've been
asking, um, all the leaders that I've been speaking to.
And again, a question without notice there, who is the greatest leader
that you've had in your life?
Okay.
Not when he comes to mind straight away, but I was always impressed with
Gandhi, um, because of course I didn't meet and Martin Luther King for the
same sort of reason that, um, they had no enemies, Gandhi said that he, he
could kick the British out.
Of India because he kind of liked them.
Um, and, and he'd go to England and then there's pictures of him with all these
women who wove the cloth in Lancashire and, and this skinny little guy with
this little nappy on, you know, remember the pictures of Gandhi and there's all
these women with their hair in rollers and they're just giggling and carrying
on with, with Gandhi, you know, and the next thing he's kicking the British
empire out, but he was absolutely committed.
And Bob Brown is the same.
I've talked to Bob Brown about this and.
He doesn't hate anyone.
He just thinks some people a bit, a bit lost, you know, no, I find that really
hard, you know, I hate quite a number of Australian prime ministers in, in, in
order and, and, and I was a street kid and I was raised on hating and it's hard
to, so I admire those people because they don't hate anyone.
They think, look, this person just a bit lost, you know, we can, we'll
bring them around in the end, you know, they'll, they'll get it.
They'll get climate change.
They'll get, you know.
Whatever it is.
And, and so, so people don't feel the enmity.
Um, it's a bit irresistible when someone won't let you be an enemy.
Yeah.
And, and it was going to be the last question, but the followup, you know, to a
Gandhi type leader of, you know, as you said, to, to use peace with that amount
of power, with that enemy and the pacifism and, and, and what that did and
influenced, you know, followed by, you know, tens and tens and tens of millions
of people, do you have the positive glass?
Half full that the leader will emerge like that?
Is there one around, you said, you know, the frustration with political
leadership at the moment is, is that even possible?
Do you think going forward?
Look, I don't know.
It's, it feels like it doesn't come from politics that, that politics doesn't, um,
funnel down the right kind of people and push them to the front.
Um, so I think what we need is a lot of independence in the next election.
Um, we have some fantastic independence in, in here in Tasmania.
Um.
People, and you have on the mainland as well, people who are just in it for
their values, um, not for ambition.
And I, so I think if we're going to be a healthy country, we, we might have, um,
couple of dozen independents and they'll vote depending on what's right for the
country, not what's the party line.
And sometimes it'll be this way and sometimes it'll be that way.
And so I think the, the dinosaur parties, perhaps the day is done, um, and we'll
have.
We'll vote for people, um, who we actually like, um, you know, that you're glad if you're
glad to see them, if you're glad to see their face on the television, it's a pretty good
gauge.
You know, they come on the telly and your heart lifts.
Um, that's a, you know, not many who do that at the moment, but there are some who do,
and they're mostly independents.
Profound way to, uh, to think about that as well.
Uh, Steve, uh, as I said, I, I have, there's so many more questions.
Hopefully, uh, we could maybe do this again another time because.
Uh, did promise you that there was a time limit in the interest of your time as well.
So thank you that the book fully human couldn't recommend it anymore.
A new way of using your mind is the full title.
And, uh, it's brilliant.
It's a simple genius as, uh, as, uh, Steve gave you a great insight into how he writes
and how he thinks.
And, uh, thank you for sharing that on leadership.
You've had such a profound effect on so many, uh, of our generation and how we parent, how
we think about it.
Um, and you continue to do that.
It's always a great pleasure to, to speak to you.
Thanks for your time again.
Thanks.
Thanks for your time.
Empowering leaders was presented by me, Luke Darcy produced by Matt Dwyer with audio production
by Darcy Thompson.
Start your leadership journey.
I encourage you to go to a leader collective.com.
Take our empowering leaders indicator tool and understand the impact you have on your
environment.
Join us at a leader to learn, lead, and collaborate.