What a brilliant year it was and seeing so many incredible moments unfold when you get the privilege of sitting across from inspiring people, delving into the intricacies of their success.
And in 2023, myself and I hope you as the audience felt like you had a front row seat to conversations that reveal how success leaves clues, featuring individuals who've mastered their craft in a whole range of various fields.
At Alita, we recognise the consistent dimensions of brilliant leadership and we're continuing our special series as we explore all of them.
The superpower of curiosity we think is a priceless skill and has immense impact.
Every week on The Empowering Leaders, our discussions span across diverse industries.
We love curating conversations from sport, from business, education, social venture and the arts.
And in this episode, we've curated a remarkable group of individuals who embody the true power of leadership.
The true essence of curiosity, starting with Ed O'Malley, who I really enjoyed catching up with this year, president and CEO of the Kansas Health Foundation, a unique leader in his own world.
And Ed draws inspiration from the cult TV series, Ted Lasso.
I don't know if Ted Lasso has taken off in Australia like it has in the States.
Sure has. What a great show.
Oh, it's such a great show. But there's that one episode where he talks about being curious, not judgmental.
And I just thought that was a great line.
And it describes to me so much about leadership, to be curious, not judgmental.
And one of the problems, I think, with our current world is because we're so polarised, most people in one faction have a lot of judgments about people in the other faction.
Or if we just want to talk about politics, you know, conservatives have a lot of judgments they make about progressives and vice versa.
And I think those who exercise leadership suspend their judgments and don't let themselves get emotionally triggered by those, that rhetoric.
And they instead get very curious about why somebody is doing what they're doing and how they might engage with that person to help them maybe do something different.
Curiosity feels like a key ingredient to me for exercising effective leadership.
Dr. Shefali.
She has a Ph.D. in clinical psychology at Columbia University.
She's a three times New York Times bestselling author.
And her book, The Conscious Parent, has been endorsed by Oprah Winfrey as a parenting revolution.
Yeah, curiosity is the key for learning.
But we need to be curious to challenge what we're listening to.
We shouldn't be curious about, say, for example, how to become skinnier, prettier, wealthier.
Like, don't be curious.
Don't be curious to fall into what society says.
Be curious to ask why the hell does society say that in the first place?
That's the ultimate curiosity is to disrupt and deconstruct what we've been raised with.
What has been the intellectual food and the emotional food that culture and your caregivers have been giving you since you were young?
Can you look at that and deconstruct that and don't take it at face value?
Dare to challenge.
Why is this on my plate?
Why is that on my plate in the first place?
Who said that?
Why is that a rule?
And that is where you become really brave, right?
If you're curious about how to do more of what culture has told you, that's only being a follower.
Real curiosity is to challenge the systems in place and to look at them for their farce.
And most of them are farcical and lies.
And they're not truly upholding.
Of our deepest yearnings as a human being, which is to be authentic, to be connected, to be seen, to be valued, not for our looks, our money, our cars, our achievements.
Our greatest yearning is to be seen for who it is we are.
And yet most of us don't allow ourselves or don't allow ourselves to see another for who it is they are.
We keep piling on these belief systems.
So if society says.
As we know, we need to be high achieving, have a lot of money, be part of the crowd, be famous.
And if we're curious to do those things, meaning how can I be more famous?
How can I follow society's ways?
How can I be richer?
That is not the true maverick curiosity.
That's falling in line and following what culture says.
True curiosity is to say, why the hell are we talking about this in the first place?
Where did this come from?
And to really examine the roots.
Of all the belief systems.
So a lot of my work is challenging cultures, paradigms and dismantling them.
Mick Doohan is a five time MotoGP world champion, an Australian Sports Hall of Famer and a serious player in the global aviation world, with his business becoming the world's largest trader of corporate aircraft.
People who have success like you consistently, they're curious all the time.
They want to learn.
They want to know what's going on.
And.
And through that, that's how they constantly get better.
Does that resonate with you?
The idea of constantly trying to find that curiosity and things?
Um, yes, less so now, but, but yeah, without a doubt, trying to keep pushing yourself, uh, when, especially back in the competition days, you keep pushing yourself to try and find, you know, you keep pushing that limit and pushing those, that line a little bit further out.
So that, that, that gray area is, is, is very clear.
You know, the more you keep pushing yourself that clear, that, uh, that, that, that gray area becomes, and I think that's the same with everything, the more you understand and the more you do, whether we just want to put into aviation when I'm first in there and you're fumbling through things, you know, and you are fumbling through things because you haven't done a lot of it in the first time, but after you've done it a hundred times, it's, you know, it's pretty second nature.
And, and I think that's the same thing as what you're saying, but, uh, but you keep pushing through, keep wanting to understand more and more and more.
And, and that's just called being an old father.
I guess with the experience, yeah.
Coming up, we're going to hear from the inspirational Sandy Brondello, the head coach of the Australian Opals and doing a brilliant job as the head coach of New York Liberty and the WNBL.
And one of Australia's favorite ever people for mine, a man I enjoyed spending some time with this year, the great Dr. Chris Brown.
Found it really interesting to hear from Dr. Shefali, Mick Doon and Ed O'Malley.
Very different backgrounds, diverse worlds they come from, but they all talked about genuine curiosity.
And that's really important.
It's just, you know, it's so interesting to see today's leaders.
A lot of us have come from a place of curiosity involving challenging societal norms, leaders,
suspending judgment to cultivate a curious mindset.
And that curiosity is required to push yourself beyond your limits.
It's pretty clear the transformative power of curiosity in both personal and professional development.
And we heard that right across the year on the empowering leader series.
At a leader, we are really passionate about creating a world of collaboration, inspiring connections, and bringing together these diverse leaders from different backgrounds around the globe to share our prisoner's story.
Thank you for joining us today.
I'm Simon ontario.
share to learn, to connect and to collaborate.
We would love you to check out Alita Connect,
our signature program.
Head to alitacollective.com.
You don't have to be a global head of marketing
for an international company
or a superstar coach to be part of Alita Connect.
We would love to book a discovery call,
have a chat to us,
and we'd love to share your leadership journey with you.
Big thanks as always to Jason Nicholas
and his team from Temper, Australia and New Zealand
for their ongoing support
and empowering leaders podcast.
We know that getting a good night's sleep
is a pattern that we see in all great leaders.
Temper is a mattress like no other.
Check it out today.
The next group of guests all speak to how curiosity
has kept them on the path to a life of great success.
Let's first go to Peggy O'Neill,
the former president of the Richmond Football Club
who couldn't have had greater success in her role.
I'm someone who loved being a student
and it's sort of a, you know,
get to the point you're not doing formal education
in the same way,
but you're meeting new people that you learn from
if you...
if you let yourself.
And I think that goes back to
understanding a bit more about the kind of person that you are.
And I think that my curiosity about people and places
is really sort of the theme of my life.
And I often think that if I weren't...
didn't take on some of the jobs that I have now,
that I'd love to go work on a PhD in something
because everything is just wonderfully...
I'm curious about it.
It's just a...
a wonderful experience to meet someone new,
to get the new ideas and whether...
I'm sort of more in the arts kind of thing rather than science,
but I can be fascinated by science too.
But I just think to meet someone who writes something wonderfully
or a musician who does something that creates beauty in the world
and how little we know,
or how little I know about that whole process
and who these people are.
And more and more,
sometimes this information overload is...
How many people are doing things out there
that would be exciting if we knew more about it?
And so every day I learn something new from someone or about someone.
So I think that that means you're never stale.
That means you never feel like you've arrived
and that you can continue to be excited about new experiences.
Sandy Brondello is Australian basketball royalty,
representing Australia at four Summer Olympics,
and playing over 300 games for her country.
Her extraordinary post-retirement coaching career
sees her as the current head coach of the New York Liberty
and the Australian national team, the Opals.
You know, I've spoken about this has been my passion since the age of nine.
You know, obviously starting to play basketball, learn basketball,
seeing where basketball has taken me, going to the Olympic Games.
I mean, who would have dreamt I went to one Olympic Games?
Not everyone gets to do that. I went to four.
You know, it's just...
It's blown away.
I love the competitiveness of everything.
But I think you have to...
Like I said, the curiosity is more is continue to learn.
I always wanted to be the best player I could be,
not be better than my teammate or someone else,
but trying to learn from others how they do things, you know,
asking questions, finding mentors.
I think that's critical for anyone's development at any level.
You know, I think mentors, they can help you along the way
because it's not just a physical thing that we do with basketball.
You know, there's the mentors.
There's the mental part, the emotional part,
the physiological stuff that we all have to learn
to be the very best that we can be.
And, you know, I've got to know a lot of different people
and the curiosity part comes from just digging,
asking them questions.
How?
And that's why I love the letter because it's fantastic
just because we had so many different leaders
that you could just, you know, connect with.
And I've had Zooms, you know, I love just reaching out to them
and just digging deeper in how they do things.
And regardless if it was in the NFL, the NRL, the AFL, just coaches.
And I love that we wanted to share and help each other, you know,
because we can all learn from each other.
And business world too, I mean, because leadership is not just in sports.
I mean, you see leaderships because it's all about developing a culture
where you can actually grow the most.
And I'm massive on that.
It's not just what you do in practice.
I'm really big on let's build the right culture.
What kind of team do we want to be?
And how are we going to get there?
Dr Chris Brown is one of Australia's most popular and respected people.
A vet, a television presenter and an author,
he's an inspiring modern leader and making a huge impact
in the world of animal welfare.
I can be my harshest critic often, which I think is a useful skill
but also one that you need to keep an eye on
because you're probably doing okay,
but your inner critic can sometimes have the loudest voice in the room.
And I think that's something to be always to be mindful of.
Look, I once got told by a television executive that I'm a difficult dog
to keep on the porch.
And I appreciated the animal sort of link to the analogy.
But what he was trying to say was probably something that is quite relevant.
I get bored easily.
And I'm always looking for a new challenge.
And it's kind of that situation where curiosity is a really useful thing to have
and it's sort of guided me through a lot of what I've done
because I want to learn more and I want to be better.
But it can mean that I never like to be stuck in one thing for too long
and always want to be moving on and trying something else.
So that's potentially a bit of a challenge.
I do find it hard to stay in one place for too long,
which probably has flow-on effects to relationships.
I probably would have thought that I'd probably have kids
and potentially be married by now.
But that hasn't happened because I probably prioritised work a little bit,
potentially in hindsight, a little bit too much.
But that sort of thing's there.
It just barks quite loudly, you know, to use another animal analogy.
It can be quite a demanding thing to focus on work.
So, you know, there are probably any regrets I have.
It's probably around not necessarily having enough time for myself
and for the people around me.
Funnily enough, in Iceland, I had this really profound moment.
I was hiking in the highlands.
I was in the highlands of Iceland.
And deliberately, I was there by myself and I just was hiking
and just going up and down these little, these volcanoes, basically.
And I was just sort of pondering, pondering life.
And it's a great place to do that because the natural beauty
of things there is just off the charts.
And it just kind of is a really interesting reminder,
the fact that when you are driven and when you're determined
to always strive to be better and curiosity leads you
on those paths and you invest in the, you know, creating a show
or working on a production and, you know, it's such a privilege
to be the front and centre of those productions.
Something like I'm a Celebrity, Get Me Out of Here has 400 crew
and you have the honour of standing in front of the camera
essentially presenting the work of 400 people.
It's a reminder that you sometimes get obsessed with it.
You're obsessed with the climb and the climb up that mountain.
And taking on a show and working on a show is like climbing a mountain.
You gather all your reserves at a base camp, if you like.
You fuel yourself up.
You get yourself whole.
You feel like you're ready to take on a challenge.
You store up all that adrenaline.
You're ready to go.
And you start the climb.
And creating a show is a lot like that.
And you take the hits.
It's hard at different times.
But you want to get to the peak of that mountain,
which is essentially your rating success.
It's a show that's well received.
Your performance is something that is well regarded.
And you reach those heights.
And you come off air in that final episode of the series.
And you're like, done.
What a great high.
And then you kind of look around from the top of that mountain
and realise there's about 50 or 60 other mountains out in the distance
that are also there.
As high, if not higher, than the one you're on.
So you think, okay, I'll go back down this mountain
and go back to my base camp.
And then you sort of refuel again.
And you realise that in life everyone's climbing mountains,
you know, in their different fields.
But it's kind of the climb's not important.
The view from the top's not important.
It's kind of like it's basically what happens in the base camp
is kind of the most important part of life.
And I think that's probably I probably neglect my base camp,
a little bit too much.
And the nurturing sort of refuelling, fulfilling aspects of that,
I think are probably something that, you know,
I probably would look to spend more time working on.
And I know I'm not alone in that respect in terms of being able to switch off
and I guess re-engage with the world around you that's not as adrenaline-filled
or cortisol-fuelled as that world.
And I'm sure sports people who get themselves up for a season,
that's their mountain they're climbing.
It's fairly relevant across a lot of people.
And so that's kind of been a really interesting lesson for me.
And something we talk about in the Elite Collective group a lot is just that
how do we switch off and how do we refuel and how do we reconnect?
And I think that's been a really,
really interesting one to see how shared that challenge is of switching off
and of recharging.
That's probably the biggest one that I think is an ongoing challenge
for so many of us.
Once again, I really enjoyed going back to listen to Peggy O'Neill,
to Sandy Brondello, Dr Chris Brown and their reflections
and the patterns that emerged.
The constant pursuit of new challenges was a common theme.
All continuous lifelong learners.
I've heard that so much in 2020 through,
that constant and never-ending self-improvement desire to keep learning
regardless of what stage or age of your life and career you're at.
And learning from diverse teachers and mentors from different backgrounds.
The idea that learning does show up in different forms
was something that I certainly enjoyed hearing a lot more about.
A huge thanks to all of our guests featured on this episode.
You can find the links to the full-length in-depth conversations
that I had with each of them in the show notes.
I encourage you to go back and listen to those episodes.
In our next Success Leaves Clues episode,
we'll shift focus to the leadership dimension
of communicating with clarity.
You can hear from some extraordinary guests
about the pivotal role communication has played
in each of their unique journeys.
If you have enjoyed listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast,
I'd love you to hit the subscribe button now.
If you have a moment, please leave a review for us
so we can hopefully reach more listeners
and empower more leaders in 2024.