I've been fortunate enough to work in media and broadcast and calling sport for more than
15 years now, but recording the Empowering Leaders series is the most enjoyable thing
I've ever done.
And it's incredible to sit down across from so many inspiring people, as we did in 2023
for this podcast, talking about all the ways that success leaves clues with people at the
top of their game and in their chosen field.
At Alita, we know that there are consistent dimensions of what brilliant leadership looks
like, and we're covering them all in this special series.
We know that having great leaders in your own life can shape your path and inspire you
to reach greater heights.
And every week on the Empowering Leaders, our conversations stretch across different
fields.
We're really passionate about curating people from different backgrounds, sport, business,
education, social venture, and the arts.
You would have heard me talk about that a lot across the year.
And in this episode, we've handpicked a remarkable group of individuals with heartfelt stories
about the great life.
Leaders who've left an indelible mark on their lives.
One of my favorite things to do is to ask people who has been the greatest leader in
their life.
And I want to start with Bob Murphy, one of my great friends in life, former captain of
the Western Bulldogs AFL team, and a very unique thinker in every way.
Luke Beveridge.
Luke Beveridge has been the greatest leader in my life.
I like leaders for lots.
I mean, there's, yeah, again, there's so...
Leadership's so big and so broad, but I love people who can stop momentum of atmosphere
to go, hey, wait, what just happened then?
So there was a moment early on in his coaching time when we didn't really know who he was
or what was...
And someone announced that, oh, Marcus Bontempelli, who's probably a close second, Marcus is
putting himself to be a part of a charity about violence against women.
And it's, oh, that's great.
Yeah, I mean, 19-year-old kid.
And it was a sort of, it was a bit of a footnote to the meeting in Borussia, and Luke stopped
and said, hey, hey, hey, everyone, sit back down.
This is a young kid who's in our program who's going to put himself out there for a cause
that he really means it.
And it's about...
It's about protecting women and helping society, and that's important.
And I just remember sitting there going, we are a different football club as of that moment.
Little things are big things.
You know, I just, I always remember those sort of, those little touchstones of like,
that's one aspect of leadership that I hold in a really high regard.
Yeah, and it's such a...
It's such a unique part of our history, isn't it, Bob?
We go back to both of, you know, where we met and this history and love of football club.
And as you know the history so well, and you mentioned it beautifully that, you know, I
was there many times when it looked like you're going to go out of business and it was going
to be over and arrive just after the fight back.
And that was really fresh in everyone's minds that, you know, it was days away from being
not a club anymore.
Yeah.
And then you see this sort of...
This sort of paradigm shift that happened when, you know, in your combination with Luke
and the whole environment, but the point of difference was Luke Beveridge at that time
and you being a captain.
It's, you know, when you look back, it's provided some sustainable success.
Yeah, it's just a magical time, you know, like one of the hard things about football
at the elite level is everyone's trying.
Yeah.
Like they're ready.
They're headlining it.
They're trying so hard and they care and they're emotionally invested.
But if there's not an emotional alignment, particularly with the leaders, it's hard
because there's a lot of effort and there's a lot of strain.
But if it's not going in the same way, there's a lot of conflict.
And just for that brief period at the Bulldogs during that time, it was like a...
It was like an orchestra, like a symphony, and it just clicked and we made some music.
Anita Jacoby is one of the most respected and decorated producers in Australian television history.
For more than 40 years, she led the way in her industry on shows including 60 Minutes,
Enough Rope and Grew and Transfer.
She's currently the chair of the ABC's Advisory Council.
Probably a man called Kevin Weldon.
Kevin Weldon, to your audience,
if they don't know of him, he formed and founded a company called Paul Hamlin's here
in Australia.
It was one of the largest book publishing companies in Australia, extremely successful.
And I worked with Hamlin's when I first came out of school.
And Kevin was an incredibly entrepreneurial man.
So I was about 18 and I started there and we were given mini minors and we were dressed
up in outfits and sent out to sell books because he was such an entrepreneurial character.
But what he taught me really was to always not to be afraid of risks at all.
At 18, he gave us all an assignment.
There were eight of us, eight marketing trainees that he brought on straight out of school.
And the assignment was that we had to go and ring somebody important and set up an interview
and go and interview them.
Now, you can imagine at 18, I was pretty intimidated by that, even having had a very strong father.
I was given Sir Robert Norman, who was then the CEO of the Bank of New South Wales, which
is now the Westpac.
And I went home and I did all my research and I spent an hour with Sir Robert Norman
talking about the economy.
I knew nothing about the economy, I've got to say.
I just sat there and actually spent an hour talking to him.
What it taught me was that anybody's accessible.
And Kevin Weldon gave me these great skills to recognise resilience, courage, entrepreneurial,
being entrepreneurial.
He was just a terrific boss to have.
At a young age in my life, and he informed a lot of my thinking about the way to approach
business and be a leader.
Meggie Palmer is a Walkley Award winning filmmaker and a former foreign correspondent and journalist
for BBC World, CNBC and Dateline.
After her own personal experience of discrimination and inequality, Meggie founded Pep Talker.
She now works to close the gender pay gap with her thriving global business and community
of more than 60,000 professionals.
That's such a great question.
I mean, I think there's sort of like, there's definitely family members, you know, my family,
my siblings inspire me, obviously my parents, my grandparents, even my grandparents who
I lost really early, you know, who I hardly even remember, but just like the lessons that
stay with my mum, my aunts and uncles, you know, my mum lost her parents quite young.
And so, but those lessons and those values really are instilled in me and my cousins
and all of our gatherings.
And then the same on my dad's side, like family is so important and I'm so grateful to have
that connection with my cousins.
But then I also reflect like on a business sense, like early in my career, I had this
great news director, Kathy Schnitzeling.
I started my career at Channel 10 in Brisbane and she was the news director there.
And she was like, awesome.
She kind of modelled vulnerability and authenticity before it was cool.
Like she was very like hard on the table, like this is the situation, highs and lows
of her life.
And now I reflect on that.
I was like, she was kind of like living what Brené Brown was like.
Yeah.
She's got some practices now, but she was doing it all those years ago.
And even when it comes to pay, she modelled for me, Luke, really early.
I was kind of there for a year or two and I was getting a bit bored and I was kind of
like, maybe I should get another job.
I don't really know.
And I didn't talk to her about it or anyone about it.
I just started like Googling what should I do next?
And then she called me into her office and she was like, so you've been here a year,
a year and a half.
You should really ask me for a pay raise.
And I was like, what?
And she was like, wink, wink.
Like.
So.
I was like, I'm going to ask for better money.
Possibly I could do something about that.
And I was like, oh, so she was kind of like leading a horse to water.
And I was like, could I please have a pay raise?
And she was like, yes, yes, you can.
So she kind of coached me, you know, from a really young age that it's OK to ask that
there was money available.
And I actually wonder what would have happened to my salary if she hadn't taught me that
early on, because we know that, you know, if you don't negotiate your first salary,
which by the way, I did not when I took the job while I was still at university, I just
took what they offered, which I think was like twenty eight grand or something.
And I thought I was so rich.
If you don't negotiate like I didn't because of compounding interest and superannuation
and all that kind of stuff, you're going to retire with half a million dollars less than
someone else who did negotiate in their first job.
And so, again, I just try to pay that forward to anyone who will listen.
Like, please tell your daughters, your cousins, your mentees, anyone who will listen, like,
please negotiate your first salary.
They might say no.
But if they say yes.
It's going to make a huge difference over the course of your career.
Coming up, you're going to hear from Richard Burnett, the global CEO of Body Fit Training,
Donna Urquhart, ultra marathon runner extraordinaire, and Danny Green, the four time world champion
boxer who has a unique way of thinking, a really remarkable guy.
Bob Murphy, Anita Jacobi, Maggie Palmer all just talk beautifully for me about leaders
who pause and acknowledge significant moments.
The power of authenticity.
And openness in our leaders and the lifelong lessons learned when someone throws you a
bit out of your comfort zone.
Loved hearing from all of those remarkable people and leader.
We are really passionate about creating a world of collaboration, inspiring connections.
Love you to have a look at our signature program called Alita Connect, where we bring together
bespoke groups of five or six from diverse backgrounds, whether it be sport, industry,
social venture or the arts to come together, to learn, to share, to connect and collaborate.
Head to Alita Connect.com.
And book a discovery call.
Can't wait to chat to you.
Big thanks as always to Jason Nicholas and his team from Tempur, Australia and New Zealand
for their ongoing support for the Empowering Leaders podcast.
We know that getting a good night's sleep is a pattern that we see in all great leaders.
Tempur is a mattress like no other.
Check it out today.
Next group of guests all have brilliant stories about the greatest leader in their lives and
how they were instrumental to the life that they've gone on to live.
Let's go first to Richard Burnett, the global CEO of Body Fit Training.
Richard, welcome to the show.
Thanks for having me.
These guests all have brilliant stories about the greatest leader in their lives and how
they were instrumental to the life that they've gone on to live.
Let's go first to Richard Burnett, the global CEO and director of Body Fit Training with
over 600 franchises sold across the world and a personal path that's had more than its
fair share of hurdles and life challenges.
Different people for different circumstances to ask I think, but if I think back to my
time, I had a couple of...
unbelievable managers at BP and John Clark and Lance Ed who gave me the confidence that I was
just a young buck as a BP graduate trainee. But they only choose five a year out of uni
and I was one of those. And these particular managers gave me the responsibility at a very
young age to be a regional franchise manager looking after 30 or 40 BPs in Melbourne.
And that's where your franchise came from, out of that.
Yeah, exactly. Out of that, randomly. Yeah, because BP, a lot of the service stations
are franchised. And then Lance and John both backed me in to go and run a company owned
and operated 12 site, multi-site franchise in North Queensland, in Townsville and in
Cairns. So I was there as a 25 or so.
Or seven year old, maybe, yeah, 25 or seven, one of those ages, looking after 110 staff,
living remotely by myself up there to deliver bottom line, you know, millions of dollars
for BP. So they backed me in and believed in me. And for me, they've been incredibly
influential and I don't thank them or see them enough for that. And then you-
Can I just start on that? I mean, for a size, a company size of BP, that seems incredibly
flexible.
To be able to trust a 25 year old, put them into, with all the bureaucracy of a hundred
thousand people globally, that seems pretty unique that they're able to just go, yeah,
we see something in you, go and go for it.
Yeah. I think I mentioned it a little bit, but I loved that people development aspect
to BP. And that's one of the things that they were incredibly strong with. I was there for
six months as a 21 year old and I got the tap from my manager and he said, we need you
to go to Papua New Guinea.
And to evaluate our distributorships in PNG. So I lived in PNG for six months as a 21 year
old because I was part of this graduate trainee scheme where they want to expose you and throw
you in the deep end all over the world to really test your ability to cope under pressure
and to deliver. And that's what they, you know, that's why they invest in you obviously
as a graduate trainee. But you're right. It was, they were some incredibly influential
and defining moments of my life being in PNG and then moving.
And then moving to Townsville and running the show up there.
Donna Urquhart is a physiotherapist and pain scientist, a Polar ultra marathon record
in December, 2023. Running 1300 kilometers over 30 days in Antarctica, her mission is
to raise one and a half million dollars to support the next generation of young females
in sport.
My mum, she has been the greatest role model. And I've only just realised, you know, I've
only just realised that I can do this for the next generation of young females in sport.
that recently, Luke. Just over the last sort of five to 10 years, having more conversations with
her, now being a mum, I've learnt just what she has taught me. I think when you're younger,
you don't necessarily realise that, you know, what you learn from your parents and how that
sort of washes over you. But just stories she's told me, I've really thought, yes, that part of
me that is prepared to step out and have a go and that curiosity to be on that cutting edge and find
out new information that has really come from her. Because she tells me about how she had my brother
and I, and she was in her 30s. She hadn't particularly had the support to do well at school.
And, you know, you can imagine back in that day for a mother with two young children to then go to
university, do a psychology degree and become a psychology teacher. It was quite a unique step
for her. And I know she's talked about people around her, her neighbours, her friends, really
raising eyebrows about that. And it wasn't the thing to do as a mother back then. So I think
that's just one example of the example she's given me.
Set that I've then, that's washed over me and helped me then step forward into areas that are
quite unique, like running in Antarctica, 1300 kilometres. I think that's given me the courage
to do that. And she has been incredibly supportive all the way through. She has had concerns.
We have talked about it. She actually did say to me at one point very early on when she didn't know
really the intricacies of what I was doing.
She did say to me, do you know, Donna, if something's to happen to you, that could have
quite a significant impact on your husband and your son. And I think the word destroy was in
there mixed in. I can't remember the exact words, but yeah, she was quite concerned to begin with.
And as her daughter, I didn't quite understand that. Like I found that,
really hard. I was like, where's that full support? I knew it was coming from a
place of love and concern. But now as a mother, I know exactly where that comes from. Because if my
son told me he was doing that, it would be a different story. But in fact, I have spoken to
my team about that and they've explained how pivotal that comment has been for them, how that's
really driven them to tick off all the risks.
And be really honed in on the incredible dangers that we can face when we're in Antarctica.
Danny Green is the only Australian boxer to win four world titles across three
different weight divisions. And he's represented his country at both the Commonwealth and Olympic
Games. Since self-funding his anti-violence movement, the Cowards Punch campaign,
his efforts have formed a legacy that may well outweigh all of his achievements in the boxing room.
My father. Yeah, my father, Malcolm, without doubt. No, he was my footy coach when we were
young from the age of nine to I was 17. We won three premierships, 14s, 15s and 17s and only
junior footy. And I was the smallest guy. The only place she could hide me was on the floor pocket.
And occasionally I'd get a crumb every now and then. And yeah, but we were not one of us in our
team. We played against guys at, you know, 17s grand final, Daniel Sirikowski, David Sirikowski
Southern. And then Mark Miranda as well, I think, played in the team we played against in the
grand final. So, you know, really good footballers. But in our team, not one person played reserves
footy. A couple of guys played a few games of Colts. We were ordinary players, but we were a
fantastic unit. So, for instance, this will make you smile. My old man was, he loved his footy. He
was a good footballer in the bush when he played. And then he loved coaching and he was a really,
really good, he knew how to get the best out of young blokes. And he was a dad who, he was a
pick up and drop off boys who couldn't make it to training or his old man wasn't present in their
life. And they all keep in touch with me to this day saying, your old man was just so good to me,
granny. You don't realise how much of an impact you had on my young life. And so that makes me
very proud. But on the way to our grand final, the 17s grand final, we played at Claremont Oval
and they were already on the ground. So we'd organised to meet at our home ground where we
played. We all go there, we all go in our gear, we all train and warm up there before.
We all get in a bus and we drive to the venue on the bus. When the bus got there, it got there like
five minutes before the game started. We ran straight off the bus onto the Oval, did a few
laps, a few warmups, bang. Soren went and we kicked the first goal and hit the ground running.
So his idea was let's rattle them. Let's rattle them. No one knew where we were. They thought
we'd gone down the ground because there was not one person from our team at the Oval and there
was five of us in both. Once again, I have really enjoyed going back to listen to Rich Burnett from
and her incredible mission to break the Guinness World Record in Antarctica for an ultramarathon and
the great Danny Green, one of the great sportsmen in Australian sporting history. And even though
they're unique and different backgrounds, you can see the patterns, all of them talking about having
someone trust and believe in your abilities to take on significant responsibility, the courage
and resilience to defy cultural norms and stand up for what you believe in. Along with kindness
and empathy and generosity of time, you see that pattern emerge.
A lot in the conversations I had across the year in 2023. Huge thank you to all of the guests that
featured on this episode. You can find the links to the full length in-depth conversations I had
with each of them in the show notes. Love you to go back and listen to some of those episodes.
In our next and final Success Leaves Clues episode, we'll hear about the power of collaboration,
something that we are really passionate about at Alita and the dream collaborations for a
carefully selected group from our 2020 season.
If you have enjoyed listening to this Empowering Leaders podcast,
please subscribe to our series. Love you to do that right now. Simply hit
the subscribe button. If you have time, leave us a review. We would love to reach more
listeners and hopefully empower more people in 2024.