What a great privilege it's been recording the Empowering Leaders series and witnessing
these incredible moments unfold when you sit across from such a unique group of inspiring
leaders delving into the intricacies of their success.
And in 2023, I hope you've felt like you've had a front row seat.
I certainly have, to conversations that reveal how success leaves clues, featuring individuals
who've mastered their craft in a variety of different fields.
At Alita, we recognize the consistent dimensions of brilliant leadership and the patterns that
emerge, and we're continuing our special series here where we explore them all and share them
with you.
Every day, we see the superpower of collaboration, unlocking opportunities for people that they
could only have dreamed of in the past.
Each week on the podcast, our conversations span diverse industries.
We love speaking to people from sport, from business, from education, from the arts or
social venture.
Thank you.
And in this episode, we've collected...
We've collected insights on collaboration from a small group of our guests who joined
me to share their wisdom, experiences, and leadership lessons, starting with the remarkable
Rochelle Courtney, the founder and managing director of Share the Dignity.
Especially when you come to big global problems like what we're trying to fix, I think collaboration
is everything.
So we collaborate with three and a half thousand charities because we couldn't actually get
the period products to the woman who's living on the street or fled domestically.
So it was really important for that collaboration piece to happen.
And then our volunteers collaborate with that charity and then make relationships with them.
But we've even done that on a global scale.
We held a global period poverty forum here in Australia with people who've been working
in this space around the world.
Never before have they all been brought together to try to work out how could we eradicate
period poverty around the world.
So collaboration is our middle name.
It is.
About everything that we do, because we can't solve these problems on our own.
And I always think that 10 heads thinking about a problem is better than one.
In the same vein, we are passionate about collaboration.
We have a leadership business, a leader connect, and we connect leaders from around the globe
and so fascinated and passionate about collaboration.
If you could collaborate, Rochelle, with anyone on anything, is there a name that springs to
mind?
It might be in the Share the Dignity space.
It might be in another area of passion.
Is there someone that springs to mind?
Brene Brown.
I just, I mean, I've read everything, but for me and for a lot of women, there is such
a, you know, that whole piece around being in the arena and, you know, not thinking that
you are good enough to be where, you know, I will stand on the stage and accept an award
and I will absolutely be on the inside dying because I don't believe that I should be there.
This imposter syndrome, no matter how much I try to overcome.
And it is a real thing for women.
And I would love to work with her further on, not me, but all of our volunteers and women
in general.
Jeff Dimmery is CEO of Alinta Energy and one of the key people leading Australia through
the energy transition.
If I had one sort of desire, it would be to see collaboration on a global scale.
So I'm talking about politics, unfortunately, now.
And we kind of let East and West get in the way of one another.
I mean, I'll go out on a big limb here, but I don't think the US is going to invade China
anytime soon.
And I certainly don't think China is going to invade the US or for that matter, Australia.
And so I wonder about how much money gets spent on things like submarines and defense
and whatnot.
And, you know, whether we not be better investing that $360 billion in the energy revolution
that we're in.
And that needs to take place, you know, rather than protecting our borders, let's all work
together and save the planet.
If you want the ultimate collaboration, that's it.
Tara Winkler is an extraordinary Australian humanitarian and co-founder of the Cambodian
Children's Trust.
Her work in Cambodia has helped to shine a powerful light on the ineffectiveness of our
current model of international aid.
Collaboration is the backbone of everything that we do, local collaboration that is.
And that was a real big challenge through COVID because everything that we do is done
in co-creation, in collaboration with the wider community.
That made it really difficult to do through COVID with all the lockdowns and things.
It's all done through collaboration with the wider community.
In the spirit of collaboration, and I love asking this question, in the space you're
in, have you thought about if I could collaborate with that person or that organization in any
area of your life, Tara?
Clearly.
What the work you're doing is the passion that jumps out.
Has there been someone that you've thought that would be an ideal boost to the work that
you're doing?
Dream collaboration.
I mean, honestly, anyone really, like all the dreamers and rebels and renegades and
people who believe what we believe and willing to kind of collaborate and help us make it
possible, build a more fair, egalitarian world, I'd welcome any collaboration because it's
not.
It's not something that we can do alone.
It's not a job for one person or one organization.
It is going to take an army of people to create systems change on that scale.
So the more, the merrier.
And I think sometimes we think that, you know, a job like that is kind of a utopian fantasy.
But, you know, if you think back through civilization, all of the major changes that were, you know,
democracy, the end of slavery, vote for women.
And gay marriage, they all, once upon a time, seemed like a utopian fantasy, so.
Coming up, you're going to hear from one of the most successful Olympians of all time,
Olympic swimmer Tracy Stockwell and Ivan Cleary, the coach of the Penrith Panthers, fresh from
a triple premiership success that is worth hearing more about.
I really loved hearing from Michelle Courtney, from Jeff Demery and from Tara Winkler and
their unique perspectives from different worlds.
Tara founding the Cambodian Children's Trust.
Jeff with his passion for the.
Landscape of energy in Australia and Michelle Courtney with Share the Dignity, quite remarkable,
but all passionate about how collaboration can take your efforts to a bigger, sometimes
global audience.
And in order to take on big challenges, the nature of collaboration really has a huge
impact when you get it right.
At Alita, we are really passionate about creating a world of collaboration, inspiring
connections and bringing together these diverse leaders from different backgrounds around
the globe to share, to learn, to connect.
We would love you to check out Alita Connect, our signature program.
Head to alitacollective.com.
You don't have to be a global head of marketing for an international company or a superstar
coach to be part of Alita Connect.
We would love to book a discovery call, have a chat to us, and we'd love to share your
leadership journey with you.
Big thanks as always to Jason Nicholas and his team from Temper, Australia and New Zealand
for their ongoing support for the Empowering Leaders podcast.
We know that getting a good night's sleep is a pattern that we see in all great leaders.
Temper is a mattress like no other.
Check it out today.
The next group of guests will speak to how collaboration has played a really vital role
on their path to success.
Let's go first to Olympic swimming legend Tracy Stockwell, one of the most successful
athletes in US sporting history.
I had noticed that women's sport wasn't really recognised as much back in the early
90s and the opportunities for girls and women weren't great.
And I had been involved in women's sport for a long time.
I was involved in America with the Women's Sports Foundation to try and raise the profile
of women's sport as well.
So we kind of got together and created Women's Sport Queensland and create more opportunities
and awareness about women and girls in sport because they were performing beautifully and
but just not getting the recognition.
And I think the papers and the media were giving more recognition to dogs and horses
than they were to women at the time.
And we tried to.
You know, work really hard to to change that and found a lot of good men who supported
us, whether it was corporate or through the media and often men with daughters who appreciate,
you know, they think, well, oh, this might be my daughter that might have an opportunity
if we do the right thing here.
So I think that was a really good strategy.
And so I've always loved trying to give back to sport because it gave me so much and really
proud of that.
And, you know, still catch up with lots of our founding members of Women's Sport Queensland.
And now you look at Michelle Payne, the in Rio, the women's teams doing so well, the
cricket team, the women's AFLW, the NRLW and how the opportunities for women have really
increased, which I'm really proud and like to think that we had a little bit to do with
that.
Collaboration is another thing we see people really value now more than ever and understand
the value of it.
How important has that been for you?
Oh, I think very important.
I think we're not, you know, alone and you can always do things better, I think, with
others.
And it also helps to have that support and people maybe sharing a different way of doing
something and coming up with a good outcome for everyone.
I think so.
And I think I'm pretty good at that.
I think and maybe I don't know if it's a female thing or but just mediating.
And monitoring and wanting.
I'm a bit of a pleaser as well, I think.
So wanting to get a good outcome and making sure everyone has their say and then, you
know, bringing people together and coming to a common, you know, path.
So I think that's very important to work together.
And as I said, I think Mark and I work together well as a team, whether it's in raising our
kids or running a business or our sporting ventures.
Ivan Cleary is an icon of the NRL and head coach of the Penrith Panthers.
He's just led them to secure a trilogy of premiership victories in 2021, 22 and 23.
How important has collaboration been for you?
Everything.
Yeah, everything.
I love that style.
I love getting people's opinions.
I get it.
You know, at the end of the day, most of the buck will stop with me on most things.
If not all of them, honestly, even though you're delegating all that at the end of the
day, like, as I said before, the performance of the team, that's with me.
That's on me.
But I love getting people's input.
You know, I love getting different views.
And then for me to be able to, from that, go, okay, this is where we're going to go.
I just think it's, I think that's one of the great things about coaching.
That's actually how you learn.
You just pick up little nuggets from people you least expect.
You know, it could be like an intern or something.
It could be anyone, you know.
And I just feel that's, yeah, I feel that's an essential part.
It's easier when you get older, I think, because it's easier to be a little insecure from time
to time.
And you feel like, oh, if I'm supposed to be the head coach, you know, like, I'm feeling
like this guy knows more than I do, or he's smarter than me, or, you know, that takes
a bit of time to be able to get over, I reckon, and just, you know, be able to, I guess, establish
that maturity and confidence.
And I feel like at the moment, I'm certainly at a better place there to be able to, you
know, collaborate properly.
I love listening back to Tracy Stockwell and Ivan Cleary, their unique success stories.
Tracy is one of the most successful Olympians of all time.
And Ivan Cleary, he is carving a path of success in the NRL like we've never seen before.
They both spoke about raising awareness through collaboration and shared vision and the possibilities
of getting to a point you hadn't thought of before, embracing collaboration early on and
not waiting until you feel like you have enough experience or confidence.
Huge thank you to all.
Thank you.
And to all the guests featured on this episode, you can find the links to their full-length
in-depth conversations I have with each of them in the show notes across 2023.
We really hope that you've taken a lot from this series on the dimensions of leadership.
We'll be back next year with a brand new episode as we kick off 2024 in a big way with a number
of inspiring conversations on the Empowering Leaders series.
If you enjoy listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast series, we'd love you to subscribe.
Just hit the subscribe button now.
If you have a moment, please leave a review.
We are passionate about reaching more people and empowering more leaders in 2024.