Well, what a great privilege it has been to sit down across from so many inspiring people
in 2023 for the Empowering Leaders podcast.
And we talk often about the fact that success leaves clues with people at the top of their
game and in their chosen field.
Certainly learnt a lot from a remarkable group of people last year in 2023.
At Alita, we know that there are consistent dimensions of what brilliant leadership looks
like, and we're going to cover them all in this special series.
We know that the ability to create and share a vision in a way that has impact is an incredibly
valuable skill, but it's a skill within reach for everyone who puts their mind to it.
Each week on the Empowering Leaders podcast, we hear from people across all industries,
from sport, from business, education, social venture, and the arts.
And when it comes to the dimension of successfully creating and sharing a vision, we've hand
selected some phenomenal people from this group you're about to hear from and learn
from as we go.
I want to start with an AFL.
I want to start with an AFL legend, Michael Voss, one of the greatest players that I've
ever seen play the game.
Ruthless in some ways, but a very passionate leader on the field.
And he's really evolved his style of leadership over the time to a very successful new generation
of young men at the Carlton Football Club.
Have a listen to the great Michael Voss.
What's actually really important at the start is that everyone has a say on the way forward.
If there's one thing I've learnt about...
You know, groups now is that they want to belong to something and they want to own something.
And having a say on that direction actually really inspires them to want to be a part
of it.
So at the start, it was quite literally, I said to the players, how do you want to play?
Let's scribble it down.
Let's write it down.
And they're not far off.
They're smart guys.
They know their footy.
And then, you know, asking, I guess, then permission, which sounds like a silly thing
to do because that's your job, right?
I was like, oh, can we take that away?
And as coaches, we'll come up with something and we'll come back to you and let's work
through the language.
And let's really sort of hone in what really sort of sits well with you.
And so that's what we did.
As coaches, we went away.
We formulated some plans.
We formulated some principles.
We come back.
We check with the group.
What do you think?
Yeah, we love it.
We go back again.
Okay, can we put some structure in that?
Can we put some roles around that?
What roles would that look like?
And then sort of your themes start to emerge out of that.
So I feel if you can have that approach and the players can buy into it and they all own
it, when you come back as a coach and say, hang on, didn't we all, it's not going, didn't
we say...
Hey, we're all in on this.
It has much more power.
It has much more meaning rather than it's just the coach's idea.
And it's just the coaches that are running the schedule and we just follow what they
do.
It's important to bring them along on the journey.
But also what's really important is that using as many opportunities as you can is to show
or talk about your vision and talk about what it should look like.
Because I think we want that.
We want to see what it looks like.
But also then how is it relevant for what I'm doing right now in the moment today?
And that's what all the...
Research says, of course, if you co-create it with the team and they are in part of the
process of determining their own vision, it's just so much more pet sticks, doesn't it?
Yeah.
If you come in over the top and just it's your words and not theirs.
So...
Yeah, I love that co-create.
I love that co-create.
And even just with the training environments, what we try to do is try and enable them to
be able to problem solve and have those conversations about what's working and what's not working
and skill our leaders to be able to have those conversations.
Because there's no stronger conversation than peer conversation and them getting on the
same page.
So we certainly haven't perfected that.
We're nowhere near by any means the finished product on it.
But there are some of the things that actually are really important to us in our environment.
Richard Oppie is Vice President of Global Brands for the largest consumer goods company
in the world, making his role arguably the biggest marketing job in the world.
His company is responsible for leading beer brands,
including Budweiser, Corona, Stella Artois, and many more.
When I think of a vision, one that springs to mind is the marketing leadership team.
So that was when I, 2017, I remember we were in Mexico.
We had our global marketing leadership team conference.
And we had this conversation.
We were like, I'm sick of being known as a zero-based budgeting company.
I'm a company known for mergers and acquisition.
Why aren't we renowned as a marketing company?
A company that can grow organically, top line.
Because there aren't many more other companies to buy where we're going to be able to take
the synergies and increase our bottom line.
We need to start driving top line growth.
And so there were lots of debates at the time.
And we decided, you know what?
We want to be the best marketing team in the world.
And we decided, how are we going to measure that?
And really, the two big measures were like,
we want to be known as the creative marketer of the year at Kahn,
which is probably the biggest reward you can get,
the biggest award for marketers in the world.
And then we also want to be the most effective marketing company in the world,
which is the Effies Index.
And so it's been a big five-year journey.
And it hasn't been a fluke.
So we've sort of put systems in place.
And it really came down to, we call it the three Ps.
So people.
Sorry, for those listening before,
you've just won those awards on a global scale,
which is a remarkable achievement to put you competing with the Nikes.
And they're the previous winners.
Sorry, before you continue on.
Yeah, it was this year, we sort of had all-time volume high.
So the highest volumes we've ever had at the company.
Our brand equity, which we call brand power, is at an all-time high.
And this year, we won creative marketer of the year at Kahn.
And number one for the most effective,
marketing company in the world.
So you talk about dreaming big.
Five years ago, we were ranked 42nd.
And we said we wanted to be number one.
And people laughed at us at first.
AB InBev, you're an M&A company.
And we're like, no, we're going to be the best marketing company in the world.
And credit to the team that have been involved.
Miguel Patricio was our CMO at the time.
And he really led the way to foster this creativity across the entire organization.
And he put the right people in place that were modern marketers.
And then we created culture and capabilities team across all our markets.
And then we put processes in place.
So we created like a creative spectrum, the way we talk about the work from a one to a 10.
And we set up like a brain trust.
We would have external and internal people to talk about the work, to make the work better.
And then we sort of overhauled our partners.
We got the best people around us, the best agencies around us.
And having those all set up, you know, it wasn't just one country that was being recognized.
We had basically all our countries around the world being recognized as the best marketers in the world,
which ultimately became the global company.
So it's been something that I've been privileged to be part of this team.
And it's been an incredible journey.
Andrew Gaze is the greatest name in the history of Australian basketball.
As a five-time Olympian, he was Australia's flag bearer
at the 2000 Summer Olympic Games in Sydney.
Well, for me, and that depends on the circumstances,
whether it's family, whether it's business, whether it's the sport, coaching,
all those different things, is always going in there and appreciating that we're all different.
And the way in which people will approach certain environments or challenges,
can sometimes be different.
Accepting that sometimes a preconceived idea on how things should be done,
as opposed to being open-minded and being objective about other suggestions,
I think can be detrimental.
Now, you might always come back,
and you might come back to your own preconceived idea about a certain thing,
but not having an openness and a willingness to take on the challenge,
and a willingness to explore and see that there are always alternatives out there.
Progress is made by innovation and new things all the time.
And one of the gross criticisms of me is Gaze sits on the fence.
Gaze sits on the fence.
He never makes a decision.
No, no, no.
Gaze doesn't sit on the fence.
Gaze has...
I love him in a third person, Gaze.
But what I try to do is understand that,
no, no, I've got an opinion, I've got a view,
but I'm not going to dismiss someone else's view until I understand it,
appreciate it, make an assessment on it, and then go,
no, that's for me.
I come into situations often with a predisposed position,
but that doesn't mean you can't change.
And I think that approach to leadership, I think, is really important.
Why?
There are times where I can be, as a coach, highly dictatorial,
and that would fly in the face of everything I just said,
but that's in the moment.
So, we've made a decision.
We're going to run this play, and in order for us to have the best chance,
we are running, and if you don't do it, I'm going to hold you accountable to that.
Now, after we've gone through it, we look at the statistical data,
we check out over a sample size.
We've done that.
we've gone through all the process, and you've shown me
and demonstrated, well, there's an alternative, absolutely.
Let's make that change, and then we'll incorporate those things.
But a lot of, especially from a coaching standpoint, this is it.
I'm doing this, come hell or high water, because I know it's been successful.
I'm going to do it, and I'm going to teach you how to do it,
and that is all there is to do with it.
Well, there's a time and a place for that.
But you also have to be open-minded enough to understand
and consider alternatives.
Coming up, we're going to hear from Olympic gold medal winner Steve Hooker
and his unique style of thinking, soccer star Harry Kuehl,
one of the great players in Australian sporting history.
And as Michael Voss, Richard Oppie, and Andrew Gaze share,
there is real power in dreaming big, bringing people along for the ride
and being open-minded, even if you already feel like you've got an idea
of the best way forward.
At Alita, we are really passionate about creating a world of collaboration,
inspiring connections, and bringing together these diverse leaders
from different backgrounds around the globe to share, to learn,
to connect, and to collaborate.
We would love you to check out Alita Connect, our signature program.
Head to alitacollective.com.
You don't have to be a global head of marketing for an international company
or a superstar coach to be part of Alita Connect.
We would love to book a discovery call, have a chat to us,
and we'd love to share your leadership journey with you.
Big thanks.
As always, to Jason Nicholas and his team from Temper, Australia and New Zealand
for their ongoing support of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
We know that getting a good night's sleep is a pattern that we see
in all great leaders.
Temper is a mattress like no other.
Check it out today.
This next group of guests all speak to how the power of creating
and sharing a vision with your team has led them to a life of great success.
Let's go first to Elizabeth Broderick AO,
Australia's longest-serving sex discrimination commissioner,
and now an independent expert on the United Nations Human Rights Council,
working on laws and practices that discriminate against women.
Sharing the vision is about engaging people's both their heads and their hearts.
I mean, what I learned early on is you could share all the data
which supported your vision.
My vision is for a much more gender-equal world,
a kinder, more compassionate world, a prosperous world for sure,
but one where everyone has.
A place everyone's valued, treated with dignity and respect.
And to get people along on that journey often means that they need to shift.
Now I can put all the data about, you know, the gender inequality stats.
You know, women are paid less, they're experienced more violence.
They're sexually harassed more, all that data that will never be enough.
What I need to do is engage people's hearts and I do that through the,
I mean, just that story that I told then and read verbatim, that letter.
It's the stories of human harm that are happening in this moment.
If I can engage you on that, then I think you will more,
be more likely to step up with me on my vision of a gender-equal world.
Because change usually happens not by taking a giant leap.
It happens by adding, adding to, continuing, adding more.
All these things.
Small nudges and really about healing the part of the world that touches you,
that's around you.
And to do that, you have to get proximate to the issues and listen to the stories
or what I, what I call the other voices, the voices that are outside, usually your remit.
Um, so to get people to come on board with my vision, um, I'm helping
them get proximate to the human harm.
I'm investing in storytelling.
I'm engaging both.
Yeah.
And then helping them see what part they can play in creating, um, you know,
creating this more, more gender equal world.
And actually I, I love the work, um, that I think it's, um, just trying to remember,
uh, the guy who wrote the, um, uh, a humor Chi, it was, uh, he's written a lot, but his
new book was on the kindness pandemic.
And he said there, look, if we, if we, if we, if we, if we, if we, if we, if we, if we, if
we dare to dream of a more loving country, a kinder, more compassionate, more
cooperative, more respectful, um, country, then there's really only one
way to turn that dream into reality.
And that is that each of us must live our lives of if, as if that country
already exists, because if enough of us do that, then that country will exist.
And, and I love to, you know, kind of move along in, in
that vein to help others see that if we just shift a little bit and live in that way, then
we will create this vision of a more gender equal Australia family nation.
Steve Hooker is an Olympic track and field gold medalist and the first Australian man
to hold both Olympic and world championship titles concurrently his incredible commitment
and work ethic has seen his outstanding success in sport.
Replicated in his business career.
There's a huge difference between having your own vision and then turning that vision
into a shared vision by broader group.
Like that's, that's a really hard thing to do.
And I probably didn't understand how hard that was at first.
I assumed you tell people once, and then we're all saying the same thing and we're
all running in the same direction.
And that just couldn't be anything further from the truth.
Even if you do one beautiful presentation that really shows people like that, everyone
interprets it, interprets things so differently.
And then also like having a really clear back to purpose plan vision, breaking that down
to the simplest plan.
So everyone can say each day, what the element is that you're working on, how does it fit
into the overall plan?
How's that going to get us to our vision and finding 50 different ways, not one to explain
that story so that over time it becomes a shared vision and understanding that that
takes time.
There's no.
No one trick that's going to get everyone saying things in the same way, persistence,
varied messages, varied mediums of trying to get that message across and just doing
it over and over again.
So it's almost boring.
Everyone's like, yeah, we get it.
And then that's probably the point when you're like, okay, it feels like if everyone's saying
this is boring, then we're probably all of a sudden seeing the same thing and we can
talk about it in the same way and we can see the pathway that we're going to get there.
Harry Kuehl is recognized as Australia's greatest ever footballer.
He's currently the first team manager with the famous Celtic Football Club in Scotland.
Oh, easy.
I mean, I, I love creating.
I'm a creative person.
I was a creative player.
And that's the one thing as me being a manager, I've, you know, I've always written
everything like I always wrote everything down, but I never really like had a plan.
I mean, the one thing that always amazes me is when I used to go, go for jobs and people
go, well, how do you play?
How do you, you know, how do you do this?
How do you, well, I don't know what team have I got?
What players have I got?
And that was one thing that people say, no, you must have a certain style.
Well, of course I have a certain style of how I want to play, but if I don't have them
players, right, then how am I supposed to be able to play that I want to play?
You know, you, you got to be able to be adaptive, especially at the start.
So that was me as a coach.
But then as I've gone into a player, I mean, as an individual coach, I've looked at it
in completely different ways where I'm looking at.
I'm looking at movement patterns.
I'm looking at body language.
I'm looking at shift and defenders, and I'm only going through experience of what I got
taught when I was younger.
And I go back to even when I got taught how to strike a ball or the cross the ball or
the volleyball, these things got broken down for me, like where my foot got, how my foot
had to be placed, how my knee had to be bent, how my shoulder had to be pointed.
And I don't know.
I've always remembered it.
And I knew, and I knew how to do it because the one thing I could do in the game was I
was a very good striker of the ball and a very good crosser of the ball.
So when you put me in situation, I can tell when my wingers don't cross the ball properly.
I can just hear by the noise of the ball.
You know, I can see by the pattern of how the ball slides across the grass and I'll
just go, no, I'll just go, no, I'll just go.
And then when they hit it perfect, I'll go, do you hear the sound?
And then even now they're listening to the sound of it.
So it's not about me having all this.
Information and not sharing it.
I will share anything with anybody if they're willing to learn, you know, and I think that's
the important thing is that's why I say it's gotta be a two way, uh, two way, um, street.
Cause if it's not, then you're just talking to, to deaf ears and don't get me wrong.
I've got one or two players up there that are not interested, you know, they, they will
sit there and you do a drill with them and all that.
And you know, well, if they need anything, they'll come to you, but then you have the
other ones that really want to learn.
And you just put all your energy and effort into them.
Really love listening back to Liz, to Steve Hooker and Harry Kuehl and could see the consistent
pattern of storytelling to engage people's heads and their hearts in creating and sharing
a vision, understanding that everyone at the table interprets things differently and finding
a way to connect with people consistently was really interesting to hear, focusing on
the people who are willing to learn as well and letting them be the super storytellers
in your ability to share a vision.
And a huge thanks to all the guests featured on this episode.
You can find the links to the full length in depth conversations I had with each of
them in the show notes on our next successfully as clues episode, curiosity is a leadership
dimension that shapes our learning and development.
And we're excited to explore its transformative impact on the journeys of some exceptional
guests next week.
Make sure you tune in for that one.
And if you have enjoyed listening to the empowering leaders podcast, we'd love you to hit the
subscribe button right now.
And if you have a moment.
Please leave a review for us so we can reach more listeners and empower more leaders in
2024.