I think first and foremost, it is about turning up for you.
I think there's a lot to learn in all of us trying to lead a balanced life.
I've asked the question, who's got the control panel here?
Like, I want to control myself right now.
Yes, you have to understand yourself, but you also have to understand them.
That's why it's important to ask questions.
What a great privilege it has been to sit across from so many inspirational,
unique, different leaders from diverse backgrounds throughout the year,
all with their own unique leadership story.
At Leader, we know that there are consistent dimensions of what great leadership looks like,
and we'll cover them all across the next seven episodes.
And I'm really keen to start with this idea of self-leadership.
We know it's very difficult to lead others unless you've got a strong sense
of what self-leadership means to you and this idea of leading yourself well first.
On every Empowering Leaders episode, we hear from people at the top of their industry,
whether that be from the world of sport, from business, education, arts, or social venture.
And when it comes to the dimension of self-leadership,
we knew we were sitting on an absolute goldmine of wisdom
from the selection of guests you're about to hear from.
We have the incredible Andy Kelly, one of Australia's leading music label directors and managers,
and such a fantastic person, Andy, in every sense.
The remarkable Umrah Omar, a Kenyan humanitarian and community conservation strategist,
and the founder of Safari Doctors, and what an inspiration Umrah is in every sense.
So, right, Eddington joined us.
throughout the year, highly distinguished Australian businessman, community leader,
former deputy chair of News Limited, and was the CEO of British Airways
before moving on to incredible roles across so many different areas.
Let's get started with another inspiration, and that is Hugh Van Kylenburg,
the founder of the Resilience Project and the Imperfects podcast.
I'm seeing my psychologist once every two weeks at the moment,
and with the challenges we've got in our family at the moment,
I've been finding really...
really difficult of late, and I've been saying to her,
I'm doing this stuff, and there's the exercise that keeps me...
Exercise is the big thing for me, plus performing with our live tour,
but I noticed even those things weren't starting to really have the effect I wanted them to,
like they weren't, you know, whenever I exercise I just feel so happy,
or performing so happy, or journaling and gratitude, empathy and mindfulness stuff,
and I've noticed in the last few months it hasn't quite been...
it just hasn't been working the way it usually does,
and that's made me panic a bit and go, oh my God,
if these things aren't working, where am I at now?
But she said, you've just got to drag yourself towards these things right now,
and the wheel will turn for you, but you've got to keep dragging yourself towards this stuff,
so I don't think I've really answered the question,
but I know that no matter where you are, we're all on the mental health spectrum somewhere.
Some people are sitting at the top, and life's great, and some are down the bottom,
but if you come back to this stuff, the research says if you practice gratitude,
which is where you pay attention to what you've got,
you don't worry about what you don't have,
you can practice empathy, which is when you put yourself...
in someone else's shoes, and you look for compassionate action from that,
and if you practice mindfulness, just being wherever you are,
the only thing that is really happening in our world is what's happening right now.
Those things will have a positive impact on your mental health.
Those things will help you to experience more joy,
and even... I used to say this from a place of privilege,
which I was just so happy, no problems in my life.
Life was great. Come on, guys, do this stuff. It really helps.
I'm now saying it from a place of life's pretty tough at the moment,
and I know this stuff is going to get better.
It's going to get me through, even if it doesn't feel like it is at the time,
I could have kept dragging myself to the treadmill,
dragging myself to the gym, dragging myself to my journal,
dragging myself to breathwork, whatever it is, and the wheel will turn.
And do you feel that consistency is the key?
And like a lot of people, when it gets stressful,
it's almost the hardest time.
You say drag yourself to the treadmill.
Absolutely.
Hard to write in your journal when you're feeling shit.
Hard to be mindful when there's chaos going on on whatever front there is.
And do you think sometimes we kid ourselves a little bit when we go,
it's not working, but if we actually write down,
we go, I may have let that slip a little bit more than I understood.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, and it's so hard when you're not feeling good.
It's so much harder than when you're feeling good.
You have a good day and think, gosh, shit,
things are going pretty well for me at the moment.
I might write a gratitude journal.
That's not hard.
It's good for you.
It's good to do it.
But when you are really up against it and you've got some stuff really going wrong
in your life, stuff that you may not be able to control,
which makes it even more challenging at times,
that's when it's hard to, you know, fuck doing a gratitude journal.
I'll have a beer.
You know?
That's like who's in control of you?
Like who's controlling you?
Like who is in control?
But it's like just if you're looking at a couple of options,
which is staying up later, having a beer,
or journaling and going to bed early,
or doing the stuff that makes you feel good,
if you're taking the option that you know in that moment,
like I know this isn't the right thing to do,
but I'm going to do it anyway.
You just ask yourself the question,
who's got the control panel here?
Like I want to control myself right now.
I think often I think I do so many analogies around running,
but as a runner, you'll have those days where you get up and you're like,
I'm not feeling it today, but you do it anyway.
And it doesn't, it's not as quick as you usually go,
but you've got the miles in your legs and you go, well, I've done that.
It wasn't my best, but I dragged myself there.
I've sort of got that approach to everything right now.
This idea that success leaves clues is a term I use every week on this podcast.
And we've seen these traits of different leaders,
and I'm fascinated with you because you're such a deep thinker and so articulate.
The idea that it's hard to lead anyone else without a sense of self-leadership
is something we talk about a lot.
What does that mean to you, self-leadership?
Oh, self-leadership.
I have thought about this because I hear the term come up,
a bit throughout a leader.
Self-leadership, I think self-leadership is giving yourself,
it's like protecting your energy and giving yourself space to think about
what is best for you, understanding that that will also be best
for the people who are around you.
And I think the tendency for a lot of us is to see a spare hour
in our calendar and fill it, or see a spare afternoon in the calendar
and just fill it and go, oh, I could do this then, I could do this then.
We go from one thing to the next.
And the more, in the last few years that I have protected those,
like just have nothing to do, I think more creatively.
I think about, I end up thinking about the people around me.
Like I think about our podcast team, I think about the Resilience Project team.
And I think about what's, what I need to do for myself to be in a good place.
And I prioritize that stuff.
I think that makes me a better leader.
The more time, ironically, the more time I have off, the better leader I am, I think.
It's a brilliant answer.
And I haven't heard anyone go there before, isn't it?
Around, yeah, allocating that free time.
And my mind was going to that analogy of the, give yourself the oxygen mask first
on the plane because you can't save the infant next to you.
Is that, is that?
I think so.
I remember, I can't remember, like protect your energy has been a big thing
for me in the last year or two.
Cause I've burnt out, I think 2019, 2020, I burnt out three years in a row.
I got to November and I was really unwell.
And I wouldn't say it was like a,
I wore it as a badge of honor, but I was like, well, I've given everything this year.
I've gone so hard.
But then when you go so hard like that, you're not the only one who suffers.
Like the people that you love most in your life suffer,
the people who are closest to you suffer.
So my partner, my kids and the teams that I, I love my podcast team.
And I love my resilience project team.
They suffer too.
And I think we forget that sometimes.
And so I managed to work out a way of like, I'm protecting,
but my overall thing is protect your energy.
And to do that, protect this time.
So I've got in my calendar and I've got,
there are four people who have access to my calendar and can schedule stuff for me.
And I've just got Hugh not available.
And there's big chunks that go for the next two years.
I've already got them just out there and I'm not,
they're not allowed to touch them.
I know they can't touch them.
And it's not, I'm being lazy.
It's like, I am, Billy Slater said the 2022 series,
Save Origin series.
He said to the players really early on camp, he said,
you only have one energy pool.
I said, you've got one energy and we've got a game in 10 days time.
And I want you to remember that the time you spend on social media,
worrying about what fans think,
the times you spend reading what the paper says,
the time you spend in this 10 day camp,
I want this to be about protecting as much energy as possible.
He didn't say protecting energy.
He said, I want it to be about understanding you have one energy.
It's not like you can go, well,
I'll just lie on the couch and give those energy to social media and have
energy left for the game tomorrow night.
So you've got one energy and I want you to be very focused on keeping it as
full as possible.
And that really spoke,
to me not about state of origin.
That was not for me.
It was just, yeah,
I only have,
I only have one energy.
And I think to myself,
I can do all these talks and I can run during the day and then I can come
home and have energy for the family,
but you only have this one energy.
So my running is,
is the analogy of running is like I'm a sprinter and with sprinters,
it's like it's preparation for races is trying to have as much energy as
possible.
So you don't smash yourself in the wake,
letting up to the training.
You,
you're really clever about it and you taper.
And it's almost like,
I'm sort of tapering for life now.
I'm like,
if I want to have energy at the end of the day for the kids,
which is the hardest part of the day,
I can't do four talks.
I can't run.
I need to have time where that,
that to me is like,
I know it,
it doesn't sound like self-leadership,
but my version of that is it's like,
look after yourself,
leave a lot of petrol in the tank for the people around you.
I think basics are just really important for me,
like self-leadership,
like,
um,
eat well,
exercise,
uh,
every day and try and get enough sleep.
And,
uh,
that's it.
And do those things consistently,
um,
do the basics consistently.
For me,
it makes me feel really,
um,
up to it,
up for the task and,
and to be clear headed,
I guess,
because,
you know,
every day you're absorbing,
you're absorbing people's anxieties,
their,
their difficulties,
um,
and,
and to not spend my free time absorbing too much,
like social media,
TV,
you know,
um,
of course I do,
you know,
like,
of course I'll watch something or whatever,
but not too,
not too much.
I'm conscious of like,
I don't need to pick up my phone and check Instagram every two hours.
Like I'll re I'll read the news at the start of the day and the end of the day.
I'll make a conscious effort.
I don't need to know.
I don't need to know what a local council bus does going on.
I don't,
I don't need to know it.
It's too much information.
So that's it for me,
like pretty straightforward,
which is sounds easy,
but in the rock and roll industry that that must have taken some courage to be
able to,
and the peer pressure must have been enormous.
As you said,
it's an industry where it's the rock and roll lifestyle,
isn't it?
So to be someone that's like,
I don't need to do that,
um,
takes incredible leadership.
It's a,
it's a great story.
We're really passionate about the impact people are conscious of having on others.
And I want to ask you the question,
is,
is there one piece of leadership advice that you've taken on board that you
share regularly?
Is there something that comes to mind on that front?
I think it is.
I don't know if anyone gave me the advice or it just came over time.
Like,
well,
maybe again,
it's really simple.
Luke.
It's like,
have fun.
Are you having fun?
Like if you're making music,
is it fun?
Are you having fun?
And always ask yourself,
why,
why am I doing this?
Like the whole thing when we all get caught in the minutia of what we do every day and
we get frustrated and,
um,
nah,
I mean,
of course we're going to get for it.
So I'm not saying,
you know,
I'm a Buddhist monk,
things annoy me and,
and stuff,
but,
but to just strip it back,
just keep it really simple.
We don't need to overcomplicate what we're doing.
You know,
like if I'm operating to remove a tumor from someone's brain,
I suspect that is pretty complicated.
But if we're trying to put some music up on a streaming service and sell some tickets,
is it fun?
And why,
why are we doing it?
And that's,
that that's it.
It means so much to me because it's a reflection of when we look at a seed,
if you look at a seed,
it's like this,
just this tiny little something.
And then what people come to see is when they're eating the fruits of it.
And when you're like,
you know,
you have a tree or a bush and it's like,
Oh my God,
this is amazing.
But you're like,
actually it started as a seed.
And what,
what is the seed that defines us?
And not being overwhelmed by thinking of,
okay,
we have to become this huge mango tree or this huge bush,
but just being focused on nurturing that small seed.
And then so many things come together,
the weather,
it's the weather coming together.
It's the soil.
So that's how we are as humans and in the work that we do.
And for me,
that's what really helps me not get too overwhelmed,
overwhelmed about what we're doing.
It's like,
do your part and then the rest will take care of itself.
And that's what happened with Safari doctors.
That's what's happening.
That's what happens with raising kids.
You don't get a manual told,
okay,
this is how your adult would look like.
Therefore do this today,
this tomorrow.
So that's the philosophy around that consistency.
It's because of,
you have to pace yourself,
knowing that what you're a part of is much bigger than yourself.
So just do your part.
And you mentioned raising kids and you're a mother.
And do you take that same approach to you that you're really just in,
in every day you can do small things.
And hopefully at the end that you've made the contribution you want to your
own family.
It's because,
you know,
you trust in that DNA,
what makes you up and you do what you can because,
or else it's kind of,
you know,
like moving countries.
Someone's like,
you know,
so what's your plan?
What are you,
you know,
in five years,
three years.
I know there's something bigger that this is a journey off.
And sometimes you can define what your,
where,
you're headed.
Sometimes you just open trusting that the steps that you're taking in your
leadership journey,
in your parenthood journey,
in your workspaces,
that it being open to what's unfolding and trusting that you're,
you're wired to go through that on my end,
more severely though,
I is like,
I have a serious allergy to injustice,
like super allergic to that.
I'm talking,
I will not be quiet.
And I think for me,
that's what pushes me to kind of,
maybe it's almost like proving a point that,
you know,
you say whether it's like,
Oh,
as women,
you can't or shouldn't be able to do this.
I'm like that invoke some serious self-leadership to prove otherwise.
You're talking about,
Oh,
you know,
talk about race.
You talk about nationalism,
you bring it.
But for me,
it's like really puts up that fire.
And especially in like seeing it for the next generation,
because I feel like we're,
we're almost in that phase of,
it's no longer about aspiring,
but about transmitting before then checking out and being like,
okay,
you've done what you've done.
So also the young,
the next generation is really inspiring.
It drives me to have that push of,
okay,
we need to pass that baton on.
You need to be on top of your stuff.
You need to be that role model.
You need to explore,
find the boundaries.
Yes.
You have to understand yourself,
but you also have to understand them.
That's why it's important to ask questions because when you ask questions of
people,
you begin to understand them as well as the issues.
Um,
but I think leaders need to be comfortable in their own skin in many ways.
And for someone like me that came from sport as well as the classroom,
you know,
I think I learned more,
about leadership on the sporting field than I did in the classroom probably.
And I think I'm not unusual in that sense.
So,
um,
the other thing you have to,
if you're going to lead in a business sense or in a sporting sense,
you better really understand the industry or the game you're involved in.
I think the best leaders are passionate about the,
the business they're in or the sport they're in or the business of sport.
They're passionate about,
they think about it in the shower in the morning.
They don't sort of pick it up at nine o'clock and put it down at five.
And they're constantly curious about understanding the new things that are coming in.
So,
you know,
aviation when I retired was very different to aviation when I joined.
Technology had changed,
aeroplanes had changed,
but the way in which we use it systems had changed remarkably.
No,
we'd gone from people booking a flight on the telephone to doing it online.
I mean,
there were,
it was constantly changing and you've got to stay abreast of those changes.
We are really privileged to have many of the guests that you hear from the empowering leaders podcast who are part of our leader connect program.
We bring together groups of five to six people from around the globe from unique and diverse backgrounds who come together to learn and to connect and to share.
We are really passionate about what happens when you connect great people together in a really trusted environment.
We'd love to tell you more about it.
Head to elitacollective.com and book a discovery call with us today.
We are super proud to be working alongside one of the world's great learning institutions,
Victoria University as our support partner in 2025.
No one sees you like VU.
Victoria University is uniquely you.
We see a lot of great synergy between the world of Victoria University and our passion for the world of a leader and the empowering leaders podcast.
This episode is also proudly brought to you by temper mattresses,
adjustable bases and pillows.
The difference is temper.
The next group of guests all speak of how self leadership has driven them to the highest levels of success.
We're going to hear from Reggie Butler,
the founder and CEO of performance paradigm,
one of the world's most respected leaders in connecting teams and developing great people.
Kirsten King joins us,
the founder of fluid form Pilates,
a brilliant success story in her own right.
But let's first go to James Tonkin.
Oh, I am a sport Australia hall of fame legend and perhaps best known.
Okay.
As one quarter of the awesome foursome that won world titles in 1990 91 98 and Olympic gold in 92 and 96.
The Olympic village is the example to the rest of the world of what is possible.
You've got every race,
color,
creed,
religion in there.
And because of something,
and in this case,
it's sport just bringing everyone together and it doesn't matter.
Christian,
Muslim,
black,
white,
you know,
whatever you cry,
or maybe the Ukraine,
Russian things might be a bit of tension,
but,
uh,
you know,
because of something,
it brings that whole world together and it's,
it's a fantastic example.
And I do think that there is a lot to learn from the history of the games.
Um,
if you ever get the chance,
Luke,
the Olympic charter is fantastic.
And there's a notion of Olympism and it's the joy of sport that everyone loves.
Um,
that everyone should be able to participate in,
but it's also striving and leading a balanced life of mind,
body,
and soul.
So academics for the mind,
athletics for the body and arts for the soul.
And this all came out from the games in antiquity,
you know,
what is it?
Two and a half thousand years ago,
seven 76 BC was the first games and long winded answer.
But.
Back then when you died,
the only way you would ascend to the gods was if you'd led a balanced life,
a little bit of those three components.
And you look at the way we live now,
and we're so fixated on one aspect and it might be sport like I'm a footy player.
I'm a row and that's all I do.
And I don't do,
you know,
I don't have any context or anything else in my life.
And so I think there's a lot to learn in all of us trying to lead a balanced life.
Um,
and it's not a third,
a third,
and it'll float around.
But I think it's really important to have other things in your life.
If you're working,
learn a language or an instrument or do an event where you actually need to train for it.
Not like a two K fun run,
but something where you've actually got to put some time into it.
And I think having other things in your life and having,
having that balance is really,
really important.
So,
and that was a couple of thousand years ago.
The Greek philosophers were onto this job.
You retired on your 45th birthday.
And in a grueling sport like that,
you can see why I'm watching teenage girls burn out because of training at 16 or 17.
But you had that perfect build up and Olympic cycle was four years and you just seem,
you know,
the Olympic ethos,
wasn't it?
You take your time off.
You take,
yeah,
we take a year off after every Olympics,
full year off,
full year,
sometimes jump in a boat,
not jump in a boat,
go and do,
you know,
we're staying active.
We're doing to play footy,
um,
ride your bike,
bike,
go surfing,
you know,
running,
stuff.
But then,
but then you're fresh,
fresh to go again.
You're keen to get back on the border and,
and,
um,
and reengage with it again.
And,
you know,
we talked to the swimmers and they were so scared of missing a session because they thought we'd lose the feel of the water.
It's like,
you're bloody world's best swimmer.
You're not going to lose that skill overnight.
Just take a break.
And,
uh,
but I think that,
and that's being brave to back yourself and,
um,
again,
balance.
You know,
if I wouldn't have gone six Olympiads,
if I'd gone all the way through it,
no way.
Yeah.
So taking those breaks along the way and resetting and refreshing,
ready to go again.
Yeah.
I'm a pretty positive person.
I think,
uh,
you know,
rowing is the ultimate team sport.
I mean,
in footy or netball,
you can have people out on the wings that aren't having a great game and the team can still win.
And,
but that,
that can't happen in the boat.
Um,
and we got to the point,
I guess,
you know,
however,
it's such a long career.
You,
we were probably doing things or I was probably doing things that didn't realize what we were,
what it was,
but then toward the back end of your career,
you realize,
oh,
wow,
that's actually really good behaviors and you're luckily doing the right thing.
And I think I can describe it,
uh,
by saying that,
you know,
when we finished up my,
so drew rowing with drew,
in Athens,
my goal in,
in rowing with him was to row in such a way that allowed him to perform at his best.
So zero self-interest,
like I could sit in the boat and row as hard as I possibly could and tear the side of the boat off and make it so uncomfortable for him that he couldn't perform his best.
But if I go,
how can I run such a way that allows him to absolutely nail it?
And if he reciprocates,
yeah,
I mean,
that is the ultimate team.
And that is the ultimate in selflessness.
I think that's the ultimate in leadership.
Take the ego away,
take the self-interest away of your next promotion.
What can I do to help my team absolutely thrive?
Yeah.
And if they thrive,
yeah,
again,
the byproduct is I'll probably get that promotion instead of worrying about the promotion.
You'd go and get your team absolutely up and thriving.
What I'm saying to make a stronger human connection,
you should,
you want to know what a person's priorities are so you can be supportive of the priority.
You're still going to get other things done,
but we're not.
We're transactional at best.
I believe this and I don't want any listeners to hear this out of context,
but we,
most of us are selfish first.
Like when we wake up,
we have a list of things to do,
whether written down or in our head of things.
We need to do to make our day better of things.
We need to do to get things done through other people.
And we start with us and then somewhere in the middle of the day,
if something dramatic or traumatic happens,
we'll pay attention to somebody else's thing that they need.
But most of us are selfish first.
When I am talking about what I need leaders and companies to start to figure out how to do
is how can you wake up and be centered on what other people need as a part of your day to day life?
Yeah.
Part of your daily routine still do what you need to do for you.
But in parallel,
can you think about who am I going to help today or this week or next week?
How can I be supportive of somebody today or this week or next week?
I didn't say don't pay attention to your own list and your own priorities,
but we need to start to add other humans to our,
our planning phase of our days,
our weeks,
our months.
And you'll see a very slight shift,
toward people are caring about one another in a different way now because you did it on purpose.
It was intentional.
You woke up.
I got a leader who said this to me,
says,
Reggie,
you know what I wake up and I do on Mondays.
Now I ask people on my team,
what do you need from me this week?
I don't ask them about their weekend,
their weekends for them.
Why would I encroach on that narrative?
I asked them,
Hey,
let's get started.
What do you need from me this week?
And people get to take it.
They tell me what they need.
Will they still talk about their weekends?
Maybe,
maybe not.
I don't need to use that as the entryway to get to know somebody.
So I said,
what do you need from me this week?
You know what happened,
Reggie?
People started telling me,
Hey,
uh,
I've got a doctor's appointment with my son on Thursday.
There's a really big meeting.
I was supposed to be a part of,
I'd like to see if there's a way I can have somebody take my place.
They would have never asked that question.
If the leader hadn't led with,
how can I help you this week?
Think about that.
He said,
somebody else on my team went,
uh,
sons or daughters,
um,
got a special celebration happening at their school.
I have never been to one of them.
I would love to go.
It happens to be tomorrow.
And I didn't put in time off.
I didn't tell anybody,
but you were asking me how I can be helpful.
That would be helpful.
Now those,
both of those sent sent seemed personal.
Remember work,
family,
health,
spirituality,
community.
Those were both family related.
Somebody else in this person's team said,
you know what?
I need you to extend a deadline because I'm not going to make it by
Wednesday and I'm telling,
I'd rather tell you,
ask me what can be helpful is can you move some things out of my
way and help me prioritize so I can either meet the deadline
or can you extend the deadline again?
That person's prioritization was work,
but that leader would have gotten none of those answers had he not
repositioned his framing for interacting with his team.
For something as simple as Monday morning catch up.
I think first and foremost,
it is about turning up for you.
You know,
you are in my role as a leader.
I'm very compassionate,
caring,
supportive.
Um,
so in order for me to fill everyone else's cup,
my cup needs to be filled up and don't get me wrong.
I'm not always great at it,
but you become aware really quickly.
When you're starting to be depleted,
whether that's in your workplace or at home,
you know,
I'm not,
I'm not only a leader at fluid form.
I'm also a leader at home.
I've got three young girls and I want to be the best
possible role model I can to them.
So I thought I have two leadership hats and that can be,
you know,
draining and fatiguing as well.
Um,
so for me,
you know,
making sure that movement is part of every day for me,
whether it's 15 minutes,
you know,
at home,
whether it's a class in one of the studios,
I'm making sure I'm having time just to think,
you know,
to think about,
to dream,
you know,
about that big picture stuff,
because that really motivates you when you're dealing with the day to
day.
Uh,
I think making sure that your dream is constantly there and you're
thinking about it is so important and not being so hard on
yourself.
I think we are just as human beings,
just so hard on ourselves.
These days from,
you know,
the access of social media and everything that is thrown at us and what we
see and the pressures we just need to be more compassionate to our own
self.
And if we need that time out to have it,
you know,
you need our eldest daughter,
Charlie,
she graduated from primary school.
Um,
it was like a fanfare.
There was so many activities on and,
you know,
I was trying to juggle work the entire week and it was just,
at one point I was like,
okay,
I can't go to work on Wednesday.
I've got too much on.
And,
you know,
I I'm always really honest with my team guys.
This is what's on with Charlie.
Can't make it in.
Call me if you need me,
but I'll see you on Thursday.
And just knowing that I had that time for her and didn't
have to worry about anything on that day,
it just allowed everything else to continue to flow.
Cause it's all about flow,
you know,
find your state of flow and stay in it.
When you can.
And how brilliant is that for your team that you've just shown them
that family comes first by taking that action.
And as the leader,
no matter how busy work was,
I'm having that day because that is the most important thing in
my life.
And that allows them to be able to ring you one
day and say,
Hey,
Kirsten,
I really need this day and know that they're going to
be supported.
And that's,
you know,
how great culture starts and continues.
Huge.
Thanks to all the guests featured in this episode,
Hugh van Kylenburg,
Andy Kelly,
Umrah Omar,
Sir Rod Eddington,
James Tompkins,
Reggie Butler and Kirsten King.
And you can find the links to the full length in-depth conversations I
had with each of them in the show notes in our
next Success Leaders Clues episode,
we'll hear about the power of collaboration from a carefully selected group
of our 2024 guests.
And if you enjoy listening to the empowering leaders podcast,
be sure to subscribe.
And please,
if you have a moment,
leave a review for us so we can reach more
listeners and empower more leaders.