Felt like a great privilege to record so many engaging conversations with remarkable leaders
in this past year, uncovering their keys to success. In 2023, we'd like to think that we
gave you a front row seat to conversations that reveal how success leaves clues featuring guests
from across the globe at the top of their game. At Alita, we understand the consistent dimensions
of brilliant leadership and we love exploring them in this special series. The art of communicating
with clarity is an invaluable skill and one worth honing with practice and good advice.
Every week on Empowering Leaders, our conversations stretch across different fields from sport,
business to education, social venture and the arts. We love the diversity of thinking
and bringing that to the table each week. In this episode, we've curated what I think is a
remarkable group of individuals who take communicating with clarity very seriously
and they have a unique way of explaining why it works so well for them.
Starting with...
Susan McLean, Australia's foremost expert in the world of cyber security.
Hopefully with clarity. It's interesting. One of the things I say when I speak to young people
is that, and I'll say at the start of my talk, I'm going to be blunt. I'm going to be direct
and there is no wriggle room in what I say. And for me, that's important because I need to share
really important facts and especially when I'm talking about laws. If I give any audience wriggle
room, I'm going to be blunt. I'm going to be direct. I'm going to be direct. I'm going to be blunt.
I know what they will do. They will twist it to suit them or they'll twist it to what they want to
hear. So then that's a failing as well. So if you leave my sessions confused, then I failed. So no
wriggle room. Here it is. Is it always fair? No. Is it factual? Yes. And you cannot expect any
person, particularly young people, to make or even try to make a good choice if they haven't
been given the facts. It's like saying, read this book, but we're going to test you on a different
one.
And hope for the best. And the cost of harm to young people that get themselves into situations
on the internet, get targeted, et cetera, is enormous. And we all have to do more to make
sure that, for me, every adult has a responsibility to try to keep all children safe online so that
children don't get mixed messages. It's like the good cop, bad cop parent. The child will go to the
good cop to get the lollies, but they won't ask the bad cop parent because they will say no. So
it's the same thing. You want them to get the same message from school, from home, from the sport
club, the co-curricular activity, from grandparents, aunts, uncles, and cousins, because consistent
messaging works.
Rod Campbell is a firefighter, a football coach, and a father of five who has dedicated his adult
life to helping people. Rod has created an education program called Learning Life Through Sport
that tackles bad parenting behavior in junior sport across Australia,
and the world. Yeah, I think you need to keep the message really simple,
but you need to be clear and concise, and you need to inspire high standards. So high standards
aren't only applicable to the highest level. High standards we can apply at any level. So you need
to have that about you or part of your makeup, so you have high standards when you're teaching. But
again, letting your passion and enthusiasm flow in specifically because I'm from a fire service
background, so as a station officer. So communicating with clarity is critical,
because they could be life and death situations. So an example of that would be you have a crew
working with you. You might go into a fire situation. So you'd explain, you discuss the
method of how we're going to control this situation, and then you discuss that with your
team. But then as you task them, you'd identify the task and then get them to repeat that task
back to you. Okay, so we've got absolute clarity on what we're doing. And then when they go in,
we know that they can perform that task or are aiming towards that goal. So that clarity,
it's super important in emergency services. So I guess that's where I learned that. But
when you talk about communicating with clarity, so in the road safety space, a little bit different.
So it'll be the key messages. So in RAP, the Road Awareness Program, we'd have the key messages
of, you know, you get to choose the risk, you don't get to choose the consequence. What we do
know is that most people will take what they feel emotionally away from that presentation,
and that'll give them the passion to go forward and want to be part of it. But what messages will
they remember?
So that consistency of that same saying. So we might say that saying 20 times during a
presentation, and it might be the one thing that they go away with. So keeping it simple,
reinforcing the message and understanding that people aren't going to take away lots of messages,
they might just take away a few. And if they take away the main ones that are going to empower them
to change their behaviours, they're really important. So that reinforcement of the message.
So I say to the parents, this is the new paradigm we're coaching under. These are the three values.
And in relation to respect, your children will no longer be able
to argue an umpire's decision. We'll teach it at training, we'll teach the reaction,
and I will never argue an umpire's decision as a coach. Can you guys support me? I'm talking to
the parent group now. Can you support me in doing this? Well, the parents look over at their kids
that they love, and they're looking over at me, the coach that hopefully they'll respect,
that's trying to bring good values to the game. Well, they're not going to say no in front of
their kids. So they make a commitment to their children who they love. They make a commitment
to the coach who hopefully they respect. They're also making a commitment with their cohort of
parents. They're also making a commitment to the coach who hopefully they respect. They're also
not going to say a word about umpire's decisions. So now we're all on the same page. So the coach
who, that's his job to coach, he's actually coaching the whole team. He's coaching the
kids and he's coaching the parents. And this is just one area of it. But I can tell you in four
years of coaching this same team, we have an unbelievable relationship with the players and
the parents. But my parents, they police that. I don't police their behavior. They know that's what
we're about. They want to be honest to their kids and they want to be honest to the coach.
So they're all supporting it. So we don't have issues from our parents. Honestly,
we don't, mate. And this can be taught. It's a taught behavior and we need to take that
responsibility. Richard Goida is the former CEO and managing director of Wesfarmers,
Australia's largest private employer. He's currently the chairman of multiple listed
companies and a key business advisory to the World Economic Forum.
I think I've, you know, there's been a journey, Luke. I've learned to be a bit more direct with
people without, hopefully without being sort of rude and impolite. So I can have very direct
conversations with people with, you know, whether it's Alan or Gil or Meg or directors, because I
think that clarity is important. Do I enjoy sitting down with someone and say, I think you did a
really rubbish job? No. You know, I don't know who enjoys that stuff. But have I learned to sit
down and say, actually, you know, you could have done that better. And these are what I,
you should have done. I think I'm a lot better at that now than I was 20 years ago. And it's a
skill I think you sort of have to develop. But also, you know, I've also, I've had feedback
along the way that people have felt they weren't getting enough feedback from me. And I was shocked
when I got that feedback. I thought, oh, gee, I'm pretty good at that. And then I reflected on it
and said, actually, no, I'm not. I'm bloody hopeless at it in the circumstances I was
talking about. So yeah, hopefully I'm a bit better. It also comes with relationships,
I think. Once you, once you build trust with someone, you can have that much more direct
conversation. Coming up, we're going to hear from Australian lacrosse legend Stacey Morlang,
one of the most successful people in the world of real estate, Nathan Parris. Fascinating hearing
from him. And Hall of Fame NBA coach, George Carr. Really enjoyed hearing from Susan McLean,
from Rod Campbell and Richard Gorda, all from unique backgrounds. And they talk compellingly
about the thought of pulling no punches when delivering really crucial
information, the clarity required in an emergency, choosing your audience wisely,
and the time it takes to feel comfortable being direct. At Alita, we are really passionate about
creating a world of collaboration, inspiring connections, and bringing together these diverse
leaders from different backgrounds around the globe to share, to learn, to connect and to
collaborate. We would love you to check out Alita Connect, our signature program. Head to
alitacollective.com. You don't have to be a global head of marketing for an international company
or a superstar coach to be part of Alita Connect. We would love to book a discovery call, have a chat
to us, and we'd love to share your leadership journey with you. Big thanks as always to Jason
Nicholas and his team from Temper, Australia and New Zealand for their ongoing support of the
Empowering Leaders podcast. We know that getting a good night's sleep is a pattern that we see in
all great leaders. Temper is a mattress like no other. Check it out today. Really looking forward
to this next group and hearing them speak about how communicating with clarity has helped them on
a path to great success. Let's go first to Jeff Dimery, the CEO of Alinta Energy, a unique leader
in his own right and one of the key people passionate about leading us through this next big
energy transition. Keep it simple. I mean, we're very fortunate as leaders today with the
advancement in technology that we have. So the means to communicate, visuals, use a lot of
visuals. There's an old saying, pretend you're talking to intelligent 12-year-olds.
That's not meant to be demeaning to people, but the reality is that when, for instance,
if I'm giving an hour-long presentation, I've got to focus really, what are the three or four things
at the end of that hour I want people to remember? And make sure that you're clear about that,
you talk about it, you tell them you're going to tell them about it, then you tell them about it,
and then you tell them what you've told them, effectively. And like I said to you, Luke,
we've had the same strategy for 13 years. Our people get it now.
Um, and, and that's the value of consistency. Now, like I said, we'll play around with
the execution of that strategy and the emphasis within the strategy of what we're doing at a
point in time. But, um, we always need to be, um, true to ourselves and what it is that we're
trying to do, because it's at that level that our people understand what we are trying to do.
Stacey Morlang-Sullivan is an Australian lacrosse legend who still holds the NCAA
World Cup title. She's been a member of the Australian Lacrosse League for over a decade.
Division One record for the most goals in a game. She's a business owner, the co-founder of
Show and Tell, the online women's lifestyle brand, and co-host of their brilliant podcast.
All the time, particularly when you're coaching, I think, in sports and in other areas as well. I
think the most important thing for me is getting to know people well enough to know how they like
to be communicated with, because people are different now. Like it's not on a phone or
face-to-face. Some people don't like that.
It might be, you know, I remember, you know, leading players in this team that needed me to
go straight at them between the eyes. Just be better. This isn't good enough. But then another
person might need a different form of communication of, let me give a positivity first. And then,
so it's, I think it's about knowing how people want to receive communication and make sure that's
two-way. I don't, I don't think it can't, it can't be one way. Um, so learning about the language
they respond to best, I think is important there.
But for me, it's, I just lean on the truth always. I always lean on the truth because if I would never
want someone to wonder if what I said was true or not, or if I was just saying it to make them feel
good. But that goes back to building relationships so strong they can bear the truth. I think that
that's one of the most important things I lean on is truth. I think for probably two hacks I've
had that I use on the day-to-day, I think it's one of the most important things I lean on is truth.
Bailey almost is, or particularly when I was doing, you know, pregame speech, halftime,
you know, even in meetings, delivering things in meetings, whatever it was is
delivery over content. I used to spend so much time on the content I was delivering to the team,
like my halftime speech, my pregame speech, my this, my that, instead of how I was delivering
it to them. And that's like passion, body language, all those things that go into it is the cell.
I was watching literally Darcy yesterday, watching Kevin Hart,
talk about green super powder. But he was so engrossed in what he was saying because of the
way he was telling the story that I was like, I need to buy that. I didn't even hear what it was
about. It was just so captivating. And I know I have spent way too much time on content and not
enough time on delivery. So when I heard that, I was like, oh, this is what I need. Obviously,
the content needs to be good still.
But people are watching how you're giving it to them more than what you're saying.
And look, you know, there's the little things like I don't give more than three things in a
halftime or, you know, I don't give my kids more than one thing to do at a time. You know,
there's little ways to be clear and it's by not over speaking, not over coaching,
not over complicating, but also, you know, to just deliver something with a little bit of
gusto and it kind of goes a long way.
Nathan Paris is the managing partner of Emerge Capital, an independent real estate advisory firm
that has executed more than $30 billion worth of transactions over the last 15 years across
Australia, Asia, the Middle East and Europe. When you can actually crack through that and that
becomes the way you're operating rhythm, your efficiency goes through the roof. It's like a
vertical curve.
Because you're not trying to have to explain things. You say what you mean. If you're not
saying it fast enough, you'll be sped up to get to the point. And then we thrash out. We will
rigorously debate. If you weren't part of our organisation, you'd find that it was almost
offensive the way that we talk to each other. Not in terms of language, but like, what do you mean?
That doesn't make sense. You know, say what you mean. And then what happens is this just this
beautiful sort of cycle of ideas comes out of it.
And it gets tested at a rapid rate. And then all of a sudden, you've got a solution. And so it's
that it's not for everyone. But those guys that are in the team that can, can handle it, thrive in
it. And then they create that culture for the next generation to come through the organisation,
because we're literally plucking kids out of universe.
George Carl is a former professional basketball player who went on to become one of the youngest
head coaches in the world.
In NBA history, with a career spanning almost five decades and 1175 wins, the sixth highest of all
time, he was inducted into the NBA Hall of Fame in 2022.
Well, you've got to be, you've got to be tough minded and caring at the same time. You know,
whatever you coach and whatever philosophies you have, they're fundamentals. And how you make them
teachable, acceptable.
And committed to is the beginning of coaching. We're teachers. We are mentors. We are psychologists.
But we are also friends. I don't think the old school of dictator, angry man, angry woman,
boot camp type of mentality is going to win anymore in coaching. Our players today are smarter.
They're wiser. And they more they know more stuff.
And then we know when we started to coach, when we started playing. The window of learning how to
motivate, how to inspire, how to connect, how to get out of the way, how to allow the process of a
team to come together. I think the best wisdom I had is what I said at the beginning of the show.
I mean, I've always believed in communication. But now it's more than communication. It's
connection. It's communication. It's communication. It's communication. It's communication. It's
connection. It's not only connection with the one-on-one between coach and player, but the
connection between what you are selling or what you are coaching to the team. Do they accept your
philosophies? Do you accept your demands? Do you accept your fundamental demands? And also,
do they accept your punishment? How you push them? How you push a button?
One of my favorite things is a pat on the back and a kick in the ass is six inches apart.
And that is so true in the game of sport. Some guys, they don't want to be kicked in the butt.
Other guys, that's all they want to be, is kicked in the butt. Everybody likes a pat on the back.
But when they go hard at them, when to be demanding, and knowing when to push those buttons
over a six-month period.
That season is probably as important as anything.
Love listening back to Jeff Dimry, the CEO of Alinta Energy, and his unique thinking,
Stacey Borling, who's joined our leader team. Nathan Parris is a brilliant individual and
NBA Hall of Fame coach, George Carl. And you can see the patterns emerging. Connection
is the new communication with something that I picked up a lot across the year.
Tailoring communication styles to effectively connect with individuals was something we heard
a lot about, and the benefits to culture.
It thrives on clear and candid exchanges. And when you don't get clear communication,
people fill in the gaps, often in a negative way. And the power of simplicity, that you need
to be able to condense your message in a way that isn't too complex, that people can remember and
then act on in a positive way. Huge thanks to all the guests that featured on this episode.
You can find the links to the full-length in-depth conversations I had with each of them
in the show notes. Go back and have a listen. I certainly will across the summer. In our next
season, we're going to be talking about how to connect with people. So if you're interested in
this episode, you're going to hear from some amazing guests again on who they describe as the
greatest leader in their life and why. And if you've enjoyed listening to the Empowering Leaders
podcast, please subscribe now. Love you to do that. And hopefully you take some time to leave
a review for us so we can reach more listeners. Empower more leaders in 2024. Thanks again for
listening.