What a great privilege it has been to spend another year sitting across from inspiring
leaders at the top of their game as they share and unpack the learnings and life lessons
from their chosen field.
At Alita, we know that there are consistent dimensions of what great leadership looks
like, and we're uncovering them all in this special series.
In our work, we see so many people in positions of leadership who are really conscious of
how they positively impact others in their environment on a daily basis.
And each week on the Empowering Leaders podcast, we hear from people across all industries,
whether it be from sport or business, education, social venture, and the arts.
And when it comes to this dimension of positively impacting others, we had a pretty difficult
time, it's fair to say, in narrowing down a select group of people that we wanted to
share with you in this episode today.
Starting with Craig McRae, who had an incredibly positive impact as the coach of the Collingwood
Football Club, winning the premiership in 2023.
And in lots of ways for me, reshaping the way we see senior coaches go about their role
with great empathy and great effect.
I think that's a natural course of my own energy.
I don't find it that difficult to see the glass fall, or close to it, see the good in
people.
So I think that's important.
And obviously with tiredness and being pulled, your focus gets pulled in all sorts of directions
through performance and the role.
But coming back to what you're good at.
And, you know, I remember we lost three games in a row that time when I had to go to that
board meeting, and it was only my first year as a coach.
And there's a lot of different pressures that come with that that you haven't experienced
before, and I don't know what will come again.
You know, I was sitting in a coma for two days in my bed going, how do I get out of
this?
You know, like, what do we do?
And, you know, playing a Friday night and finally getting myself into an energy level
just to communicate with my wife, little anyone else.
And she goes, you know how to do this.
You know how to get out of this.
I said, what?
She goes, just be you.
It's a positive version of you.
So instead of looking at all the things we didn't do in that game over the last two weeks,
I scrapped it and just said to the coaches that day, I said, boys, don't come tomorrow
and show us what we didn't do.
I'm not interested.
Find evidence of all the things that we have done and what we're going to do next.
Like, let's concentrate on the team we want to be, not the team we are right now.
So, and funnily enough, it was a great reset of, like, we might have tried to go too fast,
too quick with the group.
When you go, no, they got that.
They got that.
Let's go to this.
Yeah.
So we just.
Went back in time a little bit and said, boys, if we're going to be this great pressure
team, we're going to do this.
Yeah.
So funnily enough, we won the next 10 games in a row, I think, from that.
But it was a moment that the group was potentially waiting for, you know, that heavy stick.
And not to say that you can't give a heavy stick, but at that time, they probably got
what they least expected.
And it was a moment to go, all right, no, we need to be this team.
Let's go be this team.
So the 80-20 rule, if you like, of positivity or reward behavior.
And then the 20% of, like, hey, let's get better in this area.
Sarah Grinberg was the executive producer of Australia's most iconic radio duo, Hamish
and Andy.
Now she's the host of her own chart-topping podcast, A Life of Greatness.
Well, you know, especially with the people that, you know, are in my team, I, you know,
again, I think I got this from Hamish and Andy and it's so basic.
But when they're doing good work, I tell them that they're doing good work.
I tell them that I appreciate them.
I don't do the opposite thinking like, oh, if I appreciate them too much, then maybe
they'll, you know, I don't know.
You can't over-appreciate, can you?
Exactly.
You know, it's little things like that.
Again, something I learned from the boys, like actually at Christmas time, buying them
something nice.
It's their birthday, celebrating their birthday.
These are all such little things, but they all make such a big difference.
Being an ear for them if they need to talk.
I mean, there was.
There was someone that works for me that was really having a hard time the other day
and called me and we just chatted about their personal life and I gave them any help that
I could and any resources that I thought would help them along the way.
Like, you have to lead with compassion and you have to be real when you lead too.
Like, you don't want to be a bumbling mess, obviously, but at the same time, I think when
you're a leader and you do show that you're a human and you have emotions, that is a big
thing too.
Because it allows them to realize that they too can show that.
And I remember years ago I interviewed Simon Sinek and he was very, he's obviously a leadership
expert and he was saying like during COVID, he's not going to pretend that he's not suffering
to his team.
He was suffering and people would reach out to ask him if he was okay the same way that
he would do the same.
So I think it's that whole idea of realizing that you're all human, you're not robots and
that you need to.
Treat people in a respectful manner and be compassionate and know that sometimes they
are doing long hours and maybe that means that they don't work the next day or they
start later.
It's just little things like that so they don't feel like they're a number rather than
a person.
Jules Lund is a celebrated television and radio host and one of the most passionate
and positive people you'll ever meet.
He's also the founder of Tribe, a global marketplace for social influencers and the brands that
need them.
How do I positively impact?
Well, I genuinely believe that people should have a big swing.
You know, I get super excited by speaking to people who are a bit hungry.
Like that to me is, that to me is something I'm super passionate about, which is that
sort of 18 to 22 year old where you're out of school and you're trying to look at the
big wide world.
For me, I love that.
That innate coaching, you know, when I speak to them and I'm like, what are you going to
do?
You're going to travel overseas or I do, you know, like I just love that coaching.
And so I think when I speak to friends who are like, you know, what do I do next?
I get, I think I positively impact them by, you know, helping them strategize, write up
a plan, be clear on their vision to confront limiting beliefs and then start.
Mark Bunn.
He's a former professional AFL footballer who moved on to become one of the world's
most sought after experts in Ayurvedic medicine.
His book, Ancient Wisdom for Modern Health is a three times bestseller.
It's ever evolving for me.
One of the things I've really, life certainly isn't perfect.
You know, that bubble of sort of, you know, there's this ancient wisdom that has this
theory on life and it all sounded fantastic.
But, you know, like you, I'm bumbling away.
And trying to live life and not get too stressed and, you know, all that sort of stuff.
So I find it changes and evolves.
I think one of the best things we've heard over the last five years, and I'm sure you've
interviewed many guests who've touched that whole idea of embracing our imperfections
and our, you know, being vulnerable.
And that's been a big one for me.
Shame was a massive thing for me as a young sort of boy and adult and sort of putting
on the mask of bravado and fear of failure in footy.
Not rewards of success, all that stuff.
So for me, it's really been coming back to just self-kindness is probably the best term
for it that, hey, life is tough in many cases.
Yes, there's these great wisdoms of life and cultures that have sort of been a lighthouse
for how we live individually and collectively, but it's not easy unless you're in those
cultures 24-7 to do it.
So let's sort of be kind, kind to myself, kind to those around us and just try and embrace
those wisdoms gradually over time.
So that collectively and as a society, we can embrace them.
Because I think that's the real game changer when we do it, do it en masse.
Well, some fascinating insights for me already from Craig McRae, from Sarah, Jules and Mark.
Their success in each of their chosen field, to me, clearly demonstrates what's possible
when intentionally building up the people around us.
I love Mark Bunn's story about the power of getting out of the shame cycle and how it
helps you show up even more for the people around you.
At Alita, we are really passionate about creating a world of collaboration, inspiring
connections and bringing together these diverse leaders from different backgrounds around
the globe to share, to learn, to connect and to collaborate.
We would love you to check out Alita Connect, our signature program.
Head to alitacollective.com.
You don't have to be a global head of marketing for an international company or a superstar
coach to be part of Alita Connect.
We would love to book a discovery call, have a chat to us, and we'd love to share your
leadership journey with you.
Big thanks.
Big thanks, as always, to Jason Nicholas and his team from Temper, Australia and New
Zealand, for their ongoing support of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
We know that getting a good night's sleep is a pattern that we see in all great leaders.
Temper is a mattress like no other.
Check it out today.
Coming up, we'll hear from Peggy O'Neill, the former president of the Richmond Football
Club, author Dr. Kirsten Ferguson, and the global head of marketing for Budweiser, Richard
Oppy, one of the biggest marketing roles in the world.
Just this last weekend.
I went to be the guest of honor at Annie Smith's restaurant in Trentham, Victoria, to celebrate
Mother's Day.
And she was having this lunch and said to the room full of people, which was very lovely,
Stephanie is my kitchen mother.
Everything I know, she taught me.
Well, that is absolutely not true, but it was lovely to hear her say that.
And she had asked me to design the menu, which she then cooked.
So that is, she is one of my very, very special foodie friends.
But there are a lot of people who have worked with me and alongside me.
And I think I would reiterate that what they've got for me is very positive modeling, because
I really do live what I say.
You know, I just don't eat fast food because it doesn't seem to me to be as interesting
as the food I can cook myself.
That doesn't mean I don't eat a bit of street food here and there.
But.
I do like sushi, but, you know, I'm not tempted by the packaged product when I can go home
and make something much more beautiful.
I've watched people go on to run their own restaurants and it's over such a long time
now.
Often we've lost touch, but when I meet people or I go into a restaurant, there's often somebody
who comes up and says, I worked for you at such and such.
Now that includes, of course, the dishwashers and the front of house stuff.
And I don't always remember.
But they remember the experience as positive and enthusiastic.
So, you know, I stick with it.
Enthusiasm sweeps all before it.
When I'm working with somebody in the kitchen, I can't help sharing with them a bigger picture.
You know, if we're chopping up leeks, I might say, goodness, I remember having this beautiful
pasta dish or this beautiful pastry, which was full of leeks that have been softly stewed
in butter.
For about 15 minutes, then drained and then mixed with such.
And the person who's chopping the leeks just hears that it's a sort of part of it's another
track going through their mind.
But if it happens every day and a different product every day, they do get a different
sense of the possibilities of food.
And a lot of the people that I influence positively, I'd like to think they were young people full
of enthusiasm.
But they often.
Didn't have very strong food backgrounds.
They were interested and they became very competent.
They took on a lot of knowledge and they understood that food was more than just nutrients.
You're not just absorbing calories.
You know, you're eating people's stories.
Peggy O'Neill was the first in her family to go to university, the first female lawyer
at her legal firm.
And she became the first female president of an Australian.
Rules Football Club when she started with Richmond in 2013.
She's currently the chancellor of RMIT University.
I think also that constructive criticism is much more helpful, that you want to help people
get better at what they do to understand what you're trying to do.
So I think the positivity is helping people find out more about themselves and about their
capabilities.
It doesn't mean that you.
Stick with things that aren't working, but that you give people a chance and that you feel you've been fair.
And I remember early on when I had this partner in a law firm and I had to accept the responsibility of some people aren't going to work out and some people on my team, I'm going to have to have those terrible conversations with.
And I thought, if you can put your hand in your heart and say, you know, you've been fair and they're going to be no surprises, because if it's me, I want to know where my shortcomings were.
Along the way, and I was given a chance to fix it, and it could be this job isn't for everybody, but I think that's part of helping people develop and helping them understand that perhaps what they're doing isn't isn't their real strength and they need to look somewhere else.
So I think it goes back to being somewhat easy to get along with, not not getting angry at people for something that is usually about you more than about them.
I think that we all like to work with people that seem to like us.
Dr. Kirsten Ferguson is one of Australia's most prominent leadership experts.
She is an award-winning, globally recognised executive coach, public speaker, company director and writer with a 30-year executive career and a PhD in leadership and culture.
Firstly, our sense of self-awareness is much greater than it actually is.
So that's something to be aware of.
And research shows 95% of us think we're self-aware.
And only 10% to 15% of those that we lead agree.
So that's a pretty scary statistic.
So when you say having a positive impact, I guess my first thought is how do you know it's positive?
Because we may have a sense that they love it when I fist pump them every day when I come into the office.
There could also be a situation where everyone dreads that they've got to do that every morning.
Because you do.
That is a perfunctory thing.
But then for the rest of the day, you're the dickhead.
So there's this whole sense of understanding how you're impacting people, but only through feedback.
Like unless you're actually checking how that impact is being measured, I think it's hard for us to judge.
Sorry, that feels like a complicated way to answer your question.
But whenever we say a positive impact, how do you know?
How do you know?
That's great.
That's a great thought and one that is challenging in some ways, isn't it?
Because you're right.
I mean, you think you're self-aware, but if you're not measuring it and asking people and not reflecting constantly, then how do you actually know?
Can I give you an example?
During the pandemic at the start when we were all at home, there were a lot of leaders who thought they needed to check in with their teams online like every hour, every day or whatever.
And there were team members just going, can you just back off?
Like, I know you care, but this is now really irritating because I don't need you to check in.
So, I mean, that's so simple an example, but it's that idea that we must get feedback and we must create a feedback culture where people feel they can say, mate, the fist pumps, we love the intention, but let's focus on this instead.
Maybe once a week.
Yeah.
Wander back, dude.
Wander back.
Yeah.
I talk to the team a lot about the power of positive energy.
I came across this presentation years ago by this lady, Amanda.
Gore and it really stuck with me. She spoke about the power of energy and that you can wake up in
the morning and you can make a choice to either be an energy giver or an energy sucker. It's a
choice you can make. They're both as powerful as each other. They're both contagious. I wake up
every morning. I try and get to the gym if I can and I always go to work with a positive mindset
before the kids go to school every day. I say, kids, don't just have a good day,
have a great day. They roll their eyes every time and they're like, dad.
But I know that even if 10% of it gets through, I'll be happy that they have a great day.
When I go to work, sometimes you underestimate the impact you have on other people. When I go
into a meeting, I make the choice that I want to have a good day. I make the choice that I want to
have a good day. I make the choice that I want to have a good day. I make the choice that I want to
have a great meeting. I want to greenhouse rather than what we call shithousing and a lot of it's
sort of body language. So I'll start a meeting with a bit of banter, a joke, have a bit of fun,
tell them I'm excited about the meeting. And then you get the best out of people because people
are going to be more, put their ideas out there that you can greenhouse and talk about.
Whereas if you go into that meeting and you're grumpy, you've just had a fight with your wife,
the kids are doing your head in and you can just suck the energy,
out of that room very quickly and be an energy sucker. And you'll watch your team just go into
their shell. And it's something that's really stuck with me. Now, of course, there are times
when there are tough times where you have always got to be authentic and you have to deliver tough
messages. But most of the time you can make a choice whether you're going to be an energy giver
or an energy sucker. And all my life, I prefer to be glass half full than glass half empty.
Love the opportunity to go back and listen to some of the conversations we had throughout 2023.
To connect with Stephanie Alexander, Peggy O'Neill, Kirsten Ferguson and Richard Oppie was a great
privilege. And you could see the patterns that emerged from great people doing inspiring things.
Certainly love the sense of enthusiasm and passion that every one of those people have for what they
do. A real sense of self-awareness and reflecting on the impact you're actually having on others
is a consistent theme across the conversations this year. And how there is a place for well-crafted
constructive criticism, that feedback is something that is important. It can be a gift.
It's delivered the right way. And when it's delivered with empathy, it's a real common
theme that we saw across the year. And your ability to choose between giving energy or
taking it away from others is a choice that you can make. I hope you found it as fascinating as
I did and learned a lot from the people that we connected with this year on the Empowering Leaders
podcast. Huge thanks to all the guests who featured on this episode. You can find the
links to their full length conversations with each of them in the show notes. I encourage you to go
back and listen.
Over the summer, our next Success Leaves Clues episode, we're curating the tips and strategies
told to us by leaders across the globe on how they most effectively create and share their vision.
And we have seen some unique and compelling visions across the year. If you enjoy listening
to the Empowering Leaders podcast, we would love you to subscribe. And please, if you have a moment,
leave a review for us so we can reach more listeners and empower more leaders in 2024.