My vision is segregation is a scar on the community in which we live.
So I went away and I thought about, actually, what do I want to see?
And that became the vision.
You're not going to get any help if you can't tell people what you want to achieve.
So I kind of think vision is pretty important.
As long as you have that foresight to go, I want to get to that, it gave me a bit of drive.
I always feel the great privilege to have sat down across from so many inspiring leaders in 2024 on the Empowering Leaders podcast,
talking about all the ways that success leaves a clue with people often at the top of their game in their chosen field.
At Alita, we know that there are consistent dimensions of what brilliant leadership looks like,
and we're covering them all in this special series.
We know that the ability to create and share a vision in a way that has impact is a very valuable skill,
but it's a skill within reach for anyone who puts their mind to it.
Each week on the Empowering Leaders series, we hear from people across all industries,
whether that be from the world of sport to business.
Education, social venture, and the arts.
And when it comes to the dimension of successfully creating and sharing a vision,
we have hand-selected a phenomenal group of people you're about to hear and learn from.
We'll hear from Andy Friend, one of the most respected coaches in world rugby,
former head coach of the Brumbies, Australian men's rugby sevens,
and he's recently launched Performance Friend,
a consultancy business supporting highly scrutinised leaders across their fields.
Kurt Fearnley joins us, the incredible Australian in every sense,
a wheelchair racer, a Paralympic gold medalist,
who also famously crawled across the treacherous Kokoda Track without a wheelchair.
A remarkable Australian in every sense of the word.
But first, we're going to hear from the legendary Nick Natanui,
whose legacy as an Australian rules footballer is as significant as anyone in the modern era.
The overall number two draft pick in 2008 of Fijian heritage,
went on to be a three-time All-Australian, a two-time West Coast Eagles best in Ferris,
and played without...
I've always been a big one on, you know, having a vision or having a goal,
and that probably is derived from my sort of mentors as a kid.
Like my local youth worker, Tony Maracci, was a big one.
He used to take us out and teach us the right way on, you know,
he used to show us what's going on.
You know, there's guys doing drugs or, you know, doing bad things in the corner just down the road,
but there's a pathway to go and, you know, do what you want to do.
And myself, Chris, and Michael Walters, we all sat down and wanted to buy a...
our mum's houses.
That was our goal.
So having that vision to, you know, it was almost...
I thought it was unattainable.
I thought, you know, this is a bit far-fetched, man.
Like I just want to be able to pay...
help mum pay this week's rent and rent, not buy a house, you know, firstly,
but having that end goal and there's no straight line.
You just, you know, you're always diverting and there's ups and downs,
but as long as you have that foresight to go, I want to get to that,
it gave me a bit of drive.
And, you know, that's sort of what I do now.
I have a vision of what I want to get to.
And I think the biggest thing is understanding that,
you will fail at times.
And if I'm not going to get there, at least I've given it my all
and I knew I was doing the right things to put myself there.
I think I'd be more upset with myself if I didn't do that
and I fell short because I'd just be, you know, just floating through.
So having that vision has been big and sharing it as well
and letting people know what I'm about and what I want to do, you know,
helps open doors and helps you get to where you want to do
because people out there are willing to help.
So did you...
Sonny Walters and Chris Yaron,
there's kids talk about wanting to be successful enough
to buy your mum's houses to give them that security.
That's an amazing thing for kids to talk about.
Oh, it was awesome.
And it was our, you know, Frank Caviccio,
who was our junior coach and his wife Sharon
and Antonio Miracci, those guys, they put that in their heads.
They said, guys, you know, you can do what your cousins
or your mates are doing down the road and have an okay job
or you can be the first people.
And it was not only...
It was bigger than just buying a house for our family.
It was more being the first person in your family to buy a house.
That was a big thing.
No one, you know, no one in my whole family had been to university.
No one had bought a house ever.
So to be able to do that, and I got to do it, you know,
in my early 20s was...
That was bigger than any footballing moment, anything.
I still get into those boys because I got to do it first.
You know, I said, you just boys say, but you didn't say it properly
or your clubs weren't paying you right.
So I...
No, it was always something proud.
And, you know, once we'd all ticked it off, it was awesome.
Amazing.
So for me, I get the most pleasure from that.
Yeah.
I'm so thankful that I was given a goal or a purpose to do it.
And now in life, I get the same thing, you know.
Like I said, it just gives me purpose to do what I do every day.
And I think footballers in particular should have that, you know.
Whether they want to buy a house for their family or buy a new car,
there's always a reason why you play.
Finding your why has been a big thing for me for so many years.
We're interested in vision and, you know, setting a vision is one thing,
but how could you pass on some advice on how you deliver a vision to a team?
That's something you've been doing for a long period.
Yeah, and it's probably something that I've always, up until recently,
Darce, I've struggled with, you know, that word vision.
What is it?
But I had the last, in my last contract with Connett,
so I had a three-year contract and then they offered me a two-year extension
and Kerry and I discussed it at length and I went back to the CEO
and I said, Willie, I'm happy to sign a two-year extension.
And he said, and he said, and what's your vision, friendly?
And I went to rattle something off really quick and he said, no, no, pause.
He said, I want you to look over your shoulder
now and imagine you're driving down away from the sports ground,
College Road, the sports ground was on a road called College Road.
You're driving down the sports ground at the end of your two-year tenure
and you look over your shoulder, what do you want to see?
And again, I went to race into something.
He said, no, no, no, go and have a think and come back and tell me.
He said, great question.
So I went away and I thought about actually what do I want to see?
And that became the vision.
The great Stephen Covey started at the end and worked back towards that.
So that's now exactly how I set my visions is I start with what it is
that I want to see at the end of it and then I start to share that with people.
So I can have the vision but how they can influence that
and their input into that is really important too.
So I make sure that it's a vision that, for example, one of the key part,
I want this to be a really safe place to work.
I want you to be able to walk through the door and just be you.
Is everyone comfy with that?
Friendly, that would be brilliant if we could do it.
Sweet.
So how are we going to do it, guys?
And then we start to layer on the steps that we need to do
to make sure that's going to happen.
What do you need from me for that to work?
What do I need from you?
What do you need from the other staff?
What does it need to look like when we win?
What does it need to look like when we lose?
What does it need to look like when we're 40 points down after 20 minutes?
What's it need to look like there that you're still safe?
And we just have these conversations and we build it ourselves.
It's not, you know, it's friendly's vision potentially
but it's a collective vision that we've agreed to.
But how are we going to live this out?
Everyone has input into that and over time that's when I've learned
that the best visions are actually, they come to reality.
I've had a really good team around me, a really, really,
really good team around me in everything that I've kind
of been able to be a part of.
Look, my vision is genuinely, I would say that I believe
that segregation is a scar on the community in which we live
and that whenever it exists we need to do everything possible
to make sure that it is.
That it is rid.
I think that telling stories that haven't been told in mediums
that allow the story to be told a little differently
is really, really important.
I love creating content and creating conversations
where people are invited into a space that they may not have heard
it voiced in that way before.
You know, I love Tiny Island.
I love You Little Ripper, which is a Paralympics podcast
where we just talk Paralympic sport.
I don't like that.
There's no other sport in there.
Never will.
You know, like AFL and then our World Grand Final,
not for our audience, my friends.
This is all sport for people with disabilities and it is, you know,
it is a wild world and one that is something that created, you know,
a big chunk of who I am.
I love to, I don't know, if I find a pathway that I believe
that it aligns with purpose, I love just chasing it
and just seeing where it leads.
I love chasing it.
And I could never, one of the, I guess I have FOMO to the ninth
or the hundredth degree.
I just hate the idea of seeing an opportunity in front of me
and not kind of, not shaking it as hard as I can and not making sure
that I've seen the view on the other side of that mountain
or I've gave that, you know, that pathway a hell
of a shake.
We are really privileged to have many of the guests that you hear
from the Empowering Leaders podcast who are part
of our Elita Connect program.
We bring together groups of five to six people from around the globe
from unique and diverse backgrounds who come together to learn
and to connect and to share.
We are really passionate about what happens when you connect
great people together in a really trusted environment.
We'd love to tell you more about it.
Head to elitacollective.com and book a discovery call with us today.
We are super proud to be working alongside one
of the world's great learning institutions, Victoria University
as our support partner in 2025.
No one sees you like VU.
Victoria University is uniquely you.
We see a lot of great synergy between the world
of Victoria University and our passion for the world of Elita
and the Empowering Leaders podcast.
This episode is also proudly brought to you by Temper mattresses,
adjustable bases and pillows.
The difference is Temper.
The next group of guests will all speak about their unique approach
to the world of Elita.
Their unique approaches of creating and sharing their vision.
On a daily basis, we'll hear from Belinda Stowell,
an Olympic gold medal winner from the Sydney Olympics
who now leads other athletes to Olympic and World Championship glory.
The Honourable Will Ulstergan, the Chief Justice of the Family Court
of Australia and the Federal Circuit Court,
which puts him at the coalface of family and gender-based violence
in Australia, an issue he tirelessly campaigns against
in and out of the courtroom.
But first, let's go to the remarkable Vanessa Ford,
Chief Operating Officer.
Vanessa Ford, Chief Operating Officer of Kukua,
a Kenyan-based education entertainment company
that has a primarily female executive team
and the executive producer of the first African animated superhero series,
Super Seema, where the main character, Seema,
is an African superhero whose superpower is using her mind
and science and technology.
Whereas I used to be the person who would be, you know,
the first on set in the morning and the last person to leave
after midnight, now I have something not only to go home to,
but have something to go home to.
Having a baby, you know, that baby needs their mom.
But here's something that people don't really say enough
is that actually that, like, mom needs their babies too, right?
And I feel like when I became a mom, I was like,
I actually want to be present.
I want to be there.
I don't want to be jumping on a plane to Malaysia
to save, you know, a production or, you know,
putting out fires and all of these different worldwide productions.
And I realized that, actually, what can I do to give this next generation,
i.e. my own children, something that I never had?
And I grew up, you know, turning on the television,
opening a magazine, and I never saw anyone with my color skin,
my big afro.
I never had that opportunity to, like, look at myself,
as a six or seven-year-old, as a hero.
You know, thankfully, I had a, I walked into my house
and I had my mom, I had my aunt, I had Auntie Oprah on television.
But those were really the only role models I had.
And then when I took the trajectory of science and biology and physics,
you know, I never had a teacher that looked like me.
I was often, and so I thought, wow, what if this superhero
was not only a little Black girl, but what if she,
her superpowers were the things that I think superpowers are,
which is science, technology, engineering, arts and math,
the whole STEAM framework.
So I was just, I got really excited about this idea
and about making sure that this next generation of children
would be watching and consuming things that could empower them.
And I think as storytellers, we have that, yeah,
we have that obligation to really change the narrative.
Like that's, like, it's our agenda.
We have, we are given that position.
We're given that platform.
Rather than just putting out another thing that's already there,
I felt SuperSama was like the culmination of all of these different threads
of my life as well, coming together, you know,
working still in the entertainment space, being able to pull out my old Hollywood
contacts.
Yeah.
To, you know, rope in, you know, superstars like Lupita Nyong'o
and getting them involved, you know, you can go through life positively accepting
and being like passive and being used as part of someone's vision and purpose,
or you can really claim space to be who you are and go through life
according to your own agenda.
And I think that being a Black woman, and especially, you know,
when I was working in a more corporate structure,
I think there's a certain amount of going against the grain that you feel every day,
even just being present, like particularly when your goal is to be fully authentically
true to yourself.
So it does feel like you're claiming and reclaiming your space.
And I think for me, SuperSama was a bit of that as well.
You know, I think, yeah, I think the whole kind of claiming culture,
that term kind of came back into popular lexicon when Maxine Waller,
one of my daughters, very publicly in the hearing said, you know,
I'm reclaiming my time, and she kept repeating it.
And there was something so powerful about this older Black woman within a
judicial system telling a room full of white men that, you know,
I'm reclaiming my time.
So I think there's something about reclamation and claiming that felt very
relevant and triumphant.
And yeah, I want that.
And I want to do that.
And I want to move through my life, claiming and reclaiming what I think I deserve and
what I want.
And I think SuperSama reflects that decision and also to become an entrepreneur and to
say no to other offers.
You know, I could have transitioned from one big Hollywood studio to another, and I
really decided to say no, because I felt like I would, I didn't want to be owned or to
be claimed.
I wanted to do something for myself.
I wanted to do something for my family.
I wanted to build that legacy.
And I think my vision has always been so big.
You know, I've never been someone who's just like, oh, I want to get from here to there.
It's like, no, I want to change the world.
And, and, and getting people to jump on kind of our Kukua rocket ship that I like to call it and like
blast off without, you know, leaving other careers and, and I think has been a
testament to that has been like, we literally, we will in the SuperSama office, we have a
wall of all these women that we really believe in.
And we had Lupita up there, we had Serena, we had Oprah, and, and it's still there.
We had all these pictures of all these women that we, and we always said one day, these
women are going to walk through this office.
And just the fact that we've had, you know, not only some of those women walk in our office,
but some of them support us.
Some of them.
Yeah.
Being investors, some of them being a part of our company and like believing in our vision.
That is like, that says it all.
I was talking to a sports psych once about what I was trying to do.
And, you know, he spent 45 minutes trying to ask me what I wanted to do.
And I didn't want to say, look, I want to go and win an Olympic gold medal in Sydney 2000.
But finally, after 45 minutes, he made me get it out.
But it was, I was talking to another psych a few years later and he said, well, basically
he only made one decision in five years.
I said, well, that's pretty, pretty true because everything, once you have a vision, everything
and behind it makes sense and coincidences start happening because you've got this decision
that you know where you want to go.
And I think vision is also important when running the program to be able to have a great
vision of where do I want to be in five years time?
Because what we're doing now is the result of what we were doing five years before or
what the athletes were being trained up five years before is pretty much what we're looking
at now.
So to have a good vision, you need that for the collaboration piece as well, to be able
to bring people along or to show and share what your vision is.
You're not going to get any help if you can't tell people what you want to achieve.
So I kind of think vision is pretty important.
A couple of big visions, uniting a couple of courts, as you said, with all the complexities
of that and now being someone at the face of a campaign to try and stop this.
National disgrace of violence against women.
How have you gone about creating and sharing visions of that scale?
What's been your method for that?
I think internally with my own team and getting people who are really inspirational, I think
I sort of, like a lot of people, I think you react if you've got positive people around
you.
And my team are incredibly positive.
They're visionary.
They're probably pretty patient with some of those silly ideas I have.
I'll give you one example.
Last year, just before The Voice, I think a lot of people were hearing terrible things
about what was happening in Alice Springs.
And it was mainly...
I think some misinformation.
I was really inquisitive as to what was happening and how we could support that community.
We have a once a year judges meeting.
It was meant to be in Melbourne.
And I said to my poor events organiser, Alex, look, I want to take 120 judges, cancel Melbourne.
We're going to Alice Springs.
It's not an easy place to fly into.
I rang the security officer and said, got any problems?
And he said, oh, no, it should be fine.
Thinking, oh my gosh, what are you doing?
And sure enough, six or eight weeks later, we were up in Alice Springs.
We spent three days up there.
We talked to the local people.
Went to the town camps.
Went to the communities.
And 120 judges got experiences they never had before about how Indigenous people live
in some of these communities, what the effects it can have on them from a legal system, what
they understand and don't understand, and really the challenges they face being part
of our community or part of our litigation system and how unfair it can be on them.
Now, we left that message just because I thought, you know, what, we're just going to go up
there and see it.
And it was one of the best things we ever did.
We had Eastern...
We had a lot of state judges who'd never been in a community before spending time in there
and talking to people about it, what they felt, the kind of misinformation or some of
the information that was going on, and just the education we were able to obtain from
that.
That's just sort of one idea.
But it was just great to be able to change the course and think a bit laterally.
During COVID, we were locked down like everybody else.
We decided with our courts, with the backlogs and other things that were happening, and
I think I spoke to you a little bit with John Triple M about it, we had to get the message
out.
Yeah.
People weren't alone, and if they couldn't see their kids, it was border disputes and
all sorts of other things.
They could vary their arrangements in a safe way.
I remember going on the radio, getting in the television and saying, calling people
out and saying, listen, we haven't shut down.
We're still open for business, and we can help you in making some suggestions.
We started a COVID-19 list so people could get to the court really easily.
We made sure that if women were in crisis, they could actually contact us through phone
numbers and through video hearings that they couldn't have done before.
We worked with the women's legal services.
We were just fantastic, and the men's legal services, and we probably revolutionized the
court and nationalized the court in a way we never would have had to before.
I loved going into that courtroom every day during COVID and doing these things.
Most courts went down about 40% of what they were doing during COVID.
We were at 105%.
We just smashed it, and it was great because we were just so enthusiastic to do it, and
that's all these judges.
Imagine getting a whole aging population of judges and saying to them,
in two weeks' time, you're going to do total electronic hearings.
If I'd said in two years, they wouldn't have believed me.
They all did it.
Then they started competing at who could do it better.
It was a great time, and I think, realistically, that's the kind of environment I want to work
in, and I expect people to work in.
Huge thanks to all the guests featured on this episode, to Nick Natanui, Andy Friend,
Kurt Fearnley, Vanessa Ford, Belinda Stowell, the Honorable Will Ulsterigan.
You can find the links to the full-length in-depth conversations I had with each of
them in the show notes.
On our next Success Leads Clues episode, curiosity is a leadership quality that shapes
our learning and development, and we're excited to explore its transformative impact on the
journey of some exceptional guests.
If you enjoy listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast, be sure to subscribe, and please,
if you have a moment, I'd love you to leave a review so we can reach more listeners and
empower more leaders.