As soon as I start talking, I'm like, be Max Gorn.
And then it just, it flows.
So important for me to use this opportunity to communicate, to translate.
I think it is really about having sort of clear, concise messaging.
I want you to hit these three target points.
We're all sticking to these three talking points.
Well, I've been lucky enough to record so many engaging conversations with remarkable leaders,
or what I think are engaging conversations, in the past year.
And covering the keys to their success.
2024, our audience have had a front row seat to conversations that reveal
how success leaves clues, featuring guests from across the globe
who are at the top of their game.
At Alida, we understand the consistent dimensions of brilliant leadership,
and we love exploring them in this special series.
The art of communicating with clarity is an individual skill
and one worth honing with practice and good advice.
Every week on the Empowering Leaders series,
our conversations stretch.
Across different fields, people from the world of sport,
business leaders, champions of education, social venture, and the arts.
And this episode, we've curated what we think is a remarkable group of individuals
who take communicating with clarity seriously and explain exactly how they do it.
You'll hear from Paul Watterson, the founder and chief executive officer of Australian Venue Co.
and a serial successful business investor in everything he does.
Australian football icon Max Gorn joins us.
A seven-time All-Australian,
Premiership Captain of the Melbourne Football Club,
and regarded as one of the game's greatest ever ruckman.
But let's get started with Dr. Troy Flanagan,
Vice President of High Performance at the Milwaukee Bucks in the NBA.
Troy is a sports physiologist with a remarkable background in sports technology development
that includes a PhD in aerospace engineering.
I think the first thing that comes to my mind is I'm the guy who interprets all the
technical jargon and gives it to the general manager and the owner.
And so I take,
complex medical jargon about a particular injury and I walk upstairs and say,
okay, here's what's going on with his knees.
Don't, don't, don't.
Actually, the U.S. ski team taught me this.
In any situation, you need three talking points.
And as simple as that sounds, like we would have an incident or a new sponsorship or,
you know, an athlete that's achieved good results or perhaps underachieved,
they always used to meet as a group, collective group and say, okay,
this has happened.
These are our talking points.
Everyone on that message.
You can say other things, but I want you to hit these three target points.
If anyone from the media, anyone from the organization,
we're all sticking to these three talking points.
And I've really taken that forward.
You know, if something's happening here with the Bucks,
I always get the group in and say, okay, this has happened.
You know, we've got a significant injury.
Here are our talking points, if anyone asks.
Because people will come and ask for information.
They'll come and ask for information from all different angles.
And, you know, that's certainly in good stead.
And you're talking the highest pressure situations.
You go back to an NBA championship playoff and one of the most high profile athletes
in the world has a knee injury.
Every person in your city wants to know about that knee injury.
And what are you doing, Troy?
How do we get Giannis back on the court?
So again, is it just, here's the three things that we're working on.
Let's stick to that communication.
Does that work under that extreme pressure as well?
It really does.
And one of the things that I look back on in my time in Australia is the best medical
professionals, like Peter Harcourt and all those guys, you know, they're always so calm
under pressure, like just all sorts of stuff would be happening.
And they were just absolutely calm.
Like surgeons, you know, when things are going wrong and they're just so cool and calm.
And that's what I try and if you actually see me in a game, like behind the bench, you
know, the whole crowd is roaring.
And I'm just sitting there.
I'm just sitting there.
And I'm just sitting there calmly, not so much inside, but developed that skill over
10 years of, you know, and everything is happening in the gut, wrenching stress of winning an
NBA championship.
You know, it's kind of at the end of COVID, which adds a whole nother lay of stress.
It's taught me to be calm in really chaotic situations.
And I think that married with clear communication is has been one of the keys to success.
And even when we've got Dr. Rivers now.
And he's he's a great guy.
Yeah.
He's a great guy.
assistant coaches and they're like we can't believe how calm you are in in a injury crisis
and you know i've had a lot of them so maybe it just washes off these days but that's something
that has taken years to develop you know i thought i had it after a couple of years but
you know it still get to me the stress would still get to me and and then after about five
years in the nba i'm like it's washing over now i don't i don't feel it anymore and now after 10
years it's i think i've got it got it mastered i love you described that's a skill you went after
and worked on and a mastery of wanting to be that way how important has collaboration been to you
yeah i think it's really the key to success if i talk just nba i think in the past in the nba
you know the medical staff and performance staff are over in that corner and coaches are over in
that corner and you know that's coaching and and that's medicine and i i think the really
progressive
you
I think world-class teams now are inviting the performance and medical staff into coaches
meetings there and you know to listen to hear what the coaches are saying directly about the
players and taking that information back into that preparation you know i think really the key
to our success or one of the keys to our success has been the inviting nature of the different
groups in the organization and has taught me a lot of how important it is when we've been
successful and when we haven't
it's been awful little and so so we're always striving to you know form those partnerships and
the gm and the coach and i we always say it's a partnership we work in a partnership
and and we say that word a lot you know we're partners in this and um that i think that sets
the tone i think it is really about having sort of clear concise messaging and i think being
conscious of all types of communication i think
people sort of typecast talking as communication but it's just as important to be really actively
listening so that's where i do have to really pull myself in and say just put the phone down
and concentrate on the person in front of you look at their body language look at what they're saying
to you look at where the challenges are and try and work through and sort of solve those and i
think the other thing is being very clear and decisive on your messaging we've done a there's
a lot of studies out there that show that there's a lot of studies out there that show that there's a lot of
when you meet someone new what you do within that first sort of you know 30 seconds to a minute
is really important about getting your message across so that's the other thing i really try
and focus on when i'm in a meeting or meeting someone new for a half an hour or an hour just
go in and really understand what are the key messages that you want to get across and do it
within the first minute or so because if you can do that and you still got their attention then
hopefully something comes from it
the best version of yourself is the best leader that they can be so not trying to be someone
you're not always reflecting on what you could do better but then also making sure that you're
your best self we do this we do this thing at the club that i've lived and died by now i've i'm i've
got a whiteboard at home so jess hates this she wants to be all just on your phone fam cal like
everything goes in the same and calendar but i hate using my phone as i've just said so i've got
this i will all whiteboard as big as this wall
that has like a month up there and i'm a visual person i love seeing it all there
but i set up my week to be the best version i can be so i know on monday
i need to go in the beach at some time have a sauna i need to have uninterrupted time with my
kids i need to read a book and i need to write in my diary and then what i need to do tuesday all
the way to thursday friday you've heard is no phone and that's set up my week and i do that
every sunday night i set my week up and that allows me to be the best version of me and then bang
when i'm the best version of myself and then i'm the best version of myself and then i'm the best version of
me come the time that's let's say it's midday till five i'm at the club on monday i've delegated
that time around it to be the best version i can be at 12 till five as a captain i think the way
people communicate might be the thing that we hear the most that people really have a strategy
on that we've heard about you know your discipline with your phone but if you've got a mantra in the
way that you communicate in the role that you've got uh so the the journal so i've got sort of
everything in terms of the last time i spoke to someone
if i'm speaking to them again um so i've got everything written down like you said we're
we're both visual people so it's written down um so i've got that to look at before and look at
after to reflect but i tell myself every time i go into especially hard conversations obviously
hard conversations the easy come the the positive conversations are fine but you walk in and just
before i start i'm like be max corn which is i mean like i said it's harder than you think it is
because um it can be quite challenging with the different stresses and anxieties in the world but
as soon as i start talking about be max corn and then it just it flows the harder conversation
isn't necessarily that hard we are really privileged to have many of the guests that
you hear from the empowering leaders podcast who are part of our leader connect program
we bring together groups of five to six people from around the globe from unique and diverse
backgrounds who come together to learn and to connect and to share we are really passionate
about what happens when you connect great people together in a really trusted environment we'd love
to tell you more about it head to elitacollective.com and book a discovery call with us today
we are super proud to be working alongside one of the world's great learning institutions
victoria university as our support partner in 2025 no one sees you like vu victoria university
is uniquely you we see a lot of great synergy between the world of victoria university
and our passion for the world of a leader and the empowering leaders podcast this episode is also
proudly brought to you by temper mattresses adjustable bases
and pillows the difference is temper our final two guests both speak to how communicating with
clarity has helped them to live a life of great success we're going to hear from rachel gunn
better known as ray gunn the australian professor and break dancer who we spoke to just a couple of
days before she flew to paris to compete in the 2024 olympic games where she became a global
sensation but first let's go to wayne holdsworth a father and a husband who's bravely shared the
story of his son who died by suicide
after experiencing online bullying and extortion a heartbreaking story that touched so many people
it's a story that i generally think everyone needs to listen to but we know conversations like this
may be triggering and difficult for many people so please if you are experiencing some challenges
call lifeline 13 11 14 if you're affected by this conversation we can make a difference
tiktok in a day that's right exactly done that's over yep and and i think with with him for an
it's not about the money it's about the power and that reminds me of a person that
you know terrorized his race way back and we know who adolf hitler was and i really
i really worry about that style of person infiltrating australia with the power that
he has however we now have an opportunity we know as australians that this exposure
is killing our young folk we have no no difficulty in understanding that there's a direct relationship
with what they're being fed the algorithms that are underpinning and and then the actions that
particularly young boys and young girls are taking you know through eating disorders through sexual
extortion through bullying and so we as australians have to say to the government enough is enough
you have to make a call on what our kids are allowed to do you tell them that they have to
wear a seat belt in a car and they have to wear a seat belt in a car and they have to wear a seat belt
in a car you tell them that you can't drive until you're 18 you say they can't drink until they're
18 although some do why don't you why don't you make a law that says that kids under 16 cannot
be exposed to this and if it needs to be 18 so be it because if the government does that and i know
whippers doing a really good job in lobbying um the kids be kids are doing the same thing there's a
joint select committee
set up in Canberra that I met last week. Some of the people that are involved in that, the
chairperson of that, they all agree that this has to happen. Well, bloody do it. Get it
done in August and get legislation in November and save our kids because there will be some
kids that are clever enough to get around it and they'll work it out or Zuckerberg will
sort something out. But if we can at least save 50% of those kids and make it easier
on the parents. So the parents aren't the bad guys. It's the law.
I was home last night and the conversation still every night, 17 and 13 year olds still
there. The phones get locked in another room. You fight to get them off them. I've got active
kids that are healthy and doing a whole range of things, but it's something that I have
people say to me, just take them off it. And they are always people who aren't parents.
Correct.
Who don't, this is where their whole connection, it's like asking them to cut an arm or a leg
off is what you're effectively doing.
Yeah.
Remove themselves from their whole community. What we need is some guardrails. Now we're
fighting hard on the home fronts. All of us, we're not asleep at the wheel here as parents,
but as you said, you know, Seatbelt saved tens of thousands of lives because we needed
legislation to do. There is no downside. Whippers campaign to get the 36 months and the age
limit up is an absolute no brainer.
We can go further on this, do zero damage and only have the upside. And I think we just,
we can't afford more tragedies like this. They're happening far too often, Wayne. And
for you to, as you said, take the path of education, you know, more strength to your
arm on this.
Yeah. Thanks, mate. Look, you know, the figures, there was 801 people that took their own life
in Victoria alone in 2023. There were 299 people die on the road. So it's two and a
half times the number of people died on the road, took their life compared to die on the
road. And 50 people drowned. So incomprehensible.
Comparison. And when I was growing up in the mid seventies, there was a campaign, declare
war on 1034 because it was 1034 people died on Victorian roads that year. And now it's
down to 299. As you said, Luke, we're the first country, our first state in the world
to introduce compulsory seatbelts, drink driving laws, better roads, better vehicles, better
education. So it can be done. We have to do it because our kids,
are becoming, they're so precious and to lose them because of things that we're in
control of. It's not as if they've developed a rare form of cancer or they're in a car
accident and it's unavoidable. This is avoidable. And we're lame as citizens if we don't force
the government to make a difference and to change it.
They'll look back on our generation and shake their head and say, what the fuck did you
guys do?
And the language is there on purpose because the solutions are there. And I have to mention
this beautiful, extraordinary person, Zoe Kalar, who's created We Are Right. I don't know if
you've come across it. It takes out the anonymity. So immediately 90% of the hate is gone. It's
social media for good. It's putting that 135 billion US from Zuckerberg back into the hands
of community. It's only positivity in there. They could switch off the hate and the algorithms
tomorrow, but they keep you on those apps.
With anger, because they know that's what keeps you and they jam advertising at you
to make more money. We can pull that back. Government, spend your digital advertising
on We Are Right. Let's get the community voice coming through. Let's legislate to up the
age limit, which is a no-brainer. Let's have an education program that you're doing every
single day, teaching families how to deal with this better to save lives. It's an incredible
contribution you're making, Wayne. I know it's heartbreaking to even think about it,
think about what you've been through, but I didn't meet your beautiful young lad, mate.
I wish I did, but I feel like he's going to save a lot of people, mate.
Yeah, yeah. I'm doing what I do now to create a legacy for him and to use his death as a
catalyst to do more in this space. I've been out now to see just over 1,500 people, normally
in the after hours, because I work Monday to Saturday in basketball.
I'm full-time, and my board have been really supportive to allow me to do what I need to
do to help the community. When I talk to people about the signs, it's new to them. When I
talk to them about the statistics, it's new to them. One in five people here in Australia
have suicidal thoughts. We talk about fitness in the footy field. We see someone limping
into the change rooms, and Christian Petrarca coming off the ground. That's had so much
exposure, because it was such a horrific injury, because we can see it. But mental fitness,
we can't see it. But I want people to ask, not only, how are you going, Christian, you
know, physically, but how's your mental fitness going? And if he says, shit, it's at about
five or six now, we need to talk to him more. And we need to be talking to people that have
got mental challenges, and to be able to support them through that.
And know what to do. You know, 12 people have come into my office alone. You know, big
basketballs. You think that are impervious to this. They've come in crying. You know,
I have to tell them to sit down so I can get level with them. You know, and they're in
a world of pain. But if I can do that, and then I refer them on to someone that can help
them, they multiply that by 20 and 40 and 100, and then we're fighting back. And so
my program called Smack Talk, so if anyone wants to jump online and book a session, it's
free. I go out to anywhere in Victoria. I'm going to New South Wales and Queensland on
weekends to educate people, sporting groups, corporate groups. And I'll talk to mums and
dads about the signs, about having good listening skills, about the statistics. Just trying
to make a difference, mate.
It's so important for me to use this opportunity to communicate.
To translate breaking to as big an audience as possible, because this is such a unique
moment. And also as a breaking, as part of the breaking community, you know, we learned
a lot of lessons from the early 1980s. There was not enough of an emphasis on what this
dance and culture was about. The term breakdancing being used is an example of that. You know,
it was used to describe a few different dance styles and didn't really take into account
the whole culture behind breaking.
So this is such an important opportunity for us. You know, with the visibility, we want
to have the explanation that goes alongside it of this is a culture. This is a culture
that started in the States, African-American and Puerto Rican kids. But we've also had
a scene here in Australia since the late 1970s. You know, there's many what we call OGs, you
know, like around still that would be able to tell some amazing stories of what the scene
was like in Sydney or Perth.
You know, Melbourne, et cetera. So it's really important to use this opportunity to communicate
what I think are the really important aspects of breaking at this time. Yeah.
Right. You mentioned earlier that you're turning up to competitions. There's 56 males, you
know, fully masculine and putting it out there. You're the sole female. That takes a fair
bit of courage, but I'm assuming collaboration has been a big part of how you've been able
to work your way through.
How important has the collaboration part been for you?
It's totally important. Breaking is a social dance as well as a competitive dance. So I
wouldn't have been able to do all that I've done without the support of my crew, which
is kind of like a self-made team, if you will, who always had my back at every competition
that I went to. You know, so these were intimidating situations that I was in only because I was
the only girl.
And only because I, you know, felt so different. You know, sometimes it'd be a bit in your face,
but not in a dangerous way. And it just was really nice to have their support always there.
The other way that collaboration is, of course, so important in breaking is because of the way
that we learn and the way that we train. So I only went to a studio for maybe about a year
to learn the basic techniques of breaking. The rest of the time, I've just been at my
training sessions with my crew and I would work on key skills or moves.
And I would, you know, work on going into the circle and practice. And my crewmates
would teach me. They would teach me because they've all been breaking, you know, a decade
at least longer than me. And they would teach me different moves and skills. And so it is
a very collaborative culture, very social, very collaborative. The knowledge is shared
and you're in this together. The same, you know, on the dance floor when you're battling,
there is that social exchange as well. So you are constantly kind of,
thinking about others as you're dancing. It's not just a solo activity.
Huge thanks to all of our guests featured on this episode. Dr. Troy Flanagan,
Paul Watterson, Max Gorn, Wayne Holdsworth, and Rachel Gunn. You can find the links to the full
length in-depth conversations I have with each of them in the show notes. On our next Success
Leads Clues episode, we've put together the tips and strategies told to us by leaders across the
globe on how they positively impact people every day around them. If you enjoy listening to the
Empowering Leaders podcast, please subscribe to our YouTube channel and hit the bell so you don't
miss out on any future episodes. And please, if you have a moment, I'd love you to leave a review
so we can reach more listeners and empower more leaders.