I think a lot of people can go to work these days and not feel like they're seen or heard.
Enabling and empowering everyone else in the team to be able to share their vision.
If we started caring for each other and speak to each other and listen to understand, which I work on every day, Luke, we need to care for each other more.
It's a privilege to have spent another year sitting across from inspiring leaders at the top of their game as they unpack the learnings and life lessons from their chosen field.
At Alita, we know there are consistent dimensions of what great leadership looks like, and we're covering them all in this special series.
In our work, we see so many people in positions of leadership who are really conscious of how they positively impact others in their environment on a daily basis.
Each week on the Empowering Leaders series, we hear from people across a range of industries, champions of education, social venture, the arts, the business world, or legends from the world of sport.
And when it comes to the idea of having a positive impact on others.
We had a difficult time narrowing it down to just this select group of people you're about to hear from.
You'll hear from Valerie Condos-Field, a U.S. college coaching legend voted as the Pac-12 Coach of the Century, a UCLA Coaching Hall of Famer, a seven-time national champion across a remarkable 29 years as the head of gymnastics at UCLA.
And Whipper, Michael Whipper-Whipfly, multiple award-winning radio presenter and comedian who has used his microphone for good.
Over the years, supporting and raising thousands of dollars for youth-related charities across Australia.
This year, he successfully campaigned to change national legislation that increases the age when children are legally able to access social media from 13 to 16.
Let's begin with the remarkable Zoe Killar, who is literally changing the world for good through her social media platform that she's built and created.
She's a serial tech entrepreneur of great success.
She's turned her attention to try.
To create social media for good, you need to check out We Are Right.
All the other governments are suing the social networks.
They're talking about it.
It's very simple.
It is damaging for society.
It's fueling, knowingly fueling teen suicide and self-harm.
It's knowingly making our societies, I would argue, it's just dumbing everything down, making people feel really not valued.
So just stop.
Just stop governments, take a stand, ban it, because there's an evolution now, but because that process is too slow, we've just got to get on with it.
So it's a tough old road, but with thanks to amazing women and men like you advocating and getting in the trenches with us, because I look at young girls that want to be engineers or reimagine things.
And I don't want it.
To be this path, we need to be able to absolutely be free to imagine the biggest things, work out how to do it, and have the support to execute on it.
And I can't wait to, We Are Right becomes a $100 billion company, and then we can pump, I can personally pump so much money back into founder, you know, female and diverse led teams, all the things that I want to make.
All of those things are going to make impact on using our tech, but the status quo is broken.
And there's this fragility and massive civil unrest from an economic perspective that is simply not sustainable.
I know it's almost laughable that on a macro level we think there is so much, the economic divide doesn't work.
The greed from big tech doesn't work.
Our society, these are self-harming and suiciding, the mental health of Black people.
They're also playing chess with what health schönheit or health health, not as many women, our health is of multiple shades of yellow.
Really fast growth, zero and everything else going on.
It's a pair of things,入 στο erzähل.
The geopolitical shift of how we make impact on the friends of millennials infriendly elsewhere.
Think about that, we'll be happy to use it.
We're going to be able to make impact on the people that are doing their records at once.
crisis is an epidemic the climate is screaming for our help at what point do we say oh shit we
better do something about about this i'm one of those people that ends up and some people probably
wouldn't believe this but i overanalyze self all the time i mean i i remember when um you know when
my mom i grew up in a really working class area and you know mom and dad both worked dad was a
doctor mom was a nurse you know the shopping it was you know i remember being at the supermarket
and her holding items back before going through did we have enough money to have everything we
wanted and i remember feeling i'm high high empathy so i'd feel the pain and i just wanted
out of way i didn't want her to feel like that i could feel the it was really really intense for me
as a kid and i could feel it all around me when it was too strong i used to hold my breath because i
couldn't and mom would say darling you've got to breathe you've got because i just couldn't if i
saw someone doing something really abusive or anything i just couldn't i i absorbed it so i
had to learn to stop it
so i think for me there's a real i just want to help i want to do things for others and i think
if we all did a little bit for others god we'd live in a beautiful society you know i think if
we if we started caring for each other and speak to each other and listen to understand which i
work on every day um but it's it's we need to care for each other more
you know i hear those comments that your beautiful uh commentating colleague went through
and i just think no one should have to go through that like that hearing that puts fire in my belly
like you have no idea like it is not okay and we just need to so yes and and how good it feels
when we start to care for each other that's where the joy is excellent you know that's
that's right right the highest form of living isn't it when you are contributing and what and
what you're doing at that level is quite remarkable and then it takes incredible skill and will to
change paradigm and a lot of people have that thought and think you know i should do this a
better way but under pressure we go back to our old habits and i suppose that is the intersection
of your incredible friendship as it turned out with the legendary coach john wooden and for the
audience that don't know about coach wooden one
national basketball championships in 12 seasons seven in a row no other team had won more than four
in a row or never has before or since he won an incredible 88 consecutive games as as coach but
he became an incredible mentor for you can tell everyone about how that came about well it came
about because i was i had not met coach wooden yet and i was on my way to resign and i was walking
through our student union and walking through the bookstore i happened upon a book
of coach wooden his leadership book and i just literally opened it up like this and it opened
up to his definition of success and i thought well you know what he won 10 national championships he
was hailed as the greatest coach of any sport that ever lived what does he say about winning
and i read success is peace of mind and knowing that you've done your best and i kept flipping
through the pages because i was like this made no sense to me this is like a whole
more card success is peace of mind and knowing you've done your best oh that's nice and i thought
where is he going to talk about winning coaches are hired to win we're not hired to be mentors
or second moms or dads or your pal we're hired to win so he must talk about winning and i kept
going through the pages and like i kept coming back to his definition of success
and when i was ready to
have time so i read it slowly success is peace of mind and knowing you have done your best
i've had the biggest aha moment of my professional career i had not been trying to be my best
i had been trying to be somebody else and i started connecting all the proverbial dots
whenever you try to be somebody else you will always be a second right them i will never
be as good as somebody
being them as they are being them and what i learned later on in my years when i tried to be
coach wouldn't that was equally as bad because i was never going to be as good as coach wouldn't
being coach would it and the worst part that happens is when you try to be somebody else
or even like somebody else it prevents you from truly developing into a first-rate you
and so i didn't resign i went back to my office and i thought what do i bring to the table as a
head coach of a
UCLA gymnastics team and our sport is called artistic gymnastics I grew up in the world of
ballet there was a lot of points given to artistry in our sport what do I bring well you know what
I can teach the artistry and movement quality and choreograph better than anybody else that's
gymnastics in this country I'm going to do that so that was the technical for me
and then I had to start thinking about though the bigger picture was
I just really did not buy into this world of athletics where it was all about winning
because it seemed really silly to me that athletics was all about being able to say
haha we beat you haha I beat you today haha my team's better than
your team's ever been ever been ever been ever been ever been ever been ever been ever
team it's like how many gazillions of dollars are spent every year in athletics there has to be more
to athletics than haha we beat you so what is that and then it became really clear once I got the
noise out of haha we beat you and winning winning winning then I understood athletics
is a master class in teaching really really really tough life lessons you don't learn in
a classroom athletics teaches us about resilience and perseverance and how to fall and get back up
athletics teaches us about being a part of team something greater than yourself athletics teaches
you all those things you do not learn in math and english and history and science and I was like oh
my gosh I could do this I'm going to help my student athletes become champions in life through
sport and my classroom is the gym
and I went I remember going to my athletic director and I remember saying okay I got this
but I'm not focusing on winning I'm going to focus on developing every single one of my student
athletes into the best superhuman superhero they can be and because I was at UCLA and because I
could recruit talent I knew that that would translate to the competition floor and then
guess what it did and we started winning with the pm right I don't even know whether it
was the best superhuman superhero that I've ever seen I don't even know whether you're a dutton fan or you're with albanese I think for both of them you've got a real opportunity here to become a true world leader where you can actually have a major change and I'll tell you what this topic is hot in every country and slowly state by state in the U.S. you see it and other states and other countries will pull the trigger but imagine being able to hang your hat on it I mean and that's why I talk and I don't get me wrong I'm being a bit cheeky and I'm shooting from the hip here when I say if you made this an election promise
then you would win the vote of every Australian parent now maybe you wouldn't I know you know whatever
side I vote for I would definitely jump on that ship if that was on the table out of concern for
my kids the one thing you love more and care about more than anything else on this planet
so I'm cheeky when I say that and I understand it but at the same time I think they need a nudge
and I think they could also see the opportunity so it's fantastic that Albo came out and said
I love that you're doing this we see the opportunity and I think they need a nudge
the importance of this and then put some money into some research into tech and verification
which is great but you know what you can actually make that call you're the most powerful man in the
country and you can pull the trigger on that so if we make enough noise I mean you the prime
the prime minister works for us does you realize that he works for us you and me and anybody else
listening so we need to remind him of what's important to us we're going to tell him what we
need so he can do it he can do it he can do it he can do it he can do it he can do it he can do it
he can lead and implement so we just need to remind him what he needs to do for us and I think
you've thrown that challenge down nicely it's right when election cycles come around really
quickly I think this is a thing that almost unites every parent no one thinks this is a good thing
and we all need help because if as you said if you're the only parent removing social media from
your kid they are going to be the outlier we need this is this is where governments can do good
and do it easily and have no negative effect there is no downside what advantage is there
to giving a kid social media at 13 there is no upside and we now know irrefutably we're actually
harming and losing children as a result of it so that doesn't make sense no it just doesn't make
any sense that's the other thing and and I'm sure a lot of parents do they'd be going mad when they
think let's just I mean let's run the pub test over this and I'm I can't understand why we're
okay with that and you know there's a great a great quote the other day that we will look back
and think what will we do we're going to do this we're going to do this we're going to do this we're
doing what were we doing to our kids did you know that back in the day there weren't seatbelts in
the car and you could drink as much as you want and drive you're kidding who would do that they
did I did sit on my dad's lap and uh steer the wheel with her back back in the day it was johnny
johnny whipfully used to get behind the wheel and he knew he was going straight because he could feel
the tram lines under the tires it's not that long ago whipper is it and I know and people don't
know that dad used to say it was illegal to be gay oh no what are you talking about crazy so I feel
like we have all this data that's been collected over the past 10 years or so and now we're in a
position to be able to present it let's not let's not stretch this set of data required we don't
need any more it's all on the table and it's all in front of us so let's not consider this trial
period of what we're doing to kids to go any longer we are really privileged to have many of
the guests that you hear from the
power and leaders podcast who are part of our leader connect program we bring together groups
of five to six people from around the globe from unique and diverse backgrounds who come together
to learn and to connect and to share we are really passionate about what happens when you
connect great people together in a really trusted environment we'd love to tell you more about it
head to elitacollective.com and book a discovery call with us today we are super proud to be
working alongside one of the world's great learning institutions
victoria university as our support partner in 2025 no one sees you like vu victoria university
is uniquely you we see a lot of great synergy between the world of victoria university
and our passion for the world of a leader and the empowering leaders podcast this episode is also
proudly brought to you by temper mattresses adjustable bases and pillows the difference
is temper the final two guests both speak to how impacting others positively on a daily basis
has led them to a life of great success let's go first to joanna
griggs one of the most loved and respected figures in australian television history and
the first australian woman to solely host an olympic games for the past two decades and more
joe has been a mainstay of channel seven's olympic and paralympic coverage and the incredibly
successful better homes and gardens followed by tess madgen captain the australian women's
basketball team the opals who has represented australia at the tokyo and paris olympic games
we had a promo going many many bosses back at seven where i feel very safe to say it
they wanted all of their network talent in bikinis running along the beach slapping each other
yep and i was just like no yeah and they were like why not you've been in plenty of causes in
your life i'm like a hundred percent they said you you modeled for inside sport i said i did as
an athlete yeah a hundred percent and i said well put it this way i'll do it when you have bruce
mcavaney in a pair of slugos running on the beach hitting i don't know a couple of guys on the ass
how about that and that was the end of the conversation but it was just like those those
moments and and i got even though i was a little bit of a fan of the olympic games i was a fan of the
even as recently as after the olympics and paralympics i had one of the male bosses sit
down and because i'd called him out on some bad behavior he basically wanted to talk to me about
what was i missing my kids and i was like what like my kids at that stage 27 and 26 like one
at that stage lived in cans and you know they're very very confident very you know self-assured
and very self-efficient young men i'm like how many men do you have this conversation with
because i'm fine he's like well but you must miss your husband and i'm like
is having the greatest time of his life at the moment like we've probably been together enough
through covid that he could not wait till i got sent away for six months and he missed me long
enough that by the time i got back it was just it was awesome for our relationship like we had so
much fun seeing each other again but but literally i was just saying to him hang on before i answer
any of this when have you last had a conversation with a man about these things like what has this
got to do with anything and it actually came out that he just didn't want me to call him out on
his bad behavior yeah and you will consistently i said well don't behave
and there's the answer we haven't got a problem it's it's genius and we see ladies are really
conscious around on a daily basis how they positively impact people in the environment
they're in this is right to your forehand uh do you conscious about that impacting people
positively or yeah i think um i think a lot of people can go to work these days and not feel
like they're seen or heard and i think feeling like you're not heard is horrible but feeling
like no one even sees you is horrendous so yeah i make a conscious effort you know to make sure i'm
in our production office now lots of presenters might not ever go in there but it's about going
around and talking to each person and finding out a little bit about their lives and their families
and you know i remember doing a big um like a big weekend up at the farm we had 110 from better
homes and it was just fascinating watching other people look at other people and go oh she's got
six kids now i know why she tries to get out the door at 4 30 in the afternoon you know like she's
she starts earlier but she she's getting out the door because she actually wants to be present
and this is well before covid where that was even something that was even considered so again it's
about humanizing all those people around you so that you have a greater understanding of what
makes them tick there are going to be some people who have severe anxiety or there's going to be
some people who you know i hate walking in front of a room full of people i don't know
um you've got to let all those people still be heard and be seen every time we come together
we talk about winning the gold medal and i think not manifesting it but having that as a clear
vision and then what we have to do to achieve that i think we're in a really good space on the
basketball court but just keeping that culture and that connection going and enabling and empowering
everyone else in the team to be able to share their vision and and what they want the paris
olympics to be like and where they want the team to go i think is really important so as much as
you know sandy and i can say our vision is to win a gold medal we need to make sure everyone's
aligned with that and everyone's idea on how we do that could be a really important thing to do
be different and making sure we try and incorporate everyone's ideas when you're leading a national
team everyone is a leader so just trying to empower that um and so everyone can show up as
their best most authentic self every day is probably a dream vision of any leader um and i
think by doing that ultimately you will have success sign me up tess i mean you've got me
going uh on that it sounds like a great culture you've got and sandy's such a legend as well and
have great people and lauren jackson at 43
you can picture it something special uh about to happen curiosity is a word that we use and hear a
lot of and through being curious we see people are constantly trying to learn and develop is
curiosity something that resonates with you a hundred percent but before i started a leader
i thought like i wasn't very curious and i thought i was like really set in my ways and
i can be like that for sure but i think just by always trying to be the best version of myself
trying to patty crips we had to say nice
about each other the other day and patty said that i exhaust myself trying to always better
myself and i was like oh that's really really true but i think that is being curious just
always trying to push the boundaries push myself you know ask for help ask people what they think
i didn't really realize till i started a leader that that is being curious and
probably i thought that was my weakest thing as a leader but it probably is my biggest strength so
just knowing all that now is is massive and i wouldn't have had that if i didn't have that
opportunity if it wasn't for a leader and you find that reinforcing when you've got people
who've achieved a lot that are in your corner say hey tess we see you as this great athlete and this
great leader and has that been beneficial for you yeah it was a beautiful thing we did the other
week i'm a crier like i've had some tears during this but um on a leader i probably cried four
times like i find it really hard to express that i'm proud of myself so whenever i do that i just
tend to cry so when we were yeah the new thing
a leader is that i think after the eight week block now everyone in the group goes around and
says how they've impacted um each other but we we were at our 12 month mark the other day and we did
that exercise and i was crying oh stop please and stace um who's our facilitator she's amazing
daily was like stace we need to give you a compliment and she's like no no but she said
like we do this because it is lonely being up the top and it's really nice to hear positive
things about yourself so that was amazing
i really love that exercise and i'll definitely be um taking it into the opals so look out guys
i'm coming for you yeah brilliant answer and i love that idea is that not asking someone to do
something you wouldn't do yourself and we see people like you have had great success and really
conscious how they positively impact other people every day in their environment you're about to go
into a paris olympic games how do you think about positively impacting others oh great question i
think for a memory from my tokyo olympics was rowey webbs who the captain of the sting
is a water polo team just how positive she was around the village and she made everyone feel
like they belong the olympics is quite overwhelming you're rubbing shoulders with the best of the best
athletes in the world and you can get a bit of imposter syndrome but having someone like that
around who was so evanescent and vivacious and bubbly and willing to go the extra mile to make
every single member of that olympic team feel included um i really hope to do that um at paris
huge thank you to all the guests featured on this episode zoe kallar
valerie condos
whipper
joanna griggs
tess madgen
big thank you to all of them and you can find the links to the full length in-depth conversations i
have with each of them in the show notes in our next and final success leads clues episode will
feature the brilliant and sometimes surprising answers our guests gave when i asked them who
was the greatest leader in their life if you enjoy listening to the empowering leaders podcast be
sure to subscribe and please if you have a moment i'd love you to leave a review so we can reach
more listeners and empower more leaders