What a great privilege it's been sitting across from different leaders and different backgrounds
throughout this year and each leadership story for me is so unique with so much wisdom in it.
At Alita we know that there are consistent dimensions of what great leadership looks like
and we'll cover them over the next seven episodes. Really keen to start with the idea of self
leadership because we understand that it's difficult to lead well unless you've got a
great sense of what your own self-leadership means to you and how to lead yourself well.
On every Empowering Leaders episode we hear from people at the top of their industry from sport
to business, education, social venture and the arts and when it comes to the dimension of
self-leadership we knew we were sitting on a goldmine of wisdom from the selection of guests
you're about to hear from. Starting with Danielle Laidley whose journey to understand herself
for me is just about the most remarkable one I've ever heard in my life.
I get this from my
from my son he said to me there's only one person that can can do this and that's you
and you need to be you and you need to be strong and you need to live your life and and by doing
that people will see you how I see you with the platforms we've had through the book and the
documentary your your leadership or your role modeling will be just you living as you and
and showing people that you can get through that you you can be honest and can be raw and can be
vulnerable which I think does in in society these days that attracts people. I know now by me being
me I didn't ever think it would end up like this I was just me wanting to be me living my life
and I've sort of been anointed as a transgender community role model and that and that's the
first I was a bit oh I don't know about that you know because generally we know in any any change or
any sort of leadership the first person who walks through the door usually cops one on the beak
and if that has to be me um that's me um but but I'll do it my own way you know and when we're
talking about this self self-leadership by living my life and by having the platforms which I'm I'm
very lucky to have that people can do it their own way and I'm very lucky to have that people can
people people can't be what they can't see and that was certainly me growing growing up Donna and
I both literally get hundreds of messages a day and particularly over the last month with the doco
parents grandparents um transgender people themselves saying thank you for what you're
doing and we're just living our life but we're living in a way that people see part of our life
in in public and that gives great reason for
families of transgender people um or transgender people themselves to be able to be authentic and
be themselves present their best possible self and I think that's all that I'm doing
Tim Jarvis is an explorer environmental scientist author and leadership expert and he's a winner of
the Australian Geographic Society's Conservationist of the Year Award he's taken on some extraordinary
challenges including re-enacting two of the harshest most extreme Antarctic
survival journeys well I think about my own motivations I think about being true to myself
and what my moral compass looks like but I also have a sense of humility it's interesting I was
having a very interesting conversation the other day with some sports psychologists and they were
talking about the difference between the psychology of leadership in a team sport context where you're
up against human opposition and leadership in the context of say the mountains or Antarctica or the
ocean
and at the end of the day the difference is that one involves working up against human opposition
whereas in the outdoors it's just you and what you can bring and nature is the thing you're
not up against but you're working with I suppose and that brings about a real sense of humility
you don't take seriously the things you've achieved before your CV of previous accomplishments
doesn't mean anything to nature so I bring that humility to each situation I find myself in and I
think that's an essential part of how I deal with it it's important everybody meets to be honest
don't take myself very seriously take what I do seriously when I'm there I think that's a very
important very important aspect to it all and I understand my own limitations and weaknesses
enough to sort of recruit the right people to help fill those gaps and make up shortfalls in that
area and I think being honest with yourself and honest with others about your weaknesses also
engenders a sense of sort of tragedy and I think that's a very important aspect to it and I think that's
trust and respect amongst your team.
Fleur McIntyre is the former head of exercise and sports science
at the University of Notre Dame in Australia.
But she's now breaking new ground for female coaches
after leading the Sydney Kings to back-to-back championships
in just her first two seasons as their assistant coach.
I think the capacity to reflect and seek feedback
on the things that you're doing.
I'm really lucky that I'm always seeking.
I have an idea in my head and I reflect,
but it's nice to get that feedback from people
that are watching me coach, understanding from the players
the things that they need.
And as I keep evolving and growing, things that I could perhaps
do better on this leadership journey and things where I'm strong
but there's the capacity for me to grow.
So the self-leadership for me is obviously looking internally
and being able to reflect, but I also seek opinions
from people that are important to me.
So Luke and our new coach, Mahmood, my peers, Daniel Kickett,
that I get to coach with, I want their feedback on things
that they think I'm doing well and things that I can prove
and also the players that I'm working with.
So self-leadership for me is taking on some ownership
of looking at yourself and attempting to grow,
not just staying stationary where you are,
always being willing to move forward, change things up,
show some initiative, innovation and go from there.
Nick Stone is a former Australian rules footballer
and manager of the Australian Football League.
He's now the founder and CEO of Blue Stone Lane,
a truly awesome international hospitality success story.
After opening his first Blue Stone Lane coffee shop
in midtown Manhattan, they've now expanded
to more than 60 stores across the US.
I think you just need to know who you are and what motivates you
and what you're passionate about, what your values are.
And I think when you're comfortable with yourself,
you're going to be comfortable with others.
And you'll also be a much more,
impactful leader because you'll be your authentic self.
And I think you can present with that vulnerability
that you don't have all the answers,
that you're using these signals to form a view
and that you're open to feedback on certain things
and maybe others that you've got a really strong view
that like, I appreciate your comments,
but like, I'm going this way.
And that's that self-confidence and surety that you need.
And I think doing that investment,
and for me, I didn't do that investment enough
when I was playing AFL.
I hid my emotions.
I hid the way I was feeling.
And when my AFL career finished,
it was liberating that it was over.
I was deeply sad that I probably didn't achieve my childhood dreams,
but it was liberating that I could probably be myself a bit more
and attack my next career with more reckless abandon,
with just confidence and to go for it.
I found that it's hard when you do a lot of self-assessment
and especially as a CEO,
but it takes a lot to make yourself,
that vulnerable to take it on and to change.
And everyone, I found that I can change
and sometimes we'll slip back and you need that reminder.
And I'm very fortunate that both my family support network,
both at home here,
but also in the business with my brother working there
can always give me the tap on the shoulder and say,
listen, I think you could handle that a little bit differently.
I appreciate that what you're trying to say,
but the way that you articulate it
might not be as impactful for someone else.
And,
you know,
that's something that I think we're probably,
everyone's on a journey and it's always evolving
because communication styles have changed so dramatically
with technology and social media
and the way that people process information
and how they receive information.
Coming up,
you're about to hear from Liz Ellis,
Jason Kimberley,
Larry Kesselman,
Kemi Nekvapel
and Sandy Brondello.
So far,
it's been great hearing from Danny,
Tim,
Fleur and Nick.
And I love their conviction around authenticity being true.
To yourself
and also not taking yourself too seriously
at the same time,
having the humility to self-reflect and self-connect
and to always be able to come back
to where you're comfortable with yourself
and align with your values.
I know I learned something from each and every one of them.
At Alita,
we bring together groups of five to six people
and a lot of them you've heard from just now
in these collaborative groups
where we know leadership at times is lonely.
The idea of learning and sharing and collaborating
is something we're incredibly passionate about.
Love you.
We'd love for you to get involved as well.
Check out our website,
alitacollective.com.
Alita connects our signature program,
Hooker Discovery Call
and we'd love to chat to you
about your leadership journey.
I'd like to say a huge thank you to Jason Nicholas
and his team from Temper
for their ongoing support of the Empowering Leaders podcast
and bringing these stories to the table
each and every week.
Temper is a mattress like no other.
Almost all the leaders we talk to
understand the value of great sleep
to live a happy and successful life.
So investing in the world's best embedding
with Temper,
is a decision that will seriously change your life.
Big thanks to Temper,
a mattress like no other.
The next group of guests all speak to how self-leadership
has driven them to the highest level of success.
Let's go first to the inspirational Sandy Brondello,
coach of the New York Liberty in the WNBA.
Well, I think that's the most important thing.
I know people always ask me,
I mean, what kind of leader am I?
Like I talk, I'm a servant leader
because I want to help others
to be the very best that they can be.
But self-leadership,
self-leadership is making sure
you're looking yourself in the mirror
and what are my strengths?
What are the areas I need to work on?
How can I impact people's lives?
Because that's what you're doing as a leader
in a positive way.
And that doesn't mean it's always rosy,
but you can still impact people's lives
in a positive way.
And, you know, that self-reflection,
it's always continued to grow,
that self-leadership.
But I always say,
don't be something that you're not
when you take over a leadership role.
Because I tell my players,
you will see consistency out of me every day.
Win, lose, whatever.
Because that's a part of the journey.
And I want them to make sure
we're in this journey together.
And if we can stay together,
great things can happen.
Jason Kimberley is a world traveler and adventurer
whose eclectic life experiences
led him to publishing two books
and becoming the founder and CEO of Cool.org.
The free online platform
has supported more than 175,000 educators
in building a greater understanding
of critical environmental and social issues.
I don't know anything else.
You know, I don't have gears.
I once heard Mick Molloy comment on his acting
and said it's 5% either way of Mick Molloy.
You know, so I think whatever I do
is 5% either way of Jason Kimberley.
You know, a few mates of mine
have got fairly high profile public lives.
And when they said to me early on,
when they were sort of diving into it,
you know, you've got the thing,
I said, just be yourself.
I said, the sooner you can be yourself in your job,
don't be what anyone,
what you think anyone wants you to be,
be yourself.
And the sooner you can,
be yourself in life.
Some people die without being themselves.
They're always trying to please other people
or whatever it is.
But I think I worked it out in the early 20s
that the quicker you can be yourself,
and I mean legitimately yourself,
not holding back,
not putting on something false that's not you.
And I sometimes get into trouble.
It can be a bit tricky.
Let's be clear.
But if you're not your true self,
who the hell are you?
You're poncing around,
trying to impress people that you don't like,
you know, to care about you.
You know, so I just think
my advice on leadership is
absolutely,
be you and whatever that is.
And it's difficult to be yourself.
That to me is critical in leadership.
And the sooner you can do that,
it's that.
And the other thing I would say,
that is not caring what other people think.
I know that's a trite thing to say,
but it's none of my business
what people think of me.
You know, I get the odd secondhand story
and they're usually wildly inaccurate.
My reputation exceeds me, Dars.
But if you can legitimately not care
about what other people think,
coupled with being yourself,
I think that,
to me, it's the secret to success.
Liz Ellis is one of the most respected names
in Australian sport.
She's a lawyer by trade,
arguably Australia's best ever netball player,
an experienced broadcaster
and the most recent winner
of Australia's
I'm a Celebrity, Get Me Out of Here.
It means a couple of things.
That means I reflect on my behaviour often.
I think self-reflection is really important.
And when I was in a team
and a leader within the team,
I'd often reflect on conversations that I'd had
or things that went,
went wrong or went right in the game.
What was my role?
How could I do that better?
And I've always been a bit harsh on myself
in that regard,
because I think that's like,
you've got to be honest with yourself.
And if that means being hard,
then so be it.
Sometimes I think my self-talk could be better.
But the last thing I,
and the world needs is me with a bigger ego.
So, you know,
but I do engage in a lot of self-reflection
just at home or, you know,
when I'm on the plane or driving somewhere.
A lot of people who are successful do that
because, you know,
one of the great things that sport teaches,
you know,
is you can blame the umpire,
but then you lose control of changing anything.
So actually look at yourself first.
So that's where I started with self-reflection.
And I'm really careful about,
I don't know that you can achieve balance
because you always have crazy moments,
but I'm really careful about having nice things
to look forward to, right?
Because that makes you a better leader
because you're more centered.
You're able to focus on the moment
because you know something good's coming,
which drives Matthew insane
because I'm always wanting to book holidays.
But like, it's just about looking after yourself
and,
and allowing yourself to be in a happy place
because you've got a few other things under control.
And the big thing I've learned,
especially since having kids is the power of saying no.
I used to think I had to say yes to everything,
especially when I left the law firm and went freelance.
I was like, oh my God,
this job could be my last,
but I've survived,
I don't know,
25 years doing that.
So now I understand that I can say no,
especially if it doesn't suit what I'm doing with my family.
And that makes me a better leader
because when I'm there or wherever I am,
I'm actually really invested in it
because I know that I've given myself space
to be with my family
and to do the things that I like to do.
Larry Kesselman sold Dodo,
the telecommunications business he founded,
for close to $250 million back in 2013
with a unique ability to turn his attention
to a diverse range of industries and passions.
With remarkable consistent success,
he's now a billionaire property developer
and owner of the National Basketball League in Australia.
I think it's being able
to control your emotions.
It's being able to have your own conversations
and being honest with yourself.
I think if you're living a lie
and you're not actually honest where you're at,
that is a problem.
You've got to start there.
I think if you stop being a keen learner,
I think that's a problem.
How do I lead others?
And the longer I lead others,
the smarter they are around me.
Like the people that are coming into my world now
are bloody smart people.
So if I don't keep improving myself
and keep learning,
that's a problem.
So,
I think that concept of
the way the Western world has decided
that you get some sort of a certificate after school
and college,
you're done with studying
is a very dangerous one.
So,
for me as a leader,
I want people that are keen learners,
that are open to learning,
that are self-critical,
that are positive,
but at the same time,
realize that you never stop learning
and it's a journey.
So,
my leadership style
is to care about others
and their evolution
and how can I help them.
So,
the older I get,
and I'm an operator by nature,
but the older I get,
the less I'm actually running
and operating businesses.
So,
more and more,
my job is strategy
and how do I actually set people up for success
and mentor them
and help them
and not just around business,
but actually just help them
be the best version of themselves.
They'll need to do what they need to do,
but my job is to help them
find that happiness.
Kemi Nekvipil
trained under Dr. Brené Brown
and is one of Australia's
leading credentialed coaches
for female and male coaches.
She's also an author
and a highly sought-after
international speaker.
Oh, 100%.
And I think the beautiful thing about that is,
and this is the work.
We think that work is this thing outside of us
that we, you know,
get in the car to get to or something,
but actually the ultimate work
is the work on self.
And so,
we all want to follow leaders
who are self-aware
of how they impact the people around them.
We want to be around leaders
that can identify the humanity in us
because they can identify
the humanity in themselves.
And I've literally just come off the back
of doing a Dare to Lead retreat yesterday.
And, you know,
that is the context of the work.
And Brené Brown says this,
self-awareness matters.
That so many things happen
in organizations within leadership
because we're just not aware
of what we're doing.
We don't know that we made
that offhand comment
that actually made, you know,
one of our team members
kind of really off
for the rest of the day
or made them feel like they could,
they weren't capable at their job.
And we don't have
the tool to then go back in
and just check in and say,
hey, did I make that comment I made?
Did that kind of put you
offside a little bit?
Because I'd like to know
because I don't want you to feel like
you didn't do a great job on the project.
I just want to redefine
what the project was meant to be
or something.
I know that leaders should always
be doing work on themselves
so they can show up as for humans
because we want to be led by humans.
Yeah, that's great insight into that.
And I was looking at your
Dare to Lead retreats.
They look brilliant,
but it's something you do.
You bring groups of people together,
you know, eight to 10 to 12.
Is that right?
Does it spend that reflective time?
Yeah, that's right.
So, you know, very blessed
to go and train with Renee in Texas.
And as a coach,
I can now sort of add that tool set
of the Dare to Lead program
and kind of it's her IP,
but I get to facilitate the content.
These actual retreats are for women.
I do actually do one-to-one coaching
with a few good men.
I have to let you know that, Luke,
like not exclusively women.
I birthed a man and I'm married to a man.
So that all works
because I love to bring together
women of various ages
in different industries.
But I remember thinking
at the beginning,
oh, I'll do a Dare to Lead retreat
for entrepreneurs
and I'll do a Dare to Lead retreat
for people in organizations
and corporates.
And then I realized,
why would you do that?
You want to bring together
these two different styles of working
so there can be this beautiful osmosis
and people understanding
how it is in each other people's camp.
And even, you know,
everyone always says
one of the most powerful things
about having groups of people together
where they feel safe
is that you get to hear
that what you're going through
is not a solo experience,
that someone's either been there before
or they're in the middle of it.
So it's not a solo experience.
It's not a solo experience.
They're either in the middle of it
or they're on the other side of it.
And that gives you
a really good grounding
in your leadership
and your style of leadership
moving forward.
I genuinely love the idea
and the reflection of self-awareness
as a start,
that it really is genuinely
the place to start
to know yourself
and understand what enables you
to be the best of yourself.
And hearing those voices again,
so much self-awareness,
so much self-reflection
and being honest with yourself
and the idea of constant
and never-ending self-improvement.
You could see the patterns
that you're going through
and the patterns that you're going through
even though they're
from different backgrounds
around routine,
around that discipline,
around the idea
of potentially delaying
some gratification
to have a better life.
And I heard that
in so many different ways
that people show up for themselves.
There's freedom in the routine
of what makes people successful
and I loved listening to it
in a range of different ways.
I hope you enjoyed it
as much as I did.
You can find the links
to the full-length episodes,
in-depth conversations
I've had with each of them
in the show notes
on our next dimension
of leadership episode.
We'll put together
the tips and strategies
told to us by leaders
across the globe
on how they positively impact
the people around them
every single day.
If you enjoy listening
to Empowering Leaders podcast,
it would be fantastic
to have you subscribe.
So please do that now.
If you have a moment,
leave a review for us
so we can reach more listeners
and hopefully empower more people
to live the best version
of their lives themselves.
Thank you for listening
to the Empowering Leaders podcast
powered by Temper,
a mattress like no other.
And to make sure
you don't miss an episode,
click subscribe
wherever you get your podcast.