Hello and welcome to a special edition of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Jeff Scott is the Vice President of Football Operations for the Philadelphia Eagles in the NFL.
And Jeff has been kind enough to join me only a couple of days out from Super Bowl 59 in New Orleans,
where Jeff's team, the Philadelphia Eagles, take on the Kansas City Chiefs
in what is the biggest one-day sporting event on the planet.
First, I'd like to say thank you to our presenting partner, Victoria University,
who are committed to creating a place where everyone feels they belong,
opening doors to education for everyone.
V, you are here to support and empower you on your journey,
whether you're taking your first step towards a dream,
breaking new ground in your industry with further learning,
or simply chasing your next win.
And that is not unlike what Jeff Scott is planning to do in winning Super Bowl 59.
Hey, Jeff, thank you so much. I know your time is precious.
Tell us about the week as Vice President of Football Operations.
How's it been for you?
Uh, first off, thank you, Luke. Thank you for having me.
I'm happy to be here and do this.
The week has been, you know, for us, it's been good.
I think this is a situation we're trying to approach it just like any other week.
Of course, we all understand that it isn't, but I think in anything you do,
and from top down in our organization, we really approach it as,
it's got to be normal process.
You have to repeat the process we've been doing all season and,
and come down to Sunday and focus on what we've got to do.
Jeff, only two years ago, Super Bowl 57,
the same opponent, the Kansas City Chiefs.
From an outsider's point of view, there's a great redemption story.
Is that the language you use?
Or as you said, is it just about getting the job done?
I think for us, the focus is really just going through our process and,
and focusing on what we're doing.
Yeah.
And what, what we need to handle, control what we can control and,
and go forward with that.
I think, you know, obviously there are a lot of narratives and,
and things that can be out there, but that's not something we do.
We specialize in just doing what we need to do internally,
focus on ourselves and, and go out there and handle our business.
Jeff, you're an outstanding quarterback in high school and college yourself
before a back injury ended perhaps the dream
of being a professional athlete.
Have you found that football experience has helped you in your role now?
Yeah, I, I actually, um, it's funny, I played quarterback in high school and
then, um, I started as a quarterback in college, but I quickly moved over
to, uh, the defensive side of the ball.
I'm only five foot eight.
Uh, so sometimes seeing over the line was a, uh, little issue.
Now, nowadays, uh, that's not as big of an issue with the offenses that are run, but,
um, I played.
I played defense in college.
I really think what happened for me is I got injured, um, and, and had that back injury
and my court and defensive coordinator position coach, uh, me, Clint Daniel, he
actually trained me to be a coach.
Um, I was kind of the, the veteran guy in the room.
So I spent a lot of time with him learning how to evaluate things, how to look at the
game from a different lens than you do as a player.
And that definitely set the foundation for me going forward, um, through, through to
this point in my career.
So, um, it's one of those things that, uh, one door closes and, and the injury was, you
know, was something that, you know, it happens.
It's the nature of our game, but, uh, it really opened the door for me, uh, down the
line.
I never knew that it would get here, but that definitely, uh, set the foundation for me.
So I thought we'll hear that a lot.
On this podcast where something at the time that seems like a devastation, a career ending
injury, but once you get through that and experience it fully on the other side, something
maybe even greater, has that been the case for you in your life when you've had these
hurdles that have come up that when you find a way through, there's always something good?
Yeah, I think one of the things that you have to approach, and this is something that I,
it was instilled in me as a child.
Um, my, my father.
Actually, uh, was legally blind.
Um, he, he could see a little bit, but by definition, he couldn't, um, see completely
enough to ever drive a car or do kind of a lot of different things.
And, and my grandmother told him that doesn't matter.
You have to go through and, and do what you need to do in life.
Um, he eventually became a circuit court judge.
Um, he sat on the bench for years, uh, and I would be amazed.
His, his vision was never a deterrent for him.
Um, his other, uh, senses were heightened, um, which as a child growing up in his household
was, uh, sometimes a little, uh, could catch you a little bit.
His hearing was amazing.
Um, but you know, um, but it's one of those things that you don't, you don't let those
things define you.
That's, that's the reality of things.
Um, I, I got injured.
I actually did.
I came back and played, um, my senior year, but it wasn't.
Obviously it wasn't kind of the same.
Um, but you never let those things define you.
You really just focus on what's next and what do I need to do to overcome whatever hurdles
in your way?
I think those are opportunities more than things to kind of sit back and, and be concerned
about.
Yeah.
You mentioned your dad, Judge John W.
Scott Jr., the first black judge in Fredericksburg where you grew up and he was a civil rights
pioneer.
And as you said, legally.
He was legally blind, all the obstacles in his way.
And your mother, Alda, was Stafford County's first female attorney.
She was also the first black female full-time attorney in Virginia.
Exceptional people on every level.
Can you tell us a bit more about growing up in that household and, and the influence they
had?
Yeah, no, um, it was, it was definitely something you learn to craft an argument, uh, very quickly
in that household.
If you couldn't, uh, you could, if you didn't have something specific.
You know, if you just bevelled out and, uh, kind of flushed out your idea, you, it wasn't
going anywhere.
So I, I learned that very young.
Um, but I think one of the things that, that both of them, uh, instilled in me and my mom
still does to this day is at the end of the day, you just keep pushing.
You keep, keep going.
You always keep going forward.
You never, it's not a time to ever feel sorry for yourself.
Um, you set a goal.
You go forward.
it. If you say you're going to do something, you do it. You stand up for what's right. And that's
kind of some of the foundational principles that have really shaped my life. And hopefully I'm
going forward and passing along to my daughter. Jeff, we've been really privileged to have you
part of our Leader Connect program. We curate groups of five to six different leaders around
the globe from different backgrounds. So you've collaborated with Tom Allen from Arsenal,
Ash Hansen's an Australian footy legend and respected coach, Ben Noor, the legendary
conductor of the Melbourne Symphony Orchestra, Amanda White from the US Tennis Association and
doing great things. You've caught up with Andy Walsh from our community. Can you tell us about
collaborating with leaders around the world in that Leader Connect program, what it's meant for
you? It's been awesome. I was lucky. I was referred to the program from Daryl Franklin,
an old co-worker of mine.
He's in one in a group and obviously Matt LaFleur, who is in a group. So they were lucky enough to
kind of mention me and push me for the program. It's been great. It's something I've really
enjoyed. I think my group is fun. We've been together at this point. It feels like it's been
it's a little, it's almost two years at this point, but it's been great.
I think you talk about everybody's background being so different. Amanda, Amanda, you talk about
collaboration. Her entire job is kind of dependent on working with a million different people and
helping bring something together, which is huge. Ben is, I never knew that you could learn so much
from someone in a field that's so different. When he's talking about conducting and dealing with
musicians, it's really the same kind of business we are dealing with athletes. And Ben has such
great perspectives on things. Ash, I love talking to Ash. Ash is so good at being able to motivate
and kind of bring a perspective of how, you know, how you're going to be able to do something. And
I think, you know, he coaches and he's so aware, self-aware and aware of situations that he's been
a part of. And then Tom, I laugh. I think Tom is just, Tom's a machine. He, that Arsenal program
is, you know, obviously I watched the all or nothing and I've kind of gotten into more soccer
than I ever had before. But Tom's always about process.
And putting things together and new ideas and just being able to share with that group and
share in successes, share in challenges, hear perspectives of people who are doing things that
are very similar that on the face, like at the end of the day, what we're doing is very similar,
but on the face of it, it's probably nobody would make those connections. And it's been
great for me to,
self-reflect and analyze and go forward. So I've been very happy to be in the program.
Yeah, Jeff, it's a wonderful description of what we see is this great coming together when
inspiring people catch up and learn. And you just delved into that your reflections so easily. Is
that sort of curiosity part of you always searching to find a way to do things better in
life? Is that seems like something that's a real passion of yours?
Yeah, no, I think the
biggest thing we like anybody who's in a leadership position or, you know, wants to be in a
leadership position, you need to constantly kind of be on the forefront of things. I joke, you know,
I've been lucky enough here with the Eagles organization from top down for Mr. Lurie, our
general manager, Holly Roseman. He is all about pushing the envelope and going forward and trying
to find the next and stay out in front of the next. And you know, I think that's, I think that's
of things. And he's been amazing at it. It's been awesome to kind of spend the last four years here
learning from him and really pushing to kind of go the next, let's find what the next thing is,
kind of never being satisfied. And I think curiosity is in us all. It's just sometimes,
you know, you have to push yourself, you know, that's what being a leader is. And I think that
is something that I really strive to do. So have you spent three years with the Bank of America
in a global risk management role back in another lifetime? Your experience in the
corporate world, has that held you in good stead as a sporting exec?
Yeah, I actually, it was an amazing experience. It's something I wouldn't trade for the world.
You know, I started in June of 2008. And then we had the
the
, basically, the economy had the downturn it had that fall. And it was, while it was a very
tough time, again, it was an opportunity. It was something to learn. It was being thrust into
situations that, you know, nobody had dealt with and being able to react and move and think on your
feet. That was awesome. I joke all the time about one of the toughest conversations I ever had.
I did a year in audit, and I led an audit on a subsidiary of Merrill Lynch, when Bank of America
Purpose bought Merrill Lynch. And I had to sit down with the chief credit officer and go through
audit issues. And he was, you know, he had been doing it as long as I had been alive at that
point. But those are tough conversations that we all have to go through. So when I got, you know,
on this end, I joked,
some of the tough conversations I've had, I had maybe the toughest one when I was 22 years old.
So it's great experience, really, really challenged me, just but at the end of the day,
I love football. Football had been a part of my life since I was five years old, and I wanted to
get back to it. So Bank of America, it was a was a great opportunity. But I just I really wanted to
get back into football. Jeff, I hear you've got a great passion for developing people and
the players in your environment at the Eagles. Can you tell us a bit about your philosophy on how
you you develop people to be their best? I think one of the biggest things that a lot of times we
forget is, this is a people business. At the end of the day, you know, ownership, people, coaches,
players, people, front office, you know, support staff, people, fans are people. We're in a people
business. And in order to get the best out of people, I believe you need to build relationships,
need to build equity, and people need to understand that you're invested. I think you
always can get the best out of someone when they feel you're invested in them. I joke a lot of times
that people confuse two words that are usually used interchangeably, as far as people talk about
managing and people talk about leading. Well, you manage a process, you manage a project,
you lead people, you try to influence and inspire people, motivate people,
and I think that's something that for me, at the end of the day, is my focus. If I'm dealing with
players, if I'm dealing with other staff, the people who have been invested in my career
have always made me be the best I am. So I try to be invested in others.
We all are born different. As we grow, the experiences we have develop into outlooks
uniquely our own.
Charting our life's course. No one sees an idea, opinion, or opportunity like you.
And no one sees you like VU, Victoria University. Uniquely you.
My name's Yanni, and I study a Bachelor of Sports and Exercise Science at VU. I come from a very
family-oriented, Greek culture. Comin' to VU I feel like I'm getting the same sort of community vibe,
After high school, I went straight into the workforce and I did this for about four years,
but then I felt like I want to follow my passion, which is sport.
VU is ranked number seven in the world for sport and exercise science.
So it was a no brainer for me.
And Jeff, I hear about a legendary work ethic that you've got and that comes with a bit
of cost.
I read, you know, for eight months of the year, every meal of the day is at work because
you have breakfast, lunch and dinner and you work through that, as you said, as a husband
and a father to your beautiful daughter.
How do you balance that work life balance?
I think it's obviously it's a challenge to balance for any of us.
I think any professionals have work constraints and balancing that with your family life is
hard.
But I do think, again, we approach.
As a family, as an opportunity, my wife and daughter are going to come down here and go
to the Super Bowl.
Like that's a that's an amazing experience that you probably just don't get.
So we try to lean into the experiences that you do get rather than focus on the time that
you don't have.
It requires a lot of work.
I think everybody, again, any professional who's, you know, kind of climbing the ladder
and going where they want to go, it's going to take work.
I've never been afraid of that.
My wife sometimes reminds me of that when we do have, you know, our break after in the
summer that she's like, you're not working like let's focus on other things.
But it's again, it's an opportunity.
My daughter comes down on the field pregame of every game.
I joke that she just thinks this is normal.
So, you know.
Those are the things that you get out of it.
And you try to focus on those positives that you get rather than focus on what you miss.
I also I couldn't do it without my wife.
My wife is the head of the head of the household.
She keeps things running.
She has a career in her own right.
And she's a former athlete as well.
So we we can definitely vibe on on that space.
But it's she.
She does a great job of keeping me grounded, keeping me focused and kind of keeping me locked in and allowing me to when it's time to go to work like to go.
We're literally heading towards 48 hours out from Super Bowl 59 in New Orleans.
Your opponents are chasing a three-peat, something that has never been done in the in the Super Bowl era.
Patrick Mahomes is going to be a legend of the sport.
They're quarterback.
You've got the Travis.
Kelsey Taylor Swift Super Bowl extravaganza happening again.
You can't imagine more global interest in this event.
It's the biggest event.
Anyway, does it feel that way to you that this is maybe bigger than it's ever been this Super Bowl?
I think it again, the biggest focus for us is really trying to just keep the same process.
Of course, everybody understands what it is.
This is a it's a big moment.
And a big opportunity.
But again, the focus is on keeping things consistent and just kind of focusing in.
It's a game just like the last game we played, you know, and at the end of the day, you're still going to roll out and play football.
And that's what we've got to do.
So I'm curious, just as we are so close from such an event and you keep talking about the process, but just to go into a little bit of detail, players are still going to have their tickets.
They've got to have their accommodation.
You're living away from home.
Their families are in town and they've got to be accommodated.
Their meal preparation's got to be the same.
I can only imagine the logistics that are on your schedule are enormous.
Can you tell us about the sort of detail that you need to get right in the next couple of days?
I really think like organizationally, we've done an amazing job.
This, we have some of the best people in the world who are, have set things up and make it so that.
Players and coaches can focus on what they need to do.
I think that's all a part of this is really the biggest focus of anyone is to make it so that the players and coaches can really just lock in on what they need to do.
So we have an amazing staff who's helped with tickets and dealing with friends and family issues.
You know, our nutrition staff who's helping you get all the meals are training staff.
Who's.
Who's keeping things as, as normal as possible to make sure guys are, you know, have whatever they need to be able to get ready.
It's a, it's a big undertaking, but I think that's part of what you understand and being in a, in a really top down, excellent organization is that everybody has to work together.
Everybody has to be on the same page.
And at the end of the day, if we all do our jobs, then it can make it as easy as possible for the.
The rest of the group to function, normal and normal process.
I have to ask you about a giant Australian from Western Sydney and three centimeters, six foot eight in the old 166 kilos or 365 pounds, a giant of a man.
Jordan Maylato is hoping to make some history from an Australian perspective.
Tell us about him as a character and a teammate and how big a role has he got to play?
Jordan is an.
Unbelievable human being.
We joke about it, that he, he's enormous.
He's athletic.
He can sing.
He's a great, like just personality.
Jordan really has really been a huge bright spot for us.
And it's, I know, obviously him being from Australia.
That's a, that's a big thing.
Matt, Matt jokes about it, uh, with me, uh, but he is an awesome player.
Um, he's an awesome leader, but he's an awesome person.
Um, and I think he's done a very good job this year of really stepping in and being a heck of a leader for us.
Um, so we're excited.
Um, and I think, you know, if he does, you know, what he's been doing all year, we'll be in a great shape.
I know you're focused on the detail, but yeah, obviously.
And what wonders too, it's great success of what it could mean.
And can you give us an insight into how special, you know, that would be for, for not only you, but the wider team and the wider community that support the Eagles?
Yeah, I think, uh, we all, you know, everybody who gets in this business, you're not getting in it to not win a soup.
Like that's the goal of everybody.
Um, it's the ultimate goal, but at the end, again, we try to go piece by piece and focus on today.
It's the ultimate goal, but at the end, you know, we try to go piece by piece and focus on today.
Rather than, you know, looking so far ahead, but, um, it's, it's amazing.
Uh, the opportunity, um, we have in front of us is, is awesome.
And it would mean a heck of a lot to everybody in here.
It would mean a heck of a lot to all of our fans.
Um, like I said, our coaches, our executives, our support staff, our players ownership.
Uh, it's, it's a heck of an accomplishment and it's something that's not promised.
it's you know very hard to to get to this moment and it would definitely mean a lot but again the
the it's great to look at that but you know the focus is just kind of keeping it normal
and not thinking about what's coming next but thinking about what's right in front of you
Jeff you've got a great reputation as a leader of people and a great connector of people in
everything you do and it's been great to spend some time with you and in the week that is Super
Bowl 59 in your role it's incredibly generous for you to take some time final question to you
who's been the greatest leader in your life? Luke obviously you know I've listened to the
podcast a little bit so I knew this one was coming and I mentioned my father earlier
I think he's one that was so influential to me
and one of the things that I'll never forget you know people said my father passed when I was in
college and people talked about him being able to walk with kings but keep the common touch
and my father always listened he was all he was as cerebral as he could possibly be which
sometimes would frustrate people when you know they're trying to go back and forth with him
but he listened he was
cerebral he was measured and it's something that I strive to do when I when I'm approached with
anything I really want to listen I think the best leaders and listen at the end of the day you can't
fix a problem that you don't know is there so you have to listen to people to be able to understand
what problems are are on the horizon being cerebral is you know a skill we are in a high pressure
environment I think you know a lot of people in sport are and you have to kind of never get too
high never get too low um so just seeing those things and growing up around that has been awesome
for me um I reflect on it all the time I try my best to uh emulate him I I I'm not as cerebral as
he is I'm probably a little bit more fiery but um I try my best and it's something that has really
meant a lot to me um as far as you know my football career I think you know here I I spoke about him
earlier Howie Roseman is a an unbelievable unbelievable general manager um he consistently
is on the forefront of things pushing us kind of never being complacent one um a guy who's not
afraid to go outside of his comfort zone and and find the answers wherever they may be
we have people from you know from Wall Street to Broadway who are all um in our staff and
those differing opinions and differing backgrounds all really help us kind of to
move forward so um learning from him and him being a leader for us here uh early in my career
Mike Shanahan really was an unbelievable leader he he set the tone for you know for my career
we uh obviously you know you've had Matt on the podcast before and we were in Washington together
and I know Sean's in a group uh as well Sean McVay so we were all in Washington together and
and Coach Shanahan really set the course and kind of set the tone um early in my career about how
to approach things how to work um really how to focus in uh and he was so like he was really
really good to his players and he was really good to his players and he was really good to his
people um and that's something that's never left me so for me that's something that I try to focus
on because again it's a people business you can never forget that you have to build relationships
you have to people have to think you're invested in them um to get the best out of them so um
those would be probably the I know I said three but that's probably where I'd go
well Jeff I think people get a great insight into how well placed the Eagles are heading into
the biggest event in the world and I think that's a really good point
I think that's a really good point
as we've described many times having your steady hand and your relationships and the way you
connect with people is uh is a great template for the team this weekend we wish you all the best
thank you it's been a great pleasure to spend some time with you Jeff and thanks so much for
sharing some of your wisdom thank you thank you I appreciate it