Susan McLean is Australia's foremost expert in the area of cyber safety.
Formerly a Victoria police officer for 27 years,
Susan took her first report of cyberbullying
involving a group of Year 8 schoolgirls back in 1994.
She's internationally respected for her research and expertise
and in Australia speaks to more than 250,000 students
in 300 schools each year.
Susan's passion is to educate young people and parents
about the realities of the online world
so they can minimise risk to the point
where it doesn't have to be a dangerous place.
Susan, good to see you again.
Thanks for your time.
Thanks very much for having me.
I feel we need to start.
This has been recorded a few days after a horrific police tragedy
in Queensland and your community has had, you know,
an act of complete terrorism effectively perpetrated against them.
You know, we're feeling for you.
I think it's moments like these that we really do understand
the dangers of policing.
It must be a terrible time for you and your community.
It is and, you know, I'm a former police officer now
but once you wear the blue, you're always part of that police family
and it does hit hard and especially a job like these members were sent to
because we've all done them.
Like, this wasn't a unique situation.
It wasn't out of the blue.
It wasn't an odd job.
It was a very common job and there would hardly be a police officer
anywhere in Australia that has not done a wellbeing
and missing persons check.
And a young female officer, you know,
eight weeks out of the academy, ambushed and murdered.
It's just a terrible story.
Yeah, it defies any sort of ability to comprehend the harm, the anger.
You know, it wasn't just an unfortunate situation.
They were murdered and they were butchered and executed
and you can't say it in a polite way.
And, you know, there are more good people in the world than bad
but, my God, it was a tough time.
It was a tough day.
Yeah, Susan, I hope, you know, we're all genuinely feeling
and respectful for what the police community do
and didn't feel like we could start without that.
It is a big change of gear to move on to the world
that has become your world.
And my sense is that as parents, trying to get our kids off their screens,
social media, the internet, whatever it is,
and we know it's the world we live in now,
but, Susan, it's probably the number one thing we talk about as parents.
How do we do all that in a balanced way?
With difficulty.
Like, parenting is a tough gig.
It's the best gig in the world, of course, but it's not easy.
And just when you think you get on top of one thing,
something else comes along.
And screens are a huge issue at the moment.
They are manageable.
The benefits are enormous.
So, you know, we can't demonise it.
But it's always really important to understand that every time your child,
and yourself for that matter, uses technology, there's a risk.
But being able to identify that risk, minimise and manage it,
as you said it,
is the key.
And we want it to be balanced.
Like, we don't want young people to be, or adults,
you know, sitting down with their head in a screen for long periods of time.
There's a whole range of issues for that.
Yeah, and it's interesting you say that, Susan.
I hear that word a lot, and I've been trying to,
in my own parenting world, as you say,
if you demonise it, the kids just look at you like you've got two heads
because it's part of their world and, you know, you get emotional.
And it's an important part of their world.
And you're right.
There's enormous benefit, isn't there?
I love seeing how well they connect
and how well they organise themselves
and how well they communicate.
The best part, if you try to ignore that,
we're not living in the real world either, are we?
No, and we need to, for me, it's about, you know,
focusing on the benefits of technology,
but being mindful of the negatives.
So we don't want the negatives to overtake,
but it requires effort.
It's not going to magically happen.
A lot of parents will say, oh, but my kid is much better than me.
They know it all.
No, no, they don't.
They can use tech better than you,
because I laugh at this concept of tech being intuitive.
It's not intuitive when you're an old person
because you've got to learn it.
And it's like, I don't even understand what I'm doing here.
And you watch a really young person pick up tech
and they know what to do.
They've never had a lesson,
but it is intuitive for young people, not old people.
But what they don't have is that level of brain development.
So we know that that's lacking.
So there's a gap between what they can do
and what they have the capacity to understand.
And that's where parents come in.
You've got to be,
the brain power, not the tech support, the brain power.
Which in reality is what you have to do
in every other area of parenting as well, isn't it?
This one just seems to have a bit more complexity.
Can I talk about some of the numbers?
So the eSafety Commissioner says 44% of Australian young people
report having a negative online experience in the last six months.
So that can be online bullying,
exposure to inappropriate content, harassment, identity theft.
There are a huge range of issues out there to deal with.
There are.
And in my experience,
those numbers are quite low.
I would put it at probably closer to 70%.
Remembering a couple of things.
One, it's only based on reports to the eSafety Commissioner.
So not everything goes there.
And secondly, a lot of times this doesn't get reported anywhere
or it's reported somewhere where it's not captured in statistics.
So suffice to say, it is a huge issue.
It's multifaceted.
There's lots of different things that we need to be aware of.
But again, if we educate ourselves and we get on top of it,
we will be able to do a lot of things.
So that's one of the things that we need to be aware of.
We will reap the rewards.
I was in preparation for this,
so thinking about your world,
and I was watching a little boy walk up my street.
It was probably his last day of school.
He had to be five or six.
And I was watching him on his phone.
And he's head down,
he crossed all the driveways,
crossed a couple of street corners.
And the parenting hat kicks in,
you think he's a huge chance to get collected by.
Miracle that he wasn't.
So I went to the end of my street.
I thought I'm going to walk down and firstly make sure that,
you know,
he's okay.
He would have not even have understood that I was even walking past him.
And I managed to sort of glance at his screen.
He was scrolling through TikTok and you could just see it head down,
not even aware of anything.
No spatial awareness.
No spatial awareness at all.
And I thought,
God,
that algorithm is so sophisticated and so intoxicating for a young kid.
It's very hard to manage,
isn't it?
It is.
And I think the other issue too is what parents see and experience
online is not going to be what their children see and experience because of
the algorithms.
Different stuff is pumped differently to each demographic,
each individual user for that matter.
And,
you know,
it is a concern.
And a lot of parents will say to me,
oh,
their child has to have a phone to keep them safe.
Phones don't keep kids safe.
Perfect example of the fact that that kid could easily have been barreled by a
car that he would not have even seen.
If he's walking along,
scrolling on a phone,
well,
you're setting yourself up to be robbed.
And your phone's stolen.
I think parents need to understand that phones can be handy and they can be
helpful,
but they do not keep children safe.
Far from it.
So the argument,
Susan,
will be in our own household,
it gets to an age where they're catching a train.
We want them to be able to ring in the event something does happen.
So that's when you need a phone because of the circumstances.
A five-year-old is not catching a train to school on their own.
So there's a difference.
And yes,
I always say you start to consider it for high school because they're on public
transport.
After school activities,
sport training,
I've missed the bus,
sport training's been canceled.
Come get me helpful and handy.
But if you think about it this way,
if your child's walking along and you know,
some random bad person is going to grab them,
what are they going to say?
Hang on a minute,
bad person.
Can you wait till I get my safety phone out of my bag and just ring mom before
you attack me?
All right.
It's not going to work that way.
Helpful,
handy.
Absolutely.
Um,
but they're not going to stop things.
And often,
you know,
please understand that when you give,
a device to a child,
you are giving your child to the world and the world to your child,
every single person in it,
all those people you are trying to protect them from use the internet as well.
You just can't see them.
So do you think we look back,
uh,
so,
and I know,
you know,
your view,
as you said,
the start,
we've got to take the good with the bad here.
And your,
your mission is about education so that you can have a positive experience and
on a negative one.
But do you think,
you know,
Apple has become one of the biggest companies in the world and the creation
of the iPhone and Steve Jobs' legacy.
Do you think there'll be a point?
We look back,
and think that may be the great curse of the 21st century.
Look,
I think if you speak to adolescent and child psychologist,
if you speak to many,
you know,
wellbeing coordinators at schools who continually see the negative impact of
tech,
there will be conversations about,
you know,
this generation of young people being Guinea pigs for the future.
If I look at going back to when I took that first report of cyber bullying,
the technology then versus today,
polar opposite,
like in those days,
there were listservs,
bulletin boards and chat rooms.
That was it.
Like there was nothing that we have today.
What we've seen though is yes,
technology has come across in leaps and bounds and for lots of lots of beneficial reasons,
but the safety aspect of it hasn't kept up.
And what I get to see often is a new app gets invented and everyone jumps on board because of whatever reason,
and then safety becomes an afterthought and we've got to switch that thinking to make it,
you know,
safety first,
second and third embedded in the app,
not,
you know,
adding it on at the end.
Cause if you add something on to any product,
you know,
it's never going to be as good as if it's embedded in it.
Yeah.
It's a great point you make,
isn't it?
And I think app makers are about growing their audience,
not about safety first.
And you can sort of understand the commercial world of that.
Last time I saw you,
I was fascinated.
You know,
I had this conversation with you that the world of the online troll,
you know,
from racial,
misogynistic,
homophobic,
uh,
you know,
the trash that we see on the online,
I had this perception that it was incredibly difficult to track those people down.
The big tech companies protected them because of privacy laws.
You told me that's a hundred percent not true.
Can you explain?
Yeah.
And that's correct.
And what we know is,
look,
some platforms don't work cooperatively with police or it's,
they make it very difficult,
especially for countries that are not where the,
um,
the platform is based.
So a lot of times,
um,
for some of the lesser platforms,
it is an effort.
To get that data because it like,
for example,
if it was reported to Victoria place,
so Victoria place have to get a warrant,
a state warrant.
It has to get converted to a Commonwealth board.
Then it gets conferred,
converted to what's called a,
an M lat treaty,
which is an international warrant.
Then it gets served on the company.
And by this stage,
you know,
it's complex.
It's complex.
On what sort of platform is that?
I mean,
well,
that's the,
the lesser known ones and the ones that really don't have a brand to protect if you like.
Right.
So what you'll find is like,
the meta platforms,
Snapchat,
they will allow,
um,
a legal letter for want of a better word.
So this is a legally obtained document.
It'll be signed by,
by a judge to say,
this is the information we'd like,
and they will accept that.
So you don't have to go through the M lat process.
You might need to go through that process for certain pieces of information,
but basic,
um,
user identification,
you do not need to go that down that path.
So that's really good.
Um,
what we need though,
and if we think about,
you know,
cyberbullying and all forms of online abuse are a crime,
they're a crime throughout Australia under state law and Commonwealth law.
And if we think about what laws are meant to do,
they're meant to set the standard for acceptable behavior,
punish people that break the law,
but they're meant to provide a deterrent effect.
So,
you know,
if you're tempted to go and do the wrong thing and you see last week,
Billy or Mary have been sent to jail for doing the same thing.
Well then hopefully you might go,
Oh,
you know what?
I don't want to go to jail.
So I won't do that.
We're not seeing that with online crimes to the degree we should,
because so many people do not report it.
All right.
And they don't take it to the police.
So unless you are prepared to take that step,
then we're never going to get to that point where people see that,
well,
actually it is a crime and there are serious consequences if I choose this path.
So this is something I'm really passionate about.
So,
and I'm glad you explained that as clear as you did.
So we see that in the,
in the sporting world,
a lot.
And I know you've done a lot of work in,
in Sporting Codes,
the AFL,
Netball Australia around this work that you do,
but we'll say racist comment,
horrific thing said against an indigenous player or,
you know,
something horrific said to someone.
I mean,
for me,
what we want to do is exactly that.
We want to try and make an example of that behaviour and say that is
unacceptable.
It's not the standards we live up to.
And an example is not cancelling their club membership.
That's not an example.
So what would you do then?
So,
and my advice has always been to the clubs when I go into
them and this is for anyone,
you know,
you're going to cop some abuse,
is it fair?
No,
it's not,
but you know,
you're a peanut cause you missed a goal.
I mean,
you're going to have to suck that up,
but when it's targeted abuse,
you know,
really personal targeted,
I'm going to rape your wife,
for example,
as a common one,
the racist,
the homophobic,
et cetera.
That's not okay.
That that's not,
you know,
something you should accept as part and parcel of who you
are.
So until such time as we can make,
not make,
but encourage players to come forward and make that police
report,
nothing will change.
And it's all very well.
Media articles,
no media articles are great.
You know,
Billy got racially abused this week.
Great.
But the offender is still out there keeping on keeping
on.
And we have to encourage that reporting because that's where
we're going to make a difference and change the thought process.
Can I ask you a pointed question then as a,
as a,
you know,
nearly 30 year police officer,
are you going to get a good reception?
You know,
I feel play you're walking in to say,
you know,
someone seriously threatened me.
Is that process one that encourages people to do that?
Well,
we could call it postcode lottery,
which is a really sad thing to say,
but it's real in that it does often depend on who
you speak to.
But you know,
I,
the player is not going to rock up to the PlayStation on
their own.
The player development manager for the club would go with them.
The player's manager that they'd be fronting up and going high.
This is the situation.
And I think in that regard,
an AFL player has far more chance of having something investigated
than Mr.
And Mrs.
Citizen.
And there was a case,
and I think it was a Richmond plan not that long ago where threats
had been made,
you know,
to rape his wife or something like that.
And he went to the police and the people got arrested and charged.
Now,
did they get a penalty that,
that I would have given?
Probably not,
but there was a penalty and you know,
we,
we need to do more of that because it's doable and it's
possible and no person,
let alone an AFL player or anyone in between should have to
tolerate that.
And this is all about leadership,
this podcast.
And I,
and I think it's a,
it's a massive opportunity for a leadership position to be
taken from police,
from high profile people,
from average people.
I mean,
as you said to me last time I saw you,
if you're at the front of your house and someone walked
past and said something as horrific as that,
I'm going to write you,
or I mean,
you know,
I know exactly what my reaction is.
Oh,
thanks.
See you later.
Appreciate your feedback.
You're going to get police involved.
You're going to react yourself.
Um,
but you know,
that happens thousands of times an hour online and it's
getting through.
And that's to me,
creating a huge issue with where we're at in society.
If we look currently at that amazing young man,
that's been drafted to North Melbourne,
the Jewish player and the amount.
And the amount of abuse that he's copying and his family.
And what do we have bleeding hard articles in the paper?
You know,
it is a big ask for an 18 year old who has just
been drafted to trot off to the police station.
However,
I would expect his manager,
the club,
the player development manager,
whoever is looking after him,
the AFL to be going,
hang on a minute.
It's all very well getting these comments taken down.
All right.
Okay.
And what do they do?
It happens again.
You know,
someone somewhere along the journey,
has to take a stand and not an isolated player because the,
the Richmond one would have to have been two or three years ago.
Now I can't tell you another case that I am aware of where a
player has actually gone and lodged a complaint.
And if it is racist,
racist,
homophobic,
et cetera,
not only is that under cyber bullying laws,
it's a breach of the discrimination act.
And for example,
let's say Harry got 50 racist messages,
right?
The perpetrator,
well,
it's like the one person that sent the 50 that perpetrator would face 150
charges,
150,
50 state cyber bullying charges,
50 Commonwealth cyber bullying charges,
and 50 discrimination act charges.
It's a powerful message to send,
isn't it?
So,
and I love your leadership in this space and tell me,
I'm all about accountability.
If you show people that you can get away with those things,
it encourages other people.
Of course it does.
And you know,
we've been so slow.
What,
why is that?
To me it's a free hit,
you know?
I don't know.
You know,
if you look at any other type of offending,
I don't think it's as underreported other than sexual offending,
which we know is terribly underreported.
But other than that,
you know,
if a crime is committed against you,
you go to the place like that.
That's how it is.
Whether people think it's a free for all on the internet,
it doesn't matter whether they think that laws don't count out there.
But again,
it's often because I didn't know,
it was a crime because I don't ever see a consequence.
I don't see anyone arrested and charged for this.
So therefore it must be okay.
The platforms by and large,
the main ones work cooperatively with police,
even Snapchat.
All right.
The content disappears.
It does not delete.
All right.
And again,
people go,
Oh,
it's on Snapchat.
I know.
No,
no,
no.
It is always worth visiting the police station.
Um,
unfortunately,
sometimes you have to stand your ground and go,
I know this is a crime,
so I'm not leaving here until you take a report.
Shouldn't happen.
But you know,
we've got to do more to make it unacceptable.
It's all very well saying it's unacceptable,
but what are we doing to show it?
And Susan,
at the extreme end,
I mean,
that's horrific to deal with,
uh,
not under the estimating that any shape or mind,
but some other,
you know,
in preparation for this,
there's talk,
you know,
at any one time in the internet,
there's a million online predators,
online grooming,
sexual exploitation,
a whole range of really serious.
Is that from your experience,
what's happening at that end of the scale?
Yep.
So we know that the online exploitation of children is the fastest growing crime of its type in the world.
I still have parents tell me that,
that I worry about pedophiles because they're kids smart.
Well,
you know,
I'm sorry to burst your bubble,
but they're not that smart.
Um,
or I don't worry about pedophiles because my child would pick them.
No,
they won't.
That's why these people,
they're so good at what they do because they're not going to get picked.
They don't enter into a conversation with your child.
Hi,
I'm a child sex offender.
Do you want to hang out with me?
Right?
They're going to seem nice,
sound nice,
look nice and appear nice.
They will spin them a line.
And,
you know,
unfortunately for the 10 kids that don't take the bait,
number 11 and 12 will.
Right?
They don't care.
Like they'll just keep going until they get someone to engage with.
And it is a huge issue.
And I said recently at a parent,
evening that I would much rather if I had a 12 year old child,
I would much rather let them walk around the block at midnight on their own
than put them on the internet unsupervised because I know where the most
likelihood of harm is and it's not on my street at midnight.
That's a confronting thing to say,
isn't it?
Cause no parent I know was going to allow their 12 year old to walk around the
block,
but not all of us at one.
And I have to put my hand up.
I say this all the time because you know,
as a father of four and you're passionate about this space,
but you know,
I'm on my phone.
You can't be there 24 seven.
Yeah.
And also you're sort of hypocritical cause I'm on my phone too much.
And I'm yelling at young Maxie to get off his phone as I'm on the phone myself.
So I know the hypocrisy is alive and well.
It's like don't drink alcohol darling while I'm swigging a beer.
Well,
that's right.
I mean,
it's,
it's a complex parenting thing,
more complex than any I think we've we've seen.
I,
it certainly feels like an error.
Can I change tack?
We had a huge high profile hacking issue,
Medibank and the data being released to people's private health,
uh,
information,
horrific thing.
I mean,
how,
you know,
for people who run small businesses are listening to this people who,
in the past,
it was a Nigerian scammer.
And you thought I'm,
you know what,
I reckon I'll be okay.
Yeah.
Now it's very sophisticated and they're very good at what they do.
What should you do to protect yourself?
If you are running a business that has any tech,
um,
which it will cause at least have an email,
you need to understand that there is a risk.
Now,
where do you,
and I say this all the time,
where do you sit on the risk scale?
Like,
I can't,
I can't answer that because I don't know what you do,
how you do it.
I don't know how good you are,
what systems you have in place.
I don't know your knowledge.
And I don't know,
you know a lot about you,
whether you know you are attractive to Harry,
the hacker or you're not.
So all these things are important,
but I don't want people to think that now job's right because I'm X.
Therefore,
no one's going to bother me because a lot of this is nuisance value as well.
So they don't actually get anything out of it in a monetary way other than
they've stuffed you up.
The amount of people,
however,
that are willing to pay a ransom to allegedly,
you know,
get access to their database back does my head in.
And it's the one thing,
you know,
that I fully support a Medibank with is that the minute you pay a ransom,
you are telling the offender that you have a willingness to pay and a capacity
to pay the two things you don't want them to know.
So you never,
ever do that.
And you should never,
on any circumstances,
never,
ever,
ever.
So,
you know,
so any business owner is at risk.
Obviously some more than others.
Now,
if you look at the Optus and the Medibank and the things like that,
you know,
all that data,
well,
there's a debate with Optus about keeping it a bit longer than they legally
should have.
But the one thing that they all did,
it appears that they did wrong is that yes,
you're allowed to hold the data,
but it was meant to be encrypted.
So if you know,
Harry,
the hacker did get in,
it was useless to them because there was nothing there in a format that they
could use or Susan McLean,
the name is there,
but it doesn't,
it doesn't link to anything.
So,
you know,
you couldn't match it all up.
And that appears to be something that's lacking again,
unless there are consequences for that,
you know,
nothing is going to change.
And,
you know,
to the government's credit,
they have jumped fairly quickly to put in place some consequences for future
hacks,
which there will be.
You've only got to look at Telstra this week that inadvertently published
personal information of people that had asked for their number and their
address to remain silent.
And apparently it appeared in white pages directories.
Now to me,
yes,
if I had a complex medical history that I didn't really want known,
that would be distressing that that was on the dark web.
Will it ever make the light a day?
Might,
might not.
But if I was fleeing domestic violence or I was still a serving police
officer,
I most definitely do not want my name,
address and phone number out there for everyone to see,
because you know,
that's a personal safety issue and you know,
it's not going to go anywhere fast.
What can we do?
Not a lot because you've got to,
there has to be a level of trust in these organisations,
but they're failing us dismally at the moment.
And so you clearly understand this better than I do,
but the data gathering on us and our kids,
but you can't sign into your kids,
you know,
school function without giving you know,
your address and your phone number and 14 other points of information.
And you get to the point where I do certainly where you go,
it's so far gone.
Yeah.
I think though that I think people are now with these three are starting to
challenge a bit more like,
Hey,
why do you actually need this?
You know,
is it a function of your business or is it,
you know,
something extra school login systems that I'm not a fan of a lot of those,
because again,
they gather far too much information that is totally irrelevant and is not
necessary.
I sign into schools every day,
obviously I'm in schools and I got asked recently,
am I vaccinated?
Yeah,
it's not a problem.
Which brand of vaccination did I have?
Well,
I don't think so.
Like not that I care,
but,
but for what purpose are you gathering that?
So I think,
you know,
we do need to be very clear that if,
if someone is starting to ask questions or I'm expecting you to provide
information that you're thinking,
well,
hang on this,
this does not in any way relate to what I'm trying to do with you.
Then we need to be prepared to pull back and go,
well, hang on a minute.
Cause if everyone pulls back,
then things will change,
but it's when people accept it as,
oh,
well,
what can I do?
And if everyone takes that attitude,
it's just going to continue.
And it's the same as the cyber bullying.
If you put it in the too high basket and go,
you know what?
It can be someone else's problem.
Then nothing changes.
And I am forever,
you know,
reporting accounts on social media that I say that I know are inappropriate.
Now they're not targeting me particularly.
They might be,
they're often not they're targeting someone else.
I'll report them.
I have often multiple accounts a week deleted off social media,
simply on based on my report.
It takes all of 10 seconds.
So I'm not prepared to walk past that standard.
I'm going to act.
If it simply means click,
click,
click and send it off.
If the platform does nothing,
I can't do anything more at that point,
unless it's something I need to,
to deal with in a different way.
But I think if everyone did that again,
you know,
the AI behind the programs now are starting to block people from
saying,
setting up multiple accounts when their accounts have been deleted.
There's reporting options about blocking someone,
blocking an account plus any new count they create,
you know,
so we're,
we're,
you know,
five steps forward,
six steps back,
but we're getting there,
but it takes a groundswell of people going,
well,
hang on a minute.
This is not okay.
Now you're an old school,
you know,
hardened police officer.
It takes a bit to rattle you,
but you get more than your fair share,
of horrific abuse online and probably more than given you take such a powerful stance.
I mean,
does it,
does it ever get to you?
Yes and no.
Like I just sort of think sad people in the world that think they need to,
this is,
these are people targeting me that don't even know me.
Right.
But I've come out and I've been vocal about,
you know,
something in the media or some other online abuse and you get,
well,
just don't read it or,
you know,
things like that.
I mean,
block is my friend,
block and report.
And it never,
never ceases to amaze me,
you know,
what,
what people will go you for and how they actually find you.
Like,
it's like,
clearly you're following me for,
for,
for a reason.
You know,
you want to go me online.
I'm not interested in that conversation.
And I look at my Facebook page,
which has a really nice community of 30,000 people.
And,
you know,
they're all there because they want information by and large.
And,
and it's a very respectful place,
but you get the odd person that,
you know,
comes up with stupid stuff.
Well,
they're not welcome.
And I make that very clear.
But one,
one thing that really distressed me,
it did distress me,
not greatly.
We got over it,
but my husband and I got caught up in Los Rambles in Barcelona with the terrorist attack.
So we were on Los Rambles when that happened and got ourselves safe back into a shop.
We put all the,
because shops in Europe have metal shutters.
So we put all the shutters down and we hid in the shop with a lot of other people.
And the minute that I saw that car flying past,
I knew it was,
I knew exactly what was happening.
It was a terrorist attack and we needed to get out of there.
And I put a thing out to say,
like,
I marked myself safe,
which is one of the good things you can do in an emergency situation on social media.
And you know,
the,
I was getting messages like shame,
they didn't get you,
you know,
they should have tried harder to kill you.
And I'm thinking,
I don't even know who you are.
Like,
you know,
if you get your jollies telling someone you wish they were dead,
you know, you're dead.
And I'm like,
you know,
I feel sorry for you and I'm not going to let that affect what I do.
Yeah.
It's horrific though,
isn't it?
I hear that and your mind just goes,
well,
what have we become?
And I just,
to me,
it's that accountability piece isn't it?
I love those,
you know,
sometimes those people are working sophisticated jobs and you find out that that's what they,
like to put out into the universe.
What distresses me greatly when I work with young people is the amount of them,
the amount of them that are told to go and kill themselves.
Now,
I think that is the most abhorrent thing you could do.
Say to any other human being,
whether you like them or not.
And it's common.
That happens a lot.
It flows off.
And I say it flows off their tongue.
It's coming off their fingers.
I am sent the most distressing messages and screenshots from parents about what do I do about this?
My child has just been told to kill himself.
And there was one recently where he was,
you know,
told to jump off a bridge.
Um,
and if he planned it right,
a train could hit him at the same time.
I've seen families that have been sent playlists to die.
Bye.
You know,
you know,
this is it.
This is our society.
And then you look at that,
then you look at what happened in Queensland,
you know,
and you've got to think,
are these people heading towards that sort of behavior if they're starting in primary school,
thinking it's okay to tell someone to go kill themselves and we read that it becomes acceptable.
It comes normal.
And as you said,
that's,
uh,
you know,
something you walk past is something you accept.
Isn't it?
It's a powerful message that you've got.
I've got a handful of leadership questions I want to ask you,
but just a quick one before we move on to that.
Where do you sit on schools allowing kids to have their phones in a classroom?
Um,
it depends how much you want to pay me for that answer.
So let's go back to,
I think it's 2018.
Dr.
Michael Carr,
Greg,
the adolescent psychologist and myself,
um,
and Amanda third,
who's an academic were employed by the New South Wales education department to,
to conduct a review into what should this look like?
What should we do?
The risk,
the benefit,
the dangers,
et cetera.
Now I am a hundred percent for the banning phones in schools.
Do not stop cyberbullying.
They do not write in any way,
shape or form,
because we know most of the cyberbullying happens at night.
But what our review found and we spoke to lots of young people,
parents,
educators themselves,
especially schools that had started to limit the use of phones and not one person had,
anything negative to say,
not one of them best thing we ever did.
More engagement from the students,
less distraction,
children engaging better in the playground,
et cetera.
So it's not about block,
bad and take away because it can be useful.
And there is certainly teacher directed learning.
There is amazing apps on your phone that manage your blood sugar.
So valid medical reasons,
not I need to text mom at two o'clock in the afternoon,
not that,
but medical reasons.
But the unsupervised go for your life use.
No,
no,
no.
For a variety of reasons.
I laugh.
Schools have big signs.
All visitors must report to the office.
Well,
what about the 200 or the 2000 random strangers that are in your school ground through technology?
I had a school a couple of years ago said,
Oh,
you know,
we're dealing with kids filming Tik Tok videos in the toilets in uniform.
We really don't know what to do.
So my first question is,
what is your phone policy?
Oh,
we don't have one.
Well,
how's that working out for you?
Not very well.
So it is about setting an acceptable standard.
It is about also,
you know,
people talk about preparing children for the real world.
There are plenty of occupations where you cannot fiddle on your phone for eight hours a day.
You know,
you'll check your phone when you arrive at work and you will not see it again until you finished your shift.
So if we've allowed kids to fiddle all day,
every day,
well,
that is setting them up for failure.
There is the inappropriate content.
There is a small amount of bullying and harassment.
I've seen that happens during the school day.
There is,
you know,
if my child is a student at school and some other kid brings up,
violent pornography on their phone and says,
Hey,
look at this,
that's a breach of duty of care of the school to keep my child safe.
So,
um,
I firmly believe that school should have clear and robust,
robust policy.
Policy only works when it's enforced like a law,
but I have not been given any valid reasons anywhere by anyone that says kids should have unsupervised access to phones.
So as I said,
teacher directed learning,
please bring your phone because that's a decision for a teacher,
um,
medical reasons.
But other than that,
bring them into school.
They stay in the locker and they come out at the end of the school day.
Oh,
but we let them use them at lunchtime.
So what are they doing?
Or they can check them at their lockers.
What are they accessing?
Oh,
I don't know.
So there's a whole lot of legal issues here.
And I think,
you know,
the majority of schools understand that,
but there are still some that,
you know,
live by hope.
You know,
we expect our students to make a good choice.
All right,
what planet are you on?
Kids don't make good choices.
They're children.
They need guidance.
They need,
you know,
someone to go,
this is not a good idea and help them understand the why behind it.
Well,
that makes an enormous amount of sense.
Susan,
I love asking these questions because I see leadership in different spaces and you've got a really clear,
you know,
1994 when most of us were,
weren't born.
Well,
I certainly,
I certainly was,
but working out the internet or what it was going to be,
you know,
you had,
I thought the internet was a fad that we were going to get over.
Seriously.
Yeah.
I still remember a close family friend of ours bought a computer for their children and we were invited around to see the computer.
What year do you reckon that?
That would have had to have been,
well,
it was before 94.
It would have to have been in the late.
No,
it was,
I would not have been.
So in the seven,
late seventies.
Okay.
And it was this boxy thing that really was not connected to the internet,
but it was a computer.
And,
you know,
there was things on the screen and you could play a game.
And I looked at it and think,
oh yeah,
whatever.
Like it didn't even interest me.
And then when the internet,
you know,
oh,
it's a bit of a fad or a fashion because of course the internet came from the ARPANET,
which was the American military communication system.
Again,
it was like,
nah,
not interested,
nothing to do with me.
And,
you know,
now,
now look where I am.
We think how,
you know,
young Google,
Facebook,
it's not a lot,
is it?
It's not a long history for how big they are in our life.
So we see these dimensions of leadership really common.
So there's an indifferent settings,
whether you've been an educator or running a social venture or a cyber safety expert like you.
So I'll ask you some questions.
I expand as much as you like,
or as little as you like.
We see most people start with a sense of self leadership before they can lead others.
When I say that to you,
what does it mean?
It means that I have confidence in my own ability and I'm prepared to do what I want.
I'm prepared to do what is right rather than what might be expected of me.
I think that was instilled in me from a very young age through my parents that although they were never a hundred percent happy that I joined the police force,
a very stupid,
super proud,
but I was still a little girl.
And,
you know,
when I joined 5% of police officers were females.
So it was not a female industry.
Like it clearly isn't anymore.
Still,
you know,
I was the first,
first female ever gazetted to the Eltham police station.
When I would go out on the van,
they were,
instead of saying that we're two up,
we were one and one.
No,
no separate change rooms and toilets.
Like it was a very different world.
So it was again,
the belief I had in myself that,
that it was right and I needed to do it.
And I suppose that was more evidence when I started to work in this space in the police force.
So when I took that report,
and I started to think,
well,
hang on a minute,
you know,
I had little children at that time.
I was like,
God,
is this the world they're growing up in?
I need to educate myself.
So I was very lucky in that I was invited to America and I undertook training with the FBI.
Um,
I reviewed some of the programs,
the Dallas police department were using,
um,
and I came back and I badgered and harassed Victoria police to give me a position to put into place my knowledge.
Because at that point,
what I wanted to do is make Victoria police a better place and share,
all my learnings from the States over here so that we could,
because they were ahead of us,
you know,
at the police stations in,
in Victoria,
you had a complaints book and,
you know,
you'd,
it's like the book you've got there.
You'd make a note,
be aware that there's a hoon driver at this address,
you know,
so the next shift would come in and go,
oh,
I need to go there.
Well,
they were always using,
they were already using technology to,
to do that sort of stuff.
So,
you know,
way ahead of what we were doing.
And,
you know,
it was,
it was hard getting listened to.
I had one high ranking police officer say to my face,
you are blonde and female.
You don't have much going for you.
Do you?
I had another one tell me that I needed to choose between being a police
officer and a mother because I couldn't be both.
But would they have ever said that to a male police officer?
No.
But I had a belief in myself and I,
I understood that this was going to be a problem and I didn't want to be the
problem.
I wanted to try to be the solution.
So,
um,
and I often say to people,
is,
you know,
you have to believe in yourself first and foremost,
and you have to back yourself in.
And that is a strong sense of self-leadership in every sense of the word.
And it clearly is a huge part of you and what you've been able to achieve.
We see leaders who are really conscious of how they positively impact others in
their environment on a daily basis.
I mean,
you're impacting so many people with what you're doing and your research and
your,
and your leadership in this space.
But how does that resonate with you impacting others in a positive way?
I think,
I think that's,
you know,
I think every person on this planet should be trying to do the right thing and
should be,
you know,
leaving a positive child behind rather than a negative one.
Um,
so I suppose again,
that comes back from my upbringing,
my policing career.
And I mean,
I,
I worked at Fitzroy police station.
Now Fitzroy is,
you know,
full of trendy cafes and it's nice now in the,
um,
mid eighties.
It was not,
it was a very,
very different place.
And it was,
it was,
um,
divided into three,
three clear areas.
Um,
the South of Fitzroy was a very,
where the commission flights were,
it was a very low socioeconomic rundown area.
The middle was a slight step up.
And if you were North Fitzroy,
you were the,
the gentry.
So it was a very different world,
um,
to what even any policing is today.
And I suppose I saw the worst of the worst.
Um,
you know,
I dealt with child sexual abuse.
I dealt with murders.
I dealt with drugs.
I dealt with,
you know,
I had,
um,
my nose broken in a pub.
I was punched in the face trying to arrest a New South Wales escapee.
Um,
you know,
so I did it tough then,
but it was all about trying to make a difference in a positive way.
And I think in the work that I do now,
you know,
I will never know how many people made a good choice based on listening to me
speak or me coming into this school.
But,
you know,
I'll often get a message going,
I got,
I got one the other day.
I heard you speak at a conference.
I never thought I would need this knowledge as a parent,
but I do because this,
this just happened to my child.
So,
you know,
I know that I'm making a difference.
Um,
and I think that that's just an important facet of,
of being a decent human being.
Yeah.
Well said.
Um,
we see leaders are really conscious of how they go about creating and
sharing her vision.
And you've got a really clear vision for cyber safety and,
and how we should engage in that world.
How have you gone about trying to share that?
Um,
so it was very interesting.
So I was,
you know,
pushing shit uphill,
um,
in the police force,
trying to get them to listen and they wouldn't.
And again,
it was that blonde female,
you know,
why would we listen to you?
And it got very interesting because I,
I got a little bit known.
I came back from the States.
I was,
I'm the only person in Australia with my qualifications and,
and experience and the media got wind of me.
So they would go to police media and ask to interview me and they get
replies like this.
Oh,
I'm really sorry.
Susan's not available,
but detective Smith,
he's,
he's from the arson squad,
but you know,
he'll be fine.
And then they'd request again.
Oh no,
Susan's not available.
Um,
but detective Jones is,
um,
he's from the,
uh,
motor theft squad,
but you know,
he'll be your man,
you know?
So it was,
they were stymieing me at every point and it was like,
this is ridiculous.
You know,
I'm only trying to help.
I went to work one day.
It was the Tuesday after the black Saturday bushfires.
And I went home and I said to my husband,
I'm quitting.
And I never went back.
And it was like,
I know that there is a problem.
I know that I have an ability to help not hinder this problem.
And if they're not going to value me,
um,
then I'm going to do it on my own.
And the PR this was like February.
So the preceding November,
my mother had died and she got diagnosed with lung cancer and died in six
weeks.
And she was a non-smoker.
So it was quite confronting.
But I remember like on her deathbed,
her saying to me,
Susan,
they don't value you.
Um,
you know,
and that always rung in my,
my mind that,
well,
perhaps I,
I'm not being valued and perhaps I can make a difference outside the
constraints of Victoria police.
You know,
I would never not have my police career.
I loved 99% of my police career.
Best part of my police career was an Academy romance with the person that is
still my husband now after almost 40 years.
So,
you know,
lots of benefits came with being a police officer.
And I love it.
I love the work and all of that,
but I just know that I can do more now.
And that's what I try my very best to do.
And you know,
I work in schools.
I work with corporates.
I do webinars.
You know,
I make myself available.
Um,
I make myself available to the media.
I don't get paid for any media.
Um,
but my,
my thought process is the story's going to run,
right?
Whether I'm available or not.
And if they run the story with someone that doesn't know what they're saying,
um,
you know,
the,
uh,
you know,
Eddie everywhere,
expert sort of person,
um,
then that's doing harm.
So if I make myself available,
then at least I know that I've got some control about the message that's being shared.
And I think in an area where,
you know,
there are some things that you can talk about and the whole world knows you're lying,
right?
Cause they're already facts.
They're already out there.
Everyone knows,
but with technology,
there's still a lot of lack of information.
So if I fed you a really good,
you're a really good line and I'm touted as an expert by the media,
you're going to go,
ah,
must be true.
And I challenged journalists that quote people as experts,
because technically an expert is someone whose evidence can be accepted in a court of law without being challenged.
You've quoted them as an expert.
What are their qualifications?
Uh,
they've got a website and,
uh,
they do talks and,
you know,
so,
to me,
that's a social responsibility.
Um,
and,
you know,
I provide hundreds of pro bono hours to families to step them through and help them because where else do they go?
And if I,
if the,
if the tables were turned and I needed that help,
I don't want a chat bot that did not,
does not understand my issue.
I don't want to put an online form in that might get returned,
you know,
in a week.
I need someone to help me now.
In an issue that's confronting parents on a,
you know,
in a growth industry,
tragically with more need than,
than ever before.
It's a huge amount of a positive impact that you have.
Curiosity is something we see from everyone.
I sit across from curiosity seems to be a really common trait of,
of leadership.
Does that word ring true to you?
It does in that,
you know,
I'm always curious into what's going to happen next.
What will it look like?
How can I manage it?
How can I improve myself and do better?
I think it's about having an open mind and,
you know,
not switching off from things just because,
um,
always, um,
always be curious,
always think,
well,
okay,
here it is now,
but what might this look like?
What might the potential good be?
What might the potential bad be?
And then how do we target that?
And we see communicating with clarity,
which,
uh,
you're brilliant at,
and you get your message across,
you know,
incredibly clearly.
And,
and,
you know,
sometimes it's confronting because we,
the,
the language is,
is,
is intense at times.
But how have you gone about communicating that message?
Hopefully with clarity.
It's interesting.
One of the things I say when I speak to young people is
that,
and I'll say at the start of my talk,
I'm going to be blunt.
I'm going to be direct.
And there is no wriggle room in what I say.
And for me,
that's important because I need to share really important facts.
And especially when I'm talking about laws.
Um,
if I give any audience wriggle room,
I know what they will do.
They will twist it to suit them,
or they'll twist it to what they want to hear.
So that then that's a failing as well.
So,
if you leave my sessions confused,
then I failed.
So no wriggle room here it is.
Is it always fair?
No.
Is it factual?
Yes.
And you cannot expect any person,
particularly young people to make,
or even try to make a good choice if they haven't been given the facts.
It's like saying,
read this book,
but we're going to test you on a different one and hope for the best.
And the,
the cost of harm to young people that get themselves into situations,
on the internet,
get targeted,
et cetera,
is enormous.
And,
you know,
we all have to do more to make sure that,
for me,
every adult has a responsibility to try to keep all children safe online so that children don't get mixed messages.
You know,
it's like the good cop,
bad cop parents,
you know,
the child will go to the good cop to get the lollies,
but they won't ask the bad cop parent because they will say no.
So it's the same thing.
You want them to get the same message from school,
from home,
from the sport club,
the co-curricular activity,
from grandparents.
Aunts,
uncles,
and cousins,
because consistent messaging works.
Which leads to the next dimension that I want to talk to you about,
which is collaboration.
To do that,
we see leaders are really conscious now of collaborating and you're right,
even on the home front,
if you're not collaborating with your partner on this,
you don't get anywhere or the extended family.
I mean,
how important has collaboration been for you in your space?
It's been really important.
And,
you know,
again,
I don't know it all.
I have some knowledge and my knowledge is better than most people.
But then there are other people with different knowledge.
And I think in this space,
because it's so fluid,
it requires a multifaceted approach.
So there are people,
there are tech expert people.
Like I couldn't pull a phone apart to save my life,
but there are people that can,
and they can get the data off the phone.
There are people that,
you know,
the adolescent psychologists and psychiatrists that work with the mental health harms.
There are academics that just churn through research after research to look at patterns of emerging behavior.
And I think that this is where we all need to work together because we all have something to bring to the table.
And there's no one thing that is going to solve this in isolation.
What will solve problems,
any problem,
is the mass coming at it from the same,
the same direction with the same expectations.
So if everyone expects a platform to protect their users,
then it will force the platform to do the right thing.
But,
but if people are happy to stay there and accept a substandard experience,
then what incentive is there to change?
They'll come out with all the talk.
Oh,
yappy,
yap.
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
We do this,
read our T's and C's,
but it,
you know,
actions speak louder than words.
Yeah.
I'm incredibly new to the online space of social.
I thought it passed me by,
Susan,
which might've been a happy experience,
but through the web.
Are you a TikToker?
No,
I'm not TikToker,
but I,
I did my first experience with my 17 year old daughter on that the other day,
which was mind blowing around,
you know,
are you team Johnny Depp or team Amber Heard?
I said,
what are you even talking about?
And then 40 minutes of my life was gone scrolling through,
through TikToker.
So how easy was it to lose 40 minutes as an adult?
Stunning.
So couldn't believe it.
Couldn't believe that,
you know,
someone had disseminated that case into a really skewed version around,
and,
and it just,
it was so.
So it was really easy for you.
Yeah.
With,
you know,
life experiences,
maturity,
fully formed brain,
all of that.
Think about the impact on young people.
And I laugh,
you know,
again,
I'm much older than you,
but I got a little message from Meta this week to say,
congratulations.
You are in the top 2% of content creators on Facebook.
Now,
what the hell is a content creator?
Like,
you know,
I do know what one is,
but when I sat down with my careers teacher at high school,
content creator,
an influencer were not two job opportunities.
So here is someone that is mature of age,
use technology only relatively recently,
of course,
like in the last 20 years,
but you know,
there I am being acknowledged as,
as being able to manage this sort of space.
But I do laugh at that because it's like,
okay,
I think that's good.
I think your story is a great leadership story in every sense in a,
in a space that we all have to confront,
whether we like it or not,
but asking these final two questions,
Susan,
of all the guests on this empowering leaders podcast,
who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Oh my goodness.
That is such a hard question.
And,
you know,
there's leaders in different,
in different ways.
And I look at,
um,
I look at my parents,
that certainly were exceptional leaders for their time.
And my father,
um,
he gave so much of his life,
to the country and to volunteering.
He was a world war two veteran.
Um,
he was a talented footballer and tennis player,
a life member of the diamond Valley football league,
life member of the country fire authority,
Queens fire service medal.
Um,
he never asked for thanks or acknowledgement of anything that he did.
He gave back,
um,
and then mum by default supported him in doing that.
Um,
I look at my husband as a leader.
he's a forensic crash investigator.
He worked with major,
major collision in Victoria police and successfully runs his own company as well.
So he leads,
you know,
us and has been an amazing father.
I look at,
and something I didn't mention before,
I think is important about,
you know,
obviously trusting your gut,
but getting a mentor,
getting someone else that believes in you.
Cause it's all very well going.
Yeah,
I think I'm okay.
But when you hear it from someone else,
I think that adds to your credibility.
And I've had the most amazing mentor in Dr.
Michael Carr,
Greg,
who believed in me from the get go,
told me I was actually really good at what I did.
Cause up until that point,
I was me,
I was a police officer with an interest in this.
Um,
I could clearly string a sentence together,
bit different to some police officers.
People go,
what media training did you do?
None.
But you know,
he,
I still remember the first time he heard me speak and it was like,
wow,
this is amazing.
You need to do more with this knowledge.
You are wasted in Victoria police.
So,
you know,
he certainly has been a leader for me to look up to and support me.
In,
in what I do now and moving forward.
I love your answer.
Isn't it often,
you know,
it's a,
it's a question that,
you know,
without notice,
you think about your family and if you've had great influences in your
family or a great partner,
people go there.
But to then,
as you said,
if you get someone in your life,
he backs you in like Dr.
Michael Carr,
Greg,
who's got a great legacy for the work that he has done here and around the
world.
If you could collaborate with anyone and clearly you've got a clear passion in
this space,
is there someone out there you think,
God,
if I could connect with them anywhere around the world on any of your passions
in life,
is there anyone that springs to life?
Oh my goodness.
Um,
who would I like to collaborate with?
Oh,
that is such a hard question.
Um,
I don't know that there's anyone out there that I think,
oh gee,
I really,
really,
really would like to collaborate with them.
There's people that I admire and I think,
wow,
it'd be really amazing to meet you and chat with you.
Um,
and things like that.
And you know,
I still remember like I have been extremely lucky.
Um,
and again,
I talk to kids about opportunities.
And the thing with an opportunity is you don't know it's going to happen
until it happens.
And it's about taking those opportunities.
And you know,
I have met some famous people,
if you like.
Um,
I've met Prince Charles and Princess Diana when they visited Melbourne many
years ago on a tour.
I was doing,
um,
crowd control,
uh,
for them,
for want of a better word.
I've met Prince William at an event that he and I both spoke at.
Can you imagine that I'm on the same speaker?
Speaking gig as Prince William,
who is also passionate about bullying and harassment of young people.
Um,
I went into a studio in London to film for sunrise.
I need to be met by David Williams,
the,
um,
the actor and author.
Um,
and they're all people in their own right that I think,
you know,
are doing good in the world and it's been an honor to meet them.
But the funniest story,
and you will laugh at this as,
um,
a former footballer.
I remember working in a school in Melbourne and I was asked,
the question,
have I met anyone famous now at that point?
And it was a Catholic school,
primary school.
So I said,
I've met the Pope,
which I had because again,
he was out and we'd done close personal protection for the Pope.
It didn't seem to resonate with the kids,
but I'd met the Pope.
So they said anyone else?
And I said,
oh,
I've met Paul Salmon.
Well,
the room erupted and it was like,
oh my God,
you know?
And I'm thinking,
I came in a Catholic school.
And the Pope's not winning it.
Um,
but Paul Salmon came to the forefront there.
So I've had an interesting life,
but again,
it's about opportunities.
It's about knowing your audience,
isn't it?
It is knowing your audience,
but who would have thought?
The great fish,
Paul Salmon,
who was a legend at Essendon and Hawthorne football club.
But,
uh,
it's an incredible legacy.
I feel like you're just getting started,
Susan.
I feel like we're all starting to really understand.
And as you said,
take our own sense of leadership in this space.
It's the thing that comes up the most in the,
when I'm speaking to someone from sports,
from sport or another industry,
everyone as a parent or in their own world,
they're dealing with this space.
So to have you as such a clear voice,
and really,
as you said,
there's no wiggle room in your language,
you know exactly where you sit.
It's a,
it's great to,
you know,
be able to sit down with you.
And thanks for sharing it today.
And it's my pleasure.
And thank you so much for inviting me to have a chat.
Empowering Leaders was presented by me,
Luke Darcy,
produced by Ed Gooden,
the sound design by Matt Curry.
To start your leadership journey,
I encourage you to go to
leadercollective.com.
Take our empowering leaders indicator tool
and understand the impact you have on your environment.
Join us at a leader to learn,
lead and collaborate.
Listener.