everyone talks about concussions the real epidemic are these repetitive hits that are
happening and you don't even know it's happening concussions don't come from the hit they come from
the brain sloshing within the skull every time your brain sloshes it can compromise the integrity
of the structure which can cause an injury and so when you back that out and you actually think
about repetitive head impacts and you take it out of context of just concussions it's actually quite
alarming it's like trying to say one sunburn caused your skin to be unhealthy or one pack of
cigarettes compromised your lung health hello welcome to the empowering leaders podcast at
elita we are passionate about inspiring connections and in our signature program elita connect we
curate groups of five to six leaders from diverse backgrounds be it sport industry social venture
and the arts who come together to learn to connect and collaborate dr troy flanagan
you
I've probably had some of the most radical changes out of that leadership group the
significance of their work and how much it's really about helping others it made me think
what else could I be doing and I approached our our owner and within a few weeks we'd raised
five million dollars to try and solve obesity in the underprivileged community in Milwaukee
so that's one spark that that leadership courses cause it to go
and to help them to contribute and leave the the world as a better place.
umrah omar founder of safari doctors it defines the word creativity for me the ability to like
see connections where none seem to exist and I think that's the magic of a leader definitely
not my usual you know workshop panels like humanitarian spaces but more of an intentional
um dissection of the leadership
leadership
education and empowerment
and the empowering leaders podcast at elita we are passionate about inspiring people to do so in a way that gives them the strength to contribute and lead the world as a better place
we need to be creative and keep your community of leadership to lead the world as a better place
podcast is proudly brought to you by victoria university where cutting-edge sports and exercise
science facilities like heat chambers performance labs and altitude environments mean vu is ranked
seventh in the world for sports science vu uniquely you and as always thanks to jason nicholas and his
team at temper bedding a mattress like no other if you enjoy listening to the empowering leaders
podcast be sure to subscribe and please if you have a moment leave a review for us so we can
reach more listeners and empower more leaders suzanne isla williams is the vice president of
sports marketing at q30 innovations the team behind q collar a silicon collar worn around the neck
that through a slight restriction in blood flow reports to give the brain an extra layer of
cushioning he's been worn extensively through the nfl college football national women's soccer league
the international bobsled federation and has other contact sports around the world extremely
interested given the
global
search to find a solution to concussion related injuries suzanne prior to q collar spent 17 years
as a senior executive in sports marketing at under armor and was herself a three-time all-american
athlete at liola university in maryland great to see you suzanne thanks for joining me yeah thanks
for having me pleasure to be here now it sounds like a life full of great success and when you
look back at what you've achieved and you hear me say that back to you what's the main feeling that
you receive you know
i i just astonishment i've just been so blessed i've had so many great uh experiences but really
i've been surrounded by great people and it started in high school went through college
my first job which was coaching at the collegiate level and then it flowed to under armor and
just truly blessed to be around mentors at every turn in my life and even into q
collar now with q30 i've just been blessed to be around incredible people
i want to start if i can suzanne with the impacts of head knocks and concussion related
injuries and what it means is probably the biggest issue in world sport as we speak can you tell us
about your passion for q collar and the role that it might play in this yeah it's uh it's a topic
that i've become very passionate about and if you would have told me 10 years ago i would have been
i wouldn't have believed you but i got involved with q collar about three years ago and it was
perfect timing um i've been in under armor for a long time and i've been in under armor for a long time
for 17 years loved it never wanted to leave um and i have two sons and they were middle school
aged and you know they were athletic so they played every sport under the sun and really you
know baseball soccer you know basketball tennis golf swimming and then they came to me and my
oldest one said mom i want to quit all my other sports and i just want to play football i just
want to be lamar jackson
and my heart sank and here i am you know a champion of football i love the sport
and at under armor it was our king sport i was involved in it every day but when it was time
to sign my child up i got nervous because it is a very physical sport and a week later so a week
after that happened and you know i kind of played it off with my my oldest i was like oh yeah we'll
figure it out i'll look up some leagues but really you know i'm talking to his dad like how do we get
his mind without him knowing you know we're behind the scenes like trying to figure out how we can get
him to stick with baseball a week later i got a phone call from a mutual friend and said look
um this group from connecticut called q collar has got this amazing device they're going to go
commercial they need someone to run sports marketing would you talk to them and i was like
sure this is interesting but i really don't have any ambition to leave but i am curious because
and it was almost divine intervention because i met tom our ceo and what he explained to me luke
which i didn't know because i was like everyone else i just thought concussions were an issue
right everyone talks about concussions but in reality the issue is the repetitive head impacts
that are happening every game every practice all the time and they don't have to be concussive hits
they don't have to be hits that have symptoms which is how you diagnose a concussion
the real issue are these repetitive hits that are happening and you don't even know it's happening
and so tom really broke it down for me and explained hey you know we've got this device
it's been researched for over 10 years you know all these studies have been done 25 independent
studies and the results are showing that wearing it can help reduce brain slosh can help mitigate
brain slosh which is what's causing the concussions right the concussions don't come from the hit
they come from the brain sloshing within the skull
and what i have found is that when you actually look at how many impacts athletes take and this
is not just contact sports this is soccer right this is you know equestrian rodeo big wave surfers
mountain bikers these are all different sports you know every time your brain sloshes it can
compromise the integrity of the structure which can cause an injury and so when you back that out
and you actually think about repetitive head impacts and you take it out of context of just
it's actually quite alarming and the way i explain it to athletes and i know i'm droning on very long
here but the way i explain it to athletes is it's like trying to say one sunburn caused your skin to
be unhealthy or one pack of cigarettes compromised your lung health it's not it's the overexposure to
sunlight it's the exposure to smoke it's the exposure to repetitive hits that can ultimately
compromise your health short-term and long-term and so
really luke our mission is to educate folks on repetitive head impacts not just let them focus
on concussions which is a great distinction to make because i think that conversation has been
lost in all of this that you know we've now got this incredible fear quite rightly and you've told
the great personal story as a mom you know i want my boys to be healthy i want to protect them
as we all do but i think that's a it's a great distinction and perhaps this is where
the conversation needs to go and i love the
fact story this i was reading that the inventor was studying the anatomy of woodpeckers you know
and can you tell us about the idea of how q collar has been formed on studying woodpeckers
yeah and it's a it's a great story and it's inspiring so the actual genesis of the q collar
most people don't know it came about because the u.s army went to a group of doctors and said look
we are losing too many of our war fighters in afghanistan to tbi traumatic brain injury
and you know that that afghanistan war went for 20 years so you're losing all these very
important war fighters and one of the doctors that they went to said you know the army general
said build us a better helmet and one of the doctors said it's not the helmet right if it
was the helmet we'd have a solution it's the fact that we're not stabilizing the brain within the
skull and he used the analogy it's like putting a soldier in a tank without a seat belt
it doesn't matter if you're in a tank if you move within the tank you're going to get injured
and he said we need to find a way to stabilize the brain within the skull that means we need
to find a solution from the inside out and he's an internist doctor and so he started looking at
how do i find inspiration within nature how did they do it so he looked at woodpeckers he looked
at battling rams right these are animals that bang their heads consistently but are okay just
to the extent
and so you know people get this a little bit confused because our anatomy is not the same
as a woodpecker's so it's not a translation from a to b but he used that woodpecker theory
as inspiration to start looking inside the human body and what he found is that if you compress
the jugular vein slightly which we have on the outside of our necks there's a muscle over top
of it if you can compress that muscle slightly it presses on your jugular vein
and it keeps about a teaspoon of extra blood backfilled in the veins around your brain
and those veins swell and they act like a seat belt and he took that research or that concept
that theory to a neurosurgeon named dr julian bales and he asked julian just to test it on
animals and julian did rat rats and pigs in his laboratory and found an 80 reduction in brain
injury so the theory started from you know how does nature do it and then julian did a lot of
translation over into the human body and reading more about it suzanne it sounds a little bit
alarming to say we're going to restrict some blood flow uh you know to the head uh and keep that
blood in there but effectively you're talking about the same pressure as wearing a tie if you're
wearing a suit and so it's marginal but you're then not allowing the brain to slosh around to
use your term and that's where the head injuries come from and and it's the as you're saying it's
the repeat nature of that even if they're smaller but consistent that's that's what's causing the
damage from from the rest of the brain and that's what's causing the damage from the rest of the
research you guys have have taken yeah and and the big um you know part that people don't
understand is that you're not actually restricting any blood going to your head so blood is still
going up through your artery which is inside you know you can't get to it so that's going up like
normal the only blood that's restricted is the blood that's recirculating back to your heart so
it's blood that's already been oxygenated it's gone up into your head it's now flowing back
through your jugular vein to return to your heart
so we tell guys it's like putting your thumb over a hose right the water is still getting out
it's just a little bit slowed so there's absolutely no physical uh impact negatively so
in order for the testing to to really start clinically they had to do performance testing
and so this performance testing measured you know how much of that blood needed to be restricted to
fill the veins it doesn't change your heart rate it doesn't change your blood oxygen levels it
doesn't impede your blood oxygen levels it doesn't change your blood oxygen levels it doesn't impede
any of the blood going to your head, it doesn't change your reaction time, you know, there's no
adverse effects to it. And you nailed it, Luke, it's the same pressure as a necktie.
It's a little bit over a pound of pressure, which a necktie is a little bit under a pound. So
it's very much like you're going to a wedding and you have a shirt on and a necktie. It's very much
the same feeling. There's absolutely no adverse effects. And once all that testing was done,
that's when the clinical trial started. And clinical trials included humans. So there's
real data. And I can get into it a little bit because, you know, concussions are subjective
and there's no diagnostic test that proves you had one or you didn't. All the tests are based
on symptoms. And so from a research perspective, the medical community does not accept research
on concussions because it's reliably unreliable. So in order to
find real data, they used MRI DTI scans, which actually look at the brain structure
and the white and gray matter of the brain. And by using those MRI scans, they could actually see
if the brain structure was ever compromised. And that's how they based the clinical research.
So they looked at very young, healthy brains in high school players, soccer, football, and hockey.
They baselined all of them first. They gave half of the athletes,
cue collars, half not. And they went and played their entire seasons, every practice, every game.
And at the end of the year, they re-MRI'd their brains and they compared the two scans,
pre-season and post-season. And what they found were the athletes wearing cue collars,
77% showed zero changes in their white brain matter. So their brains were as healthy at the
end of the season as the beginning. But the athletes not wearing cue collars, 73% saw
significant changes. And so they compared the two scans, pre-season and post-season.
So regardless of whether they had a symptom or diagnosed concussion, there were changes in
their brain structure. 20 of those athletes were diagnosed with concussions. Some were in cue
collars, some were not. What the scans showed were the athletes wearing the device. Their return to
play was much shorter and their brain scans showed significantly less damage than the athletes not
wearing cue collars. So when you put it in the context of a seatbelt, it's like being in a car.
You put it on because you know in the chance of an accident, it's going to help reduce your body
moving in the car. And I tell athletes it can mitigate an injury or can lessen the severity
of an injury does occur. Like I would rather bruise my ribs for my seatbelt than fly through
the windshield. So we try to talk to athletes, give them a really good understanding of you want
to reduce brain slosh. There's no magic pill that's going to keep you injury free. But if you
can reduce brain slosh, you can reduce brain slosh. So if you can reduce brain slosh, you can
reduce the chance of an injury, you're putting yourself in a better position.
So Suzanne, I'm going to ask you to put the mum hat back on for a moment. I've got this
sense that we need to have a real conversation about risk. It's an odd saying that I love. You
risk nothing, you risk everything. And what sport has meant to you, I want to talk about your
athletic career, your fiance Mike and his world of sport. That has been such a fundamental part
to your life, fundamental part to my life. There's always going to be risk. Now we want to,
you know, mitigate the risk. And some of the head issues have been life ending for people. So
we're not diminishing that. Do you think we need to still have this conversation around mitigating
risk and the incredible benefits of playing sport at whatever level you do? Does that conversation
need to be had? Absolutely. And look, look, we, we live in a world where you can't get rid of all
risk. I mean, that's just, that's just the nature of who we are and what we do. And, and what I got
from sport and how I feel about sport far outweighs, you know, any reason to not play. But if
you can put yourself in a position to avoid injury or to do all you can to be successful, why not do
it? And, um, I talked to athletes and I, I mentioned, you know, you guys eat, right? You
train, right? You sleep, right? You recover, right? You do all these little things to have
an advantage. This is no different, right? It, it, and, and I,
and I laugh about this Luke, cause you probably can remember this and Mike, you know, you mentioned
Mike, Mike was the head coach at Notre Dame for 23 years and he's now at the Atlanta Hawks. But
Mike remembers when he was at Notre Dame, no one believed in sleep, that sleep was important to
the athletes and he would be at Notre Dame and you know, they would, they would never talk about
sleep. And then some cockamamie people started showing up being like, Hey, we should really
work on sleep with your athletes. And half of the department was like, nah, that's a waste.
They're college kids are going to stay up late. Who cares? And so there,
there were people pushing this, this importance of sleep. Well, fast forward now, sleep is a major
part of training and the same thing with nutrition. And I laugh about this when we were in college,
nutrition did not exist. We got $5. You went to McDonald's after a game pregame was candy on the
bus. Like, I mean, it just didn't matter. And we were elite athletes. Nutrition just wasn't
something that was focused on. Now you go to college campuses and pro facilities.
I mean, food is the fuel. So, you know, whenever people dismiss advances in technology or methods
of training or prevention, you know, I get it. There's a tipping point, a learning curve. And I
believe this is just one of them. People have to understand there is a way to mitigate risk.
And if you can wear it, you should do it and do everything you can to try to put yourself in the
best position to stay safe and stay available. Yeah. And we understand a lot more about,
yeah.
Head and concussion too. And in our era, there was a saying that injuries above the neck don't
count. Just say your name and go back out again. And that's how archaic it was. And we have come
a long way. You mentioned a fiance, Mike Bray, legendary coach of Notre Dame and now at the
Atlanta Hawks and two young athletes in your house, two boys that I believe are great athletes
in their own right. Can you tell us a bit about, they're growing up surrounded by sporting success
with their mom and their home front. What's that like?
For you as a parent, what sort of leader are you on the home front?
Yeah. I had great mentors to look up to, which were my parents. And Mike will say the same thing. So
Mike and I both grew up in households where our fathers were high school coaches, high school ADs
and educators. And so we had the same background, right? I grew up in a gym. My dad, I followed him
around. He was the high school basketball coach, the wrestling coach, the baseball coach. He was
my idol. I followed him around. I was a gym coach. I was a basketball coach. I was a basketball coach.
I was a gym rat. Mike was the same way. And the thing that we both talk about that made the
biggest impression on us is that our parents never put any pressure on us to be successful
on the field. It just was such a calming environment where they gave us opportunities
to compete and they supported us in every way. But there was never this expectation or pressure.
In fact, my dad wouldn't even talk to me after a game. I would be dying to talk to him after a game.
How would you think of this layup? When I miss this, what did I do here? He wouldn't talk about
it unless I brought it up with him. He would get in the car. He'd never say a word. If I made a
mistake, he never talked about it. My mom was the same way. Mike's parents were the same way. So
we have a very strong opinion about that. We do not encourage the boys to
take things to heart. They're young. They're learning. You're supposed to enjoy the game.
Be well-rounded. We both are multi-sport athletes. My children are multi-sport athletes. We think
that's healthy, healthy for their mind, healthy for their body. We just have probably a little
bit more of a relaxed environment. But we also are very passionate about schoolwork and teamwork,
that you got to do your schoolwork, got to be good in school,
but ultimately you got to be a great teammate. And that might mean you're not the best on the
team or you score the most goals or you're the best defender, but you better be the best leader
you can be and be the best teammate. And a lot of times after practice or a game,
instead of asking how you did or what you think, it's always, did you try to lead today? Were you
helpful to your teammates? Did you encourage your teammates? Were you a confidence giver to your
teammates? Because ultimately, Mike was the best confidence.
To his athletes. I learned that from him. And I want my children to understand that giving
confidence to your teammate is priceless. And your teammate will appreciate that and look to you for
that. It's a real piece of wisdom you've just shared. I love hearing it. I love asking that
question because I often find that the successful athletes that have kids of their own totally get
that. And I see this other really ugly parenting thing that's happening in junior sport around the
parents are the opposite, screaming from the sidelines, conversation in the car on the way
home often kills the passion for sport with their kids because they are all about why didn't you
score more or why didn't you play like your teammate? And so to hear people who are at the
professional end and understanding the way that you just described is such a great thing. I want
to go back to ask you about Under Armour. What an incredible story that is. Kevin Plank was a 23-year
old captain of the United States. He was a 23-year-old captain of the United States. He was a
football team to go and really take on Nike and Lululemon, these huge big apparel brands with
success. When you look back at Under Armour and you were there right from the start, you had 17
years. Why was that such a success in your mind? God, Under Armour was such a special place and I
have so much love for the brand and all the people still there. And it just was such a magical time
to be a part of something. But Kevin is fabulous. He's as fabulous as you can imagine.
His ability to lead and grow a business out of, you know, his grandmother's basement home is just
remarkable. What I love the most about it, and I was so fortunate, you know, you mentioned I played
at Loyola, which is a small school in Baltimore. I like to say we're a small school, but we were
mighty on the field. We competed division one lacrosse. So we were a 3000 undergrad, small,
private Jesuit Catholic school.
But we competed with, you know, the University of North Carolina's and the University of Maryland's
and the Duke's and the Virginia's and these really great big schools. And so we were the
underdog in our league and we loved it. We thrived on it. I enjoy that mentality. I carry it with me
every day. I carry it with me in high school because I'm, you can't tell, but I'm only five
foot one. So I was always the smallest. I was always the runt of the litter. And so I always
had this chip on my shoulder and always felt like an underdog.
And so I really connected with Loyola in that way, when they were recruiting and I was making
a decision where to go, and I didn't have a lot of offers to be quite honest, cause
I'm five foot one. So I had this really strong passion at Loyola for taking me and loving
me. And I wanted to do all I could for them back. And it comes back to Under Armour because
we were in Baltimore and Kevin has started the company in Baltimore. And so, you know,
here's this young guy rolling up to our field and he's bringing these two guys. And we're
like, what the heck are you doing with this young guy? And he's like, what are you doing?
He's like, you know, you know what? He's running from the field. And you know, you know, he's bringing
stretchy shirts and he's giving them to our coach saying, Hey, you know, I got this new shirt. I
played football down the road at the university of Maryland. It like makes you feel good. It
licks the moisture off of you. Will you guys try it? So our coaches were like free gear. Sure.
So they're handing us these stretchy lingerie, like t-shirts. And we were just like, Oh my God,
free gear. We'll take it. So we started wearing it and we would go play, you know, Princeton and
go play Duke and go play, um, you know, all these schools up in Boston. And we line up on the circle
and the girl next to me would go, what are you wearing? And I'd be like, I'm wearing Under Armour.
You don't know what Under Armour is. You know, like, you don't know, like Under Armour is the
best. It like is the best on base layer. So we felt so special because we had something
that all these other big schools didn't have. So that is where my love affair with Under Armour
started. I really believed in the product. And for the record, he created a category,
right? Performance apparel did not exist. Performance footwear did. And Nike did a
great job with the waffle trainer and wonderful, but we were wearing champion cotton men's t-shirts
and shorts and champion cotton men's sweats and sweatpants. There was no synthetic fibers. There
was no more.
That did not exist. And so it truly was an amazing product that worked. And so I wore it all through
college. Um, when I got out, I coached for a year. I was a collegiate coach at Towson down the road
and I had made a relationship with the Under Armour guys at that point. So there were three
kind of co-owners, Kevin and two, two partners. And one of the partners called me and said, Hey,
I heard you're taking a job at Towson. That's fabulous. Can we sponsor you guys? Can I give
your girls base layer?
And I was like, sure. Like we'll take free gear. We're a college team. We don't have anything.
And so we, we played a season and I realized quickly, I was, I love to play the sport. I
wasn't ready to be a spectator. So I didn't enjoy the coaching side of it at that point. And
Ryan called me back and said, Hey, you know, we're gonna, we're gonna give you another year
sponsorship. And I said, Ryan, that's great, but I don't think coaching's for me. I'm going to try
something else.
And he was like, Oh, great. He's like, well, would you come and interview with us? Because
we are a company of men and we need some females to come in and help go talk to other college
teams, women's teams, soccer, field hockey, softball, because right now our whole division
is men and we're having a hard time breaking through. And so I was like, sure. I'll come
interview. I actually went and interviewed at a lacrosse company and was offered a job with them
um,
for double the pay and a better at a better title for the record. But I went to Under Armour,
I interviewed with them and the DNA match was just so incredible. It was like, I knew the
product was great. It was a bunch of young, hungry, underdog kind of guys that were fighting,
you know, these behemoths out West. And I was like, you know what, you offer me half the money
and no title, but dang it, like I'm in. And that was the start of it. And so I spent,
um, my first few years there, cold calling every division one football school on the East coast.
So I would show up, walk down the corridors of universities. So I was, I was cold calling at a
very young age, which is very intimidating. And I'd walked in and down the hallways and I'd knock
on the doors and I'd say, Hey, I just happened to be in town. I'm with Under Armour. Have you
ever heard of this stuff? And, you know, I talked to the softball coach and the women's lacrosse
coach and the field hockey coach and the baseball coach and the softball coach. And, you know,
these guys, they're, they're, they're, they're, they're, they're, they're, they're, they're,
people at that time were like, man, I've never heard of this. And no one's ever called on me
before because at that era, these big university deals did not exist. It was very much the football
team got whatever they wanted and everyone else just was ignored. So we spent a lot of time
nurturing relationships with people that don't usually have someone call on them and did that
for three years, made incredible relationships, sold to schools.
That you would not, you know, would have never had anything to do with us. And then
that eventually turned into outfitting entire universities and coming at it from a marketing
side point, you know, standpoint instead of, of sales. But it was just such an incredible
environment to learn in because everyone was learning together. We were so young
and just so hungry. It was so cool and such an underdog, which I totally related to.
What a brilliant, brilliant story. And to a global,
success. And as you said, starting with great product, but I love the way you told that of
literally cold calling door to door and building an incredible business on the back of it.
We all are born different. As we grow, the experiences we have develop into outlooks,
uniquely our own. Charting our life's course. No one sees an idea, opinion or opportunity like you.
And no one sees you like VU. Victoria University. Uniquely you.
My name's Gabrielle. I'm studying law. What made me want to get into law is I guess the reward you
get after the feelings that you get for helping other people. I'm really passionate about making
sure that people have that voice, especially for people that don't feel like they can be heard. And
that's something that's really important to me. I have quite deep personal values. So it was really
important to me to find a university that aligns with those values. And VU is that for me.
Love you to check out our signature program, Alita Connect. Several hundred people from a
range of backgrounds, sport, industry, social venture, the arts, come together
in groups of five to six to learn, to connect and collaborate. We'd love to speak to you.
Vanessa Ford, Chief Operating Officer at Kukua.
The Alita Connect experience for me has been transformational. I met people that I would
never have met from totally different spheres. And it's very basic. It's all about relationships.
It's all about how we communicate. And what the Alita Connect group does that is so powerful
is when you bring two people from two totally different worlds together, there's no ego.
It just leaves room for the real you. And I think that's what Alita gave me was bringing
back the real me and really connecting to my own leadership style.
We have this saying that success leaves clues. And I love sitting down and hearing your story and
the sort of patterns that emerge from different leaders in different environments. And this idea
of self-leadership, I want to ask you, how do you make you feel your best so that you can lead
others? What do you do specifically for yourself so that you can fill your own cup up?
Yeah, I'm very much in the weeds type of leader. So not micromanaging because that's different.
I'm in the weeds in that I really,
like knowing what you're doing. And so you feel like you're being supported because I've been
there or I understand what you're going through. And so my coach in college, who is this legendary
woman, the late Diane Jeffy Akins, who you've probably heard Stacey, one of your co-workers
talk about. She was just an incredible mentor along with my parents. And Mike, she's really
been the most influential person in my life. And she had this one saying, and, and she,
she would say it about me and it made me so proud. She would say, Suzanne walks the walk
and she talks the talk. And I really live by that. Like, I really want everyone, whether they're on
my team or I'm working with them to know that like, I'm not above anything. I will be in the
trenches with you. We are doing this together. Like, how do we get through this? How do we make
mistakes together? How do we get wins together? But just this real team mentality and this,
this confidence that, you know, I, I can imagine it because I've been there or I can imagine it
because I can, I can empathize with you. And, and so that, that's how I look at leadership.
I've also, especially in the world of Under Armour, I just was always patient
because I think patience is something that helps you stay in the moment. And so I looked at Under
Armour, like every opportunity was a chance to learn something. And I think that's, I think,
something that I, I had no idea what I was doing. You know, like you can go to college and get a
degree, but that's not a substitute for like doing it and living in it. And so with, with Under Armour,
I just was incredibly patient and really took joy in all the different roles I had. I mean,
over 17 years, you really grow and change and do different things. And so I would say walking the
walk, talking to talk, and then being patient is really, um, what, what I stay true to.
Yeah. I love that concept of, uh, as you said, walking the walk, talking to talk. What's the
one piece of leadership advice that you pass on the most? Um, I got it from Mike and I use it all
the time, which is be a confidence giver. Um, that doesn't mean you don't speak true and
transparent with people because I think people that want to develop and learn, you know, if they
truly want to develop and learn, they truly want to be coached. And that means they want
really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really,
real feedback. So that doesn't mean you're getting false confidence. That means that you're
giving people transparent feedback. That's constructive, but then you're doing it in a way
that if you see potential in them, that breeds confidence. And, you know, I was a very coachable
young woman, very coachable in high school. I was very coachable in college. And that's because I
loved getting feedback. And I always knew that if a coach was taking the time to correct me
or work with me, I was going to be a coachable young woman. And I was going to be a coachable
young woman. And I always knew that if a coach was taking the time to correct me,
it meant that I had potential and they saw something in me. When a coach ignores you,
that means they're done, right? They've tried and they didn't get through to you.
They don't see the value in wasting more time on you. And so I always feel like when I,
you know, find someone that I'm working with and I can coach them or give them confidence or help
them, you know, if they're really coachable, they want that and they embrace it. And even at
Under Armour, I love it. I love it. I love it. I love it. I love it. I love it. I love it. I love it.
I love it. I love it. I love it. I love it. I love it. I love it. I love it. I love it. I love it. I love it. I love it.
like i love getting feedback good bad ugly all of it because i just feel like it means that there's
something there's potential in me to continue to get better and i i'm very coachable with that and
and i also think that you know getting transparent feedback is healthy and that people that really
want to grow and learn appreciate it even when it's hard i love that the idea of being a confidence
giver we've all been under coaches or leaders that are confidence takers and that uh is debilitating
as you said not uh false uh feedback or not avoiding it but i love the way you described
that i want to talk to you about vision you've been involved in projects that have got a big
vision under armor was a huge bold plan when you think about it and q collar is addressing an
enormous challenge in the world of sport at the moment how do you go about not only setting a
vision like that but being able to deliver that within your team being authentic your vision has
to be authentic that was the best thing about under armor
everything we did was authentic authentic down to the i mean it was just rooted in sport by real
athletes that truly understood the culture even at q collar our vision is very much based in
authenticity and by that i mean we do not pay people to speak about the product we don't pay
people to say they like it our journey has been slow and has been up a steep mountain
and part of it is slow because we have been very very
committed to finding athletes who want to understand the problem want to address the
problem believe in the science and the technology and then truly believe that wearing it is important
to them and it's become a part of their ritual it's not something that they're paid for now
there are tons of marketing agreements out there um that we call transactional and they're beautiful
right like there's cars and food and drinks and all that stuff and and that those relationships
are wonderful and unique and i think that's what i'm trying to do is i'm trying to make sure that
we're not just selling things to people who need those and they do sell things our product is just
so unique you can't live in that world so you either love it and you believe in it and you
want to wear it or there's not enough money in the world to make you say you are and the analogy i use
and athletes like this is i say it's like me paying you to be vegan no amount of money can
make you turn down steak and butter because if you want to eat steak and butter you're going to eat it
now if you want to be vegan because you believe that's the best thing for your body and your
performance it's like you're going to be vegan and you're going to be vegan and you're going to be
a lot easier to be vegan and so i tell athletes like that's that's the nature of our business you
have to really believe in the device and wear the cue collar and then once you do then there's
sponsorship opportunities and marking opportunities for your time effort energy you know off the field
um and under armor was the same way we just found truly authentic athletes right lindsey vaughn and
michael phelps and god jordan spieth they were truly steph curry i mean he was truly an authentic
athlete in that he was a true authentic athlete and he was a true authentic athlete and he was
like he believed in the product believed in the brand and that's who you that's who you hit your
wagon to um the other side of that is that you can have great vision and still make mistakes which
i have plenty of great mistake stories i could share with you um you can have great vision and
still fall short and have mistakes but if if the vision and the authenticity is there you can get
beyond it and you can rebound but you have to be rooted in that that true authentic relationship
when i sit down and have these conversations i find
people like you're intentionally curious because of the way that you are and that's what's led to a
lot of success can you share is there a late latest rabbit hole of curiosity that's taking
you somewhere of interest that you could share with us god i i have really gotten into wearable
tech and it's almost like become too much of an exception of obsession you know the aura rings
the heart rate monitors sleep i mean it's like i'm checking my phone every day i mean like
how much i'm checking my phone every day i'm checking my phone every day i'm checking my phone
how much how much of it was good you know my heart rate was it elevated so like the whole
wearable tech thing is very addicting um which i think the companies know and i think especially
women of my age you know um i've gotten very into researching like creatine so i think this is so
funny when i was at loyola so early 2000s um we after weightlifting we had a trainer and he would
give us creatine and we'd be chugging it and we'd be chugging it and we'd be chugging it and we'd be
chugging creatine and like you know we're like bench pressing 100 pounds and like you know we
were just like rocks you know and then we kind of all got a little bit like um creatine is making
us get big like this isn't right we shouldn't be doing creatine now 25 years later it's like
women drink eat creatine and i'm like it's coming full circle so i have definitely um have been
diving down the creatine hole as well right now yeah i remember the uh the creatine uh
as well of time that's interesting that it's come back uh full circle and um yeah i've a young uh
athlete in my house uh doing the same um i want to talk to you about this idea of uh collaboration
we're really passionate about we love this quote the cost of leadership is time and i look at you
as a mother of two boys you've got your work at cucola and the demands of life how do you balance
that all out and still uh collaborate and and foster the culture that you want in all the
environments that you're in yeah i think it's a really good question and i think it's a really good
one i um probably right after i had my children i realized very quickly you cannot have it all
and that is a false narrative that people say you can have it all just go have it all everything
will be just the way you want it to be in reality you need to prioritize what is important to you
and not everything can be important and so i make very distinct decisions on what is going to be a
priority and what is not now i'm not a teacher i'm not a teacher i'm not a teacher i'm not a teacher
they can change different phases of life. Different things can phase in and phase out.
Nothing's written in stone. But I make those priorities clear to myself, my teammates who I
work with, my family, my children, you know, Mike, like we're very clear on, you know, right now in
our phase, maybe we're not going to have a bunch of home cooked meals, right? That's going to have
to be neglected because we're going to have to be working on calls in the evening. But that doesn't
mean we can't have great family time. We'll find it in a different way. So we're just very clear on
priorities. Holidays are another one, right? Like Mike's season has always been basketball. So we're
always right through Thanksgiving and Christmas in the heart of holidays. Well, sometimes you have
to sacrifice the holidays, but you make it up in different ways. And so I've just been uber clear
about make priorities, communicate with those around you what those priorities are. You know,
once you do that, you're going to be able to do a lot of things. And so I've just been
you have a clear head and a clear heart because you know that you've made a decision and, you know,
you're not trying to be fake and fill in the gaps that you can't with everybody.
So priorities for me are just super important. And that leads to the other dimension I want
to talk to you about. And that's the crystal clear communication, which is what you alluded
to, isn't it? That you can substitute some things on the basis that you're really clear
with your communication. Have you got a mantra about the way you've communicated in
all the spaces?
Yeah. So I have so many great mentors. I had one mentor who he was an Under Armour and he was a
great salesman and great marketing, but really had a sales knack. And he would always say to me,
most people make the mistake because they talk too much. Say less, listen more and say less.
Let people be heard, empathize with people.
And then once you get what you came for, get out, shut up. People don't want you to monopolize
their time. Be respectful of their time. And so I found that early on in my days at UA and has
stayed with me. It is more about listening. A good communicator can listen, actually hear what the
client or the person you're working with is in need of, where the gaps are, and then find a way
to help be a solution. And I think that's really important. And I think that's really important.
And you do that in real life too. You do that with your kids. You do that with your husband,
your spouse. You really listen to what's going on before you have an opinion, before you say
something. Yeah. Great bit of wisdom to share as well. And it's just often people talk about that
great listening is the ultimate form of communication. Suzanne, who's been the greatest
leader in your life? So many great leaders. I do have to say, Diane, Jeffy Akins, my coach in
college. I just, I have to say, I have to say, I have to say, I have to say, I have to say, I have to say,
I have to say, I have to say, I have to say, I have to say, I have to say, I have to say, I have to say,
I have such a soft spot for team athletics and collegiate athletics in particular. It was such a
pivotal time in my life of figuring out who you are and kind of growing up and realizing that you
can be a part of something really big and not have a personal agenda, right? It wasn't about you
or yourself. It was about the team. And so the lessons that she taught me about that just have
carried me through life in so many different ways. And I think that's really important.
But the other side of it is she was such a powerful woman. And to that point in my life,
I had not seen a lot of what I call CEO women. She was a CEO. She ran a team. She ran camps in
the summer. She ran her team like a business. She had to put together her roster. She had to
put together her staff. I mean, it was a full-time job and she had four kids. And to see a woman like
that as a young lady, it was like, my mind was like blown. And I think that's one of the things
I was like, oh my gosh, this woman, she is a boss. And I had had wonderful females in my life
before in high school, but you didn't see them like that. You weren't with them 24 hours a day
like we were with Diane. And so I just have to put her on that pedestal. She was just an incredible
influence in my life. And Suzanne, I understand she was going through a significant cancer battle
right throughout that time as well. To think of the influence you had on you and so
many of the athletes under her care. She's a mother of four, running businesses and putting
that together. It's incredible, isn't it? And that must have been a heartbreaking time as well
to see the person that was that great mentor struggling at the time as well.
She, Luke, she taught me the ultimate lesson, which I carry with me every day. And that lesson
was perspective. Something you cannot learn as a young person when everything is going right.
But here we were, 20 years old,
our whole goal in life was to win a national championship. Nothing else mattered, right?
Here's a 40-year-old woman with four children, dying of a brain tumor, her fourth one in 10 years.
And she would come to practice every day and just be like, ladies, take a minute. Let's look at the
sunrise at 6 a.m. Ladies, you know, let's all take a moment to really thank each other for
how hard we worked today. So here's a woman that could have been angry and sad and pissed off.
She was driving so hard and pissed off that she was dealing with this illness.
And then she said something to us that, you know, the day she told us she got sick December leading
into our season. You know, we're a spring sport. So she called us all into a meeting in December.
We're about to go on winter break for a month. She said, ladies, I have to tell you something.
I got a report back from the doctors and my brain tumor is back. And this time it's Warmeling
and it will kill me. And I was like, you know, I'm in a hospital. I'm in a hospital. I'm in a Powell alibaba.
And this time it's inoperable. And it is it will kill me.
so we're in this room our mouths are agape we're about you know everyone's crying
and she stopped and she said but I don't want any of you to feel sorry for me
because I get to say goodbye to all the people I love in my life I get to hug my children
I get to be with them the folks that went to work on 9-11 had no idea they would never see
their families again those people we feel sorry for we do not feel sorry for people like me
I get to live my life to the fullest that was her message to us I mean talk about perspective
like I just changed the way I faced every bit of adversity in my life you know you're sitting
in traffic really you're gonna be that upset about it you know what is the you're going through a
hard day is it really that hard is it really that's you know it's like you just learn to flip
things and instead of feeling sorry or thinking it's the end of the world you think
a million people out there that have it worse than me like what an extraordinary extraordinary
perspective isn't it sounds like a remarkable woman to have someone like that in your life and
the way you talk about her um is incredible isn't it the legacy that lives on through
that as a as a 20 year old to have that uh is quite extraordinary we are a bit obsessed with
this idea of collaboration in our world of a leader and what happens when you put great people
together from diverse backgrounds and the magic that often happens you've been able to collaborate
with some remarkable people in the world of Under Armour and what you're doing with Q Collar and
your own athletic career and seeing that everywhere has there been someone you thought wow
in any of your passions in life I'd love to connect and collaborate with that person is
there a name that springs to mind you know the thing I would tell you is that and you've probably
seen this more than not there are so many more people you you have so much more in common with
people than you think you think you're so different or your worlds are so different and then when you
get to talking to them you realize oh my gosh we're so much the same like it's just and it's
and sport is that red thread it just carries through which is just why it's such a a brilliant
brilliant thing to be a part of that's a great question you know I I would love to be a part of
some of these women team athletes National Women's Soccer League you know we the U.S.
national team I would love to work with with some of these athletes at that level
I have an incredible amount of jealousy for Olympic sport athletes
because when I was growing up lacrosse was not an Olympic sport so the dream of being an Olympian
I never got to you know work towards and so I look at you know Olympians in just this oh you know
amazing light that they get to represent their country which is just such an honor and I'm so
patriotic and so I love to do some collabs with some Olympic teams some you know national team
soccer players we've had a chance you know to get to work with some of these women team athletes
get with some of these these athletes and just really be a part of the world we at least fake it
for a little bit well it's been a great pleasure to spend some time with you Suzanne thanks for
taking the time the work that you and the team at Kukola are doing may be life-changing for many
people around the globe I'm sure there's a lot of interest in it I can hear your passion for it
it's coming from the the heart of a mother wanting her boys to play the sport they love and maybe
you couldn't get a more authentic path than that and really appreciate it it's a an incredible life
story it feels like many chapters to come so thanks for joining me thanks for having me Luke it was wonderful