Our next guest on the Empowering Leaders podcast is a brilliant story, Nicholas Stone.
You're going to get an enormous amount of wisdom from this chat.
He'll talk about his sense of well-being and connection for his locals, as he calls them,
at the cafes, Bluestone Lane, that he has successfully created around the US.
And referring to his staff as teammates, you're going to hear Nick Stone talk about being
on track for a really successful time in banking, but he bet the farm on his cafe venture, Bluestone
Lane, that has been a great Australian hospitality success story.
He talks about the importance of focusing on what you can control if you want to execute
your idea.
And you'll hear about the celebrity A-list customers that turbocharged Bluestone Lane
in the US, Sarah Jessica Parker, Cameron Diaz, Leonardo DiCaprio, and the incredible Malcolm
Gladwell becoming a daily customer at his Bluestone Lane cafes.
It's people like Nick Stone that inspire the work that we do at Alita.
We'd love you to have a look at our signature Alita Connect program.
We bring together people like Nick Stone from different backgrounds around the globe
in groups of five or six bespoke leadership groups.
We call it Alita Connect.
We'd love to connect with you, whether you're starting your own business or working in education
or sport or industry of the arts.
The diversity of thinking is what we think is a real superpower, bringing people together
in these facilitated groups.
So head to alitacollective.com.
You can book a discovery call.
We'd love to connect with you and tell you more about the work we're doing at Alita.
Huge thanks.
Thanks, as always, to the team at Temper Australia and New Zealand, to Jason Nicholson,
his team, the extraordinary support that they give us in bringing stories like this to the
table.
Thank you to Temper.
Sleep and recovery, as we know, are crucial in achieving success in all aspects of life.
And then investing in your sleep and your success has never been easier.
And the Empowering Leaders podcast has partnered with Temper.
And we want to give listeners to this podcast a chance to unlock their success with a Temper
Pro soft mattress.
It's valued at just under $9,000.
So you can feel empowered by a good night's sleep.
Now, this is a brilliant opportunity.
I promise you, sleeping on one of these mattresses is going to be a great experience.
Can't wait to give it away to one of the regular listeners to the Empowering Leaders podcast.
You can check out the Alita Collective website for more information on how to enter to win.
So simply go to alitacollective.com.
We'll have all the details there and look forward to giving away one of the magnificent
Temper Pro soft mattresses valued at just under $9,000.
Head to alitacollective.com.
For your chance to win.
Nicholas Stone began his professional career as an Australian rules footballer playing
20 games for Hawthorne and St. Kilda from 2002 to 2005.
His next chapter included more than a decade in corporate finance, including an extended
stint with the ANZ based in New York City.
It was while living in the Big Apple and working in banking, Nick started his side hustle,
opening his first Bluestone Lane coffee shop in midtown Manhattan.
Bluestone has expanded to more than 60 stores across the country.
He has been backed by sophisticated US billionaire investors and is truly an awesome international
Australian hospitality success story.
Nick, it's always great to see you.
Thanks for joining me today.
Pleasure, Luke.
Thank you.
Yeah, great to be here.
And you obviously were in the States recently, so I'm ashamed we couldn't catch up there,
but great to connect.
Well, that is funny, mate, isn't it?
I was up in Seattle, a town I'd never been to before, and any time I'm in the US, you
go, I've got to find a place to live.
I've got to find a place to live.
And I sent you a message and said, mate, I'm struggling here.
I'm going to have to go to the dark side and buy a Starbucks coffee.
And you said, mate, you're in the home of Starbucks.
We haven't quite gone to Seattle to take on Starbucks there, but maybe in the future,
Nick.
In the future.
I was actually up there a few months ago.
There's a new Gordon Ramsay production that's about to come out.
It's a bit like The Apprentice, but for culinary candidates.
And I'm actually one of the guest judges on this program.
And it's going to air in a few, it's going to air in a couple of months in the States.
And I think they had, without a doubt, either Howard Schultz or the CEO designate penciled
in to be the judge.
But I got this late call and I had to be there within a matter of days.
And sure enough, I was the ring in.
But yeah, in the heart of Starbucks, it's good that I was there.
And ultimately, we've got to put a plan to flag on the ground and get a blue sign open.
Well, I love that.
That's the level you're at now, isn't it?
You get the call from the production team from Gordon Ramsay.
Come up and get involved.
You look at the numbers, Nick.
I love the courage of what you did.
75% of hospitality ventures in New York City fail within five years.
You'd never worked a day at hospitality in your life.
Pretty bold move when you look at it to open Bluestone Lane right in the middle of Manhattan.
Tell us about your thought process.
Yeah, repeating it back, it does get me questioning my decision making.
But yeah.
Ultimately, Bluestone was created because I missed it myself.
It was out of self-necessity.
When I moved to the States in 2010, I was at business school and I had an opportunity to work on a project.
And I was thinking about a tech-based business.
But ultimately, I settled on coffee because I just thought that Australians, we do it so well, this independent coffee culture.
We'd proven that Starbucks and that chain mentality couldn't scale in our home market.
And yeah.
I just thought there's this opportunity based on the success of, and the limited, honestly, the limited competition in my eyes.
Because Starbucks, even though at that point in time probably had about 20,000 locations, it just, their proposition was so different from what I was accustomed to or what we as Australians are regularly accustomed to.
So, you know, ultimately started becoming a student of the industry.
And I had a very myopic view that it was fraught with danger.
And the mortality.
The mortality rate was very high, but ultimately decided to do one as a bit of an experiment while I was still in banking.
And then it just sort of developed from there.
So, you know, we're still learning and iterating, but we couldn't have forecasted what was to come over the past sort of nine, nearly 10 years.
And with COVID and the change of the way people, how they work and where they work, and we've had a lot of other fascinating and exhilarating experiences.
But, you know, it's something I'm very proud of and grateful for the team and what they've put together.
It's an incredible story, Nick, all around.
And you're right.
You look at the Americans consume their coffee, probably Dunkin' Donuts initially, and then Starbucks became this, you know, behemoth, but a very different experience to what you brought to the table.
An Australian coffee brand, when you think about it, it's an unlikely play, isn't it, for Americans to get their head around?
Why do you think it's worked in the U.S.?
Why do you think you've been able to get this cult following?
Well, if you think about the history of coffee in the States, this was very much a drip, drip coffee.
So the big one litre, one gallon jug that percolated, that would sit on the desk and it's played out in all these sitcoms and comics that we know of.
Ultimately, Starbucks were the one that were the catalyst towards this espresso movement.
And that happened in the 80s, sort of in the late 80s, 90s, Howard Schultz.
Went to Italy and decided, I'm going to partner with this group and convince them that retail is the pathway forward.
Starbucks was originally just a coffee bean retailer.
You go in to buy coffee beans and grind to make coffee at home.
But Schultz had this view about building these cafes, which really were based upon the Italian experience that he fell in love with.
So for us, we didn't have a drip coffee culture in Australia.
We were.
We had a tea based drinking culture, which was influenced from the British.
And then, you know, if you think about what happened pre and post World War Two, we had mass migration from West and Southern Europe and they brought their espresso machines, the Italians and the Greeks and the Maltese.
And and ultimately the coffee culture sort of began.
We shifted and then it's just continued to reimagine itself with the introduction of more sophisticated breakfast foods, lunch foods and really coffee.
As we know it in Australia and how I think about it is really just the ability to connect with someone.
Coffee shops facilitate connection and it's just such an incredible social medium and it's something that's more accessible.
It's daytime, not alcohol.
It's often cheaper and we've just made it our own.
And that independent movement has has had so much creativity and that that was the opportunity I saw in the states that the consumption of coffee was super high.
You didn't have to.
Educate the consumer about drinking coffee.
It was just appreciating it in a different way and introducing them to different different food that can complement coffee and then designing spaces that foster that atmosphere of human connection.
And that's one thing the Australians do exceptionally well, that that eye for detail on the atmospheric elements, that the vibe.
And that was something that I really thought with Bluestone.
That's how we can introduce our brand in a more powerful way.
By these environments where people feel that it's aspirational, yet it's still accessible.
And that's probably the underpin the secret of Bluestone building this premium brand that stands for so much more than just being product orientated, that it's really about the way we make people feel through service and hospitality.
I hadn't really thought about when you just expressed that way post-World War Two and the mass Italian Greek migration, the Maltese community.
And as you said, they brought their machines.
Didn't they?
And we know those families.
It's a city that you and I have lived in for a long period of time.
And my great friends, the dim of Tina's had mocha pan coffee, which was one of the first Lavazza, you know, was a famous brand.
And you probably realize that that started, as you said, this whole community based thing.
It isn't so loyal to your local coffee shop here in Melbourne.
I recently changed walking paths and I've got this guilt around not going back to my my latte from from because I want to say hello and connect.
And you feel like you owe them something because of the joy they give you.
And you brought that to the US, didn't you, with the flat white had never been heard of before.
And then also, you know, avocado on toast, stuff that we, you know, as routine here.
That was revolutionary in the US, wasn't it?
Well, that's right.
You know, when when we launched the avocado smash in 2013, no one, no one knew what we were talking about.
Now it's ubiquitous.
So I think that's a signal of how successful it's been.
But same with the flat white.
When it was put on the core menu at Starbucks, the acknowledgment from the green siren is pretty impressive.
Honestly, thirty four thousand stores may decide to add the flat white, which is a beverage really only found in Australia, New Zealand.
It's it's pretty amazing.
And that focus on being a local, not having customers on having locals.
And that's what you're talking about, Luke, that that relationship, you know, in Australia, making good coffee is just a ticket to participate.
It's not it's not an element that's going to necessarily underpin your success.
And you have to have good coffee.
That's just a lay down there.
But you really want to foster that relationships.
And I found that it was pretty transactional through the commercial success of Starbucks that that you can just focus so much more on being on investing in that relationship with your locals where, you know, the name, face and order.
And I used to walk out of where we worked on Collins Street.
And there'd be 15 coffee shops.
We'd have a coffee shop.
We'd get in a couple of hundred meters and everyone had their had their local and they would advocate for them unsolicitedly.
You would and you would really have to convince someone to come with you to yours because everyone feels like they didn't want to cheat on their local.
So, you know, those those elements, those artisanal elements are existing in the states.
When I moved there, I could see what was going on with the class fitness revolution, just the way that people would would do anything to get in a certain soul cycle classes.
There's one class that my wife and I used to take 7 a.m.
every Tuesday in NoHo, and it would release the class seven days in advance.
And if you didn't secure your spot within 30 minutes of that going, going live, you weren't coming in because people were using it as a way, yes, the endorphins of getting fit and working on your health and fitness.
But it was really that social that that that social media bumping into each other before you go in the class, the smiles on the on the treadmill.
The jokes, the music, the chat post class that, you know, those things that bring people together.
It's just so critically important.
And and right now, you know, if we think about our real purpose at Bluestone and I truly feel it is to be this human connection, this this this community where we bring people together and make them feel like they're part of something bigger and try to address some of the biggest societal issues, particularly with young people, is about isolation and sadness and loneliness.
And what's the.
Better place to go and connect with someone and have that ritual.
It's going to get a coffee.
It's just amazing how it can liberate the way that you feel and just give you a sense of being part of something larger than just the problems or whatever's going on in your your own discreet life.
It's it's funny you mentioned the SoulCycle craze that took off in America.
She sent you an email and said, Hey, can we push it back?
Because I've got my spin class this morning, which I even say those words out loud.
And I'm thinking, have I been reduced?
reduced from someone who used to exercise for a living to a spin class but a great mate of mine
started the spin kings he's on the board at St Kilda after you know Shane Warren's tragic
passing and said no we got to get our mates together and get healthy and it's that community
and and connection and you're sitting on a bike with you know a dozen mates and you're having a
laugh and you as you said you're connecting and community one of your investors and you've done
incredible job of raising capital along the way uh Nick and to take on that sophisticated level
of investor the owner of the Miami Dolphins Stephen Ross who also was a big shareholder
in Equinox Fitness and SoulCycle can you tell us about you know that that comes with a level
of accountability I assume when you take money off people who are uh pretty good at uh at what
they do what's that experience been like well there's a there's a level of accountability for
for any dollar you raise whether it's from Steve
and and Matt or uh so many of my friends and family that kicked in in the first time we
raised $350,000 you know I that's something I take very seriously and there is a lot of
responsibility and and we've had some really touch and go moments in COVID we lost 87% of
our revenue in two weeks and the amount of operating leverage or fixed costs in our business
to try and deal with such a deceleration of revenue is super hard but as it relates to
Steve
and and and Matt where they are the co-founders of RSE Ventures uh they you know Matt approached me
back in uh 2017 actually and and uh he was asking to meet and I didn't really know who Matt Higgins
was and I was probably a bit naive honestly and I didn't know a lot about Steve I knew about Related
which is the largest landlord in New York and but I just didn't know Steve was the chairman founder
of it and that they owned Equinox which owns SoulCycle and I didn't know that Steve was the
founder of Equinox and I didn't know that Steve was the founder of Equinox so I just didn't know
that Steve was the founder of Equinox so I just didn't know that Steve was the founder of Equinox
and that they'd have a ton of different investments across hospitality uh you're talking
Mamafuku, Milk Bar and Pizza, Bluestone, um Magnolia Cupcakes and then you have investments
in technology they were the first check-in to Vayner Gary Vaynerchuk's business uh and all of
his different levels he's branched off in um Steve owns the Miami Dolphins renovated the stadium
got the Superbowl there and he's been a big supporter of the Miami Dolphins and he's been a big supporter of the Miami Dolphins
the hard rock stadium now they have the f1 grand prix they have the miami open tennis there like
he's real visionary and then of course related which has been the largest uh private real estate
deal in u.s history in hudson yards on the west side of manhattan so he's a pretty just incredible
person and takes a lot of risk and he's a huge believer in entrepreneurs and when i met matt we
had he he met me downstairs we used to have our office above a store in lower manhattan at uh down
in uh water street and uh right near wall street and he walked in and i didn't realize he was
standing in the space and the and the store was a disaster there's just people everywhere and like
the staff i won't play the right music i won't wear the right aprons there was no engagement it
was sort of like oh god you know what do i do here and then matt said hi nick i'm matt higgins and i
haven't and i and he clearly felt a bit frustrated and i'm saying you know like everything's about
the connection you know it's not about the product and we ended up going upstairs and chatting for
probably two hours and uh we just clicked honestly i think he saw some alignment and values he saw
that i left uh at that stage a pretty you know on the track for a pretty successful career in banking
and i was willing to bet the farm to to grow something i was super passionate about this
is an investment we've got a great around it and he said he's been with me for over a decade so i'm
australian coffee culture in the u.s and um you know there was a bit of a story that that we had
a great meeting and then i got a text message i think later that night or the next day um after
i googled who matt higgins was and what he's achieved and you know pretty and now he's written
extraordinary book called burn the boats but um he said uh you know can you can you come to miami
on um on monday and i said oh yeah i can go to miami and sure enough uh the you know i had the
opportunity to be flown down there and uh pick up picked up at the airport and i was taken straight
to the game and when i got out there was someone to chaperone me that took me into the stadium
and straight through onto the ground and she gave me a pass and said yeah just hang here and we'll
come and get you and sure enough i'm standing in the middle of the field by myself it's
my
night football it's the dolphins verse um the pats the patriots and next thing tom brady walks
out and he's warming up standing next to me now i don't know if this is you know all part of the
theater but it was one of those moments like a kid from melbourne who never worked a day in
hospitality i'm standing in the middle of uh hard rock stadium watching the greatest of all time
warm up next to me and then i went into steve's suite and had the chance to uh watch the game
which the
dolphins actually won so um it sort of coalesced a pretty meaningful relationship it was a great
first impression that's for sure and uh you know it's just gone from there what a great story it's
what i love about the u.s isn't it the potential and the opportunity and and i love that you know
you you played um you know your first job as i said was afl football but the access you get in
in america blows me away lucky enough to see you a couple of times when we've been over doing radio
the super bowl and you put a media pass on and you are the rock star you're the rock star you're the rock star
you can go inside the dressing room they get it so well where the money comes from in america
and if uh you're part of the broadcast team you get access anytime anywhere i'm not surprised you
were standing next to the great uh tom brady and i think there's i think there's just an appetite
to support for one risk and to support entrepreneurs and that has been i've been
the recipient of that in such an extraordinary way i'm so grateful for it that
that americans just love people that give it a go and even crazy ideas that maybe the you and i
would say there's no way i'd put a dollar into that i think if you engender a level of passion
and excitement and and you personify the dedication the requisite dedication that's
going to be required there's going to be someone who's going to back you particularly in places
like new york where it's just a you know it is truly the world city it is a confluence of
wall street and finance with the the best in the arts world the fashion world um you know
thought leaders in a whole range of different domains and people are always coming in so
multicultural with different perspectives and ideas and just different disruptions and
very very fortunate to be in new york because i do think it gives you a big advantage when you
want to start something particularly consumer because you have a big eight million captive
audience and consumerism is a big part of it and i think it's a big part of it and i think it's a
Schema and retail is very tangible.
You can touch it and feel it's easy to explain.
And New Yorkers love that.
They love when they can explain the difference between Australian coffee culture and the
U.S.
It wasn't that hard, you know, versus some other businesses are more challenging if you're
building an algorithm in the back of some of the garage, you know, and what you go to
market strategy is, particularly if it's like business to business, just very different.
But New York magnifies that in a big way.
And there's always people that want to meet you and do different things.
And if you think about the density of the city, it's built up for these innocuous clashes
between people, right?
If you live in an apartment and there's 100 apartments and there's 250 people living in
one building, there's probably a good chance you're going to bump into someone as soon
as you step out the front of your door.
Where in Australia, you know, you might live in a street and, you know, you step out, you
might not run into anyone until you go to your local coffee shop or footy training or
something.
So those innocuous incidents give you a bit of an advantage as well as starting a business.
Yeah, a bit like your story, isn't it?
One of the most sophisticated investors in the world happens to know your coffee shop
and you get the chance to connect in that way.
And I've spoken to you about this before, you know, the Australian tall poppy syndrome
is a real thing, isn't it?
Where we like, you know, Nick Stone to do well.
We don't want you to do too well, though, because that's, you know, we'll try and cut
you down a level or two.
And I love the term that you use and the great support you've had.
The koala mafia is a great term, isn't it?
The expat Australian business people that have gone over and had success in the US who
get that entrepreneurial spirit in America without the tall poppy syndrome and can explain
just how supportive that community has been.
And I know you're a great support to other, you know, aspiring people who come to the
US.
It's a real community, isn't it, that works over there?
Yeah, I definitely think it's a difference in attitude from thinking about others as
competitive threats.
Rather than you're part of something that is trying to educate and grow a market where
everyone can do well.
And I think it really came apparent to me maybe a couple of years in that there's no
competition.
Everything's about working together and growing the awareness in the market and that we can
all coexist.
And I think I took, changed my attitude from like keeping all the secrets and withholding
information just to being an open book and being an available resource.
And.
It's amazing when you pay it back, like the amount of people that will pay it back to
you.
And when you're generous, people are more generous back.
And I do think it's very much in the US spirit.
And I also think it was, it aligned with a quote that I read from Reid Hoffman when he
said, no one owns a good idea.
Execution is everything.
And I just think that's a fabulous term that everyone's had an idea about opening a coffee
shop in the US or a suitcase company.
In the US or a new shoe company in the US, like on running, but everything's about execution.
And what's execution in the hospitality industry where you almost have no intellectual property.
Everything's about how the culture of the organization works.
And that is that permeates through your team and how they make people feel great.
So ultimately Bluestone only has one, one core tenant, and that is to have an amazing
human connection, focus culture.
And I think that's the key to the success of the company, because anyone can make great
coffee.
Anyone can make a great avocado smash, and anyone can do the majority of, of things that
you find out there, but it's all through that execution base.
And I think that when I read that I was like, stop worrying about people's ideas.
Stop worrying about competition.
Just focus on controlling, just focus on what you can control and executing.
And there's lots of opportunities for everyone.
And that, and, and certainly the koala mafia plays into that.
That.
These Australian entrepreneurs helping each other, supporting each other, advocating for
each other.
Um, it's been extraordinary and we are so lucky at Bluestone that that happened.
And it really underpinned, uh, you know, the first store in our, our success.
We opened it in midtown Manhattan around the corner from where I was working at two 70
park Avenue and JP Morgan building.
We're at 47th and park.
And we opened at a 40, between 49th and 50th on third Avenue, a class B, maybe class
C office tower with no anchor lead anchor tenant.
And it was down this mezzanine, um, subterranean sort of basement.
And, uh, you had no straight visibility.
You had no signage.
You went out, but I put a sandwich board at the front or decals.
You really could only find it through word of mouth.
And the people that got that going from the first day, I think we sold 400
coffees because all the Westpac guys, the ANZ, the Macquarie guys, the nab guys, all
people.
They're friends and they're American colleagues come down and try proper coffee,
come down and go to a Australian cafe.
And that's how it developed back then.
We were very Instagram.
It's sort of just started around 2013, but we weren't using Facebook and we didn't
have the budget for it.
And, and really ultimately like the best places you go to for someone telling you,
recommending to you, and that's how it works.
And, and I do think those Australians getting behind.
So you can just go to one of the best places in Australia and say, Hey,
I'm going to buy you an American coffee.
We're going to sell you a big cup of American coffee, which is a little bit
cheaper than the one you buy in Australia.
And you can just go to a local market, you can go to a local retailer,
you can buy a coffee and they'll sell you a big cup of American coffee.
So you can just spread the word.
You can just go to an Australian coffee shop and say, Hey,
this is fantastic.
We need more of this rather than, Oh, wow, that third store is not as good as
the first and they've lost their way and they're sold out in commercial.
Uh, you know, I don't, I just think it's a very, um, myopic way to look at things.
And I'd much rather be part of growing a bigger pie and supporting everyone.
It's a great quote, Reid Hoffman, the founder of LinkedIn.
I love it.
I love that.
It's such a healthier way to live too, Nicky, when you think about it.
And Simon Sinek talks about worthy rivals.
There's no competitors.
And having someone in your space do it well is actually brilliant because it inspires
you to be better and execute better, as you just articulated.
I mean, you started, Nick, with that brilliant word of mouth and the support from the Australian
community who only found it because they loved it and passed it on because they loved it.
But then you got some pretty good initial sort of celebrity organic traction, didn't
you?
Taylor Swift was a customer and a lot of the Victoria's Secret models.
And I love Malcolm Gladwell, the legendary author, said this,
Bluestone Lane is a force for good.
We need more brands like them.
How important was that to get that level of connection from well-known people?
Well, if we go back to when we opened, the first two stores, one was this midtown Manhattan
near where I live.
So I was in there and frequenting and trying to aggregate everyone to go down.
And then the second one we opened was next to the Stock Exchange, New York Stock Exchange
and Wall Street, 30 Broad Street, which used to, the Stock Exchange used to extend into
the building.
So it was a pretty historically significant building.
And we put a coffee shop in the lobby and it was 85 years old, never had a retail amenity.
And that was really busy too.
I remember we opened on my birthday back in 2013 and that was a cool day.
And then the next year in around May, June, we opened our first cafe, the broader offering,
table service, much broader menu, more seating.
And it was on the corner of Greenwich Avenue, it still is on the corner of Greenwich Avenue
and Perry Street.
And Perry Street, for those who've been through West Village, that's where Carrie Bradshaw
out of the series Sex and the City used to walk out those big doors on the top of the
stoop.
And Mr. Big would be down in the stretch limo and pick her up and take her off gallivanting
in New York City.
So, and my wife and I, well, back then, girlfriend and I, Alexandra, had always lived in West
Village.
And we lived around the corner from the spot, Perry and Greenwich Avenue.
And there was a store there and it used to be a barbershop.
And they'd gone out of business, another one of those stats that you read out earlier.
And we just think, I just could feel like this could be something magical.
And we went.
We went out opening it and we had Australian friends.
We had Australian designer.
We had Australian builder.
And that's why we named it Collective Cafe.
And we got it open and we didn't have enough money to put proper air conditioning in.
That was a big mistake.
We didn't have a proper kitchen.
But you're right, just out of the gate, it just took off.
And then you had the who's who walking in.
And obviously, when Taylor Swift came a couple of times and then it's Leonardo DiCaprio, it's
James Franco.
It was very serendipitous that we were positioned next to the number one spray tanning salon
in downtown Manhattan.
So you had all the Victoria's Secret girls coming in and all these actors and actresses.
It basically created a category.
That was, I think, the emergence of the Australian daytime premium cafe genre, which now extends
into all of the tier one cities in the world.
You're going to find.
And these types of cafes and it was the first time it was a really light beachy color, more
feminine with turquoise, seafoam, green tiles and white walls, walls and blonde timber and
just a place which had an atmosphere of being more inviting and more relaxing than the broody,
dark, reclaimed timber and blacks that you'd often find in Brooklyn and and a bit maybe
more hipster. And we were just a bit more fresh.
And it just accelerated.
And I used to see Malcolm went there every day, I think, for two years.
I'm sure he wrote a book there.
That thought was that he'd sit outside on the patio.
But that was a pretty significant one.
But I remember one day I walked in as a couple of stories.
The first one is Sarah Jessica Parker.
Well, I walked in one day and Sarah Jessica Parker sitting at the front, having a coffee, chatting with a friend.
I'm like, this is this is the queen of West Village.
And we carry Bradshaw and Sexton City.
And I remember walking.
I'm watching that show and thinking about, wow, imagine living in New York and just the adventure, the excitement, the spontaneity of working and living and experiencing all of New York.
And then the next thing, she's sitting in your cafe.
And then there was another story.
I remember I got a phone call because you mentioned the Dimitinas.
Well, Andrew Dimitina worked with us for a while back there.
And Dima and I were at Collingwood together for a couple of years.
And Dima's great friend, Tony Pantano, who's one of the great people in New York City.
And he's one of the principals at Only Hospitality with Julian.
They've got venues all over Melbourne.
They do a sensational job.
And Tony, I came down.
It was snowing. It was in winter.
And Tony was there.
And I walked in and I said, you know, how's it going?
And he goes, oh, got a bit of a problem with the waitlist.
And I looked at the front and I saw Cameron Diaz sitting outside in the snow having a coffee.
I said, Tony, what are you doing?
It's Cameron Diaz.
And he said, well, what do you want me to do?
That's the only table I had.
And I said, you know, she was in the cafe.
She offered a turn.
She said, sit outside.
And she was fine.
And, you know, I think that also emphasized the, you know, underpin the attitude that we had, that we treat everyone the same, even if they are super mega celebrities, that just treat them like they're a local.
And that actually drove them to come into the store because they just wanted to go with their friends or their family and relax and don't make a big deal out of it.
Don't encourage people to take photos.
Don't have the staff, you know, go over the top.
And that, I think, really built around the authenticity.
And what we're doing and it just continued from there and, you know, we've been very lucky to have a lot of famous academics.
I remember just after Richard Branson is sort of one of my heroes growing up that did his first time.
He traveled with Virgin orbit up in the space and then he came back and two days later I saw him in one of our cafes in Midtown.
That was pretty cool, too.
So, yeah, very fortunate.
But we serve seventy five thousand people a week.
And.
So there's a good chance you're going to get someone who's pretty interesting in that.
What a great level of storytelling.
It's fascinating, isn't it?
From long way from Victoria Park, mate, to downtown in the coolest hipster part of New York City.
It's a serious business now, as you said, seventy five thousand people a day drink Bluestone Lane coffee.
You're the CEO, you're the M.D.
What have you found out about yourself as a leader of a business at this scale?
What type of leader are you?
Well, we've actually been.
We've been undertaking some leadership training with a with a group at the moment, Paul, Paul Ruse's group, Performance by Design, which has actually been, yeah, it's been really fascinating to to just to reawaken it, because I'm very fortunate that my mother in law is quite, quite an expert in positive psychology.
And she was at the forefront of talking to me about my personality type and my briefs and my communication style and what I should do under stress.
And, you know, I.
I think for me, I'm a very, very determined person and I love I love trying to improve.
I'm a relentlessly focused on learning and getting better and I feel I love being part of teams.
I do not like trying to do it by myself.
I love aggregating and coalescing a group of like minded individuals who want to give it at all.
And ultimately, I really look for that that value of dependability.
I think that having outstanding talent just doesn't really.
It's not what I really navigate towards.
I want someone who's so committed and so dependable that I know the effort I'm going to get all the time.
And and for myself as a leader, you know, I've had to continue to evolve because I came from an elite environment in the AFL system for six years where it's pretty.
You think about it, you have a lot of type A people that have been working towards this.
They've been conditioned or they get in the system and they've taught.
They've been conditioned at a very impressionable age and you learn a lot about discipline and routine and self-belief or lack thereof.
And then I transition into banking and banking.
It's reasonably homogenous that the people that work there have similar sort of university degrees and probably similar academic profile.
And they're very, very focused and they're prepared to pay, you know, make enormous sacrifices.
And then when I went to blue.
Stone, you know, Bluestone Hospitality, the majority of Bluestone Lane team don't foresee themselves working there in two to three years.
It's very much a gap or hobby job.
So to change your leadership style from being part of really smaller, high performance environments where you're talking about in some cases like the best of the best, reasonably homogenous to now Bluestone where you have 120 percent turnover.
You have a lot of people from very, very diverse backgrounds.
A lot that come from very unfortunate circumstances.
And we've got a chance to have a huge impression and give them a lot of self-confidence about themselves, the difference they're making to others, the opportunity for development and that meritocracy of Bluestone.
That is ultimately if you make people feel good and you play your role, you can go all the way up.
And I pride myself on focusing on developing those from within rather than looking externally.
That is something that matters.
So much to me.
And hopefully that's something that I'm really known about, that I take enormous amount of, I care a lot about our team and I care about, you know, giving them the best shot at life.
And working in the U.S. has awoken a lot of those discrepancies in childhood, in education, in how to eat well, how to, you know, a lot come from broken homes where parents are incarcerated.
Or, you know.
You know, they've never finished high school.
And that's been an enormous eye-opener and something that I'm so grateful, the experience of having.
Because working in banking and footy, it was fantastic.
But, yeah, you're sort of only dealing with a small tranche of society.
And this has been a lot more broader.
And I'm very grateful for that.
And I think it's made me a lot better leader than otherwise.
Aspiring entrepreneur listening to this, Nick.
You left the safe world of banking, as you said.
You're on the path to have a really successful life and financially rewarding and a lot less risk.
I mean, you've had to deal with 87% of your turnover disappearing in two weeks.
It's not, you know, an easy path, the entrepreneurial path.
What advice would you give to someone who's thinking about it?
I think the best thing to do is to spend an extensive amount of time becoming an expert.
And over time, what I found is, like, thinking about all of the things that potentially could,
you know, go wrong and mapping out a little bit of a mitigant.
Because what I found is through, it's just like training.
You equip yourself for the unexpected.
And I found that typically when I speak to entrepreneurs, I'm like, okay, think.
You've got to spend a lot of time up front.
Because there's no point having a false launch when you can avoid it.
And no one wants a business to fail when you can avoid it.
Paul Rose had an excellent quote.
He said that, you know, you never want to make a decision under pressure if you can avoid it.
And I see that with.
Building a business.
Really, really map out.
Really map out about what your true value proposition is.
How are you going to be successful?
Who your customer is?
What's your cost base like?
What's your cost base and cost structure like?
How are you going to manage this?
Or where do you think your role will evolve to?
Because when I started Bluestone, I had the view that I definitely wasn't the best person to be full-time CEO of Bluestone.
There's just no way that Bluestone could really probably handle my ambition.
And my probably formality in my experience in business, it needed to be a bit more laissez-faire.
It needed to be a bit more casual and grow and see where it went because hospitality isn't linear.
You have peaks and troughs and most businesses aren't.
And, you know, I think becoming a student and addressing all those questions and over time, you're like, yeah, you know, if this happened, this is what I'd do.
And I just found through that exercise.
That you gain an enormous amount of confidence because you've thought about a lot of things that could go well or might not go as well or to plan.
And that gave me enormous confidence.
So, you know, they're my tips.
And, you know, I don't think you want to rush anything, honestly.
I think you just want to say, if you think you're ready, just take another week and talk to someone about it and reach out to a mentor and take them through it.
And just bounce around a few ideas because you might as well get it right and give yourself the best chance of being successful.
Rather than launching too early and just not getting a bit more of that, you know, that value, that insightful feedback.
And then, of course, you know, you've got to pick who you're going to take feedback from.
You know, everyone's got, you know, it's easy to provide, but it's hard to take.
And, you know, you've got to work out who really understands what you're trying to do.
And, you know, that's something that I've had to learn through as well.
Lots of people told me, don't do it or you wouldn't have an idea.
And doing it or don't scale it or sell it now.
And ultimately, you know, I've had others that have just been experienced enough to say, you know, I think that you should be aware of this.
But ultimately, you've got to back your gut and you've got to back your judgment because that's why we're sitting here right now.
And I love the story.
If you think Nick didn't put some preparation in, I'm told you spent hours and hours and hours in Starbucks just studying customers.
I can picture you there just writing notes down.
And seeing your gap in the market.
Nick, I love talking to different leaders in different backgrounds.
And, you know, your story's fascinating to me or someone who's in the arts, in a creative world.
But we see success leaves clues and different patterns of leadership.
I want to ask you these series of questions that we see are quite common for people doing great things like you.
Starting with self-leadership, Nick, we feel like very hard to be able to lead others without a sense of your own self-leadership.
What does that mean to you?
I think you just need to know who you are and what motivates you and what you're passionate about, what your values are.
And I think when you're comfortable with yourself, you're going to be comfortable with others.
And you'll also be a much more impactful leader because you'll be your authentic self.
And I think you can present with that vulnerability that you don't have all the answers.
That you're using these signals to form a view.
And that you're open to feedback on certain things and maybe others that you've got a really strong view.
Yeah.
I appreciate your comments.
They're like, I'm going this way.
And that's that self-confidence and surety that you need.
And I think doing that investment, and for me, I didn't do that investment enough when I was playing AFL.
I just, I hid my emotions.
I hid the way I was feeling.
And when my AFL career finished, it was liberating that it was over.
I was deeply sad that I probably didn't achieve my childhood dreams.
But it was liberating that I could probably be myself a bit more.
And attack my next career with more reckless abandon.
With just confidence and to go for it.
And, you know, I think that that's, I found that it's hard when you do a lot of self-assessment.
And especially as a CEO.
Because, you know, of course people are going to say that you're the CEO.
You're probably really, really passionate.
You're carrying a lot of the weight of the organization.
You care about your team and their performance.
Because ultimately that will impact the company that you're the custodian.
But, you know, it takes a lot to make yourself that vulnerable to take it on and to change.
And everyone, I found that I can change and sometimes will slip back.
And you need that reminder.
And I'm very fortunate that both my family support network, both at home here,
but also in the business with my brother working there,
can always give me the tap on the shoulder and say,
listen, I think you could handle that a little bit differently.
I appreciate that.
What you're trying.
But the way that you articulate it might not be as impactful for someone else.
And that's something that I think we're probably, everyone's on a journey.
And it's always evolving because communication styles have changed so dramatically
with technology and social media and the way that people process information
and how they receive information.
And I always think with someone who is self-reflective and a constant learner like you,
you go into that category where you don't even have
to worry about because you are going to be open enough to admit when you get it wrong.
And that hasn't always been the case.
And no one is perfect.
There's so much joy for people to know that they're in an environment
where the person leading them themselves are trying to get better each day.
We see leaders are really conscious about how they positively impact people
in their environment every day in a really sophisticated way that they think about that.
How have you gone about that impact?
Well, I think for us,
you always want to, we are in the business of moving the masses.
So I'm not in a small team.
We have a thousand employees and we have a very high turnover.
We're serving thousands of people, tens of thousands of people a week.
So for us, we have to have a whole huge cohort of people moving in the right direction.
They have to be very, very disciplined and very selfless.
If a local comes in and they're having a bad day and they're rude to one of our team members or teammates,
they still have to be positive.
They still have to execute along with our value proposition and our steps of service.
And that takes an enormous amount of discipline.
So for me, I just really always need to emphasise where they're coming from.
And I need to make their jobs easier.
And I need to be sympathetic to concerns that they have.
And we've been very, very much on the front foot of a lot of diversity initiatives.
Certainly, as it relates to what happened, COVID and the killing of George Floyd,
and supporting healthcare heroes, and just being a real advocate for a lot of these campaigns and initiatives and social needs.
We just get on the front foot and we do things that are very much on a grassroots level.
You don't have to raise a tonne of money.
You don't have to shut your whole business down to campaign for something.
It's often small, meaningful contributions.
Which often...
Often can be involved or led by the team that make a big difference.
And for me, it's just being very sympathetic to the way that...
And empathetic to the way that they're feeling and the environment.
And seriously, the last three years, you probably couldn't imagine a more turbulent period to run a retail business.
And for us, it's just being very honest, giving everyone a hearing and trying to lead with positive and good intent.
And doing...
Leading with actions rather than words.
And that's underpinned us, I think, really well.
You're never going to be able to solve everything.
You're never going to be able to cure everyone's ills.
But I think showing initiative and being compassionate and just giving people a chance to voice has helped us tremendously.
And that's a critical part of leadership, I think, in times we're facing right now.
Yeah.
What a great credit to you to give away hundreds of thousands of dollars.
Thousands of free cups of coffee to first responders in that challenging time amongst all the other initiatives that you do.
Creating and sharing a vision is something that we see really common in leaders.
They understand their vision and they've got a really clear way about how they share it.
Bluestone Lane is a big vision.
How have you gone about creating and sharing that?
Well, for us, you need to be crystal clear and you need to have a lot of repetition and you need to live and breathe it.
So, yeah.
The key terms in your organization are so critical.
So, in our example of having locals, not customers, having teammates, not staff, having you're talking about the experience, not the transaction, a lot of repetition and ensuring that all of your materials and we have a really extensive digital learning management system and just having all of these introductory items that we really have got to celebrate people when they join.
And
a lot of times that people celebrate leavers, but you've got to spend even more time celebrating when they join to make sure that first impression and you give them a chance to be successful so that they feel like, wow, I'm joining something that's incredible and look at this induction and I'm going to be a star here.
I think that's really, really important.
But, you know, one thing that we did about sharing the vision is trying to articulate what it feels like and how they will see it.
And, you know, it's great for us to.
Say that we want to be the best Australian hospitality export or something big like that, a big, but what's tangibly how they're going to see it, how they're going to feel.
And I think breaking that down and being really, really selective in the core values, the core tenants of the organization, we only have four core values, and then being really clear on what the key success factors are and how they would play out has helped our business enormously.
And we, we are.
I used to have this, I've had this challenge over the years, like what is a great Australian inspired premium coffee cafe experience and, and, you know, I could articulate like it's just the way you make people feel it's great coffee, it's great food, it's great music, it's great.
But ultimately, like we had to sort of dig a little bit deeper and say, well, you know, in a coffee shop, it's probably speed, really important for coffee, recognition, quality product.
It's probably, you know, cleaning, cleanliness.
Whereas cafe's is probably spend through service.
So how you serve someone and educate them at the menu, human connection.
So beyond just recognizing someone, but really human connection, making them feel amazing because 90% of our dining transactions are two or more people.
Premium broad product, a lot broader, and then beautiful spaces.
Cleanliness, is not enough in a great cafe.
Yes, clean, it's got to be beautiful space and that's those atmospheric elements that hospitality.
You know, communication is everything, and I don't think anyone's got a perfect science on how to communicate or which method.
And in our organization, we have email, we have Slack, we have, you know, Telegram, we have text message, you know, and everyone, it's a constant tug of war between too much and too little.
But, you know, I think you need to, when you sell the vision, you've got to distill it down to what does it mean to a new joiner?
And repetition really has helped us, and just being really clear in our language and those key tangible elements that they'll see where they'll go, yeah, now I understand the role and the part I play in achieving that larger vision.
And I've experienced that at Bluestone Lane, where I've had the great, you know, fortune of a couple of weeks stint, and then you pick up your local one, you might be staying in Midtown, and you walk past, and by day three, one of your team has gone.
They've clocked who you are, they know your order, you're the guy that wants the gluten-free doughnuts, that's me, yep, along with the coffee.
And so you can see that your systems are clearly working at scale.
Curiosity is a term that we hear a lot from people in leadership roles like yours, and through curiosity, they're constantly looking at how they improve.
Does that resonate with you?
Absolutely.
There would be no Bluestone if I wasn't curious about how hospitality works.
And honestly, I have a very shallow view of Starbucks being an Australian.
You know, I think most people talk quite negatively about it and put it down.
And then I remember a day at business school, I looked up and I just searched Starbucks market capitalization, and it was nearly 90 billion US.
And at that stage, back in 2010, I don't know how many Australian companies that were that big.
I think it was bigger than every bank other than CBA.
And this is Starbucks.
This is Starbucks.
Like something that I thought that they can't make coffee, they can't provide a great experience.
So I think from that, you know, that is just the way my mind has naturally worked.
I love listening to stories and learning from others and just being curious on how you can change and consider things in a different light.
And Bluestone, I have been unencumbered with the formality of hospitality training.
I was not a trained chef.
I was not a trained barista.
I was a customer.
So everything was through those lenses of customer centricity and cost structure and building a lifestyle brand.
Because I was always being obsessed with brand building and storytelling and LVMH, Bernard and all, and these guys and women that just do the most extraordinary job to evoke emotion around the way someone feels when they see a product or go to a certain type of experience.
And for me.
That curiosity sort of underpinned Bluestone, but challenged the way we were going to do it, doing it with a different cost structure, making food that typically Americans have never made in a coffee shop, not having all processed things and coming from a commissary, making them fresh, freshly made and, and just thinking about things differently all the time and trying to actually in the case of Bluestone, be, I guess, a chain, but have an independent spirit.
Where we refer to ourselves as boutique at scale.
And I just think that, that, that constantly, constantly trialing and re-imagining and prototyping has been an amazing element in the Bluestone Lane story.
And a lot of people have got, been given enormous freedom to try new ideas and think differently about what we, how we could do it and the way we could do it.
And that, that's probably the part that, that's the spark that keeps you going.
And it's that innovation and seeing people rise to the floor and pose different things to me.
I love that.
I love bouncing around ideas and that's the type of person I am.
I socialize and I consider and I think and research.
And yeah, you know, I think that's a, that's an essential element because as soon as you're not growing, you're, you know, you're dying basically in this game.
And, and, and, you know, I love that.
I love that iteration process.
The next dimension of leisure I want to talk to you about was communicating with clarity.
And you started there and you said, we've got Slack, we've got Messenger, we've got WhatsApp, we've got text messaging.
And, and obviously you, you've had a serious think about communicating with a thousand staff and an expanded team.
You're right across both coasts of the U.S.
How have you gone about it?
Well, snail mail's tough.
And, uh.
And, you know, it's, it's a hard one.
It's a really hard one because there's also a lot of considerations because I might have 10% of my team that are accessible all the time, but 90% aren't.
You know, they're only really working for you when they're on the clock.
And, uh, so how do you, how do you, how do you communicate or how do you get their interest when they may not see themselves with Bluestone long-term?
Um, it's a tough one, but ultimately you've got to try different things.
You need to measure them and you need to challenge them.
And for us, that's, we, this is our second, uh, stint at Slack.
We had Slack for a couple of years, then we put it down and then we've re, re-imagined it.
And in different elements of the business share by different platforms, um, whether it's Asana or Dropbox and others use group, it's, it's always, it's always hard.
But ultimately, I think that the one thing, a couple of things that have helped us enormously, the monthly town hall.
We make a.
A real celebration.
So previously town halls were honestly pretty dry and I led them.
And I don't think that that was the best thing for the organization.
My communication, probably my vocabulary was, was just probably out of touch with the majority of the team.
And ultimately you want the, all your emerging leaders to run those sessions.
And now all hands where I used to talk the most, I talk the least, and I go there to learn myself, to learn about.
Those who are.
Doing an amazing job about these little random acts of kindness or, or, uh, moments where, um, uh, you know, we have a good on your mate award and where people get nominated by their, their peers, their fellow teammates, and we celebrate.
And of course it ties in with the financial performance and the key strategic focus of this month or key marketing initiatives, but it's just changed from being very content, heavy repetition to really celebrate.
The team and finding the good and celebrating the successes, no matter how challenging the environment is.
And.
In Coverage.
That's what we have to.
Do.
And my mom said, you know, early on.
I remember calling her saying, I think blue stone's gonna file.
And I, and we were alone in Santa Monica.
We couldn't get home to Australia.
Um, you know, the, the world was falling apart and she said, you know, there's always going to be a silver lining.
You just got to look for it.
You gotta be open.
It's just not for.
enough to look for it and find it and it's so true that even during really hard times there's always
something to celebrate uh and you just got to hold on to those and focus on what you can control so
with communications really being positive and certainly focusing on and as a ceo i've i don't
profess to be an expert at this at all but when you're a senior leader i've never i've always
underestimated the power of your own body language and uh paul ruse actually again awakened me to
this that he said that i've finished someone's career by the way i've looked at them at training
and i could really resonate with that that if you make a mistake and you run past the coach and they
shake their head you know i might go out and play that weekend terribly and the next thing you lose
confidence and then you're delisted it's so powerful um when you're the leader and you need
to realize that
you carry enormous responsibility that your words matter a lot and the way that you your body
language and your eye contact uh it can have a profound outsized impact on your team and
that's something i'm still sort of learning to understand and harness that power and uh you know
it's something that i'm really grateful that people actually make me aware of that you look
really negative or you look really down or you look really angry or frustrated maybe take a break
or maybe don't talk in this session
and just try and get upbeat because ultimately any feeling of frustration or anger will pass
and you know you don't want to burn your house down because you're having a bad moment
yeah and that's really really important in leadership to understand the impact your
actions have on others nick one of my favorite uh afl moments uh this year it might have caught
i'm sure paul ruse would align with this greatly craig mccray is coaching collingwood and doing
a remarkable job and you hear him talk about his career and i'm sure he's going to talk about his
career and i'm sure he's going to talk about his career and i'm sure he's going to talk about his
wanting this team to make mistakes now it's easy to say that but on anzac day his fullback
brayden maynard kicks out he's almost missed the ball nick it's come off his shin rolled two meters
his opponent picks it up and kicks a goal straight over his head we're in the commentary box and
you're paying straight to craig mccray who is pissing himself laughing he just just spontaneously
laughed now you and i played under coaches that might have ended your career had you done a
thing and it's like well you can't fake that can you because if in that moment you lose your mind
automatically you're saying mistakes aren't okay are you so it's it's that you know to be able to
you know what next one he kicked out beautifully and away you go it's uh it's easy uh to say harder
in practice isn't it but i love uh i love saying it well people generally don't go out there to
make mistakes right you've got to assume positive intent and i think that that that's an amazing
analogy that you that vulnerability this
show that no one's perfect and as long as the intent was right and they put in the requisite
work which all these guys in afl and women in afl have and you know it's a function of life it's not
life or death you know keep it in perspective and i i need to often remind myself hey had a tough
tough store visit or a tough store day but you know we got we got more days than not which are
fantastic so hang on to those learning well said how important has collaboration been for you
enormously i there's just there's just no way that um i would have achieved anything in my
professional life without incredible mentors incredible friends family and and being part
of teams where i could learn i was so lucky to have extraordinary mentors in banking in particular
that believed in me gave me the opportunity the fact that they let me build a business on the
side while i was running a team and an important team for anz was just and part of the
european america's leadership team and having a side hustle which everyone knew about because
they were visiting daily um you know like just to think about that selflessness and the bet they
took on me that they are that nick can do this and they and his performance won't deteriorate
i'm i'm indebted to them and and that they risked they took and you know collaboration is
is is incredible i think it's one of the best parts of what's the best part of team sport
sharing those tough moments and sharing that exhilaration those wins it's just nothing better
i've never been a person that ever dreamt of as much as i'd love to like stand at wimbledon with
you know the trophy or the aussie open or win the masters i've always been i want to be part
of teams and celebrate with others and and that's probably the thing i miss so much when i move to
the states that that those points of connection three times a week playing at my amateur footy
collegiates and when i
finished AFL I was 23 just about turned 24 I went straight to play at collegians um rather than play
you know VFL or another level and I just love being with others and and I've those there's
lessons that you learn from team sports I've applied them in everything I've done post
and uh you know they just it's such a structural advantage we get in Australia
because so many of our sports are orientated towards team whether it's AFL whether it's
netball rugby cricket and often the skill set is less specialized more generalized everyone has to
mark and kick and handball and pass and catch so I love that about our culture and I love that we
have amateur sport that if you don't it doesn't matter if you're not professional you're welcome
to participate and still have fun and I think that's underpinned so many Australians in business
particularly in the US where from a small population a population smaller than that of
Texas
half the population of California you find Australians always at the pinnacle of different
industries challenging challenging um you know the norm and and I think that's brilliant
yeah yeah well said isn't it uh Nick and it's that great you know love of being in that community
isn't it you've created that with Bluestone Lane you've taken you know your love of sport as a kid
and and to me that was the joy and the playing team sport isn't it those lifelong friendships
the skill set you bring when you've grown up in team sport you're automatically open to feedback
you're great get great discipline and you you like supporting others they're great people to work
with aren't they people who are passionate about team sport and I'm you can see you've taken those
lessons uh with you who's been the greatest leader in your life I think I've been very fortunate to
have a number across different disciplines that you know I'd probably say my mother you know
probably as a as a leader I've been very fortunate to have a number of people that have been
very fortunate to have a number of people that have been very fortunate to have a number of people
just someone who values that I've really and her resilience has been pretty uh inspirational for me
but um outside of family and I've been really lucky that I had probably my first boss at ANZ
was just an extraordinary guy um Dion Smith very very humble and very very thoughtful
and he's he's a man of few words but uh he was just he is just an extraordinary person
very patient he was the one that said you know in the nick um you know no matter what um always
have a skill set and he he really really encouraged me to learn the fundamentals of
corporate finance and banking and then he was so encouraging to branch out and stretch and try
different things and um and he was such a believer in in me and I was someone who who felt you know
that I'd failed in one career and I was you know going in another one I was going in another one I
was desperate to prove myself and he just really embraced and provided opportunities and belief and
that sort of dovetailed into a whole host of succession of leaders that I worked for um
Richard Schroeder, John Chavelle, Tim Maddock, Truett Tate, Doug Stolberg that really encouraged
me and and they offered to mentor me and and that that that is probably the difference between
whether I'm living here in the U.S. and whether I had a great banking career in in
the U.S. and whether I had a great banking career in in the U.S. and whether I had a great
or Bluestone is just some people that really took that vested interest in me and and uh there's one
there's one other final person that has just been sort of extraordinary his name
uh is Michael Pimley and he was he is just one of those people that men I've run into I catch up
with him maybe twice a year and every time I sit down with him the positivity he evokes about
and how he expresses how proud he is of me is extraordinary and you know I'm
very fortunate to have come from a really supportive family um my father was has always
been incredibly supportive of myself and my brother my brother um and you know he he joined
Bluestone because I said listen I'm going to go full-time why don't you come across and he gave
up his career to get on this journey and and he tolerates a lot of a lot of those dark moments
that I share with him that others you don't express only the family you really express how
you feel that um and and I think that's what I'm really proud of and I think that's what I'm really
proud of and then obviously you know my wife is just a great role model the way that she's been
able to you know with our family and the way she mothers and her her career and how determined she
is and how stoic she is has been sensational so you know I've I think that you know a lot of people
look at you know leaders that you read about and I've got plenty of those but if I think about like
who's had the most profound impact on me personally I think it's probably those who are closer near
friends that I have and um I I'm it's probably the most it's without a doubt the most special
part of my life is my uh family and friends I love the fact you get to call them out uh Nick
and the influence on on your life to reel off the names like that to have so many people just
straight at the uh the top of your mind that it's an incredible position and I know that you pass
that on in a profound way as well you know we see collaboration as this incredible thing we're
really passionate about and the work we're doing uh in our leadership space with the
leader and you know you've had some incredible collaborators already haven't you from the
investment team I know you've just done a national partnership with Hilton Hotels and a range of
different things but has there been one they've thought god if I on any area of your life and I'm
assuming Bluestone's going to be at the forefront of your mind but if you can collaborate with one
person on one thing is there has there been someone in mind that you could share with us
oh I think I think collaborating with a with a super luxury brand I think would be extraordinary
so if you if you look at it what's happened
with Tiffany & Co uh which was you know a probably the true only uh luxury American brand that stood
the test of time it was purchased by LVMH which is the largest luxury house in the world um owned
by the richest person in the world uh you know they I think could collaborate with something
something as prestigious and that has that longevity and tenure that would be extraordinary
um from a brand perspective um but you know there's there's
some
people out there that that you know you look at and Gladwell was a huge one because I'd read all
his books and he inspired me so much and then one one moment he's in as a customer but there's
people like that you think you know imagine if you had a chance to do something special but
from a brand perspective I think that you know um LVMH uh if if uh Mr Orneau called you
and said uh I want to put Bluestone Lane in the flagship uh Dior store in Avenue
Montagne would you be ready for it I think I'd jump on the plane and just like Gordon Ramsey I'd
be there in short order well and you never know do you Nick and that's what I love about the way
your story is who would have thought you'd be standing uh you know the Miami Dolphins uh
Hard Rock Stadium uh doing what you've done and it is it is a global Australian hospitality
success story of the highest order and I loved uh following it uh from afar and seeing you take
that uh step from you know coming out of the world of professional sport and to have the
courage to do what you do and be so open to share it Nick I love the fact that you're just an open
book and pass on the wisdom that you've got uh thanks for taking the time today it's been great
to catch up with you oh pleasure Luke thank you for having me on and congratulations amazing
podcast I wrote to you saying that the Jeff Harris one was one of the best podcasts I've ever listened
to so uh who I've had coffee with a couple of times at Bluestone in New York and his and heard
about his story um but yeah thank you and yeah hope to catch up again over here soon
thank you for listening to the empowering leaders podcast powered by temper a mattress
like no other and to make sure you don't miss an episode click subscribe wherever you get your