I'm not comfortable talking about myself and, you know,
you'll recognise that I'll start to deviate to where my team goes
and talking about my program rather than necessarily myself
because I come very much from a background that is a bound team
and, you know, we play a team sport and it isn't going
to be one individual that actually makes that team.
So I think that's where it shows up, where the spotlight starts
to then sort of come on to the individual.
I know that I'm one person amongst, you know, many who have helped us
over the last couple of years get the Thunderbirds back into finals
and then obviously sort of winning the past two premierships.
Hello and welcome to another episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
At Alita, we are passionate about inspiring connections
and creating a world of collaboration.
Our signature program, Alita Connect, curates groups of five
to six leaders.
from diverse backgrounds in sport, industry, social venture
and the arts who come together to learn, to connect
and to collaborate.
Dr Troy Flanagan, Vice President of Performance
for the Milwaukee Bucks.
I've probably had some of the most radical changes
out of that leadership group.
The significance of their work and how much it's really
about helping others, it made me think,
what else could I be doing?
And I approached our owner and within a few weeks
we'd raised $5 million to try and solve obesity
problems.
in the underprivileged community in Milwaukee.
So that's one spark that that leadership course has caused
to contribute and leave the world as a better place.
Umrah Omer, founder of Safari Doctors.
It defines the word creativity for me.
The ability to like see connections where none seem to exist.
And I think that's the magic of Alita.
Definitely not my usual, you know, workshop panels like, you know,
humanitarian spaces, but more of an intentional dissection
of leadership.
The Empowering Leaders podcast is proudly brought to you
by Victoria University, where cutting edge sports
and exercise science facilities like heat chambers,
performance labs and altitude environments mean
VU is ranked seventh in the world for sports science.
VU, uniquely you.
As always, a big thank you to Jason Nicholas
and his team at Temper Bedding, a mattress like Noah's,
and to all of our sponsors, and to all of our sponsors,
If you enjoy listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast,
be sure to subscribe.
And please, if you have a moment,
we would love you to leave a review so we can reach more listeners
and empower more leaders.
This week's guest on the Empowering Leaders podcast
is a true powerhouse of Australian netball, Tanya Obst.
Tanya's journey from a talented player to head coach
is full of resilience, strategy, and a deep passion for the game.
The Obst family are sporting royalty in South Australia.
Her father, Trevor, a four-time premiership player with Porto
and Adelaide, is an Australian football legend.
It is no surprise to me that Tanya's carved out
a successful sporting career of her own.
Tanya took over the Adelaide Thunderbirds
on the back of them losing 23 games in a row.
And under Tanya's leadership, the team have achieved
incredible success winning the last two championships.
Tanya, thanks for joining me this week.
Ah, cheers.
Thanks very much, Luke.
I wanted to start by asking you, it's a difficult thing,
coaching sport at the elite level.
It comes with a lot of challenges.
What's been the key to you?
To build the successful culture that you have?
Yeah, look, it's probably been getting the right mix of players,
I think, do you know?
Like, that's been a big key for me when I came into the role.
It was around, you know, three sort of pillars, I suppose,
and one of those was about creating the right environment
and having the right sort of people along the way.
And, you know, the culture piece is something that, you know,
I've grown up with and seen success at what it looks like
at the highest level, and there is no doubt that creating a culture
where, you know, people can be themselves certainly goes a long way
in helping in being successful on the bigger stage.
Which, Tanya, is easier said than done at times, isn't it?
It takes a lot of skill to do what you've done,
and you've had great growth and success as a team.
Can you tell us about some of the challenges you faced along the way
to bring that culture?
You spoke about.
Yeah, look, you know, Luke, if I think about when I first came
into the role, I was all gung-ho, had a great sort of three-year plan
and was going to build this amazing team and create this environment
and have the right game plan, and it sort of – that sort
of started to happen, and once you started to get into the nuts
and bolts of the actual season, holes can start
to appear.
And that's where, you know, I think we also sort of had COVID sort
of join us as well, and it was just an ability to sit back
and reassess where we were at and work out, well, how, you know,
we can play this game, but what is it that's sort of holding us back?
And there was no doubt that the culture piece was one
that was missing, and I think, you know, we were a new team
that had people coming from all different areas of the world,
with all different backgrounds and cultures, so it was really
about us creating that sense of belonging within there
and understanding and delving deeper than that surface level
on what is it that everyone brings, what is it that we can share,
and how do we actually get, you know, further than just the, you know,
how are you going, yeah, okay sort of conversations within our team.
You mentioned a diverse range of backgrounds, people
from overseas and different upbringings, and sports are a melting pot
of bringing those people together, as you described,
but trying to get them working for each other to achieve a common goal,
and you mentioned that sense of belonging.
Can you give us a bit more detail?
How do you make that work?
It's the key, I think, to so much success in business or in life.
What was, is there one particular story that jumps out at you?
Yeah, look, I think, you know, I sort of go back and I talk
about sort of the success that I had seen and been a part
of over the years.
In my earlier years, and, you know, that was very much people being
brought up together and learning and developing together,
but the biggest challenge was, you know, bringing in some Jamaicans.
We had some English players, and what we really had to do
was establish, well, what is it that we do want to achieve here?
And our aim was always to make finals, and that was always the aim,
but it was more around sort of the why and when, you know,
what was hitting the fan.
And on the court, how are we actually going to help each other
through that situation?
Because it can be a very, very lonely place out on that arena,
and, you know, we started to talk more about, you know,
those situations.
We started to share experiences that we'd all sort of had,
and, you know, there was some sessions where, you know,
there was tears and people being really vulnerable and opening up
and un-sharing.
And sharing some experiences that they'd had in the past
where perhaps they had opened up and it hadn't been necessarily received
in the way that they wanted it.
So creating that sense of belonging was really important to me
and really delving deep and understanding the individual
and what makes everyone tick was really a really key point.
And I do remember after one of those sort of sessions with our culture
and leadership person that it was almost like something just clicked
within the team.
There was just trust, more trust on the court.
And when it did start to get really tough and tight out there,
we knew that we were working for one another for a common purpose.
Michelle Obama says the biggest misconception about her is that she has
it all figured out.
I'm still figuring it out, she says.
I still feel like an imposter often.
And Seth Godin says imposter syndrome is the price of entry for a life spent
creating.
When I rang you and I said, Tanya, come and join me on the podcast,
she went straight to there.
She said, I'm feeling this overwhelming imposter syndrome.
It's something that, you know, I think the greatest people have that.
Can you tell me how that shows up for you?
Yeah, well, your phone call was one of it.
You know, I suppose for me I've always been it's about the doing
and the creating.
And I really like to be judged on my actions.
And I'm not comfortable talking about myself.
And, you know, you'll recognise that I'll start to deviate to where my team
goes and talking about my program rather than necessarily myself because
I come very much from a background that is a bound team and, you know,
we play a team sport and it isn't going to be one individual that actually
makes that team.
So I think that's where it shows up, where the spotlight starts to then,
sort of, come on to the individual.
But I know that I'm one person amongst, you know,
many who have helped us over the last couple of years get the Thunderbirds
back into finals and then obviously sort of winning the past two premierships.
Tina, I mentioned the legendary sporting history of the Obbs family,
your family and your dad, Trevor, or Bubbles as he was affectionately
known, a legend of Australian football and right across the family,
your own family.
Your uncles and cousins and everywhere are incredibly talented sportsmen
and women.
What was it like growing up in that family?
Yeah, yeah.
It's a little bit interbred, isn't it, Dan, sort of the Port Adelaide with,
you know, families marrying families.
But look at, well, I suppose you're in a similar situation to us where,
you know, it's what I knew, do you know?
Like I was a little bit younger, didn't see my father play,
but obviously did Barak for Port Adelaide.
And saw a lot of success there.
And so I was just very immersed in that environment.
My weekends were spent sort of sitting in the Foss Williams stand at Albert
and Oval and watching Port Adelaide generally win.
And then come September or, you know, what is now October,
I would then get to sing the song a lot of the times and had a lot of fun
on grand final night.
And it was just surrounded by success, I suppose, and that winning culture.
Yeah.
But not necessarily understanding that that doesn't happen for everyone.
You know, I've sort of learnt that over time.
But, you know, for me it was great.
I, you know, create a lot of friendships around there and with people
who were experiencing the same things.
And I think once you're involved in the Port Adelaide family,
you're there for life and there's a common sort of thread.
And it's, you know, I obviously wouldn't change it
for the world.
One of the most successful sporting clubs in the world, really,
Port Adelaide, an incredible place.
They say more ashes are spread across that famous Albert and Oval
than maybe any cemetery in the world.
It's the diehards, as your family are, are remarkable.
Yes, we've got about three or four family members whose ashes
have joined a lot of supporters there.
The ghosts of Albert and Oval.
I know those stories very well.
You've got a great reputation, Tanya, for developing young people
in particular.
What's the key to that in your world?
Yeah, I love working with young, raw athletes who perhaps aren't quite sure
what to do with some of their talent.
I think probably one of my strengths as a coach and obviously a netball coach
is the ability to spot talent.
Yes.
The learning of the game, I think probably also the tactical side
and the ability to help athletes work their way through has been one of my strengths,
and I just love when I see a young athlete sort of come through and have a spot on our team
and then just make the most of their opportunities, and it's not going to be for everyone, and
I know in my previous years and years since I've been a coach for teams, and I've been
my previous role at the Sports Institute that just to be able
to bring talented athletes in and develop habits that are for life
and it may not mean that you go on and play at the highest level
but you are creating life habits, not just sort of, you know,
for netball.
You're creating those habits that are going to help you through life
but that's probably been, yeah, like that real passion of mine
to be able to nurture that talent, to help them explore what
that looks like and you need to create, as we've talked about,
you need to create that environment that gives them that opportunity
and, you know, I think that over the last couple of years our program's
been able to bring through some of South Australia's best young talent
and we've aligned that with some of the best athletes in the world
and, you know, we've obviously sort of repped some rewards there.
We all are born different.
As we grow, the experiences we have develop into outlooks uniquely our own,
charting our life's course.
No one sees an idea, opinion or opportunity like you
and no one sees you like VU, Victoria University, uniquely you.
Hi, my name's Min.
I do a Bachelor of Social Work.
I got this tattoo done for my 20th birthday present
because I was born as a twin but she passed away
because my mum had ovarian cancer during pregnancy.
So my name's Miriindi, which means rainbow
and it means the bridge between, for our ancestors to reach their afterlife,
which is what my sister was called, which is the Wada Puti,
which is the Milky Way and that's where they go as like the stars
and they live there.
V is very supportive.
It doesn't matter if you're an Indigenous student,
wouldn't they bother to make sure that,
that you're very well taken care of.
At Alita, our signature program, Alita Connect,
is something we're really passionate and proud of.
We bring together groups of five to six people around the globe
from diverse backgrounds, sport, industry, social venture and the arts
who come together to learn, to connect and to collaborate.
Vanessa Ford, Chief Operating Officer at Kukua.
The Alita Connect experience for me has been transformational.
I met people that I would never have met.
Totally different spheres and it's very basic.
It's all about relationships.
It's all about how we communicate and what the Alita Connect group does
that is so powerful is when you bring two people
from two totally different worlds together, there's no ego.
It just leaves room for the real you.
And I think that's what Alita gave me was bringing back the real me
and really connecting to my own leadership style.
Daniel, we're very proud to have you part of the Alita Connect community
where we curate groups of five to six people around the globe
who come together from different backgrounds to learn and to share
and to collaborate.
Can you share some of the people that you've connected with in that world
and what that experience has meant for you?
Yeah, I absolutely have loved my Alita Connect cohorts.
I've actually been lucky.
I've been in two.
My first one was probably about three years ago.
And we're still catching up on probably, you know,
an eight to ten week basis now.
And Adam Vogue from WA Cricket has been in one of those.
And we've also had Alison Crabb and Jeanette Bates
from a real estate background.
And so when I was talking to the Alita group,
I had an opportunity to join not just a sporting group
but having some business people as well.
And I took that opportunity because I wanted to just,
sort of, spread my wings a little bit there.
And, you know, it's interesting that we all have same sort of challenges,
whether that be people management or, you know,
different problems that come up.
And it's been great to get sort of a business lens that some
of my first cohort have been able to share some of their experiences.
And there's always somehow how you can lap it over
into your sporting world.
And then the second cohort that I've...
I've just sort of been into our third or fourth group there now
is just with sport people.
And that is obviously also offering a different lens as well.
And I've been able to share and ask them some very pertinent questions
that they've obviously got very lived experiences with
and can share that back.
And, you know, you talk about the imposter syndrome.
You know, I'm sitting there and I'm looking at Sandy Brondello,
who's been to the Olympics.
And, you know, she's wanting to ask me how you go back to back
in a premiership.
And Emma Hayes, who is just doing, you know,
has done marvellous things in English women's soccer
and is now leading the USA soccer program over there.
And, you know, she is...
I just love her humour.
I love that Pommie humour.
And Jenny Bocek, who is the first female coach within the NBA
and just some of her...
some of her challenges that she's been able to share
and, you know, and offering us, you know,
the opportunity to give sort of feedback where we can.
It's sometimes really difficult to find that hour or hour 15,
whatever it is, but, you know, you just come off
and you still feel so refreshed and motivated and ready to go.
It's been a...
Yeah, I've loved it.
I've loved all of those sessions.
Yeah, thanks, Tan.
We've, as I said, been really privileged to collaborate with you
and I love how small the world is now that you can in real time
with colleagues that are doing extraordinary things
around the globe and your success translates, of course,
and all the wisdom that you've gained over your incredible life
in sport as well.
Speaking of patterns of leadership, it's something
that we've loved seeing the privilege to sit down
and do this podcast and I want to ask you about in the bracket
of what we call self-leadership and asking what do you do?
What do you do, Tanya, to be your best so that you can lead others
in your world effectively?
Yeah, it's probably something that I really maybe 10 years ago
I was offered an opportunity to do some personal development
through the AIS and I think it was a really great opportunity
for me to be able to understand self more and, you know,
we really delved deep into...
to some areas that perhaps I'd never explored before
and was quite a little bit sort of confronting
with some of your blind spots.
But what came out of that was that I have a real thirst
for learning and a very growth mindset and wanting to understand
and to be better because the better that I can actually be
is obviously only going to be helping the programs
that I'm working in.
I'm always looking...
looking for how I can find an edge or, you know,
be better on game day.
I tried to, you know, jumped at the opportunity to go
on this second Alita Connect cohort because I just knew
that there was going to be some pearls of wisdom drop there
and just trying to, you know, make sure that I take
those opportunities that do present and then understanding
and putting them back into my program is, you know,
wonderful.
One thing I did...
I have done in the past is maybe get all of this advice
and then it's sort of sat in a folder but, you know,
I've been able to really sort of lay that out amongst our program now
and share that and I've certainly learnt that through Alita
and, you know, conversations that you can have with those coaches.
So just always looking to be better.
I love holidays and I love holidays that generally have a sporting...
theme attached to it so, you know, when I'm over
at the Australian Open, how can I find my way in to speak
to, you know, a tennis coach or, you know, if I'm going
to the footy, how is it that I can sort of connect
with someone that just might be able to just see something
that could be the 1% or 2% difference that, you know,
makes a difference?
Yeah, we can see that intense curiosity to get better
in everything that you do and the great success you've had.
Is there one piece of leadership advice that you pass
on more than anything else to others?
I think probably, you know, with some of my...
the young girls that I've come through is they're very much
in a hurry and everything has to happen now and if it doesn't
happen now then, you know, is the world going to fall apart?
And, you know, I've been able to share...
I was never good enough to play at the highest level but, you know,
my experiences that I've gained has obviously led to me
becoming a coach at a high level and, you know,
I suppose I try to instil in my players that it's not going
to happen immediately but it's just that desire
to keep improving, keep being better and it's when it's...
luck is about having done the hard work and when
the opportunity arises.
So that's probably been a key when some of the younger
athletes that I've been working with who probably
perhaps aren't climbing the ladder as quickly
as they would like to but understanding that there
is a process and, you know, success will find you
if you keep putting in that hard work.
When you think of a vision for success, you've clearly
had a really clear vision of what you wanted to achieve
and you've gone and done that with back-to-back championships.
How do you go about passing that on to the team
and getting them to buy into the vision that you've shared?
Yeah.
I was really lucky.
Probably about four or five years to go to sit down
and listen and a chance to speak to Gilbert Onoka
who was the mental skills coach with the All Blacks
and I think was their leadership manager sort of, you know,
over 20-odd years and he broke down what they did
at the All Blacks and he just broke it down in a way
that really simplified perhaps my sort of...
when I relayed it to the plan that I had laid out
it was just sort of, you know, the three things
that really stood out for me was about empowering the athletes.
So, you know, we needed to be leaders that were worth following
was one of the things that he spoke about.
So what is it that we're doing and how do we empower our athletes
to also be those leaders?
And it needed to be something that we were work worth doing
was something else that he mentioned around what is
that meaningful purpose that we're doing and how are we creating
that environment that they want to come and do their job every day
and then the other one was about that belonging,
about the culture worth contributing to
and they were three really sort of key pillars
that I sort of added to my plan
but I really brought the team along with that
and they really, really bought into it.
So I had this plan and it was all sort of mixed up
but he really, just by sitting down and listening to him
sort of speak.
Everything sort of fell within those three pillars
and in the chaotic world that we work in day to day,
they are the things that sort of drive what we can go back to,
what our anchors are when things can get a little bit chaotic.
So, but that's not just me doing that.
That is obviously our staff and certainly the players
who are a part of and actually living sort of what we're working towards.
Tanya, we can see how intentionally curious
you are about that.
I think that's a great point.
We are and a lot of the leaders,
that is a really common word that we see.
Has there been a latest rabbit hole of curiosity
that you've gone down that you could share with us?
I have some athletes who have probably challenged me
in a good way and maybe a couple of years ago,
I would think, oh, why are they asking me that question?
I made a deliberate decision that I would open up
and go, you know, where are we heading with this?
What does this mean for you?
Why are we asking these questions?
Because it was something that I just thought,
oh, you know, are we not on the same page here?
So that is something that I've deliberately done probably
over the last 12, 18 months, I think,
to really explore some of our athletes who want to know why.
What is happening?
How does that help?
And, you know, I think that's something that I've done
By doing that, we've been able to also create
some deeper connections and maybe even looking,
I've even also looked at things a little bit differently
that maybe I wouldn't have looked at in the past.
Brilliant.
Thank you for sharing that.
We love the quote that the cost of leadership is time
and we've all got a finite amount of it.
How do you find a way to balance that with home life
and achieving what you want in your sporting life?
How do you find a path?
How do you find a way to allocating that time for success?
Yeah, I probably have real, like that work-life balance.
Is that where you're heading?
Yeah, I really try and have specific things that I like to do,
especially in the season where things get really hectic.
There are times certainly after a game where I just make myself switch off
because I've done it in the past where you just haven't
and it's just, it's not helpful.
It's not healthy for anyone.
So there are certainly times when, you know,
in the week that I schedule switch-off time,
listening to your podcast, Das, is probably one of the things
that I have on my list to do.
And I always just try to get out and get away at least a day a week
if I can, just to completely sort of check out from as much
as you can when you're in season.
Yeah.
Otherwise, I can get it all too consuming.
So certainly blocking in that time and setting that,
setting that from the start of the season and remembering I come back
to my pillars to go, no, that is actually my time and it's okay
if I haven't actually done everything because if I don't do this,
then I'm not going to be any good for anyone.
Tanya, do you have a mantra when it comes to,
how you communicate in your world um i'd like to be um as honest as i can be i can be a little bit
harsh but fair i think is probably something that i have needed to to work on a little bit i think
sometimes and early days i've probably been too honest or delivered messages maybe that have been
a little bit too blunt um but i've i've sort of really thought about that that empathy side of
things and speaking to um athletes as humans first um and uh also not sugarcoating things but
having an ability to go to give them the truth as best as i can um and being very clear and
asking questions back from them
um because i've certainly left some meetings not just with athletes but with staff and we've left
with very very different um yeah uh examples like very different sort of situations that we've left
with very different messaging so um very much around that uh that human first when delivering
messages but then seeking to understand um back from the from the athletes that i've been speaking
with tanya who's been the greatest leader in your life oh
um oh you know there's probably a number of people i i i think you know the i mentioned
gilbert anoka before and my time with him was was short but it was so impactful just
just helped me put pieces together um i think margango is probably somebody who really comes
um to front of mind marg is um a legendary netball coach here in in south australia and
she was flying the flag and she was um she was um she was um she was um she was um she was um
a head coach of uh the of the similar competition that we we play in now she was also a mother of
three she ran her house and um she was also uh the south australian sports institute coach she
was she she really did so much um and just was able to compartmentalize all of that and i i
don't know i don't know i don't know i don't know i don't know i don't know i don't know
I just admired what she did and how she really was such a powerful voice
for our sport back in the day when perhaps it wasn't getting the noise
that it needed.
I've heard you mention Gilbert Anoka, who was famously connected
with the All Blacks, as you said, and your collaboration with Emma Hayes
and Sandy Brondello in Alida.
We are a bit obsessed with collaboration, Tanya,
and I can see you seek it out regularly to keep self-improving,
as you've described in this chat.
Has there been someone else in any passion of your life that you thought,
oh, I'd love to collaborate with that particular person?
One person who I have sort of collaborated in the past
and I don't like filling her tyres too much is Tracey Neville
because she's a – we're competitors now, you know, in our competition.
But I've known Tracey for a very long time, more from on a friendship level,
and we had the opportunity.
We had the opportunity to work together in England and, you know,
she is a fierce competitor and when I started working,
we started working together, it was – I saw her in a very different light
as a leader and as a coach, but she also – you know,
we were able to really work together and add an element of fun to it.
And, you know, the work that we do and the landscape that we work in
can be really lonely at times.
And you've got to be able to enjoy the people that you're working with
and to have that layer of fun.
And I know with Tracey that we certainly – when we did work together,
we worked very, very hard, but we also had some fun along the way.
And that leads me – I'd really love to be able to work and delve a bit deeper
with Emma Hayes because I see – I just – I feel very aligned
with her personality and the way she goes about it, but I also then look
at what she's done with women's soccer in England and now in the USA.
I'd love to be able to try and link up with her if I'm ever in the States
at the same time with her just to go and have a sneak at her program
to see how she runs and how she really works with her staff.
That would be pretty cool, I reckon.
Tanya, it's an incredible story of success and you can hear
how clear-thinking you are and why it's no mistake that the people
under you get better and everything.
Everything that they do and, as I said earlier, it's been a great pleasure
to get to know you through the Alita community.
Really appreciate you taking the time and I know you're so humble.
You were – I had to almost talk you down to say,
Tanya, please come and join me.
I'm glad you did.
I learnt a lot from it and wish you all the best for the coming year.
Yeah, cheers.
Thanks very much.