Thanks for joining us on our special Paris Olympic series of the Empowering Leaders podcast
and our guest is the captain of the Australian women's basketball team, the Opals, Tess Madgen.
You hear Tess sharing her story of being inspired by the great Cathy Freeman at the Sydney Olympic Games
as a 10-year-old heading out into the paddock on her country house, putting her hood over her head
and wanting to be like Cathy Freeman.
She idolised Lauren Jackson, who won a silver medal in the Sydney Olympics playing for the Opals
and how remarkably Lauren is her team-mate in Paris at 43 years of age and into her fifth Olympic Games.
Tess sheds a few tears in this chat while talking about the impact her mum and dad have had on her life
and that she's learnt to control her fierce competitive nature so that it doesn't spill over
and affect her team-mates in a negative way.
We are very humbled and privileged to have Tess Madgen as part of Alita Connect.
Alita Connect is a curated group of diverse individuals from around Europe
the country and around the globe.
We love bringing people together to learn, to connect and share.
Tess collaborates with some legends of sport.
Paddy Cripps, a Brownlow medal winner.
Daley Cherry Evans from the NRL superstar of state of origin for Queensland.
Mitch Marsh, the Alan Borda medalist and Jiva mentor, one of the finest netballers.
They get together to learn and to connect and we'd love you to be part of it as well.
Head to alitacollective.com to check out the Alita Connect program.
Huge thanks to Jason Nicholas and his team from Tempur.
We know.
Athletes like Tess Madgen value their sleep.
In fact, we've heard Tess talk about eight hours of sleep being part of her non-negotiable routine.
So investing in the world's best in bedding, Tempur is NASA approved and a mattress like no other.
Have a look at Tempur today.
Tess Madgen is the captain of the Australian women's basketball team, the Opals.
She fulfilled a lifelong dream of representing Australia at the Tokyo Olympic Games
and captain Australia to a bronze medal at the FIBA World Cup in 2020.
The Opals have a proud history of success at the Olympic Games,
winning three silver and two bronze medals.
Well, Tess, it's great to see you.
Thanks for joining me.
The whole of Australia behind you as captain of the Opals in Paris.
Can you describe the pride that you must feel to captain your country at such a big event?
Oh, yeah, it really is indescribable.
I mean, I had a lot of goals growing up.
I wanted to play in the WNBA or WNBA, play in Europe and play for the Opals at a major tournament.
So being the captain of the team was never really on the list.
It always felt, you know, so out of reach.
So to be able to do that.
It's very humbling and the greatest honour I could have ever imagined in my basketball career.
You've ticked them all off, Tess.
You've done all of that, played in America, played in Europe, the second Olympic Games as captain.
How young were you when you started thinking of those sort of dreams?
It was when the 2000 Olympics were on, actually, when I saw the Opals run out in their bodysuit.
And, you know, they won a silver medal at that Olympics.
And our coach, Sandy Brondello, and team manager, Trish Fallon, and Lauren was on the team as well.
So it's crazy that they're all...
They're all a part of this now.
It's really...
It's a dream come true.
But, yeah, when I first started watching that, watched Cathy Freeman, obviously, it was always something I wanted to do.
And me and my mum's favourite activity, fondest memory growing up, was watching the WNBL on ABC on Saturday afternoons.
And as I, you know, realised I was pretty good at basketball, I started researching what all the great players did and all the ones I idolised.
And they all went to the Australian Institute of Sport.
They all played in the WNBL.
They all played in the WNBA and in Europe to eventually become Opals.
And I think from a young age, I've been very meticulous about what I do, what I want to do, what I choose to do.
And I think by giving myself all those goals and all those experiences really did help me become a very well-rounded basketballer.
And to play at FIBA competition, you know, you see it with the men's USA team.
It is a different level of basketball.
It's a different game playing FIBA.
And you really have to be equipped to playing all the different styles all around the world to be able to be successful.
So I'm very grateful that, you know, little 10-year-old Tess was a bit of a basketball nerd and really set up all these goals and aspirations that I've been able to achieve in my career.
Tess, I love someone who's got a clear vision for what they want to achieve.
And as you said, meticulous and can go about wanting to do that and then achieve it.
Can you describe that?
Because I think some people feel they've got an interest in something.
They like it.
They train really hard.
But it sounds like you've got a different level of focus.
You don't get to where you've got to.
Yeah, it's a bit of a headache sometimes.
I think people that are that meticulous, no matter what field you're in, they really do go on to achieve great things.
I think you need that attention to detail as exhausting and draining as it can be sometimes to be that focused on something and your whole world revolves around it.
How does that show up for you?
What's an example of being meticulous?
I think like, for example, preparing for a game.
There'll be at least 20 things I want to tick off during the week to be able to feel good mentally prepared.
For that game.
And I think it more is the mental side of it that, you know, if you feel like you can do something, you can do it.
I love that saying, if you think you can or you think you can't, you're right.
And that's going to be your reality.
So it's probably more the mental side of me, for me, that allows me to feel prepared and enabled to perform at my best.
But, you know, I have to get 500 shots up every day.
I have to do the correct weight routine, the exact same routine before I play a game.
I have to get eight hours of sleep.
I have to have a nap on game day.
I have to have a coffee two hours before the game.
There's all these things that can be draining.
But if I don't do one of them, I don't feel good enough to play.
So I think people that watch football on the weekend or watch a game of basketball don't understand how much time and effort it takes to produce those performances.
And whether you play well or you don't play well, you don't want to leave it up to chance.
And you want to make sure you're physically and mentally.
Ready to go.
500 shots a day is a commitment, isn't it?
And I love hearing it.
And I want to go back to what you said earlier.
In 2000, you watched the Sydney Olympics, as everyone in Australia was.
Lauren Jackson's running it around.
She's now 43 years of age, going to compete in her fifth Olympic Games.
Can you describe what it's like to play alongside someone you idolised as a girl and maybe describe what she's like?
Great question.
She's amazing.
She definitely makes my job as captain a lot easier.
She really brings.
A level of competitiveness, fierceness, experience, knowledge.
You know, she's been the best player in the world.
She's the best basketball player Australia's ever produced.
And just to have someone like that, to be able to impart their knowledge on the other players and just really raise the standards of what is expected at practice makes my job so much easier.
And then she is so generous with her time and her knowledge and she really does want the best for everyone.
I think she's grown a lot as a person, as a leader.
As obviously a player that speaks for itself.
But she's so humble.
She's willing to go the extra mile.
She really does care about everyone on the team.
And being able to witness that firsthand and, you know, room with her in Brazil just recently, there is no doubt why she's so good at basketball.
And then off the court as well, why she's so successful in leading her She Hoops brand.
It's incredible, isn't it?
43 years of age.
I know you've had some challenges with the knee injury that almost looked like it was going to be the end.
How close did you come?
And can you tell us about what you've done to get to Paris?
Yeah, for sure.
It definitely was very close to the end.
I did my ACL in 2017 in Poland.
And then once you've done your ACL, unfortunately, your knee degrades at a rapido rate or more rapidly than your other knee, no matter what you do.
So that's what science has proven.
And right before the World Cup, I wasn't named captain yet.
My knee blew up and just out of the blue, like I was feeling great.
And I didn't know what to do.
And I didn't really want to know what was wrong with it.
So we managed it through the 2022 World Cup.
And then afterwards, I had a scan and just a little bit of cartilage had come away, but that was causing the knee to swell up.
So I had a scope.
I was trying to rehab the scope while trying to get back for WNBL.
And I was just having no success.
My knee was so sore.
I'd lost a lot of muscle and just trying to still play while not being at my best.
I really do try and do everything to the best of my ability.
So not...
Being at that level as a leader, as a player in any way was really hard.
And I thought, this is all too hard.
But thank God I didn't quit or retire.
I went and saw a couple of different specialists who just told me to rebuild all the muscle around my leg.
And I got into the Victorian Institute of Sport as a scholarship holder.
And the staff there are just the best.
And they've definitely got me to where I am now.
And that really highlighted something.
That I've, I guess, always known.
But the people you surround yourself really do matter.
And just being surrounded by the best of the best in terms of knowledge.
But also character of people and quality of person really brought out the best in me.
And made me think, I could still do this.
So huge thanks to all of them there.
And Tess, you've been surrounded by some other great athletes around the country and around the globe in some instances.
And we've been really privileged to have you in our Leader Connect community.
You collaborate on a monthly basis.
With some legends.
And we love sort of curating these groups.
Patti Cripps is a Brownlow medalist.
Daly Cherry-Evans is a legend of his sport in NRL.
Mitch Marsh is the Allen Board of Medalists.
He's had an amazing time.
And Jeeva Menthor, one of the best ever in her sport.
Can you tell us about what it's been like to collaborate with them in the Leader Connect space?
It's really been incredible.
I think when we all kind of went into the group, I was rehabbing my knee.
Patti wasn't having a very good time at Colton.
Jeeva's Collingwood netball team was folding.
Mitch was not in the Tess team yet.
He was like wondering whether he's ever going to get another chance.
And Daly was, um, Daly was all good.
He's always all good, Daly.
I feel like he's always all good, exactly.
Well, he did get dropped from the origin for a period, Daly Cherry-Evans.
Had to fight his way back.
But there's a bit going on there, isn't there, when a group gets together?
Yeah, there was so much.
And then kind of, you know, we can credit it to Alita.
Patti's season turnaround.
They made the finals.
Mitch was back in the Tess team, um, winning the Allen Board of Medal.
And then Jeeva.
Jeeva is now doing great things over in England.
And, um, and then Daly was representing Australia.
And it was just so cool to see everyone, like, turn it around.
And being able to lean on each other through those times.
And kind of seeing, you know, the lows and the highs that everyone goes through in sport.
And, four, they're very knowledgeable.
Um, we call Patti the guru.
And there's, like, there's no wonder why he's so good and such a good leader.
Like, listening to him on those talks and how well resourced he is.
But how he uses that to his advantage and really helps.
All of his teammates, but all of us.
Um, and then everyone has their strengths.
Like, Mitch is super funny and humble and really, um, lightens up the room.
Daly's just so cool, calm and collected.
And then Jeeva loves a chat.
So, uh, she's got so much experience.
So just to be able to be a part of that group and learn from some of the best leaders, um,
within the sporting industry is massive.
And I've really loved my time.
I said the other week that I went on there as quite a raw leader.
Like, doing my thing.
Not when I, Sandy announced me as captain.
Who got me onto a leader, Sandy Brondello, um, the coach of the Opals.
She just said, be yourself.
You got selected for this role for a reason.
But I was just kind of a bit raw, you know, just, just trying to be myself.
But since being in a leader, I feel like much more of a well-rounded leader.
And I know the processes, the procedures that I can put in place.
And I've just learned so much to try and not get burnt out, trying to do everything,
delegate and really what is important when leading a team.
Yeah, it's a great answer, Tess.
And thanks for sharing.
I think it's great advice and being authentic in yourself is probably first, second and third.
But as you then gain some knowledge and we often say leadership can be lonely, isn't it?
People are looking to you and having an answer when perhaps sometimes you don't.
And so we found that people find that opportunity to sit down and maybe learn something in that hour and a quarter in a session is quite valuable.
Have you, without, they're obviously private conversations.
Has there been direct things that you've been able to put in place for you and your leadership of the Opals?
Yeah.
Yeah, 100%.
I think a lot of us within that group really needed to delegate more.
And like you said, leadership, that was the first thing I realised.
My partner also runs a business and he's a really good leader.
So I lean on him a lot as well.
But the first thing I realised that it is the most selfless job that you could ever have in leading a sporting team.
And it obviously comes with huge responsibility.
And I think one or multiple people in the group said,
it wasn't their choice to be a leader, but obviously we're selfless people.
That's what we want to do.
That's why we make good leaders.
So I think just all being kind of aligned in the same reasons why we are leaders and was massive.
And they've definitely helped me.
We, you know, we do a hurdle every week.
And my hurdle was how to connect the group when we're all over the world.
So we have seven players playing in the WNBA.
We have players playing in Europe.
We have people in the WNBL.
So we get very limited.
Very limited time together.
So how do we create those meaningful connections via Zoom, via Teams meetings?
And then when we do come together, what can I get the most bang for my buck in terms of having those connections
so that we do have the trust and the level of selflessness that is needed to win a gold medal at an Olympics?
And they all had some really great ideas of some vulnerability exercises that they've done,
connection pieces that we can do through WhatsApp groups,
things we can do on Teams meetings.
So we keep that connection running throughout the year, no matter where, no matter where we are and what's going on.
Tess, it's a storied history for Australian women's basketball at the Olympics.
And an expectation comes with that, doesn't it?
That we think our women's team are always going to win a medal.
How do you manage that expectation heading into Paris?
Great question.
I think we won a bronze medal at the World Cup and that was on home soil.
And I think the expectation and pressure going into that World Cup was,
was massive.
And we knew the responsibility, like the Matildas did,
of inspiring the next generation of basketballers and sporting people, male or female.
And I think that expectation and pressure, you know,
was just as much as an Olympic Games could have been.
So I feel like we're really ready.
We're ready to go.
We had a great tournament in Brazil where we were missing two of our players from the World Cup team.
One player who got all stuff out of it in the World Cup,
Steph Talbot, who's rehabbing an ACL injury.
And to be able to, everyone to play so well, so connected with such limited preparation time.
We had four trainings on an outdoor concrete court before we played in that Brazil tournament.
So I feel like we're in a really good space.
We're really focused on ourselves, what we can do.
And I think that's a really nice place to be.
So I'm sure the expectation and pressure is going to build as, you know,
as we get into the village and we get closer to the games.
But at the moment, I feel like we're handling it really well.
And just cliche as it sounds, trying to focus only on what we can.
Tess, the whole country is behind you heading into Paris.
You mentioned 2000.
Have you got a favourite Olympic moment growing up with your dream to compete in Olympic Games?
Is there one that stands out?
Definitely Cathy Freeman running the 400.
I grew up with, I'm one of four siblings.
And so after the, after the race, me and my,
younger brother, Jack, run around our house.
We live, I grew up in the country, so we have quite a big property.
And like, we run around the house with our hoods on thinking we're Cathy Freeman.
Um, just that whole Olympics, there was, with the rowing, um, the eights had a really good team.
And we used to sit in the, um, lounge room at home and like going row, row.
Like just, we're really sports mad in, in my family.
So just that whole Olympics.
But if I had to pick one moment, it would definitely be Cathy Freeman.
This is a brilliant now that you're going to inspire the next 10 or
20 generation and, you know, Brisbane's not that far away and there'll be people
watching Tess Madgen at the Olympic games going, I want to be that person.
And, uh, what an incredible legacy to be able to pass on.
We love the saying success leaves clues, and we've been fortunate enough in a
leader to see these dimensions of what a great leader looks like.
And we feel it's hard to lead someone else, Tess, without an
understanding of self-leadership.
What does self-leadership mean to you?
Oh, that's a really good question.
Um, I think to me, self-leadership is about holding myself.
Accountable.
I'm never asking my teammates to do anything that I wouldn't do myself and
always showing up as the best version of myself.
So no matter what, I'm always trying to learn more, uh, add things to my game on
the court, but definitely in the leadership space, I feel like that's where
I've had the most growth, um, and then just trying to impart that knowledge that
I have gained onto my teammates so that they can be their best self as well.
I think as a leader, always I've, um, loved through the
coaching space, seeing young girls and boys light up, learning a new skill.
And so I've always loved that component of reaching your potential and being
the best version of yourself, but being able to do that with my peers really,
really is amazing.
So leading myself would be making sure I leave no box on tick to reach my potential.
Yeah, brilliant answer.
And I love that idea is that not asking someone to do something you wouldn't do
yourself and we see people like you have had great success and really conscious
how they positively impact other people every day in their environment.
You're about to go into a Paris Olympic games.
How do you think about positively impacting others?
Oh, great question.
I think for a memory from my Tokyo Olympics was Rowe Webster, the captain of the
stingers, our water polo team, just how positive she was around the village.
And she made everyone feel like they belong.
The Olympics is quite overwhelming.
You're rubbing shoulders with the best of the best athletes in the world, and you
can get a bit of imposter syndrome, but having someone like that around who was
so evanescent and vivacious and bubbly and willing to go the extra mile to make
every single member of that Olympic team feel included.
Um, I really hope to do that, um, at Paris.
What a great story.
How do you go about creating and sharing your vision?
You're heading into Paris.
I'm sure you've got a really clear understanding of what you want to achieve.
You've got, as you said, athletes all over the world.
How do you share that vision?
Every time we come together, we talk about winning the gold medal and I think not
manifesting it, but having that as a clear vision and then what we have to do to
achieve.
Yeah.
I think we're in a really good space on the basketball court, but just keeping
that culture and that connection going and enabling and empowering everyone else
in the team to be able to share their vision and what they want the Paris Olympics
to be like and where they want the team to go, I think is really important.
So as much as, you know, Sandy and I can say our vision is to win a gold medal,
we need to make sure everyone's aligned with that and everyone's idea on how we
do that could be different and making sure we try and incorporate everyone's
ideas.
When you're leading a national team, everyone is a leader.
So just trying to empower that and so everyone can show up as their best, most
authentic self every day is probably a dream vision of any leader.
And I think by doing that, ultimately you will have success.
Sign me up, Tess.
I mean, you've got me going on that.
It sounds like a great culture you've got and Sandy's such a legend as well and have
great people and Lauren Jackson at 43, you can picture it, something special,
uh, about to happen.
Curiosity is a word that we use and hear a lot of.
And through being curious, we see people are constantly trying to learn and develop
this curiosity, something that resonates with you.
A hundred percent.
But before I started a leader, I thought like I wasn't very curious and I thought I was
like really set in my ways and I can be like that for sure.
But I think just by always trying to be the best version of myself, trying to, Patty
Cripps, we had to say nice thing about each other the other day and Patty said that I
exhaust myself.
Trying to always better myself.
And I was like, Oh, that's really, really true.
But I think that is being curious.
Just always trying to push the boundaries, push myself, you know, ask for help, ask people
what they think.
I didn't really realize until I started a leader that that is being curious and probably
I thought that was my weakest thing as a leader, but it probably is my biggest strength.
So just knowing all that now is, is massive.
And I wouldn't have had that opportunity if it wasn't for a leader.
Yeah.
Why that reinforcing when you've got people who've achieved a lot that are in your corner
and say, Hey Tess, we see you as this great athlete and this great leader.
And has that been beneficial for you?
Yeah, it was a beautiful thing we did the other week.
I'm a crier.
Like I've had some tears during this, but I'm on a leader.
I probably cried four times.
Like I find it really hard to express that I'm proud of myself.
So whenever I do that, I just tend to cry.
So when we were, yeah, the new thing in a leader is that.
I think after the eight weeks.
I think it's a week block now, everyone in the group goes around and says how they've
impacted each other.
But we, we were at our 12 month mark the other day and we did that exercise and I was crying.
I was like, oh, stop, please.
And Stace, who's our facilitator.
She's amazing.
Daly was like, Stace, we need to give you a compliment.
And she's like, no, no, she said like, we do this because it is lonely being up the
top and it's really nice to hear positive things about yourself.
So that was amazing.
I re I really loved that exercise.
And I'll definitely be, um, taking it into the Opals.
So look out guys, I'm coming for you.
I love it.
And I love that you've got that, uh, beautiful ability to express emotion the way that you
do.
And it means so much to you.
It's great.
My wife often says you went to boarding school.
I think that removed your tear ducts.
She says to me, because I'm the opposite.
It's not something I'm proud of, but it, uh, we, we turn up in our own ways.
Don't we?
Um, to, to be a leader, like you are, you, you're an incredible communicator.
I can, I can see that you get your words out.
Beautiful.
Is that something you've practiced communicating with clarity?
Oh, that's a, I sometimes feel like I waffle on and I don't articulate myself very well,
but it's definitely something I've had to work on.
I think as a younger athlete, I've always been a natural leader on the court.
Like I'm very opinionated of how things should be.
And, um, one of my strengths as a basketball is my IQ.
I'm definitely not always right.
So as a younger athlete, I was a bit aggressive, not a bit like
asked my former teammates.
I was quite aggressive in how I delivered the message and still, sometimes, of course, I
can fall back into those bad habits, but it's something I've been consciously aware of probably
since I was 18.
So for 16 years, basically my whole professional career career, trying to improve my
communication, um, especially in those heat of the moments.
And, you know, if you'd want to be an empowering leader, the last thing you want to do is be
berating people on the court.
So that's something I've really, really had to work on.
I love the self-reflection to be able to understand, you know, everyone I hear says
you're a fiercer competitor, you're not going to meet than Tess and that's your superpower,
but you've had to tone that back a little bit in, in your communication is, is fascinating.
How important has collaboration been for you?
Massive.
We have a leadership group of me, Seth Talbot and Sammy Whitcomb, and being able to collaborate
with them, we all have our different strengths, um, and leaning on them is huge, but not only
leaning on just the leadership group.
Like I touched on before, all the members of the Opal squad are leaders and just trying
to empower them to still be themselves.
I never want to be the leader that's a dictator or, um, my way's a highway.
And I think that takes a lot more energy and effort, um, to take a step back and empower
other people.
You think it would be the other way around, but constantly asking people's opinion on
things, how they want things to go.
It pays enormous dividends in the end because everyone's playing out their business.
And I think that's really important.
Yeah.
I think that's the best, but for a leader, sometimes that can be really hard.
Like it's a lot easier if, you know, Trish asked me a question and I make a decision
for the whole team, but I always want it to be the right decision for the team.
So that is something that I find really hard to do, but something that definitely pays
dividends in the end.
And at the end of the day, I want everyone to feel valued and empowered, and that comes
with collaboration, no doubt.
Sounds like you have great clarity on who you are and what you want to be heading into
Paris.
It's the perfect time in your life, it seems, sitting across from you now.
Who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Oh, that's a ripper.
I think Sandy's the best leader to be a captain for.
Like she's so empowering.
She just really, it comes with a lot of trust.
I've known Sandy for a lot of years, but she really does let me kind of take the team in
whatever direction I want.
And it's lucky because we're very aligned in the way we think and operate.
So as a coach, she would be the best leader.
Yeah.
I've got to say my parents, like just the way that they raised me, I wouldn't be who
I am today if it wasn't for them.
Yeah.
So, yeah.
It's beautiful, isn't it?
I love this.
One of my favorite answers to that is that if someone's had a mom and dad have an impact
like they've had on you, it's a thing you want to go to straight away.
And I'm sure they love hearing that.
It's a question that I love asking and it feels like a gift, doesn't it?
I grew up with the same thing.
It's a beautiful mom and dad and I suppose we don't get the chance to say it too often,
do we?
Yeah.
I probably should say it more.
That's probably why I'm crying because I haven't said it enough to them.
But yeah, I think if you are a good leader, you learn it from someone and just all the
qualities that I have, good and bad, I've obviously learned from them.
But yeah, just from both, like my dad's super hardworking, committed, dedicated, persistent,
and then my mom's like a beautiful angel with a kind, compassionate side.
So I guess it was a perfect mix and all my siblings kind of have different traits, different
characteristics from all of them and hopefully we're all pretty good people.
I've got no doubt that's the case.
We're a bit obsessed with collaboration and love the idea of inspiring these connections
to the leader.
And in that sense, I mean, you've clearly life of basketball success and it may be where
you go or another part of your life.
Have you thought about, God, I'd love to, that's a person I'd love to connect or collaborate
with in any way?
Any part of your life?
Is there a name that springs to mind?
Oh, great question.
There's so many.
Great leader.
I really love Kelsey Griffin from the Bendigo Spirit who plays basketball.
I mean, I've had a couple in the group, honestly, but I'd love to pick Pat Cummins, brain.
I know he's a bigger leader connect.
I listened to all the podcasts and stuff and everything that he's on.
Oh, I had this answer prepared and now I'm in the moment.
I can't think of the right word.
Great leaders.
I would love to, like, obviously LeBron James is my basketball hero.
So, to be able to be in the same room as him.
Brianna Stewart.
I think there's so many great ladies with great strengths.
Yeah.
um and weaknesses but you often see that the best leaders have the same things in common so
um anyone that's really been at the top of their craft i would really love to pick their brain
about tess been a great honor to spend some time with you could not be more excited to see you as
captain of the australian olympic team the opal's heading into paris and we wish you all the best
it feels like team couldn't be in better shape having you as their captain and again really
thank you for being part of the leader community it's been awesome to see you thank you luke thank
you so much for having me it's my great honor and i'm very humbled to be part of the community
thanks for listening to another episode of the empowering leaders podcast huge thanks as always
to our great friends at temper and we encourage you to check out our leader connect program
new episodes are out every wednesday morning at 6 a.m