Rochelle Courtney is a remarkable individual supporting and changing the lives of vulnerable
women around Australia and the world. Have a listen to Rochelle share her story of how difficult
it still is in mainstream media to talk about the topic of periods for women and even more so period
poverty. She shares the joy of having NRL players volunteer in the warehouse packing sanitary
products for women and the passion and joy that that provides. She has a really clear, simple way
of communicating the message of her charity Share the Dignity. A remarkable Australian who went from
spending six months in jail to being awarded and recognised for her leadership. It's people like
Rochelle Courtney who inspire the work we do at Alita and specifically our signature program
Alita Connect. Founded with my great friend Matt Waterwitz, we curate bespoke leadership groups. We
bring together remarkable people like Rochelle from different backgrounds and diverse leaders
coming together to learn, to share, to connect.
In facilitated bespoke leadership groups. Love you to check it out. Head to alitacollective.com.
You can book a discovery call. Myself or Matt will jump on a call with you personally
and share with you our passion for what it's like to bring together different leaders from
different backgrounds to learn, to connect and to share. Huge thank you as always to Jason Nicholas
and the team at Temper Bedding supporting conversations like this on the Empowering
Leaders podcast. We're incredibly grateful. Temper, a mattress like no other. NASA approved.
FaceAge technology. I sleep on a temper mattress every night and it is simply life-changing.
Leaders like Rochelle and those that have consistent success in their lives all understand
the value of sleep. In fact, we hear Rochelle talk about eight hours of sleep being one of the
things that she makes sure happens every night. Invest in a temper mattress. It will change your
life. Rochelle Courtney is the founder and managing director of women's charity, Share the
Dignity. Share the Dignity makes a real difference in the lives of those experiencing homelessness,
fleeing domestic violence or doing it tough by distributing period products for women,
girls and anyone that menstruates that needs support. Share the Dignity partners with over
3,000 charities nationally and has over 6,000 volunteers Australia-wide. Rochelle was recently
awarded the 2023 Australian Award for Excellence in Women's Leadership. Rochelle has made this
outstanding contribution despite suffering her own family history of domestic violence
and making a serious error of judgment that resulted in her pleading guilty to fraud,
having to sell the family home to make restitution, serving six months in a women's prison.
Rochelle, thanks for joining me today and can I firstly say congratulations on your award,
really well deserved. Thank you, thank you. Appreciate your time. I have won awards for
other things like humanitarian awards but never a leadership award so it's quite humbling to be
there with some of those amazing women that have previously received those awards. Yeah,
what a great, great story. If I could go back, Rochelle, to the start,
you're incredibly open about this but over 13 years ago you had to leave your daughters behind
to serve six months in the Brisbane women's prison. It's an incredible story for me to see
you go from there, standing on the stage, as you just said, receiving an award for excellence in
women's leadership. Can you share with us what led you to ending up in jail and how
you found a way to achieve so much? I think the major thing for me when I was
a waif, I could have been anywhere in the world on a desert island on a beautiful,
being taken away from my two daughters was the worst part of all of it. I recently saw Liz Ellis
win for I'm a Celebrity, Get Me Out of Here and she will say to you the most painful bit
was being away from her children. I didn't get that choice. That choice was put on me because
of my errors and so that was a really hefty price for me to pay but it was also a really hefty price
for my children to have to pay. I think it's a really hefty price for me to have to pay.
Michelle, you find yourself then, from what you read, it's an incredibly confronting experience.
I can't speak to it. The research says that most people who are incarcerated for any length of
time, their outcomes are significantly worse afterwards than it often is the start of a
spiral downwards. Your story is incredible. You have defied the odds. Where did you find
that resilience and that courage? People make mistakes.
I was one of those people who made mistakes and to not let it define me was what I was always
going to do. It wasn't why I started the charity. That was not the reason. I just found a problem
in Australia that I didn't know existed and was really embarrassed that the problem had not been
rectified. I think that there is so much shame when it comes to my past that finding a way
to heal myself from that was probably,
the hardest part of it all. I know that sitting in jail with those women, a lot of those women
are on a revolving door and a lot of those women come from families with trauma involved in their
past. If you don't ever fix that trauma for them, then that's why they're going to keep
returning in there. I know some ladies that were in there were there for the winter.
They would simply offend so that they had somewhere to live.
How do we create a better world where that doesn't happen?
Michelle, did you find that sitting in there and understanding those stories as you described,
what you just said then is just horrific and horrible, isn't it? The best alternative to
have a warm place is to commit a crime to end up in jail. When you think about that in
a wealthy country like Australia, it's terrible. Did that spark something in you in wanting
to help women in need?
Michelle Miller
I think the one story that there was, I think I became from an extrovert. I'd always been
an extrovert. I became an absolute introvert in there and I just sat and listened and I
think it was scary. There's no doubt that I was terrified, but I was exceptionally hurt
to not be around my kids. I was a single mother that had never spent a day, not spent very
much time away from my children.
Michelle Miller
But just to sit and listen and to hear this one woman, I will try to recall it without
crying, screaming on a phone because her parents had, her children had been returned to her
parents and her father abused her as a child, and so she'd run away, turned to drugs. She
tried to keep her children as far from possible away from her father. Just to hear that scream
and then just to sit there and listen to that child, it was horrible. I was afraid. I was
not aware of the consequences. I was holding on to my children, but I was scared because
I was so scared of them. I was so scared. I was so scared of them. I was so scared of them.
Literally, I was just patting her on the back and she was just telling the story and I was just like, how does this happen?
She's here for drug charges, but if we really unpacked it, what was it all about?
It was about her being sexually assaulted as a young girl and then the scream was that she didn't want that to happen to her children.
It's a tragic story, isn't it?
I can hear the emotion as you tell it and to experience that firsthand.
You're right, Rochelle, isn't it?
It's going back to where these things start, isn't it?
Often you end up with these people and they become outcasts.
The polite society, as we call it, say, okay, you're too hard then to deal with, aren't you?
You've been to jail, very hard to get employed, isn't it, if you've got a history of being incarcerated?
We just start to snowball, often from people who've experienced horrific things in their childhood.
It's the...
The unfairness of it is pretty profound, isn't it?
Yeah, you know, we're all quick to judge too, right?
We're all quick to judge that person sitting on the side of the streets or somebody who's addicted to drugs.
But, you know, I will tell you, if you just sit with them, you will hear and listen and learn.
And I just wish, as an Australia, that we would understand that and learn to do better.
Rochelle, the Share the Dignity story is incredible.
And as I was preparing for this interview...
I thought there's still something, you know, even for males, you know, uncomfortable talking about women and their periods.
And it's not something that we naturally sit around as part of life as it is.
Do you think that was part of why no one had done what you'd done and understood just how terrible this was for women in need?
That there isn't really mainstream discussion about it enough?
Yeah, I think that if you think about what can of worms I opened...
I was talking about periods when...
No one was talking about periods and poverty.
No one talks about poverty.
Mix them two together and bam, we've got something that no one wanted to be part of, right?
So, but for me, I always believed that there wasn't a person in Australia who wouldn't be empathetic to hearing that a woman was using socks or newspaper or wadded up toilet paper to deal with their period.
And when I first read that first article, I was like, oh my God, that is so embarrassing that I'd never ever thought of that, right?
And I'd suffered.
I'd suffered severely from endometriosis.
So for me, periods were a really bad part of my life.
So if I didn't suffer from endometriosis, would I probably have started the charity?
I probably wouldn't have because I wasn't...
I wouldn't have had that severe empathy to periods being a really negative part of your life.
And then imagine that and then not being able to afford sanitary items.
So, you know, I think that starting it was about...
I just can't believe that no one would want to do anything about it.
I think that whole leadership piece comes from just taking people on your journey to make sure that we can be part of the solution.
And I love what you said to me just before, you know, we set it low and started recording.
You said, I've just come from having eight NRL players pack sanitary products for women, which I love, isn't it?
The stereotype I played the other code, Australian Rules Football, was that, you know, big meathead footy players don't have any sense of care.
Yeah.
I love the fact that you've got them working in the charity.
How often does that happen?
Well, a couple of times a year.
I mean, we literally just heard from them the other day and said that they said the boys want to come in and volunteer again.
And we're like, not very far from that.
Like, it's incredible.
And the conversations that happen around as we're packing and doing things are really, you know, we've come a really long way.
And, you know, I think it's really important to understand that this is not a female's issue.
This is society's issue.
We are talking about periods and periods.
If you don't get your period, you come from somebody who did, right?
So they are relative to everybody.
Yeah, well said.
That's right.
Or you live with your wife and your daughters and it's as natural a part of life as anything.
You mentioned Liz Ellis before, who I feel lucky to call a great friend.
And I've known Liz for a long time, worked with Liz.
Australian netball royalty and just a champion and all around.
Yeah.
She won I'm a Celebrity, Get Me Out of Here and Share the Dignity was where she chose her $100,000.
And I thought it was worth playing Liz's explanation of why Share the Dignity has resonated so much.
Let's have a listen to Liz Ellis.
Look, I think Share the Dignity is so important because they provide much needed period products to women who are fleeing domestic violence,
who are homeless, who are struggling to make ends meet.
And with the rising cost of living, demand on this particular charity is greater than ever.
But they provide.
Sanitary packs to women who need them through 3000 charities across Australia.
They lobbied the government to remove the luxury tax on on period products.
And now they're lobbying to make sure that period products are available for free for women in public hospitals.
So it's one of those things we don't talk about enough.
You know, period is something that affects 50% of the adult population for 25% of their lives.
And if women can't access these products to help them be dignified, it affects their family.
It affects their life.
So Share the Dignity.
Really does hand people back their dignity in these really trying moments.
So I'm really proud to be able to say that, you know, $100,000 is going to them.
They've got plans on making sure they continue to stock their dignity vending machines so that women can access these products without having to ask or beg.
So I just love the work they do.
So listening to that back, Rochelle, from Liz Ellis, it must be rewarding for you to have this growing community of high profile support.
What does that mean to you?
I think when Liz Ellis talked about periods on national TV, I cried.
I cried because, to be honest, even to this day, eight days, eight years after I've started the charity, never have we been invited to speak about period poverty or Share the Dignity on any of the morning TV shows or the nighttime.
They won't talk about icky things on TV while people are having their breakfast or their night.
So for us to hear Liz openly talking about periods on a show.
You know, millions of people are watching.
We were so proud.
So the money is one thing, but the conversation is where the power is, right?
And I love having worked with Liz.
She calls a spade a shovel, Liz.
There's no gray with her.
You know exactly where you stand.
And I had the pleasure of working on the netball with her and not surprised that she's jumped in behind your great cause and just articulated that, as you said.
And I hadn't thought of it in that context, Rochelle.
Isn't it funny, isn't it?
You know, the big, big audiences in the morning find it too difficult to have this conversation.
It's not a great reflection on us, is it?
We're not, you know, you're making a big dent in it.
And that helps, doesn't it, when someone like Liz on primetime gives it the space?
Absolutely.
The only time that I've been invited to be on the Today Show was when we were fighting to remove the GST on our luxurious sanitary items.
But I think that conversation, we were allowed on the couch.
We were allowed on the couch because we were talking about money and not about periods, right?
Yeah, well, there you go, isn't it?
There's obviously a formula that needs to change.
So I will feel enlightened by this conversation.
I'm glad that you're doing it in such a profound way.
Can I ask the leadership question for you?
You're now running a big organization, as I mentioned in the intro.
That's 3,000 charities to collaborate with, 6,000 volunteers.
That is a significant enterprise in whatever space you call it.
What sort of leadership?
What sort of leadership qualities have you found within yourself?
Look, I, like Liz, have played netball all my life until I was 50.
So I only retired after my knee surgeon said no more.
So for me, I pull lots of my leadership skills from having played and coached netball.
I just believe that, you know, we were talking earlier, it takes a team of people to be able to make the magic happen.
So for me, leadership is about bringing the energy and bringing solutions to the problems but surrounding yourself.
So I think that's the most important thing that I can do.
I think that's the most important thing that I can do.
So I do not want to look at smart sheets and work out how to do that.
But I absolutely surround myself with people who have that skill set.
So I think making it easy for people to volunteer, making it easy for people to donate and making it easy for our corporates to come on board is probably, you know, my highest skill strength is like time is the most precious resource any of us have.
And so, you know, as a mum, as a juggler of many things, that was probably my highest leadership piece was making sure that we all could do what we needed to do with the best amount of time that we have.
And can I just break that down a bit because that's interesting to me.
And that is a great skill set, isn't it?
Making something that looks like a complex challenge and that is how do you distribute, you know, sanitary products Australia-wide?
How do you find the people?
How do you get the products to them?
And, you know, you just said that really simplistic.
How did you go about it?
Because that is often harder than it sounds.
Yeah, well, it is a logistical, a massive logistical beast.
But I will tell you that the same framework that I set up at the very beginning, we are still using eight years down the track.
So we have volunteer state team leaders and then they have a team underneath them.
If you donate in any Woolworths in March in, say, Bendigo, Ballarat, Tasmania, wherever they are, they stay in that central location.
Our volunteers go in, pick them up, then they register them on the phone what they've picked up and then the app tells them which charity to take them to.
So we've made it as simple as possible.
If I can't do it, I'm not expecting anybody else to do it, right?
Brilliant.
And I love it.
I want to just shift slightly gear and go back to you being a mother of your own two daughters and I'm sure they're incredibly proud of you.
I'm always fascinated by leadership on the home front.
What's your style?
What's your style there as a mother?
I now have grandchildren as well.
So my daughters are 25 and 24.
So mine was about making sure that they felt safe and heard and that we were always a team.
So we were always a team.
So if we were – I didn't clean and they made the mess.
We were a team always.
So we always turned Thursday afternoons, we turned the music on and we would all divide and conquer the chores.
So that we never had to do any housework on the weekend.
That was our retreat.
If you wore the piece of clothing, then we washed everything, put them in the centre and you wore it, you folded it and put it away.
So for me, it's always been about – it's about teamwork is the dream work.
And so, yeah, I think that's probably always been my thing.
And always – I've always taught my daughters never ask somebody to do something for you that you can do yourself.
Yeah, great.
A bit of wisdom there, isn't it, Rochelle, isn't it?
It's a challenge, isn't it?
We often do so much for them out of luck.
But then not leave them with any skill sets at the end when it's time to grow up.
And I love that.
It's a great way to frame it.
Oh, sorry.
I always said that my children are adults for a lot longer than they are children.
So make them great adults.
Yeah, well said.
And I love the teamwork aspect.
Often we talk about chores and the hierarchy.
And that, you know, is a challenge.
And I find my own four kids, you try – you know, you get frustrated.
Why don't you do this?
Why don't you – but I haven't thought of it through that lens, isn't it?
Now, we're a team.
Let's do this together.
Put some music on.
And make it happen.
I love it.
Yeah, beautifully said.
I don't think they always enjoyed it.
Trust me.
But, you know, it was about you can't go anywhere on the weekend.
None of us can go and do what we want to do on the weekends.
And most of our days Saturday were as a netball, right?
So, you know, let's just get it out of the way.
Hey, Rochelle, I've loved the experience of talking to people in different settings.
And yours is such a brilliant, unique space you contribute to.
And for us, in the leadership work we do, we love working with diverse leaders.
And we think there's –
There's some patterns of leadership that show up.
And I want to ask you about some dimension.
Starting with the idea of self-leadership,
I feel like yours is an incredible story of self-leadership.
What does that mean to you?
Self-leadership for me means about having my recipe of life under control.
And that recipe of life changes.
And for me now, it's about getting a good eight hours sleep.
Otherwise, you do not want to be anywhere near me.
That makes me the best version of me.
But also making sure that I get my walk in,
that I get to get to the gym, that I get to spend time with my kids
and my grandkids more so, and that I get to do some of the things
that spark joy for me so it's not just all emails and meetings
because otherwise, you know, life is short.
But that's about – and that for me, I have 20 staff here
and we have, you know, quite a big volunteer team leader.
I'm always talking to them about you can't be the best version of you
if you're not turning up.
So I can't ask you if you're not booking in holidays
and having things to look forward to and making sure that if, you know,
being at the gym or going for walks is important to you
and you're not doing that, then that's not bringing your best version of you
to your week, to your day, to your workplace.
Yeah, it's a great explanation for us.
And I was thinking of that analogy, isn't it?
You've got to, you know, put the oxygen mask on yourself first
before you can help anyone else really.
Absolutely.
If you don't do that and, you know, I can clearly see you apply that throughout.
Not in your own life, but pass that on in your organisation,
which is really powerful because it's not something that people get sometimes,
isn't it?
If you can't start with your own routines yourself, it's hard to impact others.
Speaking of impact others and Share the Dignity is doing that on a massive scale
and a beautiful story, but we see leaders are really conscious on a daily basis
of how they positively impact everyone in their environment.
How would you describe your version of that?
For me, my version is –
I would describe it as appreciation, making sure that our volunteers completely feel appreciated.
And I literally was spending time with a volunteer in Perth, our WA team leader this week,
and she said – she's a very successful OAM, is a CEO, and she said,
I come to Share the Dignity to feel appreciated and to get my cup full.
And I'm like, oh my God, she's so accomplished.
She said she feels appreciated at Share the Dignity.
And I would hope that that translates to everybody.
Everybody, every volunteer in our organisation.
Yeah, what a great story, isn't it?
It's that intangible, isn't it?
People are turning up who run their own businesses to get the community through Share the Dignity.
You've done something pretty special there, and no wonder it's such a success.
Really, this next dimension is about leaders creating and sharing their vision in a really clear way.
I mean, your vision has been a powerful one that no one had really seen that before and gone about it.
How did you go?
How did you go about creating and sharing that vision?
Probably through storytelling.
I think the most powerful thing that we can do as leaders is over-communicate and keep communicating to them about what our –
you know, sharing the stories, hearing the stories of a young girl who's experiencing homelessness and stealing socks,
making sure that we're constantly connecting our why to why they give their time,
even why people donate, even why corporations, big corporates help us.
It has to be – it has to come back to why do they choose us.
Because there's a lot of charities in Australia, right?
And the personal storytelling for you has always been the most powerful.
When you actually personalise it and hear the story of a young girl, is that what resonates?
Yeah, absolutely.
And I think there is – I can still tell stories from six years ago that I've heard, and I still will get goosebumps and cry.
So, you know, it's that – for me, that authentic leadership and that authentic voice that comes through, I hope, in everything that we do at Share the Dignity.
See, leaders like you are having a great impact, really curious,
and curiosity is often the jumping-off point for how people like you approach their learning and development.
What does curiosity mean for you?
I am always reading, and I'm always looking at ways that we can do things better.
We have a very good phrase here that I say, we don't make mistakes here, we just learn to do things better.
And so, you know, you learn from your mistakes.
That's what life's about, right?
I don't want to make any big monumental mistakes anymore like I have in my past.
But for me, it's about I always think in what we're doing here is sometimes just do it because we're trying to fix a solution to be able to make sure that other people just have the very basic of essentials, right?
So what really could go wrong?
What could possibly go wrong?
I love it.
And I was just as you're talking, I was talking about the mistake supportive environment that you've created.
I was talking to Ruddick Sully on this podcast, one of the creators and founders of Swiss Vitamins.
And they had a really sophisticated language around celebrating, making mistakes, wanted their team to do it.
And they turned it into something really, really powerful.
LSIs is what he called it.
I'm going to muck it up.
I was looking for my notes.
But have a listen to Ruddick's podcast.
Because one of their team had a monumental mistake and described it as a learning experience and it became their culture.
And it sounds like you've captivated that in a similar way.
You mentioned communicate, communicate, communicate.
We see that as a really common trait of leaders as well.
How have you gone about that?
We use Workplace.
So we are really lucky to be able to video content to all of our volunteers.
For example, if...
Hope Transport, who help us move product all around Australia.
I will always do about two or three videos straight to their staff.
So they understand the impact and share a story.
But there's many ways that we communicate.
We don't just do it through written communication.
We do it in video.
There's so many different ways to communicate now, right?
So we use them all.
So Workplace, is that an app?
It's like Facebook, but it's a closed workplace for our charity.
So organizations use it around Australia.
Around the world.
We were one of the first charities to use it when it came in in 2016.
It allows us to be able to break down communication.
So there is a WA.
There is an overall team of the six and a half thousand volunteers.
Then there is a communication group just for WA in each state.
And then that breaks it down even further into other littler groups.
So it's quite specific.
And all your team will log on to Workplace
and see that as their hub for finding out,
where the information sits.
Absolutely.
And I know I every day send five messages of gratitude to our volunteers.
And so I can always just send a message directly.
It's a little bit like Facebook.
So it's, yeah, it's in there.
Your five messages of gratitude.
I'm interested in that.
So what does that look and sound like?
So every day I will send something to somebody.
Like I know that this morning I sent one to Anu,
who is a...
Shiro in New South Wales,
who went out to a school to speak for Share the Dignity.
I can't be everywhere.
So, you know, like I just saw that in Workplace
where she'd put the picture and I just sent her a message and said,
I think, you know, I want to thank you and I appreciate you.
It doesn't need to be complex.
It just needs to be that they feel seen and heard.
And yeah, I'm really lucky to be surrounded by so many amazing people
and be on their team.
Yeah.
And you mentioned that.
And that links to the other dimension I want to talk to you about
was the sense of collaboration.
And we see leaders now really sophisticated in how they collaborate.
And clearly you're doing that on scale.
How important has that collaboration been for you?
Yeah.
Look, especially when you come to big global problems
like what we're trying to fix, I think collaboration is everything.
So we collaborate with three and a half thousand charities
because we couldn't actually get the period products
to the woman who's living on the street or fled domestic violence.
So it was really important for that collaboration,
collaboration piece to happen.
So, and then our volunteers collaborate with that charity
and then make relationships with them.
But we, you know, we've even done that on a global scale.
We held a global period poverty forum here in Australia
with people who've been working in this space around the world.
Never before have they all been brought together to try to work out
how could we eradicate period poverty around the world?
So, you know, collaboration is our middle name.
It is about everything that we do because we can't solve these.
We can't solve these problems on our own.
And I always think that 10 heads thinking about a problem is better than one.
Yeah, beautifully said.
But asking these two questions, Rochelle,
to all the brilliant people like you that I've had the pleasure of sitting down with,
who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Sharon Baker, who was my net pool coach when I was 16.
I love it.
I love there was not even a pause there.
Tell us about Sharon Baker.
Why did she have such an influence on you?
I just think she came...
She communicated really well.
She respected us as 15-year-olds.
And I think it made such an impact on who I was as a netball coach,
who I was as a mother.
I just...
I think that she's the first leader that I ever came across that led people
to do what give you outcomes.
So for me, everybody else had coached and they were always mums
and they were doing the best that they could,
but they were probably shoved into that job.
But yeah...
Yeah, I just think that, yeah.
Sharon just taught me some skills that I took through all of my life.
Well, great shout out to Sharon Baker.
And I love it, Rochelle, because I'm really passionate.
They're a father of four.
And sometimes a junior sporting coach can change your life
or a teacher or someone in a space that you love.
And it's a love that you've referenced that
because it is so important we get that right for our kids, isn't it?
If it's a happy place, it's really, really powerful.
Same vein.
We are passionate about collaboration.
We have a leadership business, a leader connect,
and we connect leaders from around the globe.
And so fascinated and passionate about collaboration.
If you could collaborate, Rochelle, with anyone on anything,
is there a name that springs to mind?
It might be in the Share the Dignity space.
It might be in another area of passion.
Is there someone that springs to mind?
Brene Brown.
I just...
I mean, I've read everything, but for me and for a lot of women,
there is such...
You know, that whole piece around being in the arena
and, you know, not thinking that you are good enough to be where...
You know, I will stand on the stage and accept an award
and I will absolutely be on the inside dying
because I don't believe that I should be there.
This imposter syndrome, no matter how much I try to overcome it,
and, you know, it is a real thing for women
and I would love to work with her further on...
Not me, but all of our volunteers and women in general.
Yeah, you know, beautifully said.
And what an impact she's had, Brene Brown.
And it's funny you say, for the incredible women like you
that I had the pleasure of speaking with and working with in recent times,
it's a real thing, isn't it?
You know, incredibly capable people and that is alive and well.
I mean, males to a lesser extent.
It tends to be, you know, often women who are brilliant
that still feel as though they're not worthy.
And Brene Brown's been the superhero on that front, hasn't she?
But put that on the agenda.
Yeah, she certainly has.
She's read, you know, the books that I have read
and the podcasts that I've listened to
have really helped me be the best version of me.
But, you know, it still exists and I, you know,
would love to dig a little deeper.
Well, Michelle, congratulations again.
Share the Dignity is just a remarkable contribution to the community.
Australia, it sounds like globally what you're doing
is making a massive impact.
And, you know, I love...
You know, for me, it's sitting in that space
and understanding more about it.
And for us males, it's something we do need
to have better discussions about and understand.
And, you know, as you described beautifully,
we either came from someone who has a period
or we live with it every day.
So for us to hopefully do our part
is at least the minimum worthwhile thing we can do.
So more strength to your arm.
And, Rochelle, you deserve everything that comes your way.
And I'm not surprised you're winning awards everywhere.
And thanks for taking the time today.
Thank you so much.
Thank you for listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast,
powered by Temper, a mattress like no other.
And to make sure you don't miss an episode,
click subscribe wherever you get your podcasts.