Really enjoyed catching up with this week's guest
on the Empowering Leaders podcast, Tim Hamill,
the Australian men's water polo head coach,
fresh from an amazing result at the Paris Olympics.
You hear him talk about the win over powerhouse
of world water polo Serbia in the group stage,
which for me is close to the biggest upset
of the whole Olympic Games.
A really important win for the history of our team.
When you're in the moment, you know,
you'd like to believe it's a very powerful victory,
but hearing some of our old boys speak on return,
they've spoken really nicely, in fact,
that they believe that may have been the biggest win
in Australian history, men's program-wise.
So to be part of that was really, really special.
Tim is a very proud member of the Elite Connect family
and he talks about the importance of what that collaborative forum
has meant for him and his coaching.
To be truthful, Luke, it's been a phenomenal program
to be part of.
Wonderful learnings that I've taken out.
A wonderful opportunity to share challenges
and get some feedback on that.
Tim's got a great way of explaining his use
of imagery and storytelling.
He's a powerful tool in his coaching toolkit.
We were nervous as a group
and I gave a great deal of thought to, you know,
what can I do to try and settle the group
three hours before literally the biggest moment
of our lives, sporting-wise.
And I landed on sending the group via WhatsApp
a simple graphic or image.
And each of those graphics or image
framed up the theme for that evening's game.
We are really privileged
to have Tim Hamill,
the Australian men's water polo coach,
as part of our Elite Connect community.
We curate groups of five to six people
from around the globe
to come together to learn, to connect and to share.
You don't have to be an elite sporting coach
to be part of it.
We'd love to chat to you.
Book a discovery call today.
Head to elitecollective.com.
Big thanks as always to Jason Nicholas
and his team for Tempur Betting.
Great leaders understand the importance of sleep.
It's NASA approved.
The best in world betting.
Check out Tempur today.
Tim Hamill is the current head coach
of the Australian men's water polo team
fresh from an incredible performance
at the Paris Olympic Games.
Defeating the defending Olympic champion Serbia,
the host nation France
and world number two Hungary in the group stage
before an incredible quarterfinal
seven all tie against the United States
before going down in a penalty shootout.
Tim himself had an outstanding international career
representing Australia
at FINA World Championship level.
After retiring from competitive play,
Tim has made an enormous contribution
as a coach.
His attention to detail,
focus on culture and development,
all supporting his vision of Australia
competing with the world's best.
Great to catch up with you.
Great to be here, Luke.
It's a real honour to speak with you today.
I've listened to your podcast for a couple of years now.
So to be on the other end of it's a real honour for me.
And yeah, thank you for having me.
I heard you speak in the build up to Paris
of saying that you wanted the Australian men's water polo team
to shock the world.
I feel like you achieved that
when you reflect back on Paris,
what are your emotions?
Yeah, the shocking the world piece
was a really important avenue for us to explore.
We are very much the underdogs in world water polo.
We've got the chip on the shoulder
as many Australians do as a team.
And we're really up against it,
against the powerhouses that are European water polo.
It was a really special journey for us.
And to be truthful with you,
it's the reflection post Paris
has been a really challenging one for me.
It'd be easy to sit back and enjoy the results,
which you mentioned a few moments ago,
but personally, for me as a coach,
it's been a struggle.
Yeah, it was a successful campaign in many measures,
but getting so close to a medal game
or playing for the medal for the first time
in Australian men's water polo history,
not getting there has left me quite a bit of taste in my mouth.
I remember immediately post game against USA,
I knew my words to the playing group
were going to be really, really important.
What to say, what not to say.
I ended up going down the path of,
you know, don't torture yourself, boys.
You know, we did it all in our power to get here today.
And what we've achieved is remarkable.
But I've found myself torturing myself
over the last couple of months.
Hopefully time will heal those wounds.
I had a great reflection session a couple of weeks ago
with a mentor of mine by the name of Toby Jenkins.
Where I landed with him was, Luke,
is I've used that yin-yang diagram
to try and get some peace out of the Olympic Games.
What that yin-yang means to me
is that, you know, there's a fair bit of white for us
in terms of good moments of the Olympic Games,
but there's that black dot
that sits quite defiantly in the middle of it.
And as I've landed on it,
for me, that's the price of entry at the Olympic Games.
And I'll move forward with that image in my mind
as an important one for us.
Can you give some context, Tim,
for those that maybe don't understand
the sport of water polo,
just how big it is in Europe,
particularly some of those Eastern European nations
that are perennial powerhouses,
Australia is a tiny island, really,
when you think about the funding that you get access to,
the trouble of, you know,
your players that do play overseas getting access to.
Can you maybe just frame how big an uphill battle it is?
The easiest way to articulate it, Luke,
would be that it's a national sport in those countries.
So when you look at the NRL and the AFLs here in Australia,
water polo in many countries in Europe
are that in their respective countries.
So, you know,
yes, football and basketball are big,
but water polo in many of the countries
is their national sport.
We are very much an amateur team
playing against the professionals
and the big beasts of Europe.
You know, the players that we see in Australian sport
taking up the marketing dollars
and taking up the TV time,
they're all water polo players in Europe.
So what we try and do from a small island
down here in Australia with water polo ranked,
sadly, quite lowly on our sporting list here in Australia
is actually quite phenomenal.
To try and take on those giants of the world.
You took a squad that had 10 of 13
who were first-time Olympic debutants.
And I've got to go to the Serbia game there,
the reigning Olympic champions, a powerhouse.
You kept them to only three goals in an 8-3 victory.
And as someone like me watching on,
you just were blown away by what that performance meant.
Is that something you can build on
for the future of what you're trying to achieve?
A really important win for the history of our team.
When you're in the moment,
you'd like to believe it's a very powerful victory.
But hearing some of our old boys speak on return,
they've spoken really nicely, in fact,
that they believe that may have been the biggest win
in Australian history, men's program-wise.
So to be part of that was really, really special.
As you mentioned, we had 10 on debut, so 10 of 13.
And I must admit,
an inexperienced and young coaching group as well.
So the piece that I walk away from Paris most proud about
is how the playing group accepted,
and took on the big beast that is the Olympic Games.
I remember sitting there on the bench
as the players were getting introduced to the crowd.
And I dare say all of us, 13 players and five staff,
their emotions were extremely raw and open.
And to see the group, not five minutes after that,
be able to play in their biggest games of their lives
was really impactful on us.
How we did it's a question I've been asked a lot.
I'm not sure.
I've landed on a really simple answer to be truthful with you, Luke.
As with many teams, a lot's gone into it.
Great people involved.
I know one thing from a coaching point of view
that I tried to do a little bit differently
was the use of images to create our visions and themes.
We were nervous as a group.
And I gave a great deal of thought to,
what can I do to try and settle the group?
Three hours before,
literally the biggest moment of our lives, sporting-wise.
And I landed on sending the group via WhatsApp
a simple graphic or image.
And each of those images,
each of those graphics or image
framed up the theme for that evening's game.
So a couple of examples of those for you.
I sent them a photo of a four-leaf clover.
So we get into the meeting room
a couple of hours before the big game
and I asked them, what does that mean to you?
And some of the responses that came back
were humorous and entertaining.
But at that moment,
it wasn't so much about the four-leaf clover.
I just felt the energy in the room
and the mood really settled into a nice space.
The four-leaf clover, for what it's worth,
is the whole, you know,
when opportunity's knocking on your front door,
don't be in your backyard looking for four-leaf clovers.
And I said to the playing group that, you know,
the front door's being knocked at the moment.
Let's make sure we answer it.
We delve into Australian history
and we spoke about the battle at Villers-Bretonneux in 1914,
you know, prior to the French game.
And I certainly wasn't trying to evoke any war thoughts
because, you know,
our world's got too much of that at the moment.
But as you may be aware,
there's a famous sign that still exists in Villers-Bretonneux
about don't forget Australia.
And that city outside of Paris
hasn't forgotten Australia since that time.
And our theme for that night was
let's not make the French forget us after tonight.
We spoke about John Hendry,
the 19-year-old in Sydney Harbour,
for the Japanese attack
and the bravery that he showed.
So I tried to use these images to settle the group
and hopefully lighten the mood
leading into what was a, you know, big moment for us.
An Australian example we used was the cricket pitch.
So again,
it's Hungary and Hungarian water polo.
They're the most famous water polo country in the world.
And I sent the playing group a day five test match cricket pitch,
a photo of it.
Cracks all the way through it, uneven bounce.
And I asked them, what do you think this is for?
And again, we've got some humorous examples.
Light in the room started to come in.
And that one was about that if we give the Hungarians
a day one cricket pitch, a flat track, sun's out,
blue skies, they will beat us.
But our first moments and our first contacts in that game,
we need to present them with a day five pitch.
What does that look like from a water polo point of view?
It looks like this, this and this from a tactical point of view.
So I found those graphics that I ended up using
with the other coaches,
created a real lightness to the group
and hopefully settled their nerves
walking into some big moments for us.
Thanks for sharing.
It's brilliant.
It's someone who watches your sport,
but doesn't understand.
I can get that image of, it's David and Goliath, isn't it?
Really, as you said, you really need to do something
that unsettles the big giant.
And on paper, if everything goes well,
it's really a no contest probably.
But I love how you've been able to change the psychology
and release the tension at the same time,
but create an opportunity.
Is that what you've had to do,
given you are often coming up against these opponents
that no one expects you to win against?
The David and Goliath piece was exactly that.
We spoke about that.
And we didn't ignore that.
We knew the home crowd against the French
were going to be on their side,
but we really tried to flip things in our favour.
But going up against some of the powerhouses
was the challenge.
From a sporting context,
if we played really traditional water polo,
it's very unlikely that we would have been successful.
So one of our main mantras and vision pieces
for the three years was creating chaos.
So what that looks like for us is that
if a great white shark,
and we're known as the Aussie Sharks,
if a great white shark turns up to Bondi
Beach in the middle of summer
with 20,000 people around,
there's a fair bit of chaos that is going to be created.
So in terms of our style of play,
if we played very, very traditional water polo,
I dare say we wouldn't have won.
So our theme was very much about creating chaos
with our tactics that we use,
with our approach that we use.
I've since heard some of the players talk about,
you know, in the call room prior to the game.
And we're sitting there as a very inexperienced team,
10 on debut, as you mentioned,
against these, you know,
triple Olympic champions and four or 500 internationals,
three, four, five-time Olympians.
And we had some real characters in our team
that chose that moment to test out the opposition
from a point.
And there was some laughter and some joking
and some banter with the Australian team.
And we've since learned that, you know,
the Serbians or the Hungarians or the French
are looking at us like,
well, these guys are crazy.
Like, how can they be in this mood 10 minutes before
what will ultimately determine our success
in the Olympic Games?
So we're using,
we're using,
we're using that whole David and Goliath piece
and the underdog piece to work in our advantage.
And I guess we tried to embrace as best we could
for the three-year cycle.
I heard some of your swimmers quoted throughout the games
that they felt like they were powerhouse swimmers
and that they could really hurt the opposition
with their swimming strength.
Was that another little one percenter
that you tried to instill in your group
that there was some competitive advantage
in their natural strength?
Absolutely.
For those who aren't aware,
water polo is very much like basketball,
where everyone goes up into it,
they'll attack,
and everyone comes down into defence.
So the European teams wish we'd play in a 15-metre pool
whereby they could attack or defend
and turn around and do the opposite,
whereby we would prefer to play in as long a pool as possible.
It's 30 metres at the moment,
but we had to be the fittest team at the Olympic Games
because if we weren't
and we went down very much a technical piece
against the Europeans,
again, we would have struggled.
So again, we're really clear from day one
that we were going to present at the Olympic Games
as the fittest,
and fastest team,
and it was hard work for the playing group
to get to that point,
but we certainly got there.
We spoke a lot about no 7 out of 10s,
which was another little framework we had,
and what the 7 out of 10 example for us was, Luke,
was that if you ask somebody
how's their day going out of 10,
and they tell you it's a 7 out of 10,
I would sit there and not really know
whether they're having a good or bad day.
If they said to me they're 6 out of 10,
then you know they're not having a good one.
If they said they're 8 out of 10,
you know they're having,
they're having a better day.
So from a training point of view,
we tried to not train at a 7 out of 10.
So we were clear that we needed to train
9 and 10 out of 10 at different times
to get to the level we needed to,
but we're also really comfortable
to head down to that 2 or 3 out of 10 moment
and enjoy our time, enjoy our training,
if and when we needed to,
and I believe that really helped us
because I think so often we try and mark time
and just get through session to session
and day to day and 7 out of 10s,
and ultimately I don't think we get
to peak physical fitness
if we approach it like that.
Yeah, what a great analogy
and a really clear thinking,
it sounds like, in all your coaching.
We've loved, Tim, having you
in our Elite and Connect program
and you've been in a group with Xavier Clark
from North Melbourne,
who's doing an amazing job as hopefully
AFL's first ever Indigenous senior coach.
It's great.
I hope that that will be the case.
Kenny Atkinson from the Golden State Warriors,
Aubrey Pleasant from the LA Rams,
Jacob Chance from Melbourne United,
and we bring these groups together.
This occasion,
it's an all-sporting group,
but non-competing sports around the globe.
Have you found that experience
of being able to share some of your wisdom
and learn from others?
To be truthful, Luke,
it's been a phenomenal program to be a part of.
The Elite and Connect and Elite family
is a great one,
and thank you for the work you do in that space.
Like many coaches,
you see that list of coaches
that you just presented there,
and Kenny Atkinson has since gone on
to be appointed Cleveland Cavaliers head coach,
so he only started last week
in his head coach capacity.
And I guess, you know,
to feel the imposter syndrome
start to rise in me
when you see that group,
you know, what can I offer to that group?
You know, they're far more versed than I am.
But being a part of those group
has been great for me.
Wonderful learnings that I've taken out,
a wonderful opportunity to share challenges
and get some feedback on that.
And I know even two weeks
before the Olympic Games,
I had a session with the Elite group,
and it would have been really easy
to not be a part of that,
given the games were just around
the corner.
But I find myself finishing
of those sessions
with a real lightness to me,
a real clarity of thinking,
and certainly enjoyment from it.
So yeah, wonderful piece of work
that we're involved with,
and yeah, absolutely helped my coaching.
And yeah, I hold those coaches
and Marley, our facilitator,
in great respect.
Yeah, Tim, I appreciate your feedback on that.
And I think the imposter syndrome
is something that is real for all of us
and never ceases to surprise me.
People that are doing it,
doing amazing things
and had a history of success like yours,
but a lot of people,
that is a barrier for them
that they feel as though
you need to have had
some sort of level of achievement.
Would you recommend it to others,
that idea of actually getting together
and curating a group of people
who think differently than you?
And that's what we really are passionate about.
You don't often say,
you don't need to be Tim Howie,
you don't need to be
the Australian men's water polo coach
and be at the Olympic Games.
You can be yourself.
Is that something you'd recommend to others?
Absolutely, Luke.
I'm not sure that I would have
coached the way I coached at Paris
without those communication with that group.
So that for me is a pretty strong indication
of the importance that's played in my coaching.
And also for not just your coaching,
you know, as a person,
as a father,
as a husband,
as a friend,
as a son,
as a brother.
Yeah, I've found that
you go in thinking
it's just going to help your coaching,
but I feel it's helping me
become hopefully a better person
throughout the process as well.
Yeah, appreciate you sharing that
you know our passion for this idea
of success leaving clues
and that it's very hard
to be able to impact others
unless you understand yourself first.
And I want to ask you
about a really hectic time
over the last three years
appointed Australian men's coach.
How have you been able to fill your cup up
consistently so that you can have
the impact you want on others?
I mentioned before my children.
That's a really nice space for me at the moment.
I love nothing more than taking my daughter Giselle
or my son Raf to their respective sports.
As a coach,
it becomes challenging at times
not to make comment
and I'm very deliberate
to sit a long way away and judge.
I'm not a judgmental person,
but you feel that inside you
as a coach at different times.
So my time with my kids
is really special to me.
I've delved a fair bit
into the yoga, meditation,
journaling type space,
which I think is very, very important for me.
I know, again, as a person coach
that if I'm not exercising,
I feel myself out of balance.
You know, I feel my hormonal level shift
and testosterone level
is not where they are.
So I spend a lot of time exercising.
But my big vice,
if you're looking for one,
is the ocean and it is the surfing.
I love nothing more than getting into the ocean.
I'm 45 minutes away from the beaches
here in Sydney, Australia.
A pleasingly urban surf wave pool
has just opened up at home,
which is a 10 minute drive from me.
So I spend a fair bit of time out there
at the moment surfing.
So they will be my pieces.
The other piece that I'm finding really nice
to fill the cup at the moment
is the grass.
Gratitude space.
I'm going on a journey at the moment
about providing secret gifts to people,
surprise books to their house,
recommendations.
I was at a conference,
water polo conference two weeks ago
and there was a young girl
in the session from Tamworth.
And I secretly found out
what her address was
and I've since sent her an Olympic cap
and some Olympic pins.
And she will know,
well, hopefully she'll know
that that didn't come from me.
I didn't send her a name on the back of it.
And I found that a really nice piece
to do and it's helped fill my cup, absolutely.
Yeah, brilliant answer.
And I love how sophisticated you are
in thinking about all of that.
And that last story is brilliant, isn't it?
It's a genuine goodwill gesture to pass on
knowing that there's nothing in it.
You're not going to receive anything in return.
So it's a great story.
What's one thing that has always worked for you
as a leader that you would never change?
The honesty piece becomes really important for me.
I, truthfully speaking,
didn't love my time.
As an athlete with a national team,
I was lucky enough to play in a world championships.
I didn't make an Olympic Games, you know,
before I missed out in the final squad,
but I made it play to world championships.
But the piece that I hang my hat on most
is around the honesty.
I only had a conversation 15 minutes ago
with the player,
essentially to say that I don't see them
part of the program moving forward
and here are the reasons why.
And they're not easy conversations to have,
but I find them far easier.
If I'm honest, I know in the future,
if any conversation comes up around that,
that I've spoken the truth.
So it doesn't make it any easier,
but I believe the whole honesty piece,
particularly with communication,
is vital to me.
Yeah, just remaining really passionate about what I do.
Yes, it's about water polo,
but we've got an opportunity to have an impact
on a large number of men and boys' lives.
And that's a big responsibility
that I take a lot of pride in,
but I'm also very passionate about.
I've got to ask the question,
just heard you say you didn't enjoy your time
in the Australian men's program,
despite playing at the highest level
and in the world.
Yeah, I think that's a good question.
I think that's a good question.
World Championships.
So what was missing for you in terms of enjoyment?
Yeah, it was very much an old school mentality
around you're a basket of eggs.
We will throw all those eggs against the wall.
Those that don't smash will make it.
Those that do smash won't make it.
And I was one that got broken.
I was one of those athletes that cracked
and ultimately didn't make the Olympic Games.
Even when I think back to that time,
I felt myself wanting to be a coach then.
And I have remembered stories of that time,
which was early 2000s,
about if I ever got this opportunity
to lead a group of people,
business, work, other,
that I would do it differently.
Absolutely good and bad lessons
with all coaches we have.
But I knew that if I had the opportunity,
I would do it differently.
I believe we often make a mistake around enjoyment.
When people see enjoyment,
it's like, well, they're not training hard.
They're not serious.
I don't see it that way.
I see that you can achieve great things
and still enjoy the journey and enjoy the ride.
And I think that my own playing days
have shaped a lot about myself as a coach right now.
And it was hard.
They need to be the fittest team in the world.
So it certainly wasn't easy three years for them.
And they trained amazingly well, the playing group.
But I do hope that in due course,
they enjoyed the memories and experience
and the moments that they created.
And they enjoyed the time.
They enjoyed the time with the national team.
Yeah, it's been a massive shift, hasn't it,
from the era that you were a player
and the way coaches coached in all sports, really,
as you said, that hierarchy.
And it was a brutal time, really, wasn't it?
And the eggs against the wall smashing,
I can relate to, isn't it?
And there was a body count of those
that didn't get through that
and left feeling pretty dissatisfied.
But I think you're a great example.
I feel like it's spawned a generation of coaches like you
who genuinely feel like there's a better,
healthier, smarter.
And effectively,
a more successful way to do it,
which I love hearing you share about.
I know you're really clear on the vision
and the way you've been able to set that vision.
You can hear it in what you've already shared with us.
But can you still,
a story, has there been a visionary leader
that's really inspired you
that in the past you felt compelled
to follow their vision?
I've been really fortunate in my whole life
to be surrounded by some great leaders and teachers.
I had my year six school reunion yesterday,
1988, I left school.
And I sat next to my,
year six teacher yesterday.
And he was really proud to see
where I'd landed from a national coaching point of view.
But he was my cricket coach and soccer coach
during the late 80s.
And I even think about how he used to teach us,
educate us, engage us in the program.
What a great leader he's been.
My mother and father and brother
are three people that I'm very, very close with.
My father unmatched work ethic and discipline.
My mother cared for others
and people first.
You would never see anyone better than her.
My brother, who's had to overcome some real adversity
in the last couple of years,
I've taken some real strong pieces out of them.
My mentor, essentially throughout my whole life,
is a gentleman by the name of Wayne Miranda.
Wayne was a poster boy in Balmain, Sydney, Australia.
I played first grade rugby league,
junior Australian golfer.
And he essentially had it all.
Sadly, at the moment,
he's got some really poor health,
dealing with some Parkinson's at the moment.
He's not as sharp as he once was.
But I remember back to a grand final
when he coached us in 1993 in the under-18s.
And we're in the grand final,
underdog team,
and three-quarter time presents.
And we're a group of 16, 17-year-old,
very impressionable young men.
And we're waiting for his Vince Lombardi speech
at three-quarter time.
You know, some Winston Churchill words of wisdom,
which will get us out of here.
which will get us over the line.
And I'll never forget,
he walked over,
and the 13 of us were looking up to him
with puppy eyes,
just waiting for what we need to do next.
And he left the pause
and said,
boys, if you believe in yourselves
and you believe in each other,
you'll win this game.
And walked off.
And that was it.
You know, sometimes more is more,
less is more.
And we went on to win that grand final,
11-7.
And I saw Wayne
only a couple of weeks ago.
I visited him at his home
and he's getting some care at the moment.
And I wasn't sure how much the Olympics
he was able to see
because of the time difference
and his health.
And I said to him,
oh, Wayne, did you get a chance
to watch the Olympics?
And there was a long pause.
And I was really fearful during that pause
whereby he was about to say that
he didn't know it was on
or he missed it
or wasn't able to find the channel, etc.
And he looked at me with his eyes
full of tears and said,
Tim, one of the best things
I've seen in my life.
And I get goosebumps now telling you,
I can feel my eyes getting misty
as we speak.
But for him, for me,
was well ahead of his time.
I mentioned some bad examples earlier
from a coaching point of view.
But when you talk about
genuine care of players,
yeah, he certainly set the tone
for me how it should be done.
And I've held our relationship
really fondly, fondly ever since.
And yeah, it was really nice
to see that he got to see
the Paris Olympic Games,
which he played a significant role
in terms of developing me
all those years ago.
Amazing impact, isn't it,
that people can have on you
right throughout your lifetime.
And what another beautiful story
about to come full circle
for him to see you
at the top of your game is incredible.
How do you carve out time to be curious?
We see that a lot,
that idea of curiosity.
And how have you been able
to integrate that into
what you're doing at the moment
as the Australian coach
of the men's water polo team?
Yeah.
The leader piece has been
really big for me, Luke,
as I mentioned before.
And my mum, if you listen to this,
will be really proud of this story.
Growing up, like you, I'm sure, Luke,
I wasn't a reader in terms of
I always wanted to be outside
and playing whatever I could
from a sport point of view.
And I chose to, didn't find time,
had no interest in reading.
So the joke in my family
is that I went through
12 years of school
and didn't read a book.
And I got to a point whereby
I realised that I was missing out.
And so,
as a former athlete,
I set myself a goal.
Who sets themselves a goal with reading?
But so have you.
And the first year,
I set out to read 12 books,
one a month.
And I started with very much
the traditional type books,
you know, sporting biographies,
autobiographies,
and, you know,
the Andre Agassi type books.
And I knocked over the year.
I read the 12 books.
And then year two,
I thought, well, you know,
progressive overload.
I need to hit 24.
So I went through, you know,
two books a month.
And I did that to,
for,
four years back to back.
So I ended up,
maths-wise,
close to 50 books.
So I've found reading
to be a really important piece
for me at the moment.
Pleasingly,
mum will be happy
that I've delved out
from your traditional sporting books
and autobiographies.
And I'm now reading
all sorts of different books.
And I've found that my,
my learning
has really accelerated
due to that.
I asked myself
why I wasn't curious earlier
in my coaching.
It didn't come from
knowing it all.
I've never been a person
that thinks that I know it all.
I certainly don't now.
I think I've probably got
more or less that I know now
than ever before.
But if I had my time again,
I would have gone down
this curiosity piece earlier.
I think it's greatly helped me,
you know,
in all facets of my life.
They say if you read
10 pages a day,
Tim,
you're going to get
close to 36 books a year.
And that sounds so true.
I've been trying to set myself
that 10 page a day.
And I'm not there
by any stretch.
But yeah,
I love that you've,
you know,
knocked over two a month
for four years.
It's brilliant.
I've got to ask you,
have you got a book recommendation?
If you had listeners
to pick one out
or two out,
what would you tell them to read?
Yeah, the last one,
at the moment,
I'm reading a book called
Unreasonable Hospitality.
I'm not sure whether
you've come across that book.
It's about the number one
ranked restaurant in the world.
Really fascinating story.
And essentially,
New York based restaurant.
Yes, that's the one.
I haven't read the book,
but I've heard
a little bit about it.
Yeah, in simple terms,
their service and their food
and everything
is phenomenal first class.
But one of the themes
from the book,
how I've picked up anyway,
is that extending the memory.
So when you leave that restaurant
and pay the bill,
probably a big one, mind you,
is that you get handed
a bowl of granola.
So tomorrow morning
when you wake up,
post your visit to the restaurant,
you start eating the granola
and then you've extended
your memory from that time
in the restaurant.
So again,
like I mentioned before
with the young girl
from Tamworth,
and her exposure
to the conference,
I tried to extend her memory
by sending her that gift.
I've been really fascinating
by the Johan Harari
Lost Connections book
as a young parent
and the use of phones
and social media.
I found that really powerful for me.
I was lucky enough
to have some contact
with Bryce Courtney
who worked for my uncle
in advertising for a lot of years.
So I've been lucky enough
to read his book,
particularly The Power of One.
Batavia,
the Peter Fitzsimons story,
I found a fascinating one.
And I need to put a disclaimer
on the next one.
I'm not a drug user.
I never have been.
It's something that's never been
part of my life.
But one of the most fascinating books
that I read
was a book called Marching Powder.
And it was a story
about a young Australian,
Rusty Young,
who travelled to Colombia
and South America.
And in the prison in Bolivia,
the most pure cocaine
was actually produced
in the prison.
So in the Lonely Planet,
guides 15 or 20 years ago,
they advertised this prison
as a tourist attraction.
A lot of corruption,
payoff and going in.
So yeah,
I've moved on
from the Phil Jackson's
and the Wayne Bennett's
and the Phil Knight stories
and the Kobe Bryant stories
to reading all sorts
of different things.
It's a fascinating story,
Marching Powder.
And the unreasonable
hospitality story
that I've heard before,
the waiters and the team
are so well trained there
to attention to detail.
And attuned to what's going on
with their customers.
And one of the waiters
had overheard someone say,
God, this has been
the best meal I've ever had.
But do you know
what I really feel like?
I feel like eating a hot dog.
And the legend has it
that the waiter went down
the street vendor in New York
because you've got the hot dog stands
on every corner,
purchased a New York hot dog,
put it into the kitchen.
They served it up
in sort of five-star
fine dining style.
And, you know,
talk about unreasonable hospitality.
The detail of that
is always fascinating.
To me,
we're really interested
in collaboration,
as you know,
through our leader space.
Have you got an example
of great collaboration
in your life?
Yeah, I was only
thinking the other day.
My interest in collaborating
with different people
and different coaches
is always really, really strong.
And I'm finding at the moment,
both myself personally
and the team,
depending on what phase we're at,
I'm finding a real interest
to try and seek out
certain coaches.
I was lucky enough
to spend some time
with Trent Robertson
at the Sydney Roosters,
who's also a member
of the Alida family.
And the three or four days
that I spent with he
and his team
were incredibly powerful for me.
And I walked in there
hoping to take a lot out,
which I certainly did.
But pleasingly,
it's also a reminder sometimes
that actually I might be
doing some things that are okay.
So I get the both.
There's a selfish piece
in terms of, you know,
post-paralyzing,
whereas how do you get the group
back up and running
after some big disappointment?
Yeah, thanks for sharing that as well.
You're a great storyteller
and you've got a great way
of communicating.
Have you had a mantra
about the way you communicate
your message?
Two come to mind
when I think about communication.
I only listened to one
of your recent podcasts
and it was interesting
that I've always felt
that communication
was a strength of mine.
But I think it's certainly
a work on for me,
particularly some
of the conversations
that we need to take place
at the moment.
And often we're finishing
someone's Olympic dream.
We're informing them
of non-selection Olympics
and that's a 4, 8, 12-year commitment.
So communication is an area
that I've always felt
quite comfortable and strong in.
But I guess I'm starting
to second-guess that now.
My son mentioned plays soccer
and I went down
and watched from a distance,
not too close.
I watched from a distance
and I heard his coach say to him,
there's a reason you have
two ears and one mouth.
And I really love that
in terms of the voice.
For me, where I land
with the communication piece
is the whole listen to understand,
not listen to respond.
I'm getting better at that,
but I still feel myself
at different times
wanting to solve,
wanting to react
to a certain conversation.
But I really love
listen to understand
and also getting an idea
of, you know,
what somebody wants
out of this communication with me.
You know, and if it requires
even asking that,
you know, what is it
you're looking for from me in this?
Tim, who's been the greatest leader
in your life?
Well, fantastic.
There's been a great deal of them.
I would go back to Wayne Miranda,
who I spoke to before.
I'll go to my father
and my mother and brother, uncle.
There would be the people
that, you know, really spring to mind.
I'm fortunate enough
to have a wonderful relationship
with my wife
and watching her lead the family unit
and, you know,
guide our children
through a difficult society
has been inspiring in itself.
She's a speech pathologist by trade,
does a lot of work
with the Indigenous community in Sydney.
She's exposed to some
challenging family situations
and family stories.
But seeing her navigate
through all of that,
the passion,
the leadership she's shown
is, you know,
it's really nice to see
and be part of
and hear her stories as well.
I'd ask you going back
to Wayne Miranda,
as you said,
who's been a lifelong mentor
and you've played
in the under-18 premiership with him
as a young rugby player.
Was that something
that you formalised,
that mentorship along the way
or was it just born out of a connection
that you had through growing up?
Yeah, it was...
I've spoken to a lot of the players
who played at that same time
and sometimes my memories
and reflections of a certain time
are different to the other people
in the group,
as happens naturally.
But to a boy
or to a man
that we all have
very much the same
positive thoughts
and memories
of those couple of years
under Wayne.
Wayne,
it's quite a unique situation
because he and my father
have a relationship
outside of mine.
He and my mother
have a relationship
outside of mine
and I personally
have a really strong connection
with him.
Wayne and I spent
a number of years in business
post-coach-athlete relationship.
It wasn't a deliberate choice
for me to ask him,
you know,
will you be my mentor?
You know, I need your guidance,
I need your support.
But he's always been there for me.
I've always loved
his ability to listen.
his ability to articulate
what I would foresee
as a really challenging situation
and put into simple words for me.
He gave me a
21st birthday card
which he spoke at that night
and I opened up the card
hoping, wishing, dreaming
of a long
couple of paragraphs
of dialogue
that he would produce to me.
And there was
only a couple of words in there
and his couple of words
to me were
don't change.
And I've kept that
21st birthday card
all my life.
I keep it on my desk
as a good reminder
of making sure
that I stay on track
and stay true
to what I believe in
in terms of
the honesty
and family values
and hopefully
a cup-half-full person
more often than not.
What a champion.
Amazing influence
of you.
He's had on you
by all the stories
that you've shared.
If you could collaborate
with anyone, Tim,
on anything
and you've got
clearly your visions
and passions for the success
that you're wanting to achieve,
is there someone
that's really
been forefront of mind
you'd love to collaborate with?
Kenny Atkinson's
part of the Alita family.
I'm interested to see he
in his first couple of days
literally,
they've got off to a good start,
Cleveland Cavaliers,
of his NBA career.
But at the moment,
I'm really loving my time
with our Alita group
and at the moment
that's really
fulfilling a lot for me.
It's been a great pleasure, Tim.
I've heard so much about you
and the person that you are
and to have the opportunity
to sit down
and learn a lot
from our conversation today.
I love your clear thinking
and your sense of values
and who you are
is so strong.
It's been a real privilege
for us to be able
to have you
in the Alita community
and thanks for joining me today.
It's been great.
Thank you for the work you do, Luke,
and to the Alita family.
I'm sure you get a lot
of positive comments about it,
but please be sure
that it has a huge impact
on people and coaches.
So thank you very much.
Thanks for listening
to another episode
of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Huge thanks, as always,
to our great friends at Temper
and we encourage you
to check out
our Alita Connect program.
New episodes are out
every Wednesday morning
at 6 a.m.