I hope you enjoy this episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast, powered by temper, a mattress like no other, with Tim Jarvis, an inspirational adventurer who recreated the famous Serena Shackleton adventure in the Antarctic.
To hear Tim's pragmatic, optimistic approach to any challenge in life is truly inspirational.
And he tells the story of writing himself notes before his solo journey to the South Pole that were a preemptive reminder of why he would never give up.
A man full of wisdom.
I hope you enjoy this chat as much as I did.
It's people like Tim who inspire the work we do at Alita.
I'd love you to check out our Alita Connect signature program where we bring together leaders from different backgrounds.
And we think everyone is a leader in their own environment, whether you're from the arts, whether you're from the sporting world, whether you're starting a business, whether you're an adventurer and inspiring.
A legend like Tim Jarvis.
We'd love you to check it out at AlitaCollective.com.
Huge thanks to the team at Temper for supporting the Empowering Leaders podcast, a mattress like no other.
We spend a third of our life roughly in bed.
Investing in a temper is something that will seriously change your life.
I really hope you enjoy this episode.
If you don't want to miss out in the future on the Empowering Leaders podcast, hit subscribe wherever you get your podcasts.
Tim Jarvis is an explorer, environmental scientist, author and leader.
As an adventurer, Tim has taken on some extraordinary challenges, including reenacting two of the harshest and most extreme Antarctic adventures, Douglas Worson and Ernest Shackleton's survival journeys.
Choosing to do them in the original clothing with the same gear that was used a century ago.
Tim holds master's degrees in environmental science and environmental law.
Tim's sustainability beliefs, a bit like his approach to expeditions, are based around a pragmatic optimism.
Tim provides strategic advice.
And practical sustainability advice to a range of corporate organisations.
And in 2016, was voted the Conservationist of the Year by the Australian Geographic Society.
Tim, it's a great pleasure to spend some time with you.
Thank you, Luke. Great to be here.
Tim, your newly released film, Shackleton, The Greatest Story of Survival, it's brilliant.
Thoroughly enjoy it.
I'd encourage everyone to see it, whether you know the story or don't know anything about it.
And for those that aren't so familiar, Tim, with Ernest Shackleton, can you tell us a little bit about him?
And why his leadership has been so important to you?
Yeah, thank you, Luke. And thanks for having me on the show. It's wonderful.
Look, Shackleton was a heroic era explorer.
So he was around at the same time as Douglas Mawson, which is around essentially the beginning of the 20th century, just before the First World War.
And he was an explorer who decided that he would cross Antarctica from one side to the other on his expedition.
And by doing that, he would have eclipsed what had already been achieved by Scott and the Norwegian Amundsen, which is to reach the South Pole, which is kind of the middle of the Antarctic, if you like.
So he thought, I will do one better. I'll go all the way across one side to the other via the South Pole in the middle.
And I think it's fair to say the whole expedition went wrong.
The ship he traveled south in called the Endurance was stuck in the ice and then crushed.
It sank, but it left Shackleton and his 27 crew.
Shackleton and his 27 crew stranded initially in the stricken ship for 10 months and then living on the pack ice for a further five months.
And then when the ice broke up, having to paddle to the nearest land, which for them was a place called Elephant Island, just off the Antarctic Peninsula.
There he left 22 of the men.
And he and the five strongest got in one of the expedition rowboats and managed this near suicidal journey across the Southern Ocean from Antarctica to a sub-Antarctic island called South Georgia.
Where he knew there were whaling stations.
And this is 1500 Ks across the Southern Ocean, which is rough and, you know, bitterly cold.
And he made it without any modern navigational aids, just using a sextant and a compass with mountains of seas.
Arrived at South Georgia, then had to climb through the mountains of South Georgia to reach the whaling station.
Managed to do that with no equipment and no maps.
Reached the whaling station, raised the alarm and ultimately saved all the men he'd left behind in Antarctica.
So it was just an incredible journey.
An incredible journey that took place over about two and a half years by the time you add it all up.
And I think the thing that appeals most to me about the leadership, there are so many lessons from it, is the fact that he left no one behind.
And he was emotionally intelligent enough to know that to get everybody to pull as one, he needed to, you know, pitch the message slightly differently to the different members of the team to get them to want to pull in the same direction.
Which is really what good leadership, what good leadership is.
And I think that message is so relevant to the world today, both the idea of not leaving anyone behind, kind of metaphorically, but also the fact that if you want to make issues like climate change, make inroads into dealing with them, you've got to understand everybody's motivated by slightly different things, not just guilt and fear.
So I think his time has come for his style of leadership.
Yeah, it's a brilliant recreation that you've done.
And I loved it too.
And as I said, I knew of the story, but you certainly took me into areas that I...
I hadn't thought of before.
And I didn't quite understand the genius of Shackleton.
He had an amazing ability to keep his men in high spirits in the toughest of situations.
His men loved him.
And he never asked them to do something that he wasn't prepared to do himself.
And for me, I looked at him and thought, you get this incredible care and empathy that he had.
And, you know, we're really passionate, you know, in these conversations.
I am certainly, Tim, about modern leadership.
And, you know, is it fair to say that maybe Shackleton was 100 years ahead of his time?
Yeah.
These are the traits that we see great modern leaders having 100 years later.
I think that's absolutely right.
I mean, he perhaps at the time wouldn't have described himself as an emotionally intelligent person
or any of the language we now use, but that's precisely what he was.
I mean, he really had tremendous empathy for his people.
He looked after his people.
Like you just said, quite rightly, he never asked people to do stuff he wasn't prepared to do himself.
And these are really unique, unique skills.
And, you know, I think he measured his success by how well his team got through the predicaments
or the challenges they found themselves in not looking to kind of point score for himself
so that he might be regarded as seen as a good leader.
I think he just looked to get everybody through the circumstances as best he could.
And that, at the end of the day, is another attribute of a good leader.
You know, you're almost kind of invisible to a point and the whole team moves forward.
But when asked what that success is down to,
they all kind of rate the fact that your oversight of the whole thing has been a major factor.
I think he was emotionally intelligent because, you know, he was Anglo-Irish.
And at the time, the Irish regarded him as a bit too English
and the English regarded him as a little bit too Irish.
And so he was used to being an outsider.
At a time when Michael Collins was all about, you know, Ireland separating from,
from Britain, there was a, there was a lot of that going on.
And so he was used to being clever enough to, to live in both worlds.
He lived in England, but he was, he was Irish.
And he was Merchant Navy rather than Royal Navy.
So he realized that he couldn't just rule with rank.
He had to rule with earning the respect of people as a kind of a Merchant Navy approach.
And he had a lot of women in his life as a young man.
You know, his mother and he had many sisters.
And I think that made him maybe a bit more emotionally intelligent
than the equivalent Edwardian male might've been back then.
And all of that made him a far more empathetic person.
And it is a great survival story and a great leadership story at the same time.
A little while ago, you described that boat journey from Elephant Island
where he and his men ended up across to South Georgia,
1500 kilometres, 800 nautical miles or thereabouts.
Some of the most treacherous waters on earth.
And to this day, and I think it's regarded maybe as the,
the most dangerous boat crossing that's ever been recorded potentially.
You chose to go back and replicate that journey using as close to the same equipment
as you could a hundred years later.
I mean, part of me wants to say why.
And the second part is, can you tell us a bit about it?
Well, I'm only 26.
Look what he's done to me.
The stresses of the war.
Look, I mean, first of all,
I really should say it was a team effort and I'm not just saying that to sound like a good guy.
I mean, there were, there were six of us in the boat.
I was the expedition leader, but there was some fantastic sailors and my climbing partner,
Baz Gray, who's the regimental sergeant major for Royal Marines in the UK.
A great survival expert.
So look, a wonderful, wonderful team effort amongst six people.
But look, I suppose I've always done expeditions because I like to test myself,
see what lies within.
You know, we're all interested in finding out a bit more about what life is all about
and our place in it.
And this drives a lot of human endeavour, whether it's sporting prowess or artistic self-expression
or looking for extraterrestrial life or entrepreneurialism or medical research.
I think a lot of it is driven by this desire to sort of find out more.
We're naturally inquisitive creatures, humans.
And for me, it just happens to manifest in wanting to push myself at these kind of these sort of
limits.
So I suppose it's in it's in my personality that I should want to do this.
In terms of Shackleton, it's the biggest one, biggest one that's out there.
And if you do a lot of expeditions in the modern era, wearing Gore-Tex and using satellite phones
and eating Mars bars, you can't help but think, you know, how would I stack up if I tried to do
things old school and would I stack up favourably against those great explorers of old, those men
and women who did these incredible things?
And so.
It's always been of interest.
And then his granddaughter, of course, asked me to do it.
And it was a rhetorical question.
She said, you know, will you?
She really meant you will.
And that was it.
The die was cast.
And Tim, I think a huge part of your passion for doing these adventures in Antarctica is
highlighting the devastating impact of climate change.
And it's very stark in the movie that you've released.
The word pragmatic optimist is a word you describe yourself.
You're what needs to be done as a global community to save the environment.
How do you describe your sustainability message?
Well, look, I think the sustainability message really is about pragmatic optimism.
It's about, you know, telling it like it is and having a plan to do what is required to get us out of the situation.
And look, expeditions really are all about that.
When Alexandra Shackleton, his granddaughter, asked me to do the trip, I didn't just, you know, build the boat,
get in it and start paddling in the right direction.
I really worked back from the goal I was seeking to achieve, which is, you know,
1,500 Ks, Southern Ocean, wearing cotton smocks, woolens, leather boots, eating lard,
navigating with a Sexton, big sea state, potential for some really serious consequences, obviously.
And you work back from all of that a lot to give yourself a list of things you need to have in place to give it a good go.
So the right team, the right logistics, enough money, the right risk assessment.
The right boat, the right skills.
And even then, it's very much down to luck as to whether or not you make it.
But I always work back from that outcome I seek to achieve.
And I think we need to do the same in the climate situation.
We know the goal we have.
We know it's to not warm the planet by more than 1.5 degrees Celsius, worst case 2.
We know what each country needs to do in order to make its contribution towards getting to that 1.5 degrees or no,
more than that.
And yet when we aggregate all the country's commitments and then below that companies and individuals' commitments within those countries,
we find that we're missing that target by, frankly, an order of magnitude.
And so I think we need to tell it like it is, be honest with ourselves and say, look,
how do we get back on course to making this carbon budget and the numbers achieve the outcome we seek to reach?
Otherwise, it will be like me getting.
In Shackleton's boat and just paddling roughly in the direction of South Georgia with no real hope of making it.
I find that, you know, without being too pessimistic, that's the situation we find ourselves in with the climate piece.
You know, we have an aspirational target.
But at the moment, we're not really being honest with what it will take to get us to that that end point.
And we know how to do it.
We have all the technology, all the policy mechanisms, if applied at scale, would kind of get us to one and a half Celsius.
It's just a case of getting on with the job.
That is a very pragmatic way to describe it and break it down.
Do you get frustrated?
There's loud voices that still question humans' influence in warming and want to have that debate, you know, in a loud way still.
To me, in a simplistic way, we have one planet.
We're all united in the fact that it's a pretty worthwhile goal.
We would think to save it for future generations.
And so it doesn't seem to be too hard a stretch for all of us to want to contribute, you know, burning rainforests down and plastics in the ocean.
And that's a separate conversation to the warming conversation you described.
But do you still get frustrated by the fact that it's really hard to get unity on something that should unify us all?
Yeah, look, I do.
I think I try and take a leaf out of Shackleton's book, which is to say, OK, what is going to be the kind of argument that's going to resonate with this person whose behavior I need to change?
And not everyone's influenced by the same thing.
And people have often said to me in the past, luckily, it's not a reality now.
But what would you do if you had a conversation, elevated conversation with Donald Trump, for example?
And I wouldn't have said, you know, how can you do this to the planet for my children on moral grounds?
I would have said, look, I've got a great opportunity for you that's going to give you energy security, jobs for America, keep America in the ascendancy economically.
And it's called renewable energy.
And there are almost.
A billion people working in renewable energy and associated sectors and only 51,000 working in the coal sector.
Which one do you want to back from a purely financial perspective?
And I think that's the kind of argument that would have would have worked with him.
I could have imagined him standing on a stage with me potentially and saying, look, I I'm not interested in what Tim says about the moral arguments for climate change, but I am interested in the economics of what he's saying.
And that's the sort of the shortest path to getting the outcome you want for an individual like him.
And can I say, I'm pleased it's not the reality that I'll be having a conversation with him.
But I think we need to be kind of clever in the way we package this stuff up.
Yes, I do get I do get frustrated.
But again, an expedition lesson is control what you can and don't worry about the rest.
And you keep working on the bits that you can control with people who are prepared to work with you and and progress, progress the agendas you can.
And then collectively, we'll make it to muter.
You're a passionate leader, passionate about exploring leadership and teaching it.
How do you describe great leadership for you?
Well, I mean, great leadership, if you boil it down, I'm all about really boiling it down into some fairly simple things.
I think good, good, great leadership is really about getting a group of people who maybe come from very disparate backgrounds to pull together to achieve a singular outcome.
That's really what it is.
The rest is is the conversation.
Kind of the detail.
You can be a good orator.
You can have the gift of the gab.
You can be very selfless.
You can be very honest.
You can instill trust in people.
But ultimately, it really comes down to understanding how you get a group of individuals to pull as one to achieve a singular outcome, understanding that they may all come from different start points.
And when applied to something like climate, I think we've missed a trick here.
I think we tend to still use guilt and fear based messaging.
To try and get change to happen at scale when, in fact, there are many, many more, you know, excuse the kind of the metaphor, you know, shades of green, if you like, that we can use to get people to move forward.
Not least of all, if you're talking to a super fund, it's the fact that, you know, things like renewables, blockchain technology, battery technology, electric vehicle technology, hydrogen, they'll all learn their their super fund.
Holders a decent return on their investment.
You don't even have to have a moral discussion.
You just have to want to protect their long term investment, their pension pot.
So I think I think it's about that.
It's about really understanding who it is you're leading and leading with with intelligence and emotional intelligence.
Tim, does safe nuclear energy play a role in saving the planet?
Well, look, I'm I'm I'm personally.
And these views don't reflect any of the organizations I work with.
They're just my own views.
I'm fairly philosophical about using nuclear in certain situations.
I think the conversation or the question for Australia is not whether we should use nuclear.
It's whether we should be exporting uranium in such vast quantities if we ourselves are not prepared to entertain the idea of nuclear on our shores or indeed nuclear low level radioactive waste on our shores.
So I don't know that it's right to sell uranium and make a large amount of money from it.
And they take the moral high ground with something like nuclear and not be prepared to to entertain it on our shores.
I don't think you can, you know, have one without the other.
You can't just choose to export and, you know, fill your boots and and then decide a moral grounds not to have nuclear yourself.
I think that's, you know, it feels like hypocrisy to me.
To do that.
Changing gear for a moment, Tim, the mental health crisis that seems to have overwhelmed the Western world, the World Health Organization express a view that by 2030, it will be, you know, one of the greatest, if not the greatest challenges facing humanity at that stage.
You're someone who knows a lot about adversity and dealing with adversity.
How do we teach people to become more resilient and able to cope with adversity?
Oh, look, resilience is something that really comes from, you know, there are there are there are many techniques one can use.
Personally, I take a leaf out of the expedition book.
And as I say, I mean, on our expedition, our Shackleton expedition, for example, any big storm could have wiped us off the face of the place, really.
But you don't worry about that.
You concern yourself with the things that you can control.
And I think therein lies the secret to dealing with any of these sort of existential crises.
Where you feel you're just a small player with a limited amount of control over over the direction that the planet or society is taking.
I think you need to retreat back into controlling what you can and break down the enormity of the challenge you face with into small pieces and just dealing with those.
Pick a thing and work on that.
And I run a reforestation project.
And it's amazing how, you know, individual individuals come down and plant a few trees.
And get this tremendous sense of calm and satisfaction at having planted 20 trees.
When, of course, the global situation might be such that we've lost a million trees that day or or far more than that.
But still, you personally being involved in in doing something about the problem really helps alleviate that sense of helplessness and that sense of that sense of stress or climate anxiety, particularly amongst young people.
Tim, we read Shackleton in his extensive writings.
One of the things he said.
There was that loneliness is the penalty of leadership.
Do you subscribe to that?
Yes.
Look, I think I do.
I've done trips that have genuinely been solo endeavors in places like Antarctica.
And look, they can be very lonely in their own way, of course, because you're in a vast landscape twice the size of Australia with endless white horizon on your own.
And whatever you can summon up in terms of mental and physical energy is is is the total amount of what you'll achieve.
But I have to say.
The level of loneliness one feels when one is in a position of leadership can sometimes or often, in fact, exceed that sense of, you know, loneliness when one is on one's own.
And I think it's because you're taking on the responsibility of of decision making at the end of the day.
You know, somebody the buck does ultimately have to stop with somebody on these kind of endeavors and on expeditions.
It's with it's with me where.
I'm leading it.
And, you know, you don't want to show too much in the way of for one of a better description weakness.
You want to show a sense of conviction that you can still achieve.
You want to be honest, but you want to also be pragmatically optimistic about about chances.
And, you know, taking a leaf out of Shackleton's book, you know, he had the men playing soccer on the ice when, frankly, they.
Really should have been considering how they were going to survive the rapidly approaching winter.
And I think it gave the men the confidence that Shackleton had the measure of the circumstances they found themselves in, because otherwise, why would you be playing soccer and doing language lessons if you didn't expect to make it through the winter?
And so as long as people you don't lose people's respect by them feeling you're not you've lost a grasp of the of the gravity of the situation.
I think it can really.
Reassure people if you remain calm, at least externally, and doing that sometimes, particularly on board Shackleton's boat, when you're pretty close proximity with people in some pretty hairy situations is not easy.
Tim, I'm always interested in the daily habits and routines of people like you have got such a clear sense of self-awareness and grasp and purpose around what you are and what you believe in.
And you go after these these great challenges and want to make a difference in the world.
What is.
That Tim Jarvis do on a daily basis to stay healthy and connected to the person you want to be?
Well, look, I'm very good at compartmentalizing things.
I am the proverbial goal oriented person, so I can pick something up, run with it, get it to the point where I feel comfortable that the momentum of that is where I want it to be.
Or, you know, some sort of intermediate goal has been achieved towards achieving the bigger picture goal in the long term.
And then I can put that.
I can put that down and go and pick something else up.
And I learned, you know, quite a few years ago by listening to people's feedback about how I led that that would would appear as a kind of skill that I have that, you know, enables me to do these things.
So on a given daily basis, I do 10 completely different things.
I do policy work in the environment space.
I organize the expeditions.
I work on film projects.
I work trying to motorize.
I motivate large numbers of volunteers in reforestation work.
But I'm also, you know, chasing tradies, playing with the kids.
I have this capacity, I think, to to put things down and just draw a line under them and think, OK, I'll part that for a while and move on to the next thing.
And I think it's a useful skill to have, particularly when you're dealing with these big issues that are far bigger than even the energy that a that a that a, you know, a very focused, driven individual can bring to the table.
That ability to be able to be able to put something down and move on and just forget about it for a moment and come back to it and have trust in in in the system and in the framework you put in place is a useful skill.
I'm fascinated in that, Tim, because there's always a school of thought.
People will subscribe to this.
Hey, you can't do too many.
You'll never do any of them.
Well, you take on these projects and people who are good at something really zero in on that and that becomes their life skill.
It's the opposite of of who I am as well.
I'm always jumping from one thing to the next.
And I love it.
I find it really interesting.
And the challenge I find is to do it well.
But in an example in how it works for you, you just find, you know, if you're giving that amount of time to.
To the movie, then that's that time and you can genuinely let that go until the next time comes around.
Is that always been with you or is it something that you've developed?
Look, it's something I wasn't really aware of until I saw that other people perhaps didn't didn't operate like that.
And I thought, well, maybe this is something that I wouldn't say is unique to me.
But for people who achieve things like the kind of things I'm doing, they're like project management exercises and they require different skill sets applied.
At different times to get things over the line, and I'd say in any major endeavor in life, you need a few different skills and you've got to bring them to bear at different moments.
I mean, you've got to have obviously a little bit of small P political now.
So you've got to understand how to work with people and be emotionally intelligent to work with different people that are driven by different things of different different set value sets.
For example, you've got to have a bit of technical understanding of the.
The area that you're seeking to try and work in helps if you have a particular area, even if even if it's not something which is across the whole field of endeavor, but have one niche area of skill that you can kind of fall back on.
You've got to have the resilience to see something through.
And I meet a lot of great people who have all the attributes, but perhaps not the the endurance of the resilience to see something through.
And I often say to them, you know, you just.
Keep going and you will ultimately be successful, but it does take it does take that that sense of resilience to do it.
And you need not only an understanding of the kind of the way the world works and a technical ability, but also a sense of idealism.
And I find, you know, again, this is a sweeping generalization with young people.
I see a tremendous amount of idealism for some of the older ones.
Sometimes that idealism is being blunted.
By by the world.
And I would urge them to never lose sight of that, because really, as you get into those advanced years, particularly in a business context, you know, you've got such a wealth of knowledge that if you could bring that to bear and just keep the faith.
It's amazing what what what change you could make happen.
So it's retaining that sense of idealism as well.
Yeah, it's a great message, Tim.
And I love that story, isn't it?
The skills and capability.
But that grit.
And that capacity to push through and not, you know, wilter at any stage, I suppose, isn't it?
There's hurdles all the time.
And people who have that sense of determination are the ones.
I think it's how you react to problems, you know, to quote in management speak, they talk about failing forward, don't they?
And failure is feedback.
And I think, you know, you've really got to learn to enjoy problems coming up because they represent yet another opportunity for you to either prove yourself to yourself or to others.
And also to learn and grow as a person.
And I quite enjoy a problem.
There may be a few a few bits of interesting language when when when a problem, you know, presents itself.
But immediately I click into thinking, OK, how are we going to overcome this?
And in so doing, what am I going to learn from that?
And it becomes quite addictive.
You know, on South Georgia, when we did the mountain crossing after the boat journey, retracing Shackleton.
And three of my guys ended up in very poor physical shape and couldn't do the mountain crossing.
And that left myself, Baz and Paul Larson, who were kind of the expedition leader, hard man and navigator respectively, to do the crossing.
And we could easily have looked at one another and thought, you know, how unlucky are we?
All of our safety net is gone in doing it as a team of six.
But instead, we thought, hold on a second.
Shackleton lost three men on his journey to injury.
I mean, they they were they were they were alive, but they were unable to do the mountain crossing.
And he did it as the expedition leader with Tom Crean, the hard man and Frank Worsley, the navigator.
So we're doing it as exactly the same three as he had done.
And that brings us closer to what he experienced, even though it's a hell of a lot more dangerous.
Isn't that great? And we sort of dined out on that one.
So you're always kind of trying to look for positives in any situation.
Yeah, what a sense of destiny in that, isn't it?
I mean, that story for Ernest Shackleton's granddaughter to ask you to do it and then for it to play it like that.
It's, you know, it's a universal piece of energy at play there for sure.
You do a lot of work with different corporations.
I'm fascinated in Patagonia.
What a remarkable company and an amazing story in recent times to the founder effectively donating that incredible business to the sustainability of the planet.
Can you tell me a bit about your work?
Can you tell me a bit about your work advising Patagonia on their sustainability?
Yes, well, look, I mean, I've had a very good working relationship and friendship with Dana Shanasey, who's a very inspiring guy.
He's the CEO of Patagonia here in Australia.
And essentially, I have been working for about five years now on trying to get an East Antarctic marine protected area set up down in the Antarctic.
Be about a million.
Square kilometers of ocean protected in perpetuity.
And that million square kilometers is the bit of ocean essentially opposite Australia's land base holding in Antarctica, because we actually have 42 percent of Antarctic.
Antarctica is Australian Antarctic territory.
So I've been working on that for about five years with an organization in the U.S. called Pew, who've got representation here in Australia.
And at the same time, Patagonia have been working for a long time.
In marine protection, in funding films about marine protection, in supporting charities and NGOs that do work in that space.
And most recently, I've been working with them on on adding value to their whole marine protection program, which is already pretty well advanced.
And they're a very inspiring company.
I think Yvonne Schoonard, who's the owner of Patagonia, is a climber from yesteryear.
Yeah, he's in his advanced years now.
But what a legend of a guy.
And he decided that, you know, they were going to donate all the profits of the of the company to to climate change, to fighting climate change, which is just, you know, amazing, amazing thing to do.
So, look, I'm very inspired in working with them.
But marine protection is is is the way I'm working with them at the moment.
They do so much more.
Yeah, wonderful.
From the very start, they had that vision and have lived those values, haven't they?
And shown the way for so many other companies.
The original B Corp, if you if you like, and I'm not surprised that that is the legacy that that organization will have.
Tim, I've loved sitting across from different leaders and different backgrounds and your leadership stories is so unique and so much wisdom in it.
And we feel like there are some some pretty consistent dimensions of what great leadership looks like.
And I'm keen to talk to you about starting with self-leadership.
Tim, we don't think you can really lead unless you've got a sense of what self-leadership means to you.
When I when I ask you about that, how do you think of self-leadership?
Well, I think about my own motivations.
I think about being true to myself and what my moral compass looks like.
But I also have a sense of humility.
It's interesting.
I was having a very interesting conversation the other day with some sports psychologists, and they were talking about the difference.
Between the psychology of leadership in a team sport context where you're up against human opposition and leadership in the context of, say, the mountains or Antarctica or the ocean.
And at the end of the day, the difference is that one involves, I suppose, working up against human opposition, whereas in the outdoors, it's just you and what you can bring.
And nature is the thing you're not up against.
But you're working with, I suppose.
And that brings about a real sense of humility.
You don't take seriously the things you've achieved before.
Your CV of previous accomplishments doesn't mean anything to nature.
So I bring that humility to each situation I find myself in.
Don't take myself very seriously.
Take what I do seriously when I'm there.
I think that's a very important, very important aspect to it all.
And I understand my own limitations.
And weaknesses enough to sort of recruit the right people to help fill those gaps and make up shortfalls in that area.
And I think being honest with yourself and honest with others about your weaknesses also engenders a sense of sort of trust and respect amongst your team.
But a common theme, you know, and also in the movie you just released, Shackleton was very particular.
Recruiting the men that were on that expedition and probably the reason why they all survived in the end, wasn't it?
He had a very, from the story you tell, a strict criteria about problem solvers and positive energy.
I was lucky enough in this podcast recently to talk to Matt Fleur, the coach of the Green Bay Packers, who's doing an amazing job in a sporting context.
But, you know, 23 coaching staff and he spoke about that jigsaw and every person being so important to complement the skills that he had enough humility to realise he didn't have the answers on everything.
An incredibly humble guy.
It's a common theme.
I'm not surprised to hear your thoughts on that too around self-leadership.
We see leaders, Tim, are very conscious around, on a daily basis, how they impact other people positively in the environments that they are in.
How do you go about doing that on a daily basis, impacting other people positively?
Well, I think, you know, the goal is, the role of leader really is to bring out the best in people.
And, you know, this takes a certain amount.
The maturity to really come to terms with.
I'll give you an example.
With the Shackleton expedition, when we finished, we had made a film on that original expedition with a little camera that was on our boat that filmed everything that happened.
And when it all finished, we had some exit interviews conducted by Discovery Channel.
And they interviewed me and they interviewed the five other guys in the team.
And each one of them, in their exit interview, which was an hour long, conducted immediately that we'd finished.
He was still a beard.
And probably hadn't showered and things like that.
And were in our old clothes and really looked the part.
And each one of them basically said that they felt they had been the reason why the whole endeavor had been so successful.
You know, they did it modestly, but they were confident in their own minds that, you know, they were the kind of key thing.
Bass said he felt that the way that the climbing was conducted in the mountains, really under his, ultimately his leadership for that particular component,
was, you know, it was a lot of work.
That was why we got through it.
You know, the sailors said, well, if I haven't navigated so well and got the boat through those storms we found ourselves in, I suspect we may not have made it.
The guy who built the boat said, well, if it hadn't been for me doing such a good job on the construction of the boat, I don't think it would have remained afloat.
And the guy who filmed it all and was also a climber said, well, if I hadn't been there for the climbing and also to film this, we wouldn't have had the funding to make this in the first place.
Long story short, everybody felt that they were instrumental in the whole expedition being.
Such a success.
And I remember listening to this and actually at the time being a little bit challenged by this, thinking, how can they say that?
You know, I was the leader of that and I pulled it together.
But then I thought for a moment that maybe a good reflection on how good your leadership is, is how each individual feels that they were able to bring their A game, that they were the deciding factor.
And, you know, maybe that is a better reflection on good leadership.
The fact that your people all feel valued.
Valued and feel that they could, you know, bring the best they had to give.
And your role is to enable them to do that.
And so I've kind of revisited that history.
I now feel very happy about that.
I regard that as a great success that each person felt so empowered by the whole thing.
And you use that word empowered at the end, Tim.
It's the title of this podcast, Empowering Leadership and Empowering Leaders.
Because exactly as you said, you know, that expedition was a success.
You empowered those guys subconsciously.
Consciously, all consciously to do their job so well that they realised how important they were.
It's exactly, you know, what we see consistently.
It's a great story.
Thanks for sharing that.
Creating and sharing a vision.
We see leaders are really conscious about how they go about that.
You've had some really clear visions that you've taken on and accomplished.
How have you gone about that?
Well, I think it's very important to set that all out in advance.
I mean, it's interesting.
I use the vision mission.
And the distinction between those two actually to talk both to Shackleton's story,
but also to climate as an issue.
I mean, with Shackleton's journey, of course, you know,
their vision had been to do something at the limits of human endurance,
pushing new boundaries, returning as heroes,
whatever their vision might have been in their own minds.
Their mission was to cross Antarctica in order to achieve that.
Now, with the loss of the ship,
the mission evidently changed.
They weren't going to cross Antarctica anymore.
Shackleton gathered everybody around and said,
look, this isn't going to happen.
The new mission is saving ourselves.
The good news is we're still going to achieve the vision.
It's just that the mission has changed.
And I use that kind of metaphor to talk to, say, for example,
a company involved in fossil fuel energy production and say,
look, you know, your vision might be to provide energy to businesses,
and people to enable them to achieve their life goals whatever it might be or their business
objectives none of that needs to change it's just the mission has to change the way you go about
doing this has to change you don't have to abandon the dna of the organization you just have to do
things differently and i think most people can can understand and that's a good definition by
the word purposeful leadership really is remain remembering what the why is and not being so
focused on the how and the what because if you remain focused on them it really limits your
ability to change as an organization you're just limited to how you've always done things
rather than remembering why it is you're actually doing them another great piece of advice we see
the word curiosity as a consistent approach for leaders who then take that into their learning
and develop their constant learning how does curiosity show up for you tim well i'm always
looking to learn um i approach each thing as if it's a new thing as i was saying before you know
i don't i don't take uh my list of previous achievements very seriously i i uh when you
spend enough time in the outdoors nature really ultimately doesn't care whether you're a nice guy
whether you're a parent whether you're doing something for charity you're just someone who's
chosen to try and do something in a particular space and if you're good enough and
luck goes your way and you have the right people behind you and they're motivated you may prevail
otherwise you may not and um you know i approach each thing in in in the same way i'm curious to
learn new things constantly grow as a person and accept my shortfalls and and retain that
sense of humility because i know that ultimately um you know it won't count for anything not in
not in not in the world in which i operate well assuming communication
with clarity is a pretty important tool for you and we see that with other leaders as well
particularly in the environments that you've taken and led teams in how have you gone about
communicating with clarity well i mean i think it's about uh you know a simple set of instructions
that suit the circumstances that you're uh you're in sometimes i find it's useful to actually remind
people why they said they wanted to do something um
it helps them to be able to do something and it helps them to be able to do something
helps, you know, retain a sense of purpose and helps get people through the circumstances they
find themselves in. If you remind them why it was they said they wanted to do this in the first
place. And in fact, on the expeditions I do where I'm solo, I write down the reasons why it was I
said I wanted to do this in the first place. And I know myself well enough to know my own sort of
strengths and weaknesses. And I almost have responses written down to help me have that
internal conversation when I come up against something that I know is going to be challenging
for me. So I suppose I would sit people down and urge them to remember the why we're doing this.
And it helps to reframe things and refocus them rather than just bark orders at people
when they're in a state of duress. It's another great, you know, piece of wisdom and reflection,
isn't it? We get lost sometimes, don't we, in the doing and you forget originally why you started
out to do something, whether it's a business. I remembered it from many of the expeditions.
Well, you know, you're sitting in a press conference before you go and it's easy to
sound heroic and, you know, we're going to do this and we're going to conquer that. And
I've trained hard and, you know, we've got a high caliber team. And then you get down there
and it's miserable and confronting and challenging. And you've had a disagreement
with someone on the team. And the fabric of the whole thing feels like it could easily
fall to pieces. And it's important then to just take a step back and remind yourself of why
and have that conversation. And I think that's really important. And I think that's really
important. And I think that's really important. And I think that's really important. And I think
have some advice for yourself that you may have written down in advance of going that
helps you kind of get through those circumstances. I think it's accurate. And again, I can only
imagine some of the thoughts that must have crossed his mind at various stages. Look,
on a number of occasions, as if they were doomed and there was no hope, but clearly,
he found a way and found his way through. And one of the great stories, we see leaders are
really conscious of collaboration now, Tim, and how important that is to leaders. It sounds like
that's an enormous part of your world. How important is collaboration? Well, I mean, you know,
you're collaborating all the way through a process of planning something like this, for example. I
mean, it was a five-year process of making that expedition a reality. And I think the key thing
is to go into it all, accepting that there are many things you don't know. Again, it comes back
to this humility piece and this being honest with yourself and with others and going into it and
asking even...
the you know the silliest questions because at the end of the day you're going to need answers to
to many of those many of those questions and you know you build resilience in people through
going through a really exhaustive risk assessment of all the things you feel
can or might go wrong and you need to have answers for how you're going to react in all of those
situations there's no point getting down in the southern ocean in a keel-less rowboat wearing a
cotton smock when a wave just knocked the boat upside down and then go oh right okay we hadn't
thought of this this scenario so it's very important to discuss all that before you go i
would say i would say honesty uh honesty builds trust and having frank conversations about the
kinds of conditions you're likely to face and you know having an almost childlike ability to keep
asking questions some of the most challenging talks i do are to a young audience
is where kids will always go why and you'll give an explanation and they'll say yeah but why
and you say well look i mean you know the reality is you know they go yeah but why
and at the end of it all you often find yourself saying i don't know kid you've that's a good
question and um so i think we should never lose that sort of childlike ability to keep on asking
asking the obvious questions tim who's been the greatest leader in your life
well you know that's difficult um in all honesty
i don't think i can name uh one person i think i'm i'm someone who's kind of
taken bits of advice from different people i've seen
uh over the years and i've had contact with over the years of course shackleton is a
significant player in my life because i've got inside his head and seen perhaps some of the
things that he saw being some of the situations he's been in i think my father has always been
someone who um was a very good player and i think he's been a very good player and i think he's been
or continues to be a very modest guy he's achieved a lot with his life he's a working
class guy from north london who's achieved great things uh he approaches everything with a sense
of humility and honesty and modesty and that's a great example the only thing i'd say is that
he perhaps never gives himself due credit for the things he's managed to achieve he i think
in in any situation in life you should you know be prepared to give yourself a pat on the back
if you've done something that's worthy of merit you don't have to wear a mask you don't have to
wear it on your sleeve and show off about it but i think you know um having that private sense of
accomplishment and confidence that you've derived you can derive from having achieved something
is something you should carry with you you don't need to shout it from the rooftops
but i i find a lot of individuals have inspired me over the years individual acts of selflessness
that's what inspires me not one individual necessarily yeah i love the answer it's always
fascinating um to hear that response and i think it's a great answer and i think it's a great
response and and those that have been lucky enough to have a close family member influential
in their life it's um it's a place to go straight away and i and clearly you're uh you know have
tracked the history of shackled and you know very closely and i love your point too around
you know celebrating those little moments where traditionally you know growing up in north london
or even australia never never really been great at that but it is an important thing to do is as
you see you don't have to you know i think it is i think you need those two parallel tracks you've
got the outwardly facing being
humble that's that's my modus operandi um but internally you do have to have some serious
conversations with yourself about whether you're going to really cut yourself some slack and
i'm my own worst critic but when you walk to south pole as i did in 1999 um very evidently
you've achieved something significant you know um you do have to have that private conversation
and say look i know the temptation this internal voice is the temptation is to have a conversation
for the fact that you've achieved this for it to somehow demean it but you've got to have that
private conversation and say come on you've got to be serious here that this is something
from which i must learn and give myself some credit i don't have to again shout it from the
rooftops but i do have to uh i do have to accept i've achieved something here tim final question
for me we're obsessed with this world of collaboration and some of the work we do
bringing together different leaders from different backgrounds into collaborative forums tim is part
of a huge passion for for me at the moment and i think it's a really important thing to do and i
love your diverse background as you mentioned before leaders from the arts or sport or
entrepreneurial endeavors uh bring a different line of thinking and we we love that uh cross
pollination and male and female leaders and the diversity of it uh is something we see a great
that loneliness and leadership bringing people together is a great passion for us and in that
spirit of collaboration if if you could collaborate with anyone on anything tim you've you you
articulated really fascinating to me just how adept you are at the
different things in your life and compartmentalizing but has there been one person you might think of
i'd love to do an expedition or another part of your life or collaborate with anyone that springs
to mind well i'm gonna i'm afraid i'm gonna come out with some fairly stereotypical stuff here but
i've been very lucky to work a bit with sir david attenborough i am uh vice president which is an
honorary role of his charity ffi fauna and flora international and obviously he's an inspiring
figure i i feel like um you know people like him we need to be able to do a lot of things together
we need to uh learn from and take on board all the information we can and all the wisdom we can
before um before they're gone you know and i think in the environment space we have people like jane
goodall um sir david uh sylvia earl who's the sort of grand old lady if i can put it that way
of sort of ocean health for the american uh scientists and they they're not going to be
here forever and i think it's important for us to
with them and get as much as we can in terms of wisdom from them before
we don't have them to uh provide us with guidance going forward so i'm uh i intend personally to
continue to work with sir david and try and uh spend as much time working with ffi as i can
uh before he steps away from it tim and i love um the pragmatic optimism uh you know a combination
of words i hadn't thought of uh before but i hear it in all your words and
shaming people into into doing things doesn't seem like a path that's been successful but
trying to as you said lead in the uh the great history of shackleton and what he was able to do
it's the it is the great story of survival as you called it the movie is fantastic i uh i loved
watching it uh learned so much again from you know the wisdom of it and the leadership of it
it is out now uh look it up shackleton the greatest story of survival and tim jarvis
i've been uh thoroughly enjoyed spending some time with you so much to
learn from the way you approach life i really appreciate you joining me today thanks luke and
as shackleton said you know problems are just things to overcome after all and i think um
you know it's that kind of attitude to uh to things that we need to take from him thank you
for listening to the empowering leaders podcast powered by temper a mattress like no other and
to make sure you don't miss an episode click subscribe wherever you get your podcasts