This week's guest on the Empowering Leaders podcast is Tracey Stockwell,
who under her maiden name, Tracey Calkins,
became one of the most successful athletes in American Olympic history.
You'll hear Tracey talk about the extraordinary advice her coach gave her
15 minutes before winning her first ever Olympic gold medal,
the beautiful perspective Tracey offers on the challenge of not being re-elected
as president of Swimming Australia.
You'll also hear her great passion for growing women's sport in Australia
and the remarkable contribution that she made in that space.
I loved her discussion about the relationship that she has with her husband,
Australian swimming legend Mark Stockwell,
and you hear about the legendary Stockwell family Sunday night dinners.
It's a beautiful story, a great chat that I love recording with Tracey,
and I'm sure you're going to enjoy it as much as I did.
It's legendary and iconic people like Tracey Stockwell
who inspire the work we do at Alita Collective.
In particular, I'd love you to have a look at our signature bespoke program,
Alita Connect, where we join and connect great leaders from around the globe,
incredible people like Tracey, in bespoke, facilitated five- or six-person groups.
It's a program that we call Alita Connect,
and you don't have to be an Olympic legend like Tracey Stockwell
to be part of Alita Connect.
We love the educators.
We love bringing people from the arts and from social venture,
from industry and from sport together.
And that diversity of thinking we genuinely feel
is a great asset to have in your life
and to have a team of people who are walking alongside you
to support your thinking but also challenge your thinking
is a really valuable thing.
That's Alita Connect.
You can check it out.
Head to alitacollective.com, book a discovery call,
and my great friend Matt Wadowitz or I will get back to you
and discuss you participating in something we're really passionate about
called Alita Connect.
Huge thanks, as always, to the team at Tempa,
Jason Nicholas and his team, Tempa Australia New Zealand,
incredible supporters of bringing conversations like this one,
with Tracey Stockwell to the table on the Empowering Leaders podcast.
We know great leaders understand the importance of sleep.
This is NASA approved.
The best bedding in the world is Tempa.
And so when you think about spending a third of your life asleep,
to invest in a mattress that is going to support better sleep
is a great decision to take.
Could not recommend it more highly.
Been fortunate enough to be sleeping on Tempa bedding
for the past 15 years.
It's a life-changing decision.
Thanks to Tempa and the team, a mattress like no other.
Tracey Stockwell, Niamh Calkins is one of the most successful athletes
in US sporting history.
She won three gold medals at the 1984 Summer Olympic Games in Los Angeles,
having been favourite four years earlier to win potentially a further seven gold
in Moscow before the US boycotted the Games in protest
over Russia's invasion of Afghanistan in 1979.
Her five world records, 63 US records, 48 national titles,
12 individual NCAA titles are a record for a US female swimmer.
Tracey married Australian swimming legend Mark Stockwell.
They have five children and Tracey is one of the most respected
sporting administrators in Australia.
Tracey, it's quite the CV.
Great to catch up with you.
Well, thank you for that little trip down memory lane there.
It's kind of like, did I do that?
Well, I hope I was accurate.
Yes, yes, yes.
It's quite extraordinary.
And I read with interest that nine years of age,
and tell me if I'm wrong, you're sitting at home,
you're watching the 1972 Munich Olympic Games.
And did you say that?
Then I want to be an Olympian.
Is that true?
I did.
I had only been swimming for about a year,
just at a little local swimming club with my older brother and sister
encouraging me to take part.
And I remember watching, we love sport and our family always watched
the Olympics on TV and remember watching Mark Spitz win seven gold medals,
but also Shane Gould with her green and gold terry toweling robe
and her little koala, or maybe it was a kangaroo, you know,
and that really, I thought,
well, that's a good thing.
Wow.
You know, I didn't know how you got to the Olympics,
but I did say to my mom and dad, that's what I want to do.
Do you think I could go to the Olympics one day?
It must be straight sitting here now referencing Shane Gould
and how your life's been so much in Australia.
Do you ever stop back and think, oh, growing up in Nashville, Tennessee,
it's a long way, isn't it, to where you are now?
It is.
But my very first trip overseas on a small US team was to Australia.
And I was 13 when I left, 14 when I came back.
And my mother always says, I sent away a little girl
and a young woman came back.
And we went to Sydney, Melbourne, and Hobart
to compete and do some exhibition swimming.
And first time I had swum in a saltwater pool at North Sydney
and swam in the old 1956 Olympic pool here in Melbourne,
which, you know, that tells you how old I am.
But, yeah, it was a great experience and probably made me realize,
hey, maybe I can mix it, you know,
with the best and it was a great experience.
I'm told, and again, correct me if I'm wrong,
but the swim that you did in Tasmania that is still a record to this day,
am I right there?
I believe so.
Susan Cure, who's the president of Tasmanian Swimming,
she takes care of all the records.
And she said, do you know that you still hold
an under 15, 400 medley Tasmanian record?
So there you go.
As a 13-year-old.
And that to me is just unbelievable.
Nine years of age, you have this dream,
you watch the Olympics and the famous Mark Spitz records that he broke.
But, you know, only four years later,
you win your first national championship as a 13-year-old.
You're at a high school that doesn't even have a swimming team at that stage.
Did it feel like a natural thing to you?
Did it come naturally?
Well, my sister would say I was a klutz on land,
so there was no choice and I really liked the water and felt pretty –
well, not initially I didn't like the water.
I was quite a skinny kid.
And I was always cold when we were swimming.
And I only liked to swim backstroke because I didn't like to get my face wet
when I first started swimming.
I liked to look around at what was going on.
But by the end of that first summer, I flipped over and started to, you know,
learn the other strokes and enjoyed it and thought, hey, I might be okay at this.
Yeah, so it is amazing.
Yeah, and my parents are from the Midwest,
and they could barely swim, so it was unusual, I think, for our family.
But my sister was a very good swimmer and my brother was a beautiful swimmer
and, you know, we just all took to it.
So there must be, when you look back,
some traits that separated you out from other people to get to the level
that you did so consistently for such a long period of time.
Can you name those?
What do you think was the difference for you?
I think consistency in effort and training.
Mental toughness, I guess.
My in-laws say, you know, you're not a very competitive person, you know,
but I guess in the right environment, and, you know, I was,
but I'm kind of quietly confident, I suppose.
You know, just worked hard.
I think I was very coachable physiologically.
I obviously had some traits that long arms, big heart and lungs,
good feel of the water, and had some very good coaches,
which I think really helped me.
And that really was, started me off to be, you know, a great swimmer.
I had this one coach, and for us,
the biggest deal was to go to the state swimming titles
and beat the team from Memphis, Tennessee.
And he came in and said, we're going to have world champions,
and we're going to win the national championships.
And we were all kind of looking at him like, what?
You know, we just want to win the state titles.
And anyway, within three years, we had three world champions.
Our women's team won the national championship,
beating teams from Florida.
And California, which were the powerhouse teams,
and everyone's kind of going Nashville, Tennessee, you know.
But our parents worked very hard to get good coaches.
And as I said, I was very fortunate to have some really good
and very tough coaches.
You said 13, you're on your first overseas trip to Australia.
Amazing to me that at 15 years of age, you go to West Berlin
and you win five world championship gold medals.
You're still at school.
You win the Jameson.
James E. Sullivan Award for the most outstanding amateur athlete
in the whole United States.
Going back to school in Nashville, how do you go back to class and be normal?
How did you deal with that?
Well, swimming wasn't really a very high-profile sport,
even though we had a good program in Nashville.
And I went to a small girls' school, and everyone was very supportive of everyone.
And they're like, yeah, yeah, Tracy swims, but, you know,
she's just one of us as well.
So I think, and my family, probably my brother and sister brought me
down to earth and kept my feet on the ground.
But, you know, just pretty normal.
A good balance was always really encouraged.
My mom and dad were both teachers, and education was always very important.
And that balance and working at school as well as in the pool.
And that must have stood you in good stead because not long after that,
it's 1980 and the Moscow Olympics was huge.
And arguably that's, you know, you're probably at the peak of your power.
Maybe as a 17-year-old and you win all the events and qualification.
And as I said in the intro, it's possible your favorite for seven gold medals
hitting into 1980 and that build up.
I mean, how devastating was it then to have that boycotted and not be able to go?
Yeah, look at the world championships in 78 that you talked about.
That was probably my best competition ever, hands down.
And then, yeah, obviously there was a focus on finally going to an Olympic Games in 1980.
I don't know if it would have gone.
Seven gold medals, probably seven medals.
But there are a few other Americans who were pretty tough in a few events.
But it was devastating.
And I think I didn't really understand the politics.
Ironically, it took the Soviets 10 more years to get out of Afghanistan.
So it really wasn't very effective.
It just took an opportunity away from a lot of athletes.
I was fortunate that I was still pretty young.
Yeah.
And I guess I had a lot of teammates who made that 1980 team that tried again in 1984.
But it was just four years.
It was a long time.
I lost a little bit of motivation in that because I thought I've got four years to get ready.
But it really went quite quickly.
And I did change programs, went to the University of Florida, which was really motivating,
I think, for me.
Trained with a lot of our men's and women's teams, trained together.
So that really helped me.
I had that extra competition in workouts.
So it was devastating.
But as I said, and now I think back, and had I gone to 1980 and had I done well, as well
as I might have, you know, people thought I would do, you know, I might not have tried
very hard in 1984 because in 1984, 21-year-old woman was old.
I was considered past my prime.
And, you know, it was a sport for teenagers in the late 70s, early 80s.
And now we see, you know, women swimming into their 30s and, you know, it's fantastic.
So certainly, but back then where there wasn't the funding and the opportunities there.
So if I had done well and hadn't gone to 84, I might not have met my husband, Mark.
So I think it's meant to be.
And that's the perspective, is it?
Not regret around what could have been.
It's the possibility of what happened because of that.
Is that how you look back?
Well, that's how I look at it.
I'm lucky because, as I said, I had a lot of friends.
I had a lot of friends who weren't able to make that 84 team or made it and didn't do
as well as perhaps they might have earlier.
But I look at it as it worked out pretty well for me.
You mentioned maybe losing a bit of motivation.
And I think around 82 and 83, some of your international competitors started to go a
bit faster than you.
You know, quietly said your mental toughness and resilience.
Did that sort of get you going again to think, hey, I've got a...
1984.
Was my time?
I probably, it was about a year before the 1984 trials in the US where I kind of thought
I better pull my finger out here because I had been going through the motions, still
training, okay, still winning in America, but not internationally.
And that kind of gave me the kick up the butt that I needed.
And I knew that that was probably going to be my last major competition.
And so I knew I had to...
Train hard.
And I remember the day where it sort of clicked, where I wasn't just going through the motions.
We had on a Saturday morning, we had what our coach called a get out swim.
And he would set a time and if, and he'd pick the swimmer.
And if you did that time, everybody got out of practice, right?
So everybody's like, and he picked me and he picked the 400 individual medley,
which is one of the toughest events on the program.
And so I was like, and he gave me a pretty tough time.
And so I thought, no, I think I can...
I can do this anyway.
And I started in the first 200 meters, they were all like, oh, get ready to get back in
the pool.
But what I did do was I finished the race off in the second 200 meters faster than I
had at the previous NCAA competition, unshaved, unrested, and I did the time.
And I think that kind of gave me that spark, like I can still got it, you know, and that
was probably 10 months before the trials.
So after your first victory...
So your first victory is as a 13-year-old, home Olympic Games in 1984 in Los Angeles and
you win Olympic gold, was it as good as you'd imagined it was going to be?
Oh, absolutely.
I think because my family were there and some of my friends and my high school PE teacher
was there and the crowd was very loyal to the American crowd and you would dive in and
if you came up ahead, the crowd would go wild.
And in my heat swim in the 400 IM on the first day, I got almost too excited and then I
kind of went, I got to settle down here.
You know, I've got this under control.
But I remember before the final, they take the eight finalists into the ready room to
get ready about 15 minutes before the race.
And my coach said, I want you to come and see me.
And I was expecting a big pep talk and, you know, rah, rah, rah, USA.
And he gave me a kiss on the cheek and said, well, Trace, go have fun.
I was kind of like, what?
Wait a minute.
This is the Olympics.
This is what I've worked so hard for so long.
And that's all you have to say.
It was the best advice anybody gave me because there was nothing else I could do in the next
15 minutes, but enjoy it and have confidence in the work that I had done.
And it was probably the most enjoyable swim that I ever had.
Yeah.
My first Olympic gold medal.
Well, it's the genius of good coaching, isn't it?
To just pick the right mood and it maybe could have either hyped you, isn't it?
That's right.
Yes.
That's kind of what I was expecting.
But Randy, who was our coach.
At Florida, wasn't that type of a coach.
Like he was a man of very few words and kind of by his lack of things to say, often you
worked it out yourself and then you kind of went, now, did he make me do that?
Did he want me to do that?
Is that how he, you know, but anyway, he was, he was an excellent coach and we had a lot
of my teammates do very well at those games.
I love what you said a moment ago, Tracey.
You said, you know, I've gone.
There's, you know, seven Olympic gold medals, you're saying medals, but, uh, uh, whatever
the, the, the great time in your life.
And you said, that's to me, I got to meet my husband in 1984 and it not even a problem,
you know, and I keep hearing about the relationship, uh, you and the legendary swimmer, Mark Stockwell
from Australia have, and, and your connection to family being so, so immense for both of
you.
Can you describe what you're like on the home front as a, as a leader of your family?
Well, I think we're a great team and we always support one another.
Um, and especially in front of the kids, even if you disagree, you kind of have to go have
a little side conversation, um, like, and, uh, we've always agreed to do that.
Um, but we come from very similar values and, um, similar backgrounds, I guess.
And, um, you know, we're, Mark's a very good communicator and, um, very good communicator
about his feelings, um, which some people might find interesting, you know, for, you
know, men, but, um.
Men of his era, probably, right?
Yeah, yeah.
Was he always like that when you?
Yeah.
And look, and you just have to look at his dad was, um, was very emotionally intelligent.
And I think obviously that rubbed off on, on Mark and he's like his mother and that she
was very driven and, um, and he, he gets that from his, his mom.
So, yeah, I think it's united, it's, um, love, it's hard work, it's teaching good lessons
to your kids.
Um, and I think we've done good work there.
We share a great mutual friend and, uh, I, uh, I rang him in preparation for this and
he described Sunday night dinner at the Stockwells as just this legendary thing and how much
joy you get.
So he said something really beautiful.
He said, he said, I wish that was more of what the world was like for other people because
you see all the kids are running around, one's cooking potatoes, one's picking up the plates
and Stocky's on the Barbie and Tracy's doing a thing.
But he said, it's just this.
Beautiful sense of community and, and family.
Is that what you've tried to create?
Yeah, that's right.
I think those family traditions and, and so that Sunday night dinner has always been a
tradition we've had, um, borrowed from Mark's eldest sister.
Um, when our kids were little, we used to go to their house, but then as, um, they said,
well, now it's your turn to do it.
And, and we can have anywhere from, you know, seven to 14 people and it is a little chaotic,
but it's a lot of fun and everyone does their job.
And, um, and it's a time when everyone gets to say and talk about what they want to talk
about.
And, um, you know, it's a good opportunity to listen to your kids and, and have debates
about issues.
And, um, yeah, it's a, it's, and it's just warm and full of love and fun and bit of chaos.
And brilliant because, you know, unfortunately for a lot of people, that's not their experiences
and they get that, that opportunity.
And I asked you about this because, uh.
Yeah, in the same context, you know, I love sharing stories like that because to me, that's
where people get to understand more about what happens in, you know, families that are
happy and successful.
And, um, I understand, you know, you and Mark have four beautiful children and then you
decide to adopt a fifth, a beautiful daughter, Holly, who's just part of the family from
what I understand.
That's a great commitment as a family.
Can you tell us about that decision?
Yeah, look, we didn't adopt her actually.
Um, but we are, her legal were her legal guardian.
She's 25.
Now, but, um, uh, it's a bit of a long story, but to cut the long story short, we were building
a shopping center up in, um, outside of Bundaberg.
And so Mark was spending a lot of time up there and he stayed at a, an apartment block
managed by this lovely old couple.
And, um, his mom and dad would go up as well cause they were involved with the business
and, um, got, we got to be very friendly with them.
And Mark had met Holly who had about one year.
Of age and her mom and a couple of days later, uh, gets a call from Holly's grandmother saying
that Holly's father had killed her mother.
Um, and it really had a profound effect on us because our kids were similar age and we
had then decided to set up a foundation to help support Holly's, um, education cause
that was really important to her grandparents.
And they were just near.
We didn't have the means to become, um, um, um, a doctor, um, to be a doctor, as a
child, um, during the age of retirement.
Um, and I didn't have the means by which to have her educated in the way that they wanted.
So we supported her education in those early years when they would come to Brisbane for
specialists appointments or to see doctors.
Um, you know, she'd come and spend the time with our kids.
And as they got older, they realized that, um, they needed to make some planning for her.
And Grandpa wasn't coping very well.
So they asked us if we would look after Holly when they were gone.
And we didn't know how long that was going to be or whatever,
but we thought about it.
We talked to the kids about it.
We were already committed to supporting her education, and so we did.
And at 12 years of age, she came from little town to the big smoke of Brisbane
and a big, noisy family, which would have been,
now that I think about it, quite scary for her, big school.
But she's 25, as I said.
She's got a full-time job, nearly finished uni, and a beautiful girl
and has just fit in the family really well.
What a beautiful story, Jason.
Thanks for sharing it.
So the kids had a debate about it as well.
I'm able to sit down and play.
Play.
Play a role in that?
Yeah, they probably were – I didn't know what to expect,
but we thought out of respect, you know, it's a big change for a family.
And, you know, I think they thought, well, four, what's another one?
You know, and she was right in the middle.
And I knew things were going to be okay, Luke,
when Holly and Emily are number three, and she's about a year younger than Holly.
They had a fight.
They had their first fight.
And doors slamming and yelling at each other.
And then Emily came back out, and she gets on with her day.
Well, Holly stays in her room, so I just went in and knocked on her door
and said, why don't you come back out?
And she said, oh, Emily and I had a fight.
And I said, yes, you did, and it probably won't be the last one you'll have.
And she said, I don't know what to do.
I'm in here, you know, never had a sibling raised by her grandparents.
And I said, well, you can either go give her a hug, give her a nudge.
You can, you know, ignore her if you want, but get on with it.
She's not mad at you.
And, you know, and this won't be the last time.
And so she came out, and she was a little sheepish.
But I thought, no, no, they're going to be okay.
And, you know, that's what siblings sometimes do.
And, yeah.
I've seen a few of those as well, Tracy, on the home front.
But, yeah, I can still feel the emotion there, isn't it?
Such a profound story, isn't it?
And the change I could imagine in, you know, a beautiful girl's life by having that support.
It's an incredible thing that you guys have done as a family.
Well, I think so.
And, you know, we appreciate.
The opportunity and in changing her life.
And she often says, you know, she's met some people from her previous life.
And she says, I look at my life now and what my life might have been, you know,
and she's very appreciative, you know, of it.
Thank you for sharing that.
It's a remarkable story.
Your post-swimming life, as I said in the intro,
incredibly well respected for your leadership in sports administration.
And how enjoyable has that chapter been?
That was great because sports been such a big part of my life.
You know, it was nice when I moved to Australia to find a community that in a country that is so sports mad, you know, and I love sport, any sport.
And I remember my first position was at the Queensland Academy of Sport as Wilma Shakespeare's to I see.
And, you know, I didn't know what cricket or netball or rugby.
We didn't have an AFL program at the time.
But, you know, I learned a lot about sport.
But I had my experience of knowing, you know, in high performance, what makes a difference and some of the key things there.
And I really enjoyed learning and working at the QAS, which then Wilma and I and a few others, women,
I had noticed that women's sport wasn't really recognized as much back in the early 90s.
And the opportunities for girls.
And women weren't great.
And I had been involved in America with the Women's Sports Foundation to try and raise the profile of women's sport as well.
So we kind of got together and created Women's Sport Queensland and create more opportunities and awareness about women and girls in sport because they were performing beautifully.
And but just not getting the recognition.
And I think the papers and the media were giving more recognition to.
Dogs and horses than they were to women at the time.
And we tried to, you know, work really hard to to change that and found a lot of good men who supported us, whether it was corporate or through the media.
And often men with daughters who appreciate, you know, they think, well, oh, this might be my daughter that might have an opportunity if we do the right thing here.
So I think that was a really good strategy.
And so I've always loved trying to give back to sport because it gave me.
So much and really proud of that and, you know, still catch up with lots of our founding members of Women's Sport Queensland.
And now you look at Michelle Payne, the in Rio, the women's teams doing so well, the cricket team, the women's AFLW, the NRLW and how the opportunities for women have really increased, which I'm really proud and like to think that we had a little bit to do with that.
More than a little bit.
It is an incredible legacy, as you said, to start and you look back and it's it's embarrassing and heartbreaking, really, isn't it?
To think that the opportunities that went missing for my elder sister, I think, God, that's the love that you had for sport.
I was given so many more opportunities than you ever were.
And it's tragic in lots of ways.
But it takes people like you that actually decide I'm going to do something about it practically.
And again, it's a great part of your life story and legacy.
The politics of sport as well.
You know.
And Tracey, the Australian Olympic team have their greatest ever success in the pool in Tokyo.
Couldn't be going better.
You've been a great contributor to Swimming Australia for six months, six years.
Sorry, six years on the board and take over from Kieran Perkins as president for nine months.
How do you find that?
It's a challenging environment, isn't it?
Where the politics ends up winning the day.
Yeah, look, I mean, I'm really proud of the six years that I gave to the board of Swimming Australia.
Again, it was an opportunity to give back.
And to the sport that I love and has given me so much, I was very, especially proud of being chair of the high performance committee, getting Alex Bauman on board and really putting into place some good strategies to get the team, you know, to we want to be number one in the world.
But I, my time was up.
My term was up.
I had two terms on the board and I could have one more term.
And I knew I was up.
And I knew I was up for reelection.
And I had the support of the board, but we have made some hard decisions.
And I know some of the stakeholders weren't very happy with that.
And there are politics.
And so I didn't take it too personally.
Tried to tell the board, maybe we better have a plan B just in case I don't get reelected because, you know, they thought, well, you'll be president, you know, for another couple of years and would have liked to have done that.
But I'm OK with that.
And there's some good people in there.
And but that is the politics of sport.
How much of the heart is Australian?
How much of it's American?
Tracy, there's a loaded question for you.
Oh, that's a hard one.
I think I started to change in Sydney 2000 when the four by one men's freestyle relay was happening because I had worked on the QAS for a number of years.
And Ash Callis was on that relay.
I knew Chris Fidler was on that relay and I knew him and his wife very well.
And I remember watching that.
And and Michael Clem and Thorpey, the other two.
Am I correct?
Yep.
Clem led off in a world record.
But anyway, and I I thought, oh, my heart is American, you know, although I do have dual citizenship.
But but then halfway through the race, I was kind of like I was just screaming.
I didn't care who won.
And I kind of thought I felt lucky because I had two teams to support.
But I remember.
I remember thinking at the beginning, oh, I think the Yanks will win this one.
I'll cheer for the Yanks.
I knew two of the coaches of two of the boys in that team.
But I knew two of the boys in the Aussie team.
And I was just it was and probably after that, I think my allegiance has probably swung more to the Australian because I've lived here for longer than I lived in America.
So I got over halfway.
I was half and half.
And now I'm I've been over.
Not longer in America, in Australia.
Beautifully answered, Tracy.
I think, you know, you know, that you said something as we were walking into the studio and we're talking about the theme of the podcast.
I'm sharing a bit of the history and the types of conversations you had.
And you said, yes, success leaves clues.
And I said, I actually use that a lot because someone said it on this podcast.
And I want to ask you a series of questions.
We think becoming a bit of a pattern for leadership and what we see in different people from different backgrounds, starting with self-leadership.
Tracy, we feel like it's hard.
Have an influence on others without a sense of your own self-leadership.
Does that make sense to you?
That makes sense to me, I think.
And gives you that belief and confidence to then take others with you.
Yeah.
And it's a bit like self-love as well.
And can you love someone else as deeply without loving yourself first?
So I think that's that's I would agree with that.
Yeah, it's a beautiful way to describe it, isn't it?
And you're right, isn't it?
It's hard to if you truly.
That stuff comes from inside, doesn't it?
If you're not connected in that way, it's hard to love someone else as profoundly as you just said.
We see leaders are really conscious in whatever environments they are, how they positively impact people on a daily basis.
How have you gone about that?
Look, I kind of think I'm not probably a natural leader.
But then other people say, oh, you are.
But you lead by example.
And I think I'm aware of other people.
And their feelings.
And, you know, for example, at the 84 Olympics, I was one of the captains of the U.S. team.
And somebody came running into my room saying, Tracy, Tracy Rowdy's freaking out.
You know, he's about to swim the race of his life.
And you've been friends with him on the national team for years.
Went through the boycott together.
Can you can you help him?
You know, and I went, oh, OK, sure.
You know, and I wasn't quite sure what I'd find.
But he was he was worried.
He was working himself up.
He was.
Talking to people, but not really talking to people.
And I kind of just remember holding his hand.
And, you know, we've been through a lot together and we've did a lot, went through ups and downs to get there.
And I said, your family is going to love you, whatever happens.
And I said, but have the confidence in the work that you've done and go out there and, you know, we'll be proud of you and we'll love you, whatever happens.
And he won the men's 100 freestyle and beat one Australian.
And Mark Stockwell, who I hadn't met at that stage.
I mean, I had met to say hello, but.
You might have changed your line if you had a doubt.
Yeah, that's right.
Yeah.
That's a bit ironic, isn't it, as well?
But, you know, I think, yeah, knowing what.
And it's like good coaches knowing, you know, Luke might need, you know, a kick up the bum, but you've got to be softer with that one.
And knowing what.
And it's like your kids as well, I think.
And it's like your employees.
You know, you know.
How hard you can push one, but you maybe can't push another.
And so it's reading people and being able to motivate them to get the desired outcome.
But then I think you also have to have that.
What is the desired outcome and what is the vision?
And, you know, my husband is, I think, very visionary and very good in that role with our own business and is a very good leader and clear thinker about things and where he wants to go.
And good at.
And good at communicating where you want to go and taking people with you.
He's like, you're on the bus or you're not on the bus.
It's a great story.
And that actually leads into that creating a vision is really another dimension we see and people are really thoughtful about.
You mentioned Mark and incredible, successful family business that you guys run.
How have you gone in your world about creating the visions for success that you've had and sharing that?
Well, probably done it together with Mark.
And look, I don't work day to day.
In the business, but more strategically and supporting him and am a good sounding board, I suppose, for him as well.
I think it's, yeah, what sport has taught us how to set goals and then break it down if you must into steps, you know, like my goal of going to the Olympics at nine years of age.
Well, I didn't know how you got to the Olympics, but I could do a staircase and take it step by step by step.
And, um, and, but keep an eye on the big picture and the long-term goal, but obviously do things on a daily basis, weekly basis and, and, and hold yourself accountable and responsible for your efforts and your actions.
Curiosities are where we hear a lot of, uh, Tracy for people that seem to have that consistent success.
They're curious and they, through that curiosity, you're constantly learning and constantly wanting to get better.
Is that something that you think of?
I'd like to do better at that.
But, um, coming from a family of two teachers and my sister's also a teacher, um, you know, learning has always been important and discussing ideas and trying to consider different, um, you know, options.
And I think it's good for young people to learn, you know, how to consider someone else's argument and, um, counter that if you, if you must.
But also, um, yeah, I think I'm always curious and, um.
Um, but probably could work on that a little bit more and maybe, maybe when you get a little bit older, not that I think I know it all, definitely not, but you kind of just get tired and want to, you know, do things that you enjoy and, um, yeah.
No, I love the self-reflection, isn't it?
It's we knowing yourself really well.
It's, uh, sounds like, uh, you do that, um, with ease.
Uh, you, you mentioned it just a little while ago, but we see people who are, um, what we think is consistently happy and successful around really strategic around how they communicate.
How often, how clear they communicate.
Is that something that you've thought about as well?
Yeah.
And I think, um, that's one thing.
I think Wilma Shakespeare was a real mentor of mine.
Um, Wilma coached and played for Australia in netball, um, headed up the AIS's first program in netball, then came to Queensland to head up the QAS.
Um, and I was her first, um, kind of deputy.
Um, and I think communication.
I learned.
I learned from her, but she always said that I had good communication and to have confidence in, um, that ability to listen as well, um, to other people's views, but to then be able to communicate well and clearly.
I always find Americans incredibly articulate.
I know it's a broad generalization, but as Australians, you, you know, you'll see someone interviewed on a street for, uh, an incident that may have happened.
And is that a common thing?
It seems like Americans are just got an amazing ability.
They express themselves.
You, you've got a puzzled look on your face, maybe in some parts.
Some, some, in some parts of the country, yes.
And it's other parts, maybe not.
But I mean, I value, I, I appreciate, um, you know, good education that my parents afforded me and, um, being able to further that at university.
And I think that certainly helps.
Collaboration is another thing we see people really value now more than ever and understand the value of it.
How important has that been for you?
Oh, I think, um.
Very important.
I think we're not, you know, alone and, uh, and you can always do things better, I think, with others.
And it also helps to have, um, that support and, and, and people may be sharing a different way of doing something and coming up with a good, good outcome for everyone.
Um, I think so.
And I think I'm pretty good at that.
I think, um, and maybe, I don't know if it's a female thing or, but just, um, mediating and monitoring and wanting.
I'm, I'm a bit of a.
Pleaser as well, I think so.
Wanting to get a good outcome and making sure everyone has their say and, and then, you know, bringing people together and, and coming to a common, um, you know, path.
Um, so I, I think that's very important to work together.
And as I said, I think Mark and I work together well as a team as it, whether it's in raising our kids or running a business or our sporting ventures.
Yeah.
It's brilliant, uh, skill and you can just see a sense of calmness being around you.
Which I, it sort of exudes out of you, uh, but asking these two final questions to everyone I've sat down with, uh, firstly, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Ooh, that's a tough one.
Look, I mean, I give my husband, you know, he'd be, he'd be up there because he, he, he's probably a little bit more decisive than me and, and clear.
And I, as I said, I'm a bit more that pleaser, let's get everyone together.
And, um, um, and sometimes I wish I was more decisive.
This isn't, and could just say, this is how it's going to be.
And maybe if it's your own business, you can be a bit more dictatorial.
I don't know if Mark would like me to say that, but, but, you know, sometimes somebody's got to call the shots and make the call.
And, um, and, and I think he's also, they're very good at taking people with him.
Um, and Wilma, I think, uh, you know, I've spoken about her.
I think she was an incredible leader and, and I look at how many young people, young now.
And many younger than me, but my vintage that she has influenced that are some of the best high-performance brains in the world.
Um, and she's got fingerprints on them and that, that phrase of, um, success leaves clues.
I heard that from Chelsea Waugh, who was one of Wilma, who worked at the QAS and then went over and worked with Wilma in England, in the UK sport, and has written a very good book called The Talent Lab.
Um.
And, um, you know, and Alex Bauman worked for Wilma and, you know, and we all, you know, just really appreciate, um, the mentorship and the leadership that she provided us to help us to get to where we are today.
And I think that's a good sign of leadership.
Yeah, that's a, it's a great thought, isn't it?
The effect that you've had and how many people that you've empowered to be great leaders as well.
And it sounds like she had an incredible, uh, influence from the sport of, legend of the sport of netball.
Yeah.
As you said, in the spirit of collaboration, um, you've had so many diverse parts of your life and, and clearly, uh, you know, the Olympic, uh, swimming part is a huge chapter, but has there been anyone who's thought, if I could collaborate with that person, that would be fascinating.
It could be any area of your life.
Has there been anyone that springs to mind in terms of collaboration?
No, I guess because I've had a lot of opportunities to engage with in the Olympic world and in the swimming world in particular.
Um.
You know, Bob Bowman, who coached Michael Phelps, um, you know, he's my age and we kind of swam at the same time and we've had a little bit to do with each other, but I just look at the success that he's had with not only Michael, but now he's got this several, uh, swimmers, including Léon Marchand from France, who I think next year in Paris will be incredible.
No, it'd probably have to be something at a totally different.
Field, but I don't know what it might be.
We've got creative daughters, um, who both dance and sing and act and, you know, and I always think where'd they get that from, but maybe I need some collaboration in that field to inspire me, my creativeness.
Is that, uh, have any of them followed the path?
I mean, two Olympic parents, has that been passed down the gene a bit to the kids or?
Well, our son is swimming and he's swimming at, um.
And, uh, is that the world championship trials?
Um, he's a sprinter like his dad.
Um, his twin sister was a quite a good water polo player.
Um, but then as I said, we've got the performers.
It's a performance, you know, whether it's on the stage or in the pool or, um, wherever.
Well, as I said, uh, I only hear about the, uh, incredible, um, environment it is when people are lucky enough to be around the Stockwells and, and just to hear the connection that, you know, your relationship.
And, uh, it's, uh, it's a special one to share aside from having a record that is just quite amazing when you look back and think what you were doing at such a young age.
Uh, thanks so much for sharing your story today, Trey, I heard a lot about it.
It's been really nice to spend the time with you.
Thanks a lot.
Well, thank you, Luke.
Thanks for listening to another episode of the empowering leaders podcast.
Huge.
Thanks as always to our great friends at temper, and we encourage you to check out our leader connect program.
New episodes are out every Wednesday morning.
At 6 00 AM.