How do you create and lead an environment where people feel supported and connected
in a way they've never felt before, where there is a focus on developing a better person
as a priority, and in doing so, you create a better team?
I had to work on myself every single day to be up to the task of coaching the team and
had to work hard to be ready for them.
Today, it's Luke Darcy.
The idea of self-improvement and leadership, both on and off the field, has been a lifelong
passion of mine.
With one of my oldest friends, we created a leader collective and have had the privilege
of working with thousands of leaders in education, sport, industry, and the arts that have helped
shift to what we see as the 21st century style of leadership, where everyone has a voice.
In this podcast, we hear stories from these iconic leaders.
I sit down with legendary NRL leaders.
I'm here with NRL coach Trent Robinson, who talks about how his role is to serve the players,
what spirituality means in a sporting environment, and nurturing players to be brutal on the
field and open-hearted and vulnerable off it.
Well, Trent Robinson is a coaching legend of the NRL.
At just 35 years of age, he was appointed as head coach of the Sydney Roosters and remarkably
coached them to a premiership in his rookie season.
Trent has gone on to become the only coach in Roosters history to win over 150 games
and is the longest-serving coach in the club's history.
In 2018 and 2019, Trent coached the Roosters to back-to-back premierships.
In 2013, 14, 15, and 18, the Roosters won the minor premiership under Trent's leadership.
He has been recognised for his achievements as the Dallium Coach of the Year and the Rugby
International Federation Coach of the Year.
It is a remarkable time in sports leadership.
And Trent Robinson, great to catch up with you.
Thanks for your time today.
Thanks, Luke.
Good to be here.
At 35 years of age, you're given a senior leadership position.
In sport, head coach of the Roosters.
What made you such a capable leader at that age?
I was so nervous for that job for months.
For months.
You know when your ambition's high and then you keep sort of throwing yourself into stuff
that you're not sure if you're ready for but you think you'll catch up?
Well, that was the case with this job.
I remember I took off to France.
I was at the club in 2010.
We went to a grand final.
And then I left to go to Catalans in the south of France to coach in the Superleague
at 33.
And I was head coaching and I was really, yeah, cutting my teeth there trying to practice
different management styles, different playing styles.
And then out of the blue, the funny story about Nick Politis, our chairman, I didn't
even interview for the job at the Roosters.
I signed and then the board rang me and asked me what I was going to do.
And I made up some stuff on the spot and then went about, I knew we had a good team.
I knew we had a really good team.
We had to do some things when we came in.
But it was, oh, I was, I had to work on myself every single day to be up to the task of coaching
the team.
And, you know, that's, you know, I had to work hard to be ready for them.
Well, that's a remarkable story.
I didn't realize that Nick Politis, legendary figure.
He played in New South Wales and in rugby all around.
So he didn't even interview for the job.
He saw something in you and said, Trent Robinson, you're my man.
Is that how it happened?
Yeah.
So I played here for four years, never played the top level, but I came here out of school,
had four years at the Roosters and then came back and coached in 2010.
And we had quite a successful year.
We went to the grand final that year and then I left.
And I had a good rapport with players.
And Nick usually doesn't ask.
He doesn't ask too many people's opinions before he makes a decision.
And that was the case.
I felt really lucky.
I got told I had the job and then I signed within a couple of days.
And then a couple of days later, I had to tell him what I was going to do.
So, yeah, it was definitely not a formula that people go by very often.
But, yeah, it's been a, you know, a complete change in my life.
What Nick did.
In that week.
And I've had to pay that back ever since as well.
Certainly paid it back with incredible success and what you do and what you continue to do.
Triple Premiership coach and an amazing history as a senior.
I wanted to touch on that briefly, Trent.
As a young kid, I understand you played soccer and you're an elite swimmer.
And then you found your love of rugby league.
As you said, you came through the Roosters and ended up playing a couple of games with the West Tigers and I think Parramatta.
So it was a three-game short professional career.
It was a three-game short professional career here in the NRL before going over to France.
It seems to me, you know, without having to study, that not many coaches achieve your level of coaching success that didn't play more senior football, whatever sport.
Did you always feel like as a player you were maybe destined to be a great coach or is that a bit of a stretch?
For most people, when they're in a sport and they're not at the top level, you often feel like you're on the outskirts.
You often feel like you're not.
You know, at the center of that club, you're sort of an add-on.
You know, a lot of reserve graders or second teamers feel that way.
And I guess that's what I felt playing.
I just couldn't get the most out of myself to play that top level.
And at that time, my mum was a swimming teacher and I often, I was very aware of my coaches throughout my junior years.
Even at a young age, I was aware of my school teachers.
And I, you know, I was working in gyms while I was going through uni and I was coaching.
So I'd always like learn, I was always keen on the art of coaching, on how to get the best out of somebody at different times.
But it wasn't until I went to France that I really learnt that I loved rugby league.
You know, when something gets taken away from you and you, you know, no one cares about rugby league.
It's not a big sport over there.
But then I realised how much I loved it.
And then two things happen.
I love the sport.
I found out I loved it, even though it wasn't very big over there.
And I was lucky enough to have a couple of people that would pick up somebody that doesn't have any real experience.
Because this is, this is common in our sport is people in all sport.
A former legend player is really good to have around because by osmosis,
they pass on a lot.
They have a lot of stuff that, that, that creates great teams and they were a part of that.
But is that person going to learn the art of coaching?
And sometimes they do.
There's good examples of that, but sometimes they don't, they rely on what they did as a player.
And so I guess what I had to do when I came into coaching was I couldn't rely on that.
So I had to rely on the art of coaching.
How do I manage somebody?
And the absolute technical depth.
And that's, that's a big part of it.
The technical detail and tactical detail of the sport.
So that was, that was my method of, of sort of getting there, but I was lucky enough to
have a couple of people that didn't need me to be a great player for them to employ me.
That was, that was really key.
It's interesting.
Isn't it watching sometimes the great champions of sport that go to coaching struggle to understand
why players find it so hard, something that they were able to do maybe more easily than
most.
Yeah.
I mean, it's, it's a challenge for all the former and former all time legends, and it's
harder for them to relate.
Have you found that you can have more empathy for the challenges of trying to find your
best in sport because it was a challenge for you?
Definitely.
Cause you know, you'll get to a situation where a coach will say, look, I need you to
do this.
And even though mentally you're thinking, I know what they want me to do, but physically
you just can't always get it done.
And there's a frustration point.
There's that, that observing point in between what they want me to do and what they really
want me to do.
And so there's a frustration point.
There's that, that observing point in between what they want me to do and what they want me to do.
And sometimes they can't always get it done.
what they want you to do and what you're trying to do and if you sit in that observing point and
say well um you know why can't they do it there's often some factors that you need to work on as a
coach where um a lot if you don't observe that part of your coaching and you just go well if
you can't do it then you're not good enough then you're missing the art of coaching you're missing
the art of getting um the best out of somebody or adapting well either a team it could be a whole
team or it could be an individual and i was i was often as a player in that area um sort of going
like i know what he's thinking he's either doubting himself or he doesn't understand the
steps that need to get there technically or or whatever it is um so i had to observe it because
it was in me and i love the the understanding of that
trent for me i always found playing sport that the coaches often through the year i was in were
really adept at pointing out what you couldn't do and and that was almost like a career defining
statement you can't kick well enough or you're not agile and then i reckon there's a generation
like you saying i need you to do this and i'm going to coach you to find a way now that doesn't
always work but is that too simple a way to explain it that that part of the art of coaching
is actually finding players that you think you can teach a way to do something that maybe they
even thought they couldn't do themselves yeah i reckon the biggest one of the biggest things in
in coaching is um there was you know and there still is and and you know when i'm at my worst i
coaching i feel this way as well but we're at the service of the players coaches need to understand
that we're there to serve the players they're not there to serve us now we might be in in a in a
authority role because we're the head coach and we decide on whether they play or not but
we serve the players so as soon as we work out that um the old john wooden quote about it's not
what they hear it's it's it's not what you say it's what they hear and and as soon as you work
out that your job is to work out how do they hear what you're trying to put across then that's that's
your role as a coach um and i and i feel like um ego plays a big part in coaching um you know the
the
external ego on on authority and what you think you should represent you know and that's and
there's no difference you know it plays a part in myself and and that as well but reducing that
and understanding the service aspect of our of our profession and then okay now what does service
mean what are the tools that i need to service the players um and for a young player it might be um
the progressions that need to lead to them to be tactically or
technically
um
the progressions that need to lead to them to be tactically or technically very proficient
in a tackle defense but a senior player it might be the management of them
moving from a single life to a married life with kids and they're transitioning to that
that that different role and fatherhood that you may need to have understanding of managing that
and then it varies you know and and um i feel like that's what we forget in the essence of
coaching is that um the service aspect of it um
and the continual search for their understanding about what we're trying to get across
it's such a profound thing that you just said that trent from an era that you know you serve
the players you're there to to serve their needs and get the best out of them a lot of people
listen to this who will be running small business or big business or interested in education or
other parts of their life and it's it's such we're seeing that unique leaders like you have
changed the whole way we lead now in flipping it on its head it's not hierarchy it's not hierarchy
i'm in the big office and you know i don't think the senior coaches i started with it would have
been hard to get a conversation out of them in the first two years whereas you're now working
out in a very different way that you know imagine that as an employee or a leader in a business to
say i'm actually serving the people under me to get the best out of them it relates to so much
is it is that a unique thought that that you when you were transitioning into a coach that you had
or is it something that when you were playing did you feel like that was missing i felt like the
best coaches that or teachers
that i had um had that understanding of me and and and and of how i learned the best and how i
needed to progress so i think that was definitely from the best teachers that i had and then the
other part of it for me was um as i was coming through i definitely started coaching feeling
like i had to in the first year i felt like i had to act like a coach you know i had to um yell when
they didn't do something well and then i had to act like a coach and then i had to act like a coach
well and i had to you know drop someone because they weren't playing well enough and you know i
felt like i was rote learning coaching um and i had you know early doors i even it was one of the
years i think it was my third year of coaching i felt like i had an average team and i capped the
team in my head not not externally but in my head i thought um they're not a good team they can only
achieve that much and guess what they didn't so you know i put a limit on what i was doing and
what i thought i could achieve with that team and i coached to that limit and so those lessons
have been really good early about you know finding my style of coaching like how am i going to coach
um what do the players need not just what do i want to do who am i but also who are they how do
they um how do they need to be coached um but then also allowing um the freedom for those players to
players will exceed your expectations you don't dictate
play all the time and and if you don't put a cap on them sometimes they'll underachieve but often
they'll overachieve there's there's so many players where when you start with them you think
you know i wonder you coach them to get the best out of them without limit and often they will
overachieve with that so clearly your lessons in in france uh served you well when you arrive at
35 years of age which you know to me is incredibly young and one of the youngest ever
coaches at a head coaching role in the nrl and then you win it in your first year you win the
minor premiership a remarkable start to your career did you feel was that belief in you trent
that first year did you feel like there was something special that you could take them all
away as i said i woke up every morning for months nervous about going into work just but that was a
part of my process about i had to accelerate my learning i was 35 um i'd only been coaching for
uh what was it you know six years seven years up until that date so i was i knew i had to learn
quickly and then we did some things in that pre-season we needed to shape this the the team
a little bit better we had a bit of a soft underbelly we were a pretty team but we weren't
a hard team so we made some recruitment changes around that time and then a couple of additions
would really help having sunny bill williams come in and james maloney and we ended up having a
squad and then i remember halfway through the year we had a staff um a couple of days in one of the
buys and we sort of said these guys are ready to win it's up to us to to manage them because you
know we felt like we had to be good enough to win as as player as staff because the players were
ready um and so i felt like every day was setting an emotional control on myself i had to make sure
that the nervousness that i was waking up with wasn't seen externally i had to try and um set my
energy for the day um and the thing that my skills were at would i could coach him technically and
tactically i was really confident in what i had as a product i just didn't know all the other stuff
that went to being a head coach whether i was capable of um so i sort of had to learn on the
on the run clearly you were you can hear you know reading about a lot of your work the psychology
of your work and you know connecting your players to each other and themselves and
coaching the whole person seems an incredible passion and it's you know really interesting
to hear how you did that in in real time as a 35 year old and i wanted to jump uh to one of my
favorite stories in australian sport and it's clearly going to be one that resonates with you
and watching cooper cronk play a grand final with a broken shoulder affected broken scapular it was
as we found out afterwards it was one of the most courageous things i think i've ever seen in in
sport and i i want to ask you about the complexity for you as a leader you've got this great on-field
leader who's clearly playing you know at best at 30 into a grand final how hard was that decision
for you to give the green light to play understood it was up until the hour before the game before you
went with it was it a really challenging call to give that the green light and can you talk us
through how you went about it there's no one as strong mentally as cooper cronk that i've ever
come across like i've coached some amazing players i've coached some amazing players i've coached some
players but i don't know anybody that would have played in that game it was a it was a clean break
of a scapular it was incredible the break in that and cooper cronk i've never seen somebody
dictate to themselves how they should feel more often than cooper so therefore that was the
biggest part the injury wasn't going to play a part in him wavering mentally during throughout
the game he actually did it i think it was after about 32 or 33 years old and he was
injured for about 33 minutes before half time in the game before and he got treated during half time
i remember them working on his shoulder and then he played a whole other 40 minutes with this broken
scapula you know and he kept it away from trouble and it was incredibly painful but it was sort of
funny we what happened was i think it was saturday night we played sunday morning we met in the
doctor's office we sat there broken scapula um a bit controversial but we said okay what are we
going to go out with because we're going to play a game and we're going to play a game and we're
going to play a game because we won't you know we said he was going to have a shoulder injury but
we didn't want to go into we didn't want to say that he had a broken scapula and then we talked
about is he going to play or not and it was sort of a um and this is where cooper was really strong
he said right yeah let's let's sort of go and find every method we can um and um what we'll do
is we'll prepare we won't be able to prepare all week so we knew how to play with cooper in the
world and we knew how to play with him and he was a very good player and we knew how to play with
him and he was a very good player and we knew how to play with him but we didn't play that's what we
had to plan for um which sort of was true but we had to have a plan with him being on the field and
not really playing as well but so what what we did was that sunday afternoon i sat down and went
through the strategy about how we would play with and without him um walked in monday morning with
the coaches and the senior players and this is sort of an important part of it i had a slight i
had a different player that was going to play in in the position and the so we had the strategy about
tactics about moving players to play extra half roles and who was going to play in the halfback
position and the senior player said no i don't think we should play him i think we should play
another player and then we talked about the the strategy of the game and so we worked it out that
morning and then we went and presented it to the team and then we trained that way all week
and then the method that we had with cooper didn't play was actually it was like a fake halfback role
um and we were going to swing our two young players in latrell mitchell and joey marner was
playing as the extra halves so when we decided that whether cooper was going to play or not
that was the ideal scenario anyway because we could cover for cooper not being on the field so
and this is the funny thing i don't remember it was such an easy decision because and i'm not sure
why but it was really clear that he was either
in or out and we had our two plans the players were really clear and then we went about
training that week and then cooper said he was out friday morning and then he did a different
medical intervention friday afternoon and he said i'm right to play and then he asked the
players on the saturday morning are you right if i play but don't basically you know i'm going to
play a decoy role they went yep you're without a doubt we want you in there
and then we had to wait till an hour before to see if the injection actually worked to numb the pain
and we went with it it was you know it caused a big distraction for the opposition
but it was just yeah it was just an incredible feat from cooper but also from the guys around
him to handle the changes within the biggest week of their lives amazing sporting story there's so
so many layers to it, isn't it? You initially go to the bravery of playing with a clean break of
your scapula, which is extraordinary. And then what you're able to do and the tactics around
the part that I think I love the most out of that trend is the fact that you came with a plan to
your senior players and they told you, no, they wanted a positional change. I mean, for most
people in senior leadership roles, that's a really hard thing to take on board, your players
feeding back to you that there's a different alternative. What was that like for you?
That's, you know, our job is to line up and do most of the strategy, but we've got to leave space.
Some of the most intelligent players in our game for now and in the future are actually on the
field. So leaving space for that choice and then with that choice comes much more buy-in to the
way that you're going to play. So that was really natural because, and that was the key, the way
that a couple of those guys responded.
Because the guy that actually played the halfback role was going to play that fake position. He was in that
meeting and he'd never played it before and he said, I'll do it. And then Luke Keery, who was the
best player on the ground in that day, he also said, I will cover Cooper in his roles and I'll do it this
way. So I feel like our job is to do the majority of the legwork, but also you need to offer choice.
To get the ultimate buy-in for your players, because then they feel like there's ownership in
the game plan.
And you still have to, if you're Cooper Cronk, stand there and lay a tackle as he did on, I think,
10 occasions, you know, 110 kilo powerhouse machines running at him. And he was able to find
a way remarkably with that injury to do it on grand final day against his own side. An incredible
story in every sense. I read that you've got an acute sense of history, Trent, and around your
club and what the Roosters mean and that you really take the players on a journey of understanding
it. And I've been reading a bit about it in preparation for this, and I didn't quite understand
the East's history and that Bondi and Paddington, those suburbs were really essentially working
class and it was not where people wanted to live. Clearly they're sought after now. And
tell us why that's important for you to take your players on that journey and do they buy into it?
And does it mean something? Definitely. I think anybody, you know, the idea of
I'll go back to the ego of a coach. I can't walk in here. I can't think that my role is to
just plan for the future. I have to honour the past as well. And sometimes you have to unload,
unpack some of the bits of your DNA that you don't like and discuss. And it's like yourself,
you want to improve yourself. So you have to talk about that. And then you have to pattern
and continue.
You want some of the parts of the history that are vital to your club and your success.
And that's why for us, you know, we're seen as quite a wealthy and glamorous club in rugby
league. You know, we represent the city and, you know, the Opera House and, you know, the
Centrepoint. They're all on our land and Bondi Beach and the wealthy houses of Vaucluse and
Point Piper and all of that type of stuff. But as I say, we aren't the right people.
We aren't the right to live in this area. We aren't the right to represent this area.
This was the slums of Sydney were in our area. And all the immigrants that kept moving into
the area over the last hundred years have gone into our jersey. They've rolled up their
sleeves and they've built this city. And so the good stuff that's come out of that
in the last 20 to 30 years, you know, will stand tall, put your shoulders back and feel
comfortable.
Yeah.
I'm confident about the club that's been built in this area and who we represent, that
we've earned the right. So, I mean, I'm not a suit guy. I don't, you know, I wear a suit
to every game, all the games that I've coached. But that's because I represent this area.
You know, it's not, if I was at the Catalans in France, I'm not wearing a suit because,
you know, I represent the club. I don't represent myself in that. So, trying to honour that
history is really important. And we've had to go through a lot of things. We've had to
pull out some of the dark times as well.
So, I love the connection to storytelling and clearly your history and what that means
in the world of professional sport now that is transient. Players move more than they
ever have done in the history of the game. But I believe you're also, you know, big on
grabbing stories from elsewhere and themes of, you know, for a particular year. And I
understand you really delved into the Barcelona story with Pep Guardiola and Messi at their
peak. How do you combine that? Where does the...
How does the connection work with, you know, a Spanish giant in the round ball game? How
do you connect that back to the Roosters?
Well, I think that's the, you know, there's inspiration in many parts. And we've used,
you know, who are like the guys that are really good storytellers and have been for a while
are the New Zealand coaches. You know, the history of their storytelling have been really,
really strong for a long time. So, some guys that are really good at this.
You know, Verne Cotter was over in French Rugby Union for a long time and he really
bought in. I think they won 74 home games in a row. And they had the theme that they
would protect their home. Scott Robertson, who's won many titles with the Crusaders.
Scott's really good at telling the story through themes. And we've often discussed, yeah, the
different theming. And the guys enjoy it.
They enjoy an attachment to a story. And often, you know, there has to be the passing
on of your DNA and your understanding of your history. But there's also that learning, whether
it's been Barcelona and that, you know, that big city and representing that city and the
way that they played and the style that they played with was really big. And there's been
other ones that we've used each year.
It's a different theme that ties into the year and how we want to play. But I think
it's such a, it's a cool way to get everyone to buy in. And also, you know, you've got
to do it with the families and the staff as well, like everybody. There's about 250 people
that are a part of that story.
Verne, I can hear the lifelong learning part of who you are and the people that I've spoken
to that know you will say that you are obsessed with improvement and learning. And that is
where we've crossed over ever so slightly in the world of a leader and my friend, Matt
Waterwitz, and the group that you've been meeting with regularly. I wanted to ask you
a bit about that, if you're okay. Justin Langer, Australian cricket coach, John Worsfold, a
legend of AFL, along with Don Pike, who's had an incredible history. Your assistant
coach, Matt King, Melbourne Storm legend, if you don't mind me mentioning his history
there. Will Weaver started it, who's now an Australian basketball coach with the Houston
Rockets. Can you talk me through?
Why that sort of connections work for you, Trent, and what you've got out of it?
What Matt set up and you guys are involved with, it's just, the first thing is, you think
it's about sharing your knowledge, but what it is, is it just, the first thing is, it's
a real support. I haven't met Woosh in person, and I've heard of Woosh for a long period
of time. I haven't met JL. I got to just meet Pike.
If you're familiar with Joaquin, he was from Australia, and he was a champion in the rugby
and football, but he had a dear old friend who was from Australia, and he was a major
fan of mine, and I looked him up, and I was like, well, I don't know if you know him.
And he said, well, he's a very good coach, but he hasn't been here for a long time. I
don't know him. I don't know him very well, and I said, I don't know him for over 10 years.
He said, well, he's not a good coach. I don't know him, but he's not a good coach. I was
the second player to me.
And that was the only person I knew.
It was a very good player. I was the second player. That's the only person I knew. He was,
You feel like you've had that relationship with them
and that depth of relationship and that's probably the biggest thing.
That's why we don't stop.
You know, I think it would have started as a six-week meetings
for six weeks during COVID in April and now we're still going
every two weeks and we make Will jump on from Houston Rockets
and tell us some MBA learnings and we don't want to stop
because it's become our little coaching community.
And then there's the other bits about like let's share some
of the theming or let's share some of the, you know,
whether it's how to set up a pre-season or lots
of different learnings.
It's been wonderful.
It's been absolutely wonderful to be a part of a group
that cares so much and is willing to share openly to get their teams
and clubs better.
And, Jim, we're sort of excited about and we, you know,
through telling these stories and we really appreciate you being generous
enough to do it that there is something in that for a lot of people potentially.
The word I use is almost like your own personal board of directors
without wanting to make it sound corporate because it's not necessarily that.
But to have a group of people you can reflect with and bounce ideas off
and as you described so articulately there to be able to, as you said,
you haven't met some of these people but they're probably lifelong friendships
out of it as well.
Is it something you could see a benefit for other people who wanted
to form a group that meet you at the same level and support each other
in the way that you've done it?
I will do this for, you know, this form for the rest
of my coaching life, you know, or business life.
You can't – so I'll have, you know, I'll have something that will be big
for me that will come up and the ability to go and ask the question.
You know, and they will have genuine, varied solutions to that.
You know, and the idea of sharing that knowledge between a group
that also don't have any – they don't have any ties to the club,
that there's no biases that need to come into play.
So it's that pure honesty that they give you and they're just –
that is really important to have in your professional life.
You know, you can do it in your personal life as well,
which sometimes comes up, but your professional life,
it's so important that people openly share and get advice
but from common people but outside your own field.
And, yeah, it's just been a wonderful experience.
Yeah, we're really, you know, grateful that you were prepared
to be part of it and excited on the 10th of February next year
if schedules line up.
Trent and all those guys are going to get together at a summit in Adelaide.
We'll leave you the details at elitacollective.com
if you're interested in that group getting together,
which I can't wait to be a fly on the wall to see those friendships in person.
So it's worth getting to the Adelaide Convention Centre on the 10th of February.
I'll give that a small plug.
And Elita Connect is the program that Trent's talking about
that we've been – you know, we've been talking about for a long time.
We've been really passionate about seeing unfold before our very eyes.
I hear a lot, Trent, when listening to you and in the past,
a sense of spirituality.
It's maybe not something that sport would see that link in the past.
Is that something that you talk to your players about?
And what does that mean for you, your players,
and having a sense of spirituality in what you do?
It's a funny one, Luke, because it's sort of one of those ones where you –
like how much do you open yourself up to?
This is a – you know, there's usually the sporting side that you want to hide
and that you – sorry, you're open to, and then there's the other stuff
that you are interested in that you're not sure whether to share openly,
whereas spirituality is a really different one because there's so many people
that either have religious influences there and beliefs or people that don't,
but we all have – everybody has a spirituality, you know,
and when you think about that,
like a spirit, meaning that especially mostly internal,
that breath or that feeling of understanding about who you are
and then the shared connection of spirituality,
and that can come out in many ways.
So religion has a major part, but also being able to experience things
in different ways, either through –
through breath or through philosophy or through poem or through experience,
and it's often seen as the yin part of our life where we're okay to sort of go
into the softer side that sort of opens up, yeah,
a bit of a deeper understanding on our essence of where we come from
and where that purity comes from because that's what –
there's so many layers.
There's so many layers before we get there.
So it's often saying how do you – how do you work towards offering
that to the people around you?
And usually we start with our partner or our kids and then you sort
of have your close circle of friends, but with your spirituality in any form,
how do you open up that wider and wider and what methods do you use?
And it's – yeah, it's a bit of a life's work and trying to do that
in a footy club has become –
yeah, really, yeah, it's become a fundamental part of how we try
and go about it, and different people have different experiences
and that's cool.
It's okay, but understand that that's a big part of our connection
in what we can offer to everybody around us.
I love the contrast.
You're training athletes in one of the most brutal sports
in the world effectively, you know, to spill blood.
On the field and it happens regularly in the amazing intensity of NRL,
but at the same time, you know, the heart and the softness
at the same time, it's a –
You would have found that though with, you know, the teams that you play with
because this is – you know, when I talk about that, it seems like a –
it seems a bit airy-fairy, right?
So it's something that is a bit weird to go into, but, you know,
the best teams that you've played in,
there was an emotional bond or connection with those players that I mentioned.
100%.
I couldn't agree with you more.
I just love that we're openly talking about it now as a –
you know, I say new generation coach.
You've been doing that for a long while.
The best people in my life were exactly that,
and those connections and friendships to me is the best part of sport.
When you do open yourself up and you do break down, you know, that level,
as you described it so well, isn't it?
You maybe start with your partner and your wife and then you really truly drop
all of the facade amongst your friends.
You end up with these lifelong friendships in sport.
So I love that it's come to where you are now, where it's talked openly about,
and it seems to me the Roosters are a destination for people wanting to be
in that sort of environment from what I can see.
Well, that's – I mean, this is the part of it, right?
Because it always felt like it's a bit soft to talk about it in a brutal sport.
But the more work we've done is, you know, that's what warrior cultures are about.
Like, they've understood.
They've understood.
There's a Trojan warrior that used to talk about – it's written around how he would
spill blood in the morning and carry his baby in the afternoon.
And what's more of an ultimate warrior than that?
And so we talk about sport and we want to see the warrior on the field,
but you have to balance that off the field.
You know, the samurai used to talk about how they would, you know, swords –
the swordsmen that they were and they used to defend their clans,
but they also –
they used to have the imbalance of doing poetry or painting to balance out their sides
because they understood that they – that's how a warrior was.
And so there's no difference in our walk through life.
We've got to balance the two and that's – I guess that's what I'm talking about there
is being open to talking about both sides.
True.
My mind's going.
I've had the great pleasure in this series on this podcast talking to a range of different people
and Steve Butoff.
Steve Butoff comes to mind.
He's the author of – you know, sold over 4 million books in Australia on raising kids
and his book Raising Boys is one of the best-selling books.
You would have heard of Steve and he speaks about being in rooms of big theatres
and he presents to big groups and often to females and he asks them a question around
what do you want in a man?
What's the ideal man?
Which he says is an interesting question and, you know, you start off with the banter,
but he said it comes down to two things really quickly.
Females want a male with spine and a big heart and he sort of puts it in those two categories
which I think sums up a little bit of what you're talking about, isn't it?
Yeah, and that's, you know, that's our role.
Like I say, just coming back to rugby league or our sport, we get men walk in at 17, 18
and walk out at 35 and if we're not looking at that part of their life, you know, if we're
not trying to help.
If we're not walking the path of that, building that man and then, you know, we're missing
the point of coaching.
We've really got to do that and that's, you know, Steve and his books have been really
key in how do you, you know, how do you develop yourself and the people around you into being
that and there's no difference.
That's why I say brutality is really key for the Roosters, how we play.
We have to play a hard style.
But the method about getting that across has, it has changed over the years.
You know, it's been, it's getting more open and to be honest, the hardness is harder than
ever.
It's just the walking the path of a good man off the field is getting a bit clearer.
And what a healthier way to be and, you know, producing great people at the end of their
time in the game.
Dream, we're seeing a number of characteristics.
A number of characteristics of leaders like you and the language you use is aligned with
this community we're seeing of 21st century style leadership and a number of dimensions
and I'd like to ask you about them and please feel free to expand as you like.
But starting with self-leadership as a dimension of leadership, what do you think of when I
talk to you about self-leadership?
Well, I think there's often like, am I on a path myself just because I've got a role?
Am I thinking that I'm a leader because I've been given a title?
And I feel like that self-leadership is, I don't expect to be perfect, but I have to
be on a path to getting myself better as a leader.
You know, there's a real responsibility for that.
So self-leadership, I feel, is me continuing to, you know, get better and open myself up
to more leadership and different leadership methods.
And I think you need to lead yourself well first before you can lead others.
Positively impacting others in your environment.
Clearly, that's a passion of yours, just listening to the way you think about coaching young
athletes.
What do you actively do about impacting people positively in the environment you work?
Well, I think we have our principles that we apply, but I'm sort of, I think treating
them as, seeing them as a person, you know.
So I think if you see them as a commodity or as a, you know, as a player with a cap
value or whatever, you're missing the point.
So I think authentically seeing them as a person, and that means everybody in the place,
you know, staff and players.
I really feel like that's, yeah, that's a big part of seeing them and then coaching
the health.
I think that's, I think everybody wants to be seen, you know, me included.
Yeah, well said, isn't it?
We're finding that in the education space, isn't it?
Listening to the kids about their own learning environment, you know, hearing their voice,
which maybe hasn't been necessarily common in the past.
You've created some incredible visions for the environment you're in and had amazing
success, as I said off the top.
How do you think about when you create and share a vision?
How do you go about that?
So my process towards that is there's sometimes, there's two different ways.
I will often brainstorm, always say let's go to the architecture first.
You've got to be an architect first and look on a bigger scale and see the whole framework
and then you go about building the foundation to create whatever.
you want to create um i think it was david walsh who put together the um the great museum in
tasmania talked about iteration but you've got to have a vision and then you've got to iterate that
vision over and over and again um and i think that that's you know important i like the idea
of a secret as well you know when you're trying to offer a vision probably not um it depends if
you're doing the theming at the start of a year then the idea of sometimes you want to spill it
out you want to you want to tell everybody what what you're planning but the idea of keeping a
secret's really important and then allowing that um it's like um it's like your first kiss you
want it to be that that sparks flying you know that first introduction to um the theme you want
it to hit somewhere special inside them so
really having a small team if you're working on a theme or a big event keeping that tight and even
i won't tell my assistant coaches not because but i want them to feel that excitement of that theme
on that night um or a bit like the grand final like i was talking about is um build out the
picture and then have you can have a shared experience when it when it's going to take
multiple people to to execute it it depends
yeah it depends on what what um sphere we're in so you might hold something back if you've had a
vision around a season coming up and a theme for the year that there might be a little something
there that you've you've saved for a big final or an occasion that that feels right is that is that
how it sort of unfolds for it well definitely throughout the season i'll split the season into
certain periods and you'll you'll have something ready that you know that is aligned with the the
team it's not something new it's not something new it's not something new it's not something new
you know it has to be aligned but you hold on to it for certain points throughout the year
um definitely the holding of that um yeah the holding of that's really important and putting
it in at the right times whether it's periods throughout the year um or um yeah even within a
week you know when when do you want to get um you know so a brand new game plan you better get it
sunday for a monday you better get that out there um but if it's um an emotional link into a game if
you feel like that's something that we don't always do but it's not much use spilling that
energy on a tuesday for a saturday game you know you want to sort of get it closer to thursday
friday and have a having a build up to it we're seeing curiosity as a really key thing that
leaders uh like yourself um
are really you know big on and then they approach their learning and improvement often through their
their sense of curiosity when i ask you about that dimension of being a leader what what does
that resonate with you the sense of curiosity i think there's two things luke when you when
you mention that is curiosity is vital for for continual progression um but
i also think you've got to have a foundation if you don't have consistency in your work
like i'm
you know i've got new ideas or i'm exciting or whatever but i know that the players will walk
in every day knowing that um defense is the most important walking in for now the 10th season
um that they will have will play a consistent style of play you know that you have to have
consistency about yourself most coaches have to know where home is
so you've got to have consistency about yourself and you've got to have consistency about yourself
so you can so curiosity is then put on top of that have a foundation know who you are you've got
to have a style that really works and then the curiosity goes on top of that to keep that fresh
and new and evolving as well whereas if curiosity makes you jump uh constantly from year to year and
change i think we should do this and that um my belief is you won't be successful you have to have
um a style of play a style of coaching a style of management and add curiosity
on top of that yeah it's an interesting uh way to think about the foundation as being the
the uh the essence and the curiosity on top i haven't heard someone describe it that that way
but it makes a lot of sense the way you go about your life and your and your leadership uh
communicating with clarity is a common trait of uh of all great leaders how do you think about that
yeah i think your choice of words is really important and i think that's a really important
key i think you'll often when you start coaching um you'll work so hard on the presentation and
you'll get out what you want to get out but the clarity of words and the use of words is vital
you know words have energy so making sure you don't um that you choose carefully the words
that you use on on your presentation and as i said um you might want to present in a certain way
um but ask for the words that you want to present in a certain way
are they going to hear those words um and i feel like the clarity of message um as i said i might
want to be um really uh curious or really vision focused and all of that but our players need the
fundamentals they need to be you know they need to walk in every day and um work really hard on
building principles before we get to the funky stuff um and so you've got to hold you cool and
understand what you're doing and what you're doing and what you're doing and what you're doing
what message you're getting across because if you know if i say five things that are principle
driven and then one thing that is um exciting and and funky then that's the one i need to
i need to be sent saying 20 30 things that are principle driven in early stages of building a
team and then sprinkle in the the funky stuff on top of that and it depends what team you got
you know i've just
we've just um moved out a lot of leaders that had a lot of principles in them and we're reforming
that um so that's really key in what we're trying to do at the moment and that's why i'm speaking
that way is i've got to hold myself back from the fun stuff and and constantly go over principles
and fundamentals over and over and over again because that's what the house will be built on
yeah it's interesting just to hear how systematic and thought out you are on
on that process no mistake at all in in in your
language and how you use it uh collaboration we're seeing is a real trait of uh of great
leadership as we see it at the moment how important is collaboration for you yeah i think
when you say collaboration luke are you talking about within the sport are you talking about
outside of the sport where do you probably that shift away from hierarchy and one person being
the voice to we're seeing leaders now understanding that that the shared voice and using people around
you and and you know probably your example of actually listening to your own playing group
and making decisions based on that collaboration and probably even the collaboration you're doing
in your own learning outside of it it seems like it's something you do effortlessly yeah i think the
the first one the collaboration within the group um we just had a big change over in in physical
performance stuff i have dave missen come back he's been in afl for a long time and um we've
been in a consistent form of training and we've been in a consistent form of training and we've
been in a consistent form of training and we've been in a consistent form of training for a while
so it's been interesting in saying my learnings on that about well how do you throw everything out
and then um everybody co-create a new model um and so that's been really it's been a good learning
for me about collaboration and and how you have to allow space for everybody to have a choice
and then you then everybody will buy into the program a bit like we talked about earlier in
the podcast about um
um the grand final week you know that and it's hard you know it's not i'm not saying it's easy
me at my worst in coaching i want to go in and control um that environment and it's really common
for coaches so i said when you get that role you want to go in and go no no i want to do it this way
and sometimes you have to but not when it's when the you have to do when it's right not because
you're feeling
like you're losing control when you collaborate um and i know that's you know i'm having to work
on that constantly i feel like when you sit in a meeting and you're running it eventually
it just it doesn't feel as good when you sit back and everybody's running that meeting you
have an agenda but everybody's got a voice and i feel like that's you know for me that's when i'm
at my best and at my worst there's there's two different styles of of
leadership and um so i think that's such an important um part of coaching and sharing
we heard brian gorge and speak to us really openly um the australian basketball coach incredible
experience at the olympics and turning up he's had amazing success as you would know he's 67
years of age i think gorge he turns up at the olympics and he's got two leaders in
patty mills and joe ingles who have absolutely clearly set out the tone for what they want to
achieve at the olympics and you know he had to really listen and and
uh and understand he just was this gift of two people who were really going to set the tone and
you know for him at his age to be able to uh adapt to that and understand that that was such a
powerful asset that took them to their first ever olympic medal was it was a great story and a you
know probably a great story of uh self-reflection but also the collaboration to see the leadership
that he had before him it was incredible yeah i mean i mean brian i've never met brian but just
the the way that he continually comes back and and you can see
that players everywhere he's been that players continually play um for him and he's got a really
um that's i feel like he's a really good example of someone that you know is a head coach he's got
the presence of a head coach but he's never um suffocated his teams you always feel like his
teams are um are a team and a collective that he's a part of that team from a distance that's
um it's been incredible to watch him over decades
um and now i think i feel like that's you know the the best coaches that i've seen are those ones
that um are the head coach because that's the role that they're in but there is this shared
responsibility throughout the teams and the head coach knows when to to step in and um and be that
role because the players need it you know they need the head coach to look after that at this
time but the then the coach pulls out and allows patty mills to you know
to do something special you know and he allow him to be the ultimate leader of that olympic
campaign there's a brilliant uh brilliant story and uh beautifully summed up through your insight
about asking all these leaders final two questions uh trent i've been time to think if you need it but
the first one is um if you look back at your life who's been the greatest leader in your life
greatest you know i always go back to um my mum has always been
you know she was a teacher from when i was a young age um and she showed me uh the strength
of uh teaching you know she was disciplined but really caring um at the same time and i feel like
that um really you know i really enjoyed watching mum teach um um when i was a youngster and that
that was the greatest leadership i had in in sort of
teaching and if you could collaborate with anyone firstly i love hearing that isn't it close to home
and to hear from your mother and i i read that uh further education was a given in the robinson
household for that you that was just going to happen and you know you've got the science degree
as as the older brother dean as well so i'm not surprised it's great to hear that uh before i
move on that collaboration we mentioned is a key thing that we're really passionate about
trent asking this question if you could collaborate with anyone in the world
who would it be phil jackson i would absolutely love to um you know he's i've read all his books
um uh in in coaching and i i just love the way that he went about the art of the game and then
the art of the dressing room you know i just um and he had a big spiritual side to the way that
he coached as well and he felt um open to to offer that to people and i think that's a really good
thing to do and i think that's a really good thing to do and i think that's a really good thing to do
to his players and and they were really non-judgmental in the way that he did that
but i just he he he was sort of the first one that um allowed through his books allowed me to be the
coach that i wanted to be yeah wouldn't that be brilliant to uh to connect if you've ever been in
a room with him if you had the chance to it's pretty accessible world did you i'm assuming you
would have uh as everyone did love the the last dance documentary and we we got an insight into
but a lot of phil jackson in that time as well yeah it was sort of quite i mean it was very
plagiarism which we loved and it was quite subtle on on on phil's role but understanding you know
the way that he did dance between the different players but um some of the you know sacred hoops
you know amazing book on on how spirituality and sport came into his coaching um and even
some of his sort of his early books but he he um
yeah it was just um he did have lots of fights with the front office that was one of his strengths
as a coach which um but yeah the understanding of the court and the way to play and then also
the dressing room uh he was an artist uh it's been a great honor and a great privilege uh to
meet you first of all to get understanding of what you do for the people in your environment
there's so many great lessons i've got a couple hours worth of more questions but in the interest
of your time uh i'll leave it there
thanks so much we've loved the fact we've been able to connect with you and see the influence
you're having on so many coaches in the same way that phil jackson's had an influence over you
thanks again for your time thanks i really appreciate what you guys are doing you know
you've offered a big development in my coaching and um you know i love the the shared knowledge
that you guys are offering with matt so thanks very much empowering leaders was presented by
me luke darcy produced by matt dwyer with audio production by darcy thompson
start your leadership journey i encourage you to go to a leader collective.com
take our empowering leaders indicator tool and understand the impact you have
on your environment join us at a leader to learn lead and collaborate listener