A Listener Production.
Terea Pitt is one of Australia's most remarkable people.
If you don't know her story, we hear it from Terea herself.
But it is incredible, a story of overcoming the most immense of challenges,
both physically and mentally.
This chat for me was truly unique and there are so many takeaways from the conversation.
But for those listening and for myself, you'll hear in the conversation
some really practical learnings Terea offers that we can apply to our day-to-day life.
Terea's work ethic, incredible resilience ties in with the passion that we have
at our organisation Alita.
It was founded with my great friend Matt Waterwitz,
a space where incredible leaders come together to collaborate and learn
and open up about how they're leading in their world.
If you're interested in this space, you can find it at alitacollective.com.
We'd encourage you to check out our signature Alita Connect program
to get started and to understand how, like Terea, you're leading in your world.
Terea Pitt.
Had completed a Bachelor of Engineering, landed her dream job,
was building a career in modelling as well as being an ultramarathon runner.
In September 2011, her life would change forever while competing in an ultramarathon event
on Equestro Station in the East Kimberley region of Australia.
An out-of-control fire surrounded her.
She sustained burns to 65% of her body, losing the fingers and thumb on her right hand,
enduring more than 200 surgeries over six months in hospital
that would ultimately save her life.
In the more than decades since, Terea has inspired millions of people around the world.
She's now a proud mother of two, a best-selling author of three books.
She's competed in the Ironman World Championship a couple of times,
despite having been told that she would never run again.
She's an in-demand motivational speaker, a successful entrepreneur,
and the host of a brilliant podcast titled Terea Pitt is Hard Work.
Tough title, that one, but it is brilliant.
I urge you to check it out.
It's great to catch up with you, Terea.
It's a remarkable life that you live.
Thanks for taking the time.
Yeah, thanks so much for having me, Luke.
I appreciate it.
Terea, I wanted to start with your podcast.
I love it.
It is brilliant, like everything that you do.
As I said, Terea Pitt is hard work.
I encourage you to check it out.
But I wanted to discuss, in particular, the episode you did with Kate Sanderson,
your fellow ultramarathon runner, who was severely burnt alongside you in that fire in the Kimber.
It is an incredible interview.
They all are on your podcast.
But you catch up with her.
I think nearly 10 years after the accident.
And amazingly, it's the first time the two of you have discussed what happened on that day
from both of your perspectives.
It is just amazing to listen to.
Are you okay going back talking about that?
Or is it something you're trying to avoid these days?
No.
Well, I guess that's, I've got to think about, that's why most people know me, right?
Because I went through that horrific experience.
So, it makes sense that people are interested in it and intrigued by it.
And to listen to that, sorry to cut you off, Terea.
No, no, no.
I'm full of questions.
You're running the show.
You're running the show today.
Look, it's all good.
I've got so much I want to get through.
It is, I mean, all your interviews are brilliant on the podcast.
But I was fascinated to some of the detail in that interview.
Kate talked about remembering you jogging past her.
And she looked and said, that's a good looking girl.
Well, you know.
And you two had that exchange.
And then you almost apologised to Kate and said, I've taken this very public path in my life.
And she's been incredibly private about it.
That was a fascinating exchange.
Was there some sense of guilt for you and, you know, being very different about how you've approached it post that event?
No, I think it's just an illustration of how different we all are.
So, for me, being public with my story, putting it out there on an open stage.
I found it helpful.
I found it motivating.
In a sense, I felt it made me accountable with my recovery.
So, when I was doing my rehab or when I was with the physio or when I was training for the Ironman,
having everyone know about those experiences or know about what I was planning to do
and people stopping me on the street and saying, you know, like, how's the training coming along for the Ironman?
I felt like I was accountable to all of Australia.
And even though at times I'd think, far out.
Why did I tell them?
Well, everyone, that I was, that I'm, you know, that I'm doing these things or that I'm doing this stupid race or
I think it definitely helped me with my recovery.
But as you heard in the interview, Kate is the complete opposite of me.
She's very private.
But she's still done tremendously well.
Like she's, she did a 250 kilometre ultra marathon through the Sahara Desert, which is totally nuts.
Considering that, you know, she's burnt to 60%.
She's burnt to 60% of her body as well.
So she has trouble regulating her body temperature as well.
And she lost half her foot in the fire.
So like, that's just, you know, I think she's way more hardcore than me, to be honest.
And if you listen to that interview, as I said, it's a really moving thing to hear the two of you sit down and talk about it.
And as you said, Kate lost her foot.
She's quietly gone about her well.
But she's totally, you know, as you said, we're all different.
We all approach things differently.
And she's...
Of course, an enormous, you can feel the bond that you two have for life.
And you even said at one stage, I was really pissed off you got in the chopper first, you know, so...
I was so pissed off.
I was so pissed off because like I was in, I was in pain.
I wanted to just get the hell out of there.
We'd been stuck on that hill for four hours.
I wasn't quite lucid.
But when Kate was in the helicopter first, I was like, oh, come on.
Like I'm awesome.
I'm so really badly hurt right now as well.
It's an amazing conversation to hear.
Can I ask you, how hard was it to move past the anger initially that, you know, should that event even have taken place?
There was 30 grass fires burning around the Kimberley region.
Why did the organisers allow that to happen?
How was there four hours delay before you actually got held by...
That must have been a huge amount of anger attached to that.
Was that hard to move past that?
Yeah, look, initially it was.
And I think for anyone that's had a life-changing experience like mine,
there's always that element where you say, why me?
Or why did this happen?
Or, you know, you're thinking about all of the different ways that you ended up in that time and that place.
But at the same time, Luke, like I'm an engineer.
I'm quite a logical, practical, rational person.
And I've just thought throughout my journey,
like it doesn't really help.
Like getting angry, getting pissed off, getting annoyed, getting bitter
doesn't do anything for me or for my recovery.
It doesn't help me run faster.
It doesn't help my relationship with my husband.
It doesn't help me to be a better mum.
It doesn't help me with my job right now.
So I've kind of like accepted that anger in my life.
And I think it's perfectly normal and really understandable
to be angry about something that's happened to you.
But also, it doesn't...
It doesn't do anything for me to sit in that place of anger
or sit in that place of being bitter.
And I'm really proud of myself
because I think the way I've reinvented myself
and the life I live now is pretty amazing.
And, you know, I live this great life with my wonderful husband
and my beautiful kids.
And I feel really proud of what I've done
and what I've achieved as well.
And I think Kate feels the same too.
Yeah, she sounds equally remarkable, Kate.
And as you said, different paths.
But you can feel the strength
when you hear that interview on your podcast.
Your latest book, and I want to come back to this,
Happy and Other Ridiculous Aspirations.
I did want to pick up on, as you just said then,
so articulately that, you know,
we all experience those emotions, don't we?
And we all have anger for certain things.
Yours probably more justified
than maybe anyone else on the planet.
But if you linger there,
you're really not going to find happiness.
And you've written a whole book
and it's a brilliant book as well.
To be able to understand those emotions, Thierry,
and deal with them
is a pretty profound bit of wisdom, isn't it?
Yeah, look, I don't know if I would say
I'm the wisest person out there.
I don't think I am,
but it was just probably just realising
through my journey that, you know,
we all know how we feel when we feel angry.
It's not a very comfortable emotion for us to feel,
but it is also just another emotion.
So just like feeling happy and excited,
and energised and enthusiastic,
those are all really positive emotions.
Those emotions all feel really good.
And so it makes sense that we'd prefer to be happy
and excited and enthusiastic all of the time.
But life just doesn't work that way, right?
So just as we have some days where we feel happy,
frothing, can't wait to get stuck into what we're doing,
looking forward to a great holiday we've got coming up,
we also have the other side.
We might be pissed off at our boss
because they've asked us to do extra work,
we might have a fight with our partner
about something that's mundane, about doing the dishes.
We might be angry at our kids
because they're not listening to us.
So we do feel all of those emotions all of the time.
And so I do think that we've got this culture
of toxic positivity these days.
And it's almost like we don't let ourselves be sad
or be annoyed or be stressed or be irritated.
We've always got to, you know,
find the silver lining or look on the bright side
or pick ourselves back up or whatever it is.
And I think that we're doing ourselves a disservice
because I think feeling angry or sad,
they are real emotions that we feel.
And I think just by accepting them and acknowledging them
and letting them pass over us,
I think that's more empowering
rather than just bullshitting to ourselves and saying,
no, no, no, no, no, I'm all good, I'm all good,
everything is good, everything is good.
You know?
It makes huge sense to me, Terea,
and I think you're right.
You feel that need to try and put that mask on.
A lot of people do.
And even anger, I know playing sport,
anger was a pretty useful emotion,
playing a competitive sport and also...
For sure, for sure.
It would have been incredibly useful for you.
Incredibly useful.
Not so useful sometimes around the kids.
But it's as you said, you know,
if someone's breaking through the door of our house,
you want to find them.
You want to find them.
You want to find your anger again pretty quickly.
It's not as though, you know,
an absence of that is a good thing.
So you're right.
There's that guilt associated with it sometimes, isn't it?
It's the understanding that they are just emotions
and when you can be real and acknowledge them,
there's an opportunity to live a more productive
and happy life.
I think you sum it up beautifully.
Yeah, and just, yeah, acknowledge them
and just allow yourself to sit in that emotion,
even though it's not comfortable,
even though no one likes feeling angry or jealous
or irritated.
They're not irritated or envious.
They are just emotions
and emotions change all of the time.
And we all feel them, don't we?
Even if you're not a jealous person,
everyone understands what jealousy feels like.
It's just, it's there
and when you can get in touch with that,
you know, reading your work,
it's something that you articulate incredibly well.
I look back at you, Therese, a 23-year-old,
you're a serious achiever.
You know, you've completed an engineering degree.
You've got your dream job.
You've got a great partner.
You're running ultra marathons
and then you have this unimaginable hardship
that people like me,
we can't even pretend to know what that was like for you.
Is it possible to think that even post that,
that you're an even better version of yourself
or is that condescending to say,
or is it just that you've channeled that same inner strength
in a slightly different path because of that hardship?
Yeah, it's a tricky question to unpack.
I don't know if I am a better person necessarily,
but I do think out of everything,
like if I had one regret,
it would be that before the fight,
I had all of these amazing people in my life.
I had this amazing boyfriend, right?
And I thought he was great,
but I was just like, you know, my family,
they were amazing as well.
I thought they were great,
but I didn't really think that much more about it.
And, you know,
I've got to temper this by saying I was a young woman.
I was 24 years old.
Young people by nature are maybe a little more self-absorbed.
I think with age comes a bit more wisdom
and being a parent as well,
you realise that your world doesn't revolve around you anymore
and it's more about your family.
So, but I think as a young person,
I had all of these amazing people in my life.
I had all of these things going for me,
but I never took a moment to let those people know
how much I appreciated them,
how much I was grateful for them,
how much their support and love and encouragement
meant the world to me.
Because I think I was definitely an overachiever.
I still am today.
But the only way I was able to do that
was because I had all of these things going for me.
I had great parents who gave me a solid foundation
who, when I said I want to do this thing,
they were encouraging and supportive.
I had a great guy next to me who was my rock.
I had amazing friends who were fun
and encouraging and supportive.
And I think, and you would know this, Luke,
you know, with team sports,
the only way that you get to achieve
whatever it is in the sport
is by having those people around you
who help you and help you achieve the vision,
I guess, that you're going after.
So if I have one regret,
it would be that I never told the people in my life
how much they meant to me
before I had this.
This hardship.
And do you do that more now?
Way more now.
Way more.
I'm probably too much the other way.
But I think it's so important, right?
Because, you know, it's our relationships with each other
that really matter when it comes down to the wire.
Yeah, absolutely.
It's, again, there's so much wisdom in your words
and in reading and listening to your podcast
in preparation for today,
there's some of your words,
but I just felt compelled to read back to you.
And this particular quote stands out for me.
If I've learned anything,
it's that we are all much stronger
and more powerful than we'll ever know.
I'm trapped by my body,
but others are trapped by their attitude.
And I think that is a worse tragedy.
Can you describe that incredible attitude that you have
and how it served you so well?
Oh, no, that is a very hard,
that is a really hard question to answer.
Well, I guess I've got a can-do approach to life.
I have the attitude that just give something a go.
Doesn't matter if you're shit at it.
If you keep trying, you'll get better.
Just show up.
You don't have to do things perfectly the first time,
but if you keep showing up, you will improve.
And I think that open mindset
or that willingness to test yourself,
that willingness to fail at things,
that willingness to do things,
that willingness to do something,
even if you're not particularly good at it,
I think all of those are really great qualities.
They're qualities that I got
or that were instilled in me by my parents
and they're the qualities I try to instill in my kids.
And you think, you know, if you look at little kids,
they're so willing to try things for the first time,
you know, walking, running, soccer, whatever it is they try,
they might be really average at it to start with,
but they know that if they just keep trying
or if they persist, they'll get better.
But I think as adults, you know,
you try something for the first time
and surprise, surprise, you're shit at it.
And what do you say to yourself?
You just say, oh, I'm shit at soccer.
I'm not good at this.
I'm not going to try it again.
I'm terrible at IT.
I can't operate my computer.
I can't do all these things.
They're all coming to me straight away, Terea,
but you're right.
It's that persistence that springs to mind.
I also wanted to pick up,
and I was just, as I read that quote,
I was thinking I had the great pleasure to sit down
with Dr. Terea,
who did the National Pallet Party,
who had a serious motor accident,
ended up in a wheelchair
and was the first doctor to actually be able
to complete a medical degree from a wheelchair
and with the serious injuries that he sustained.
And he talked about when he was a young lawyer
getting depressed because he was doing law
because he really felt like that was what the family
wanted him to do.
He wasn't living what he should be.
And his words to me when I spoke to him,
that was much more debilitating.
Being in that mindset than being in a wheelchair
and that your power of your mind is so much more
to overcome than even the most challenging physical
challenges we face.
Does that resonate?
Yeah, it does.
And I also think with the language that we use
with overcoming hardships, right?
It's like I have to beat this thing.
I have to rise above it.
I have to overcome it.
That language to me, it sounds really intimidating
because for me, I don't really think like I've smashed
my recovery or I've beaten down this hardship
with a big stick.
Rather than that, if I have hard days, I accept them.
I remind myself that I get to do,
you know, I've got a great job.
I get to speak to interesting people like you, Luke.
I get to write really great books that people want to read.
I get to teach women how to run in my running program.
So I live this really great life.
But I think it's not, for me, it's not so black and white.
It's not like I reached this turning point where I was like,
whoa, I've done it.
I've overcome my adversity now.
And now it's, you know, now I don't have to think about it anymore.
It's more just something.
It's something that I live with, which is what anyone would say, right?
So like I forgot that doctor's name who you spoke to.
Dinesh Pellopani.
So his injuries would be something that he lives with on a daily basis.
Same with my injuries.
And equally, if you lose someone that you love,
if your partner's going through a battle with cancer,
it's all things that we live with.
And so rather than, you know, I don't want the audience
to walk away thinking, oh, well,
if I don't have a doctor, I don't know what I'm going to do.
If I have an accident, I'll reach a point
where I'll just magically be over it
and then I'll get to continue living my life as normal.
I think it's something that you learn to live with.
But also you can have a really great life with it as well.
Yeah, beautifully, beautifully said.
I mean, it's the essence of what you're delving into in the podcast.
Sharia Pitt is hard work.
I love the title.
Do you though?
Well, it sort of catches you off guard.
It does, doesn't it?
You're going, you know, what does that actually mean?
But I think when you jump in and you are talking to people
that have experienced, you know, hardship and challenge
with the idea of learning, you know, what the lessons are from it,
can you share with us what have you found so far
from those that have been able to overcome hardship?
As I said, that language I'm using, which, as you said,
it's not a magical formula and it's overcome,
but is there some patterns that you're finding?
You know, I think the thing that I found after speaking to the guests
that I've had, and I've had some really amazing guests.
I've had Dr. Charlie Teo, Kurt Fearnley.
I just spoke to Richard Harris, who was the anaesthetist
who helped rescue the boys in the cave in Thailand.
So I think the commonality between all of those people is to start with
they really enjoyed what they did for work.
And I think this was part of that episode that you spoke to with Russell, right?
Because you asked him about work.
He said work-life balance, and he said there's...
It's bullshit.
He said Russell Howcroft you're talking about,
who's a legendary figure and co-host of The Gruen.
And, yeah, he said work-life balance doesn't exist was his answer, wasn't it?
Yeah, because he said that's just like you go to work and you don't like it.
And then as soon as you clock off, it's like, whoa, now I can start living.
But he, you know, he obviously loves his work.
And I think that's been the commonality between everyone I've spoken to.
They all have something really positive.
That they're channeling their focus or channeling their energy into.
And another commonality I've found is that they all still do experience those harder times
or those hard days, but they don't let themselves become floored by it.
So they may have a shitty day, but they all have the presence of mind
to realize that it's just a day.
And in the broader context, they do enjoy their lives,
but that's not to say that they don't occasionally
have bad days.
And I think that's really important.
That ties back into what I was saying before.
You don't reach this point where you suddenly transform into this mythical being
and you no longer feel sad or angry anymore.
It doesn't quite work like that.
But I love, and sometimes it does sound cliche, Turia,
when you hear people, you know, follow your purpose and find your passion.
But the cliches actually often make sense, don't they?
Because, you know, I look at you and I just see purpose and I see passion.
And in every chapter of your life, and I think one of the saddest things
is when you see people, you know, trapped in their own mind,
in a job they hate or in a relationship they hate
or in a life they don't like, when it is hard,
but there are choices, aren't there?
You can always change your paradigm with, you know, with purpose.
Yeah.
Yeah, look, I think most of us can.
I think for some, I know there's some people out there
who might not have the privileges or the opportunities
that we've both had.
So, you know, I don't think everyone is in that position
where they do have that clear choice.
But I agree with you.
If you find something that you enjoy doing, whatever it is,
and you feel like going to work isn't a grind for you
and it's something that you enjoy doing and that you, you know,
dare I say you love, I think that's really great
and you're really lucky.
And if you're not enjoying what you're doing right now,
maybe there's some extra study you could do.
Maybe.
Maybe there's some extra training.
Maybe you could just back yourself or challenge yourself
and take that leap and have that little bit of faith in yourself
to try and find another, I guess, another vocation
that you might prefer.
Turi, your latest book, and they're all bestsellers
and brilliant, Happy and Other Ridiculous Aspirations
is the title.
It's another brilliant bit of work from you explores
can you actually get happier?
I wanted to ask you the daily routines, there's a chapter on it,
and the habits, the stuff that you do to try and be happier
and live a happier life.
Can you share with us some of the things that work for you?
Yeah, so there's a couple of different things.
I think to start with, it's easier to be happy
if we're doing the basics, right?
If we're eating well, if we're moving our body,
if we're getting enough sleep,
if you've got those three things down pat,
it's going to be easier for you to be happier, right?
And those three things,
they sound really simple,
but it's so easy for us to come out of whack with them.
We might be stressed, might have taken on a lot at work.
We might have just eaten, like not eaten very well that week,
or we might have had a big weekend on the pierce
and Monday comes around and we're feeling pretty shit.
We're feeling pretty shit about ourselves.
But I think just going back to basics, right?
If you're feeling down or you're feeling crappy,
go back to those basics, check in.
Are you feeding yourself nutritious foods?
Are you moving your body?
Now, for me, obviously, I like running.
Luke, what do you do?
Do you still play footy or are you-
I don't, Cherie.
I finished, God, how long ago is it now?
15 or 16 years ago.
So I didn't play again after I finished playing for a living.
But morning routines are right in my wheelhouse, Cherie.
My wife, Bec, is a yoga instructor.
So I start with a bit of meditation.
I'm into a bit of yoga.
We go for a walk together every day.
It sounds very, very soft and it is very soft,
but I'm pretty-
I'm pretty consistent at it and it works.
Okay.
Okay, well, that's good.
Amazing.
So you look really smug over there, Luke.
You look really smug doing your yoga.
That sounded smug, didn't it?
Doing your yoga, meditating.
It didn't mean to sound smug,
but I know what it's like to have a big night on the piss still
and wake up and not do it as well.
So it's-
And you feel shit, don't you?
You do feel shit.
So check back in.
Are you eating good food?
Are you moving your body?
You don't have to.
Are we doing yoga and meditating like Luke,
if you want to go for it?
But if there is another form of exercise that you love doing,
do that.
And then I'm a really big believer
in having a great morning as well,
because I think how we set up our morning
affects how our day goes.
And I think my morning routine
is nowhere near as extensive as yours, Luke.
So when I wake up in the morning,
I have a good morning.
I drink my coffee, right?
And then the first thing I do is something that I don't do.
And I don't pick up my phone.
Because I find like that's,
it's almost a habit that we have, right?
We wake up, we grab our phone, we look at it.
And then our mind is suddenly elsewhere.
We're suddenly thinking about emails,
what our boss needs from us
or what our team needs from us,
what we haven't done for other people,
writing back to people's messages,
looking at Instagram stories.
And before we know it,
we've just lost 20 minutes of our day,
just staring at a little box.
So I don't pick up my phone,
I try not to pick up my phone until like eight o'clock,
which is when Michael does the school drop-off.
So he takes the kids to school.
And then I'm like, oh, thank goodness.
I've got a bit of peace and quiet in the house by myself.
And then that's generally when I start my work day.
But yeah, trying not to look at my phone.
I find that helps me a lot with how I feel about myself
and conversely, how happy I am as well.
Yeah, it's a common thing, isn't it, Therese?
Yeah.
I'm getting over the smugness of my answer before.
But Mike Dunlap, who I spoke to just recently,
the assistant coach of the Milwaukee Bucks,
has coached around the world.
And he really made a point of that.
And I still get sucked in, don't you?
That algorithm is so powerful, isn't it?
The light comes on and you say,
I'll just check this one message.
And before you know it,
the first 45 minutes of your day
has just been into that vortex of work.
And then I feel it's hard to get back.
Your day then has started on you.
Oh, it is.
Because you're starting in a really weird spot.
And you almost start your day feeling resentful and irritated.
And I don't think that's the best way to start your day.
Yeah.
I think a better way is to start having a coffee.
For me, it's like playing with the kids
or getting their stuff ready for school.
It's drinking my coffee outside with my partner,
having a little chat to him.
It might be five minutes.
It might be 20 minutes.
You know, so however much amount of time it is,
I'm just happy for it and grateful for it.
And I try to think about what it is in that day
that I'm looking forward to.
Because I find that, you know,
if we're looking forward to our days,
then we look forward to our week.
And that means we, you know,
by extension, we're looking forward to our lives.
And I also think just trying to start your day
with a grateful frame of mind.
So I try and think of the things I'm grateful for, right?
Grateful for my business.
Beautiful family.
Grateful for my mom,
because I had a good chat with her yesterday.
Grateful for the cup of coffee that my partner made,
whatever it is.
Just really simple things.
It doesn't have to be something flashy and instantaneous.
You know, if you are going on a boat
with Beyonce and Jay-Z in the south of France,
like awesome, good for you.
But for everyone else,
we probably don't have things like that
coming up in our lives.
So just small, littler things.
Like what you're looking forward to on the weekend
or if you had a nice bit of quality time
with your kids, reading them a book, whatever it is.
And I think that if we start our days feeling grateful,
I think that helps us to build a more positive mindset, right?
Because we're laying down those grateful.
I don't know what they're called, actually.
The wires.
The neural pathways, aren't you?
I was listening to...
Neural pathways, that's it.
That's it.
Very smug there.
Very smug.
I've got some smugness, haven't I, today.
I was thinking of that because Joe Dispenza,
I was listening to a podcast the other day,
and the science behind what you're saying,
Drew, is so relevant now.
And the data is there.
It's a practice what you're talking about.
And then when you open those neural pathways,
then they get stronger, isn't it?
It's a bit like you running and post,
you get fitter because you put one step in front of the other.
No one expects to be able to run an ultra marathon
without building that pathway.
And so to not think our mind doesn't work the same way
is really a naive to think.
And you know that with that positive pathways you create,
it makes us healthier.
The science is there.
It makes you healthier and happier.
And likewise, the negative thoughts make us sick.
And not a lot of people still grasp that, Drew, in lots of ways.
And clearly, you read your book.
It's a big part of what you do.
And it's not as challenging as some people may think.
You know, to think of three things that you're grateful for every morning.
It's quite a simple little exercise.
You can also journal every night of three things in your day that went great.
And those are very simple, very straightforward exercises
that people might, you know, they might almost think,
oh, that's so easy and so straightforward.
That won't work.
But actually, the science is there and the proof is there.
And Dr. Laurie Santos, who did, she did this, like,
course about, you know, positive psychology and wellness.
And she said that she found through her data that if you write a thank you letter
to someone, you know, to your postman, to your family, to your mom,
whoever it is, she said the increase in wellness for yourself
or the increase in well-being for yourself can often last up to a month.
So if you think, if you sit down, write a thank you letter to someone,
post it, and then that's going to help you feel better about yourself
for a month.
Like, that's a pretty amazing impact that it's going to have on your day.
And that process will probably take you, I don't know,
maybe five minutes to write the letter, five minutes to stop by the post office
on your way to work, so 10 minutes.
I think that's a pretty good return on investment.
Yeah, beautifully said.
And as you, you know, the alternative of starting on your phone
and getting sucked into that or writing or just even thinking three things
to start the day you're grateful, it can be life-changing.
It can literally change the way you,
you live and clearly you do that.
You mentioned your partner, Michael.
He sounds like a ripper.
He sounds like the sort of guy you'd love to have a beer with
and catch up with.
Yeah, he's annoying.
Everyone always loves him so much.
It's so annoying.
Everyone's like, oh, where's Michael today?
Where is he?
We want to meet him.
Does he have a brother?
But I love there's some words that I again want to read back to you
because I love what you're saying this.
And when talking about Michael in the past, you said,
if you want a partner who's mature and in touch with their emotions,
are you mature and in touch with your emotions?
And, you know, you sort of get the partner you deserve to hear in some ways,
don't you?
Because clearly you've attracted the person you have because of the person you are.
Yeah, I think so.
And again, you know, I think for everyone that may not always be the case.
I know there's things like coercive control and abusive relationship,
so I guess if you're talking about general healthy relationships,
you know, I think if you're living your best life, if your life is full,
if you've got people around you who love you, who encourage you,
who aren't afraid to tell you the hard truth, I think that's really important as well.
I know that's what Michael does for me because so often,
and you might get this too, Luke, you might have people who blow smoke up your ass
all the time.
And tell you how awesome you are.
And it's so, you know, and Michael and my dad actually are probably like the only people
who will just tell me how it is.
Like I remember the first time I gave a speech, my dad came along with me
and I was so nervous, forgot what I was saying, like quickly flashed all of my slides
and then I got into the car with my dad and I said,
Dad, how was that?
And he goes, it was shit ass.
He said, that was terrible.
He goes, did you get paid money for that?
And I said, yeah.
He goes, well, you should be embarrassed.
Like he was, he was, he was ruthless.
But like I think it's important to have people in your life who aren't afraid
to tell you the truth and aren't afraid to tell you the uncomfortable things as well.
And I know that's what Michael does for me.
So he'll still do that to you if he feels like you're going off the reservation,
you'll get the direct feedback from him?
I'll get the direct feedback even if it's not solicited.
And I think feedback, you know, is a bit of a gift to you.
It's misinterpreted sometimes.
It hurts your feelings though at the time.
I know it's a gift.
But when someone tells you your speech was shit ass.
So what do you say to your dad in that moment?
What was your response?
Really, dad?
Yeah, it was pretty terrible.
It was pretty horrible.
And then I was like, oh.
No, but dad was good.
He was like, look, if you want to pursue this as a career,
you're going to have to get better at it.
But he said, if you don't want to do this,
then like don't invest the time and energy into getting better at it.
Yeah, brilliant advice.
So like that's, you know, that's great advice.
It's like, well, if you want to do something, you've got to spend energy,
time, commitment, focus into getting better at that chosen sport,
whether it's footy, whether it's running, whatever it is that you're doing.
And if it's something that you don't actually want to do,
then like don't waste your time.
Don't beat yourself up because you think you should be better at it.
Just let it go.
I love hearing that engineering, pragmatic, data-driven part of your brain,
that comes out in, you know, it's a matter of fact.
And the way that you operate, how it serves you incredibly well.
Is there a spiritual side in there?
As well as the engineering part to you?
I'm not religious as such, but I do believe in energy, right?
So I think if you're feeling, if you're in a good mood and you walk into work
and you say good morning to people and you're dynamic and you're charismatic,
then you have the ability to lift people up, right?
You have the ability to make others feel better about the people that they are.
And you said Russell was like that, Russell Howard.
Russell Howcroft, yeah, absolutely.
Sorry, Russell Howcroft.
Sorry, Russell.
I'm a big fan, but sorry, I didn't know your last name just then.
Conversely, if you walk into work and you're shitty, you're annoyed, you're grumpy,
you give people one word answers, you're not going to particularly light anyone up.
You're not going to particularly make anyone feel good about themselves.
So I do think the energy that we have, how we carry ourselves, how we conduct ourselves,
how interested we are when we ask people questions,
how much we listen to their responses and how we make people feel about themselves.
I think definitely I'm a massive believer in that.
And I know with myself, I always try to be a positive influence on others.
And I always try to do that with other people.
So I'm not spiritual as such, but I do believe in energy.
Yeah, I get it.
I understand your thoughts on it.
And it leads into what we are seeing from leaders and your story is remarkable.
And I love the privilege of sitting down and being able to hear it.
In person, and we're seeing people who have the impact like you do.
There's some consistent dimensions of what leadership looks like in different settings,
whether from a sporting background or doing what you're doing and inspiring people.
And we think most people start with a sense of self-leadership,
that without self-leadership, you can't lead others.
Do you think about self-leadership for you?
Honestly, no.
Well, you tell me, what does it actually mean?
Well, to me, it means, Terea,
the idea that I've got an opportunity myself to live up to the person I want to be.
And if I'm not actually practicing that really smug routine that I shared with you before,
if I'm actually talking to other people about how to start the day in the morning,
if I'm actually not doing that, then I haven't really tapped into self-leadership.
If I'm asking questions of other people and giving my thoughts,
but I'm not living that myself, that's how I think about self-leadership.
But for other people,
it's got a different meaning.
Does it resonate with you at all?
Yeah, I think it does.
I think it's firstly, you've got to practice what you preach.
I think another aspect is not asking people around you to do things that you wouldn't do yourself.
So that can be, for example, with my team, or that could be with my family as well.
But it's also holding yourself in high regard.
And I think we've got, and I don't know if it's just,
actually, I think it is mainly,
where it's not, we don't like it when someone has tickets on themselves.
We don't like it when someone's too ambitious, or not humble, or too braggy.
All of those are very un-Australian qualities.
And so it can be really difficult to say,
no, I hold myself to a high standard of conduct,
and I hold myself to a high standard across the board.
But I think that's what self-leadership is as well.
And I also think part of that surely must be acknowledging that you're not perfect.
So we're not these Audemars robots walking around being like,
I hold high standards for myself, that we're not perfect.
And we do slip up, and we do fail.
And we don't always say the right thing at the right time.
But we're okay with that as well.
So I think there's an element of self-compassion there as well.
Yeah, beautiful answer.
I heard you mention this before,
but the second dimension of leadership we talk about is,
you know, the leader's really conscious how they positively impact others in their environment.
And we heard you say that from every room you walk into,
you've got a chance to have an impact on someone.
Is that how you think about it day to day?
Is that the opportunity's there to positively impact others?
Yeah, I think so.
And that can be hard, right, when you're bogged down in the detail.
Like if I'm looking at the spreadsheet, or if I'm looking at a penis,
or if I've got to make decisions with my running program,
or if I've got to, it can be really hard to remove yourself from that and think,
hey, I have to think about making an impact on people.
So it actually can be hard to remind yourself of that on a day-to-day basis.
But I think, you know, if you tie that back into your morning routine,
you can be grateful for the opportunities that you have that day.
So, for example, this conversation with you.
And I think it's good to remind yourself,
you know, not all the time, because that's how exhausting would that be,
reminding yourself all the time that you have to be a positive impact
for everyone else around you.
I think that would be quite exhausting for anyone to carry out.
But I think it's good to remind yourself from time to time
that you do get to make a positive impact on people.
And whether that's by people listening to this podcast or your podcast, Luke,
or whether it's even at work,
being that person who walks in in a good mood
and is a good, like a good egg for people to work with.
But people don't really care what your skill set is.
But like if you're a good, well, sorry, I shouldn't say that.
People do care what your skill set is,
particularly if you're like the engineer for a large construction project.
So they do care what your skill set is.
But I think if you're a good person for people to work with,
I think that says a lot about the person that you are.
And I also think with your family,
so often we give everything to our jobs and to our careers.
And we might come home and we're so exhausted
that we might only mutter a couple of grunts to our partner
and we might be a little bit annoyed with our kids
and we might not give them the, I guess,
the energy and attention that they need as well.
And so I think life isn't perfect.
And, you know, some days, some weeks you might be more invested in work
and I think that's normal and that's okay.
But I also think it's great to give some of that positive influence
back onto your family and your personal life.
We talk about leaders really clear around creating their vision
and how they go about sharing it
and what you have done right throughout your life.
But in the second chapter, you know,
to have one book that is a bestseller is an extraordinary achievement.
You're consistently doing it.
You've got a great running community and building an incredible business
and having a massive impact on others.
Have you been, can you share with us how you've sort of created that vision
and how you've gone about making it happen?
Yeah.
Well, I think at the start, it's okay if you don't know exactly
what it is that you're trying to do because, you know,
so many people might get hung up on creating a 10-year bulleted out,
detailed, extensive business plan with multiple spreadsheets
inputting into it.
That might be overkill because you might not actually know
what it is that you're...
or thinking about doing is what it is that you want to be doing
or maybe you don't enjoy doing it or maybe it might change.
So I think a general direction is helpful,
but don't get hung up on knowing like the exact degree
where you're going to end up.
I think that, you know, not getting too hung up on that
and also acknowledging and understanding that as you go,
you'll work it out.
You know, we had those really bad flyers in...
It was in the summer of 2019, right?
So the fires were burning all up and down the east coast of Australia
and actually all around Australia they were burning
and in my hometown of Ulladulla, the fires were really bad.
We had fires burning north of us, south of us, west of us.
So our town was pretty much encircled by flames
and a girlfriend and I, we thought we wanted to do something
to help our community or help the communities
around Australia that were going through these bushfires
and we wanted to help small businesses
because in our community, all of the beautiful little businesses
that rely on that summer trade, there was no tourists in the town.
Everyone had gone home.
So we were worried about all of those businesses
because they would have, you know, ordered extra stocks,
organised extra supplies, all of that type of stuff
and then they wouldn't be able to sell it.
So we decided we wanted to do something and we wanted to do this,
spend with them.
We had a spend with them campaign which we thought was going to be
an Instagram page and we weren't really sure what we were going to do.
We were like, we'll just profile some businesses.
Don't really know what's going to happen.
Now, we could have sat down, put more thought into it,
planned it out more, got on board extra resources,
done all of this work, mapped out everyone's,
what everyone's job role was going to be and mapped it all out
and spent weeks doing all of that or we could have just gone,
fuck it, we don't know.
Let's just put it out.
Let's see what happens.
So we just did the logo in Canva, put it out there and we were like,
oh, well, this could just fall over.
We might not get anything.
And within a couple of days, we had over 200,000 followers.
The businesses that we profiled, you know,
they were making enough money from people buying stuff
from their store to make their mortgage repayments.
People made more money from one post than six months worth of markets.
So we really helped Swansea.
We helped small businesses around Australia and if we had have stopped
and if we had have thought about it and if we had have put on additional
resources, cause we were both staying up until like, you know,
3am to write back to everyone.
And I was two weeks away from giving birth to my second child.
So it was a crazy, crazy time.
But if we had have stopped and thought about it,
then we might have not have done it.
You know, we might have been like, oh, it's heaps of work and I don't know if
it's going to work.
And.
You know, maybe by the time we were ready, it would have been three months down the track
and then maybe the businesses might not have needed so much support.
So I think if you've got an idea, don't overthink it.
Just put it out there.
See what happens.
Maybe people will froth on it and you'll say, great, awesome.
This is a good idea.
Let's get let's get some more.
Let's build the team.
Let's get more help in.
Maybe no one cares about it.
In which case there's your answer as well.
It's brilliant advice to read and you do.
Hear that in different ways, isn't it?
We can spend so much time, as you said, creating something that we don't really know
anyone cares about.
But I love that story, as you said, isn't it?
Get it out.
And then sometimes you can just improve it as it goes and you test it straight away.
And what you did was change people's lives, you know, in the time they needed it more
than anyone else.
Curiosity is a dimension of leadership.
And through people's sense of curiosity, we're seeing that word a lot.
That's how people approach how they want to get better and learn.
Just.
Does curiosity form part of your thinking?
Look, I'm probably not as articulate as that, but by nature, I am a curious person.
I presume you are too, Luke.
That's why you've got this podcast, because you're obviously curious about other people
and how they've applied, you know, leadership to their lives.
So I think by nature, I am a curious person.
I don't know whether or not during the day, you know, I don't stop at something and be
like, huh?
I'm curious.
I'm curious about that.
But I always want to find out the reason, right?
So even with, we've just finished one of our recent launches for the running program.
So I've got all the data to go through and I really like doing the post-launch reports
because that kind of, I love looking at the data, but I also like seeing what works and
what wasn't as effective.
So I guess that is an example of me being curious as well, but I don't know if I'm ever,
if I ever notice it as much.
Yeah.
I love the way, you know, you articulate, clearly that's, you know, something that you
do every day, but not overthinking it, it just, it just happens for you.
And you get another incredible contribution, the running club that Turia has created.
Communicating with clarity is again, you know, we're pretty, pretty formal here in lots of
ways, Turia, but you know-
We are very formal.
I don't know what a lot of this stuff is.
Yeah.
I don't know what a lot of this stuff means.
Except you do it more easy, more easily and better than anyone else.
I mean, to write three bestselling books, to host your podcast and do it as, as brilliantly
as you do, clearly your communication works.
I mean, again, it's probably not, it doesn't sound like it's something you overthink.
You just, you just do.
Is that-
Well, I think, yeah, I think don't overthink things to start with.
Put it out there, whatever it is, like that's the approach I've taken with my writing.
Yeah.
I send out a weekly letter every week to, I don't know, I don't know.
I send it out to over 50,000 people and I don't overthink it, right?
And at the start, they were pretty shit because it was the first time I'd blogged, so I wouldn't
know what to write about.
And then I just got better at it because I was consistent with it.
And then that's how I've written these books, just by being consistent.
You know, you don't, well, maybe some people do, I don't write a book overnight.
It's like 20 minutes every day.
Just sitting down at my desk.
Writing, I might write something really articulate and really insightful.
I might write something really rubbish, but it doesn't really matter because I'm in that,
I'm in that practice or I'm in that habit of writing every day.
Speaking to people on my podcast, you're obviously a far more experienced podcaster than me, Luke.
I've only just started, but even if I listened back to past episodes, you know, I think,
oh gosh, that was really awkward.
That episode was terrible to read.
Yeah.
Terrible.
But I'm, but I'm getting better at it.
And the same with the running program as well.
I think if you do something every day, if you allow yourself, if you give yourself a
bit of grace to not be perfect straight away, to not have all of the answers straight away.
And I think that's important in leadership too, right?
You don't have to have all of the answers.
You can just say, good question.
I don't actually know the answer to that right now, but let me come back to you or let's
work it out together, or maybe we'll be able to figure that out in the future.
Yeah.
So I think that's really important in leadership, but not overthinking things and whatever it
is that you're doing, whether it's a book or a podcast, or you've got this great idea,
put it out there, see what people think, see if there's a desire for it, see if there's
a need for it.
And like I said before, if people run with that idea and they like it, that's great.
If people give you some insight onto what you could do or what you could do differently,
that's also a great result.
And if no one cares, again, not so much a great result for yourself, but also it is because then
you're not wasting all of this emotional energy thinking about this idea whether or not it will
work. I love hearing your courage just to do. It's brilliant. And be prepared to reflect and say,
you know what, I started there. If I look back, I was always going to get better. But a lot of
people don't have that courage just to start, isn't it? And become an author or have a go
knowing that, as you said, and I love how you explained that really well, isn't it? If you find
out really quickly that no one's interested, that actually is pretty beneficial too, isn't it?
Yeah. That's obviously, if you've got an idea for this pizza holder eater thing and you think
it's brilliant, you think it's going to change the world and you put it out there to your friends
and family and they go, oh, yeah, I guess it could be a good idea. Or maybe you start a website or
you start a social media blog.
Or whatever it is. And you don't really get much back or you just hear crickets,
then it might be disappointing for you, but that will be an answer as well.
Therese, how important has collaboration been for you in your world?
Really important, I think. And I feel really grateful. I've got a great team of women that
I work with. And I think it's incredibly gracious to have people that are working
with you. And I think it's incredibly gracious to have people that are working with you.
And I think it's incredibly gracious to have people that are working with you on your vision.
They're spending their time, their energy, their focus, their attention. They could be doing that
for something for themselves or they could be doing that for someone else. But instead,
they've chosen to be doing that to help me to execute my vision. So I think that's incredibly
gracious of people to do. And so I think collaboration, I feel like, again, I'm not
as formal. I'm not as formal as you. I don't sit down with my team and be like, okay,
we're doing this. I'm not as formal as you. I'm not as formal as you. I'm not as formal as you.
We're doing a formal collaboration session right now. Let's all collaborate. But we'll
have a chat. And if they say, what about this? And I try and listen to that idea and try
and investigate it a little bit further and try and see if it's an idea that's going to
stick.
Brilliant answer, as they all have been asking these two questions of all the leaders and
inspiring people like you, Terea, and your story is remarkable and inspiring and learn
so much from listening to you.
Thank you.
Thank you for speaking to you today. Who has been the greatest leader in your life?
This is probably going to sound sappy, but I think my partner, Michael, because he's a
beautiful human being. He's humble and he's self-effacing and he's just a good egg,
just a good guy. And I think I'm someone that's, like I've already said, I'm an
overachiever and I'm quite ambitious and I can get really caught up in what it is that I'm
doing or what it is that I'm achieving or what it is that I'm moving forward towards.
I think he's a really great reminder to take a step back and to reflect on my relationships
in my life. So my relationship with him, our relationship with our kids, our relationship
with our families and friends. It's a really great reminder for me to step back and reflect
on the fact that it's our relationships really that are the most fulfilling and the most
enriching thing in our world.
And it also can be our relationships with our work colleagues as well. Like I said,
I've got a great team of ladies that I work with. We have a lot of fun together.
So I think those relationships too are ones that I cherish, but I think probably would be
Michael would be someone that I would look up to a lot.
What an amazing answer. And I have had this conversation before, I think even on the podcast
where, I mean, clearly as you just articulated, then he reminds you of how important that is.
And for you to actually spend some time, we often,
all of us are, when we're trying to grow a business or trying to expand stuff, we can
put all this energy and all this thought and you've got incredible wisdom to share, but
we don't often apply that to the people closest to us, do we? And we expect good results in
our relationship. So it's a void, isn't it? I think it is for a lot of us. We don't apply
that same wisdom. Does that make sense to you?
Yeah, that's so true. We go into work, we've got an outline of what we're going to achieve
that day. We've got all of our meetings booked in. We get through the day, we do our work,
everything. And then we come home and we're just like, fuck, I'm exhausted. What are we doing for
dinner? And then you sit down, you eat dinner, you watch TV, then you go to bed. And I think
some nights are just going to be like that. Because I do think it's, if you enjoy your work
and you enjoy what you do, then you're going to put a lot of yourself into it. And that's not a
bad thing at all. I think that's great. Especially if you find your work fulfilling. There's this new
concept going around called quiet quitting. Have you heard of it?
No, I haven't.
Yeah, well, it's when people go to work, but they don't really love their job.
But so they just, they put in the bare minimum, which is also a strategy, right? Because if you
just go to work, you just want to get paid, you just want to go home in the Arvo
to your family. I also think that that is a strategy. And that might be a strategy that
works for some people out there as well. But I think with our relationships,
we know we have all of these plans,
for our business and our plans for our lives. But we don't ever do any of that with our
relationships. We don't ever kind of plan out our weekends. And I know a lot of people will be like,
no, I'm not planning out my weekend. I've just spent a whole week being in meetings and everything.
But I think having a little bit of thought into that time with your family or into that time with
your partner, whether it's date night or whether it's spending time together, I think just applying
a little bit of thought to that can be really, really helpful. And I think that's a really,
really helpful for us. Because there's, I don't know if you've seen that meme, it's like
everyone else gets the best of you and then your family just gets what's left over. And I think
it should be more of an equilibrium. I haven't seen that meme, but it does make
sense, isn't it? We do it ourselves sometimes to our own parents and then we see it through
our own kids as well. Yeah. And I think particularly for women,
not saying that being a dad doesn't have challenges, but I think for women in particular,
especially these days, for example, if Michael drops off the kids at daycare,
people will be like, oh my gosh, he's such a great dad. But she is, he is a great dad. But if I pick
up my kids at daycare, do you think anyone is saying, oh my gosh, she's such a great mom,
she's picking up her kids from daycare. So the standard of care that we have for women and their
kids is extremely high. And I think that's a really, really important thing. And I think
the standards we have for men and their kids is extremely low. And even if I'm, you know,
if I go for a surf, people will say, oh, where are the kids? Is Michael babysitting them?
And I always say, well, no, he's not babysitting. He's with his biological children. They are,
they are also his as well. So I think something needs to change there. I think
the standards that we hold women to account to with children and the standards we hold
men to account to with children are very different. And I think that's a really important thing. And I
think that's a really important thing. And I think that's a really important thing. And I think that's a really
count to with kids should become more of an equilibrium as well and that is a really powerful
statement terry and i and it's very true you know um a father of four four three yeah you're a bull
i'm not sure i'm not sure we thought it through yeah terry but uh my wife beck is just a is a
superstar and and it's it's the you're right to have equity in your relationship is i find it
really unfair that often the burden and the the feedback dad sweep in and get all this glory and
we get all this praise for doing very little really a lot of the time and exactly the role
that she's played in their life has changed their lives remarkably um and you're right we need to
shift that conversation you know big time i try to but i think uh not enough to sort of say you
know the four kids that we've created they are overwhelmingly who they are because of the
influence of of
their mother and um yeah it needs to be celebrated more we um are a bit obsessed with collaboration
uh terry we've got a leadership space and passion about a business we created seven years ago
called a leader and our whole thing is about this world of of collaboration and great things happen
when great people get together and collaborate so my final question to you if you could collaborate
with anyone in the world on anything there's a whole range of interests that are in your space
is there anyone that springs to mind i wish i had prepared
for this question because now i'm like i feel like i'm in a test situation i'm under
i'm under a lot of pressure uh i can't actually think of anyone right now
and i like i'm gonna buy you some buy you some time here terry because it's it's a touch unfair
um to to land that that on you but uh and maybe that's so unfair what do you mean a touch unfair
if i had have had homework i would have done it
yeah that's right i like it's the engineer coming out give me the give me the
parameters and i can make it work yes yes if i don't have the parameters i don't know what it is
that i'm doing i love it uh on any of your passions it could be surfing it could be marathon running it
could be uh writing books could be your family anyone in out there that i'll tell you so we've
had people from elon musk to a childhood friend to um the answers have been vast and and some
people have just said exactly this you know what i don't know i don't know i don't know
and that's just as good as well well look i'm gonna leave that as my answer i like it very
disappointing not at all very disappointing i'm all stressed now i felt really good about
that interview and now i'm walking away kicking myself and i uh i love that yeah you can tell
the authentic you is uh is not going to be anything anyone's ever going to change and why
would you uh as i said in the start it's such an inspiring uh life that you've lived all the way
on you know how you've been able to uh to uh to inspire so many of us and sitting down with you
today it's been incredible uh privilege again i encourage you to check out all of terria's work
the podcast terria pitt is hard work is the title it is brilliant um buy the books have a listen
join the running club is there anything else that we should know about through before we let you go
no that's it it's been a pleasure thanks so much thanks so much i really appreciate it
empowering leaders was presented by me luke darcy produced by matt dwyer with audio production by
darcy thompson
start your leadership journey i encourage you to go to a leader collective.com
take our empowering leaders indicator tool and understand the impact you have
on your environment join us at a leader to learn lead and collaborate listener