On the team side, I've always made sure that you have people from diverse backgrounds, diverse cultures, thinking differently that make up a team.
And I guess I do come from a bit of a sporting background.
So, you know, I'm kind of quite conscious that you don't want to all have strikers in your team or, you know, full forwards or anything like that.
Because if you do, you spend your whole time managing the egos.
So as a leader, I have really enjoyed the creating of diverse teams.
Seeing them thrive and grow has probably been some of the most rewarding parts of my career.
Hello and welcome to another episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
At Alita, we are passionate about inspiring connections and creating a world of collaboration.
Our signature program, Alita Connect, curates groups of five to six leaders from diverse backgrounds in sport, industry, social ventures,
and the arts who come together to learn, to connect, and to collaborate.
Dr. Troy Flanagan, Vice President of Performance for the Milwaukee Bucks.
I've probably had some of the most radical changes out of that leadership group.
The significance of their work and how much it's really about helping others.
It made me think, what else could I be doing?
And I approached our owner and within a few weeks, we'd raised $5 million to try and solve obesity in the underprivileged community.
In Milwaukee.
So that's one spark that that leadership course has caused to contribute and leave the world as a better place.
Umrah Omer, founder of Safari Doctors.
It defines the word creativity for me.
The ability to like see connections where none seem to exist.
And I think that's the magic of Alita.
Definitely not my usual, you know, workshop panels like humanitarian spaces.
But more of an interaction.
More of an intentional, um, um, dissection of, uh, leadership.
The Empowering Leaders Podcast is proudly brought to you by Victoria University.
Where cutting edge sports and exercise science facilities like heat chambers, performance labs, and altitude environments mean VU is ranked seventh in the world for sports science.
VU, uniquely you.
As always, a big thank you to Jason Nicholas and his team at Temper Bedding, a mattress like no other.
If you enjoy listening to the Empowering Leaders Podcast,
be sure to subscribe.
And please, if you have a moment, we would love you to leave a review so we can reach more listeners and empower more leaders.
Tyson Ballard is a multifaceted entrepreneur, legal tech innovator, and creative force with a career spanning technology, music, lifestyle, and business transformation.
As the founder and CEO of Stellar Legal, he is revolutionizing how legal teams operate, implementing AI-driven solutions, contract lifecycle management, and legal operation strategies that drive efficiency.
With executive roles, experience at Consilio, Sky, and Cognita Law, he's advised some of the world's largest organizations on legal transformation, combining deep industry expertise with cutting edge technology.
Tyson's creativity extends far beyond the legal world, though.
A lifelong music curator and DJ, he has been at the heart of underground music scenes, blending house, disco, and electronic beats in clubs and events across the globe.
In music, he met his partners, Joe Vidler, and Jason Nicholas.
In music, he met his partner, Jeff Alarm, which led him to the creation of AMFE Group, All My Friends Everywhere, a global lifestyle collective that fuses music, art, and travel, crafting immersive experiences that connect people across continents.
AMFE is built on the philosophy of extraordinary pleasure, creating one-of-a-kind, mind-blowing events that push the boundaries of imagination and luxury.
AMFE's success led to the creation of a family office investment arm, strategically diversifying into real estate across Europe and Asia.
Tyson 크래mith, Alcymелаshoe, also provides educational and business support for health and disability chois and employment projects, as well as free transportation.
Tyson BC is 450 miles south to theMEUSM towel so 30 ro watchful leg 450 miles left to a commuter car ride basta seeing a
Tyson Kremi, the leader of public understandings at Consilio, said he sees it as an opportunity for him to share stories that can help small businesses, net some oil profits, and
land those gaps.
featured in high-fashion campaigns for Valentino and Louis Vuitton,
as well as making their way onto the cover of Playboy magazine.
As a partner in Wavegliders, a surf brand known for its handcrafted boards,
Tyson helped launch a special edition board series
in collaboration with music artist Jose Gonzalez.
Adding to his portfolio, Tyson also founded, with Anthony Dodds,
the cameraman behind some of Deus Ex Machina's finest images,
House of Sawa, an eco-resort in the Batacarus Indonesian island
that blends surf culture with sustainable luxury.
And across all his ventures, Tyson is driven by innovation, craftsmanship,
teamwork, and community, where he's shaping the future of legal tech,
spinning records in an underground club,
or crafting experiences that redefine lifestyle and culture.
Tyson, that is an extraordinary life.
And I know you love being in the background,
but we're pushing you out in front today.
I really appreciate you joining me.
Yeah, thanks, Luke.
It's good to be here.
I think you're probably the only person that could get me up this early in the morning.
So, yeah, appreciate you having me on.
And, yeah, definitely feel like shriveling after listening to that intro.
But let's go for it.
Well, mate, it's been hard to pin you down.
And from wherever you've been in the Middle East or the Alps
and doing extraordinary things,
and I mean it since I wanted to read your bio in full
because I'm 180 episodes into recordings.
I've never...
I've never seen anyone with that sort of diversity in their life.
It's extraordinary.
But you grew up in this small town called Wollonga
in the McLaren Vale of South Australia.
You went to primary school with our great mutual friend, Matt Wadowitz,
who co-founded Alita and is the champion of Alita, really.
I've got to ask, you look back growing up in a little country town in SA,
what do you think's been the secret for you to this amazing life around the globe?
Yeah, it's an interesting question, actually.
I think, I mean, it was a chance...
I've found life, if I think about it, you know,
growing up with Maddie in Wollonga.
I found out pretty quickly that my football career was limited
when I kicked my, I think, a known goal in my first five minutes on the field.
Yeah, and I think there was something in me,
even just as a little child, to go out and explore the world.
And, you know, I quickly latched on to American culture and films
and, you know, episodes of Seinfeld.
And friends and things like that growing up
that I think always made me want to explore.
And I was pretty lucky enough to have parents that thought the same.
And, you know, we spent a lot of time overseas as a kid,
whether it's in Bali or Europe or Asia.
And, yeah, I think it gave me this curiosity for exploration.
Yeah, that's kind of what led me to leaving as a pretty young kid, I guess,
or teenager.
So those parents sent you to a Steiner school in your secondary education.
Can you explain to people what the Steiner philosophy is?
And do you think that was part of where that curiosity has led you
to do these extraordinary things?
Yeah, 100%.
Actually, I didn't go to school for about a year just leading up to high school,
a bit over, actually.
We were travelling in Europe.
And I think my parents coming back thought that maybe going into a state school system,
you know, probably wasn't the best environment.
And I still remember, like, going to the Waldorf school up in Mount Barker
in that outside Adelaide the first time.
I honestly thought it was like an Ewok village.
You know, I thought I was in Caravans of Courage or something like this.
But it was just such a beautiful school in terms of the nature and the buildings
and the architecture and things like that.
And I think I pretty much, you know, thrived in that environment.
So the classroom.
The rooms are small.
And they have a philosophy where you learn something quite intensely
for a short period of time.
So, you know, it's called a main lesson.
And for the first three hours of a day, typically when your brain's the most awake,
you learn for three weeks something really intensively.
And then you move on to the next thing.
But you dive deep into a topic.
Like, we could be learning Romeo and Juliet for three weeks.
And then you compile a document.
A document of everything that you know about Romeo and Juliet
and submit that to the teacher.
And then in the afternoon, you focus more on arts and sport.
You know, when your digestive system is probably starting to slow down,
maybe your energy levels are lower.
And so maybe your cognitive skills aren't there.
But it was definitely an environment where I thrived.
And I don't think it's for everyone.
You know, I also do see,
and I love my dear alumni a lot,
but I do see a big difference between those who have gone through
from kindergarten through to high school
versus those who have kind of, you know, attended some, you know,
state school or, you know, private school
that is different from a Steiner education.
And I do feel really lucky that, you know,
I did participate in the high school arena.
But I think I would have been a different person
if I was there.
I want to dive into that.
You're a father of two yourself.
And we see parents around the world
are often obsessed with the marks.
In Australia, it's your ATAR and the score that you get.
But I think when I've got older,
some of the most creative people and happy people,
one of my closest friends I've had on the podcast,
Craig Ellis School, just wasn't for him,
but he's got this brilliant creative brain
that takes him into so many,
reminds me a lot of you actually,
so many creative spaces.
So what,
what do you think as a parent,
what's your solution to education?
How do we get it right?
Yeah, that's another good question too.
I actually, my little ones,
not little ones so much anymore.
They're changing schools next year
and they've been at a Swedish school here in Portugal.
And now they're going into a borderline,
I would say kind of private Cambridge education,
but maybe with a slight Steiner twist to it.
So I've been,
I've been delving a bit deeper into the curriculum
and things like that.
And I think probably in the world that I live in,
which is quite an AI led environment,
I'm quite worried about setting up our kids for future success.
You know,
like, you know,
five years ago it was like everyone should learn how to code,
but by the time that these guys are finishing school,
there will be no coding.
And, but,
but what I am kind of deeply worried about is that the
curriculum,
you know,
hasn't really changed since,
incremental change really since,
you know,
the twenties or thirties and the idea of them,
sitting in a four by four you know,
concrete box for six or seven hours of the day and,
you know,
write it on a blackboard and copy it into your book.
And now you learn.
I think it's obviously progressed since those days.
And now it's a lot more,
you know,
interactive learning.
The kids are learning at their own pace and things like that.
But I guess my fear is that it hasn't changed as quick
as probably the outside world has,
but I think you need to supplement that with the parenting,
right.
Which is probably,
you know,
teaching them,
critical thinking and adaptability and exposing them to,
to kind of different cultures and,
and,
and different things and,
and travel does that.
And,
and as you know,
we spend a lot of time on the road,
but yeah,
like it does worry me.
And,
and I,
and I wonder if,
if the whole education system at some point,
maybe it needs a little,
it's its own doge system where,
you know,
it goes in and,
and gets shaken up and kind of,
you know,
with a blank sheet of paper.
What do you think you've got?
You got two,
two empty nesters and,
and,
and I,
I know our kids have spent time with yours.
Is it like the beautiful kids?
Like,
you know,
what was your kid a success?
Yeah,
it's a good,
it's a great return question,
Tyson.
And it's something that Beck and I thought about deeply.
And I,
I,
you know,
looked at the Steiner and the alternative to me,
the one thing in the world that needs disruption is education.
Almost everything else has been disrupted.
And,
and with you,
sometimes there's a sadness when I look at kids and you open the textbook
and you're right.
It hasn't changed.
The right learning still there.
And,
and you know,
there's a,
the number one Ted talk in the world is about schools,
killing creativity.
And I think as parents,
you get to see little parts of that creativity die in your kids.
And I think probably exactly what you said is how do you keep that alive in
your own home?
How do you give them experiences?
How do you potentially travel with them or be around them enough that you can
do that?
Because there's also the stability of supporting your kids in their passions.
If they,
as a pretty sporting focused.
And so,
yeah,
I love brains like yours that didn't have the necessarily the regular
education.
I can see the genius in,
in,
in something like yours,
which is,
you know,
there's so many questions to jump off.
I want to come back to AI because I'm fascinated in your thoughts on AI,
but,
but I look at you and I know you had this,
this brilliant mass brain.
You still have got a brilliant mass brain and a brilliant music brain.
Very few people on the planet,
I think get them working at the same time.
Did you always feel like that was a bit of your superpower that you had these
two really different ways of thinking?
Yeah.
Like actually I think mathematics is quite similar to,
there is a lot of mathematics in music.
And I mean,
I come from a like percussion and drum background.
I,
I have always,
I have always loved this combination of I kind of think about it and I don't
know if it's right or not,
but the,
the right brain and the left brain and,
and kind of,
you know,
challenging both to kind of,
operate in equal,
in equal measure.
And yeah,
like I've,
I've just always enjoyed maths in,
in,
in that the you're solving a problem essentially.
And,
and it's got an answer and I love getting to the answer.
It's,
it's like a,
a choose your own adventure.
And,
and obviously I went kind of pretty deep into statistics,
but,
and then,
you know,
applying that to,
to,
to rhythms you know,
on,
on the musical side and,
and as a drummer,
you know,
you,
you learn a lot about time signatures and things like that.
And it is quite mathematical.
Obviously it's physical because you've got lots of things going at,
at,
at one time.
And I,
and I've always just somehow just loved that challenge.
You know,
my dad was a drummer,
my grandpa was a drummer.
So,
and now my kids are learning drums,
which is hilarious.
It's,
it's a very antisocial instrument to learn in the house.
I'll tell you that.
But I think it's a good foundation of kind of maybe applying some of the
mathematics that you learn about other in school,
or if you do have a curiosity to kind of,
you know,
take it further and you know,
still have a something where you can collaborate with others in,
in things like a band.
Tyson,
you've done so many interesting things and I didn't do it justice at all in,
in the intro,
but all my friends every year,
I'm so curious about how you landed on that.
Can you share a bit about some of the events that you hold and some of the
creativity that,
that world is,
is opened up?
Yeah,
it's such a beautiful project.
You know,
it's with two of my dearest friends and,
and actually the sparked off by,
by chef,
the chef and I actually had an electronic band.
We played together about 15 years ago and for one hot summer we toured the world.
I think our first gig was after rehearsing in the kitchen was about to 15,000 people.
And so yeah.
And but since then we've always remained great friends and you know,
he always dreamt big.
So chef was always the guy that,
you know,
if he would always have time for you and if he had,
if he had a hundred bucks,
the hundred bucks was for everybody.
And so,
you know,
he,
he was there for everybody no matter what and and he was very lucky enough just before COVID to meet a very high net individual that basically said you know can you help me organize a party for Halloween and I think in our true fashion you know like a party to us means you know spend I don't know like a thousand bucks get all our mates together and have a great weekend where this had quite a much bigger impact on my life.
So yeah I think that was a really good thing.
And it was a really good thing.
Yeah.
And I think chef just took it in his stride and you know he ended up renting a castle outside England.
I had like I think kind of imagine eyes wide shut meets you know an electronic grave and you can use your imagination to kind of see where it went.
But essentially that sparked AMFE.
Yeah.
And it kind of snowballed from there.
We're now like nearly six years on.
We have around a hundred and fifty people there.
And so it was a really good thing.
I mean,
you know,
it's a really good thing.
You know,
we're a family of people and we've had a lot of fun.
And I think chef was really,
you know,
he was a great guy.
He was a great guy.
And essentially that sparked AMFE.
Yeah.
And it kind of snowballed from there.
We're now like nearly six years on.
We have around about a hundred and fifty staff.
You know,
we've done some pretty incredible events.
So maybe about a year and a half,
two years ago,
they broke the world record for the longest private flight whilst having a party in the air.
So we,
I think it was a 767 that we,
we customized um so we took all the all the seats out um and build a dj booth and nightclub inside
the inside the jet and flew from uh bangkok thailand to bogota um columbia and um unbeknownst
to us at the halfway through it at that kind of middle point the the pilot came on and said um
look this is my my final private flight of my career so i wanted to go for the record so we've
we've passed the no return zone so uh here we go and you can imagine the the the the crowd erupting
in in the jet you know like uh to hearing that like whilst uh listening to some of the best djs
in the world and yeah thankfully they landed uh you know in bogota safely and then just recently
we we we organized an event for about 25 000 people in in the pyramids in outside in cairo
coincided on my birthday which was a really nice event um but yeah i think it was the first
event as close as to the pyramids since shakira in 2006 or something like that so you can imagine
all the all the bureaucracy and all the all the uh workarounds we had to get to get there but
you know we're i guess we're behind some of you know some of the biggest events and probably some
of the more creative events we don't tend to do the you know the run of the mill
find a field and and stick up a stage and and uh and have an event we always look to challenge
right now we're we're looking to have the first party in space um and so yeah we're having having
some interesting conversations i think we're competing against lady gaga at the moment to
try and get there but uh yeah let's see how we go it's never boring having a conversation with you
it goes off in a direction i love it i mean who who's thinking that that's even possible
and you know you can imagine the the fun and that's what it seems like it's just fun being
around you i look at the to me the definition of the entrepreneurial spirit i'm looking at it on
the screen i'm looking at in portugal today what do you think about when you get go down that path
and have you got advice for others that want to maybe take on the same path as you it's been an
interesting journey and i don't think you ever really set out to maybe deliberately be an
entrepreneur or you know wonder about my younger self what what advice i would give to my younger
self kind of and i guess that kind of is similar question and you know i think everything that i've
done has kind of led me to to where i've got to now and and and i think my advice is you know i've
listened to a bunch of your podcasts as well where you know like you've got a lot of guys that come on
that you know find one thing that they're great at you know have the drive and discipline to kind
of focus on that um and and i think that's a really good question and i think that's a really good
and and do amazing things and you know world champions and things like that and and that
that's that's amazing and you know even in my leader group there was you know guys like amit
and troy who were and and vanessa as well who were just like you know amazing um human beings
but um i think probably mine has been a little bit different it hasn't been a you know a single
trajectory and and i guess the advice is that's okay too you can still have um success
you know success can maybe be defined in a different way um for you it doesn't need to be
gold medals or you know a single career or i think like that and and i kind of have enjoyed the
process of of being curious about many things um maybe i'm a master of none i'm not sure but um
but either which way i've had a lot of fun along the way and um and you know in in terms of success
happy family um you know you know i've had a lot of fun along the way and um and you know
living a wonderful colorful life like i i think i've definitely have had it and and i think
probably maybe the other just the other piece of advice is like i felt like every step of the way
i've been where i'm meant to be um you know i you know it hasn't always been a bed of roses
um you know like i've i've taken lessons that i've learned along the way that now you know i
think there's kind of that that theory of 10 000 hours maybe i've spent you know 50 000 hours on
on six or seven hours and i've had a lot of fun along the way and i think that's kind of the
thing i've had a lot of fun along the way and i think that's kind of the thing
and things so i i don't know if i subscribe to kind of you know you really need that 10 000
hours to to be successful at one thing curiosity and drive maybe yeah it's interesting malcolm
gladwell was the author of the the 10 000 hour rule and i think he's actually gone back and
revisited that and said you know what i don't actually agree with my own thinking uh if i
look back 10 years later it's uh there's a great book called range which talks about exactly you
so the people that sample a range of different things end up building a skill set in in a
in a whole heap of different areas and you did mention a leader and we've been so privileged
tyson to have you as a great creative thinker in that world and you mentioned some of your group
we love the idea of bringing together uh people from different backgrounds in this sort of learning
and sharing environment um can you explain what the elita connect group's been like for you
oh mate like i remember about was it five or six years ago when we sat at your pub in in melbourne
and and talked about this idea about bringing some of the
the best leaders in the world together and i think that was kind of a pivotal moment
where i was just like this is just such a golden idea and just to see that you guys um you know
deliver on that is just been amazing and and i guess as a mate of maddie i've just been so
so proud of everything you guys have done at elita in terms of the group that i had like
from the very first session with troy amit
and hugh was there as well and and vanessa um it was it was really really interesting because i
think um you know very quickly you know we did our obligatory introductions you know rattled off
all the achievements that we've had in life and i think it was you that just started immediately
talking about his kids and then it just broke down the the whole sessions from then onwards
that set a tone i guess that that made us all a lot more vulnerable and i think that's what i'm
to to talk about some of the challenges and like proper challenges that we're having in in in work
and life um and for me it was i mean it was definitely life-changing you know seeing troy
and and vanessa kind of having these pivotal moments in their career and and also seeing
the things that amit delivered at the bulldogs last year in terms of the you know the new facility and
whilst also same as you delivering a renovation on his house which uh you know we've had a lot of
which is double whammy yeah i i really felt like so privileged to be involved um quite often
you know a little bit of imposter syndrome um thinking about some of the achievements that
these guys have had and and and the world that they're living in um but yeah it was life-changing
i mean i i during that month that was the moment that you know like really cemented me to kind of
you know jump off and and start stellar um you know
with the with the guidance and support of those guys and i'm really proud to say that you know
that i count them as dear friends and you know there's a lot of banter on the whatsapp group
whether it's you know try it at the box in terms of you know winning or losing and you know i meet
um having some of the challenges uh you know not making it to the to the grand final last year
and things like that and yeah it's it's just been such a wonderful experience
and tyce i remember that beer very well and and it's interesting when you've got an idea and matt
is the absolute creator behind it and i've been lucky enough to be associated with your great
friend and my great friend he's a he's a one-of-a-kind person and um i haven't met too
many like him to be honest with you and it's based on his uh he's great thinking but i love sitting
down with you because you just tell you're a great ideas person and all you saw is possibility
yeah and you ask some awesome questions it's interesting it's quite often you know
when you share an idea with people i reckon 90 of people go the other way and tell you why it's a
stupid idea and tell you why you shouldn't do it and tell you how hard it's going to be and how
hard a path it is so it's uh it's a rare thing someone like you and it's why it's a great story
to share there's a lot of people that are probably going down a university path they've got no idea
what they want to do their parents are wanting them to do something safe for or secure but i
think you're a great living example to me of of someone who just followed their passion just takes
it all away and loves you and and maybe even be left for some reason i don't know what exactly
do others feel uh it would be a moment to concede but instead i i think it's a well-resinterpreted
way of telling people that you know it's not how they go to campus you could literally walk
under someone's roof and say hey i'm going to be driving kind of like i'm dancing you know
like you know what like every group i've served too many yes or no people will want to take up
that call
an NG
uh
can do today there's no doubt that this is a you know a proper industrial revolution moment in in
history in terms of where we are with ai and there's no doubt that probably for the first
time in humanity especially given the leap from machine learning to generative um you know when
chat gpt was introduced and and kind of you know everyone jumped on that for the first time there's
probably a lot of brilliant minds focused on um making it better and finding use cases and
and um obviously probably looking to get rich in at the same time no doubt it's going to have an
impact on on the workforce i probably spend at least 30 hours a week talking about ai to clients
and i don't go into one phone call where um you know with a with a potential client or an existing
client where ai is not mentioned now if i cast my time back to two three years ago it wasn't like
that it was more
around data and you know some of the kind of like maybe some more of the kind of process
orientated challenges but yeah i think across every single realm um from sport to creative
to to business to to finance to um to health to to education i think there's just a wonderful
opportunity to enrich the lives if we um use it in the right way but then also it's scary
it's it's a bit of a um you know out of control uh bucking bronco that um you know if we don't
you know approach it in the right way could be potentially harmful towards uh you know
towards humans and so yeah i think we need to approach it with um you know some care and some
thought and and thinking about you know how we use it to enrich the lives um you know i feel like
you know having this this untapped you know limitless knowledge is a very powerful tool um
and we just need to make sure that we apply it in the right way but i am incredibly excited about it
obviously i've built a business around it you know i i love right now being able to find kind
of you know today what are the practical applications of it and especially in in the
field of work that i've kind of you know that i've focused on you know i've focused on the
are you playing around with it in in your daily life are there things that you now do that
chat gbt is is the obvious uh place to go or is there other sort of micro things that you're
already saying that are that are working for it yeah like so i mean stellar the company we
founded a couple of months ago um we're partners with a with a bunch of um kind of leading
ai tools for for legal they're focused predominantly around um you know i guess
you know making the practice of law uh more efficient uh whether it's contracts or knowledge
or research or or some of the kind of the more the process and kind of um you know like uh
workflow orientated um tasks most of the organizations when you when you're talking
about law it's quite a private um environment obviously you're dealing with um privileged and
and um highly confidential information that a lot of the people that are involved in the
world don't tend to go towards chat gbt however i would um hazard a bet that nearly all of them
are going it's chat gbt and in terms of kind of their their own um you know their own environment
and and i guess like i've always been fascinated that law has been a bit of the last
the last bastion of uh adoption for technology you know the mystification of what lawyers do
and i'm sure you've dealt with a few in your day um you know it's it's quite it's
quite smoke and mirrors in fact you know if you think about it and being able to kind of
enrich that environment with ai is uh something that is you know is incredibly challenging but
also incredibly rewarding if you think about like uh the happiness levels of of lawyers
it's an environment that is probably one of the most unhappy um work uh mental states um
and you know if we can do something that makes
the
practice of law more happy um then um and more efficient um then then and i feel like we've done
our job we all are born different as we grow the experiences we have developed into outlooks
uniquely our own charting our life's course no one sees an idea opinion or opportunity like you
and no one sees you like value victoria university uniquely you
hi my name's min i do a bachelor of social work i got this tattoo done for my 20th birthday present
because i was born as a twin but she passed away because my mom had ovarian cancer during pregnancy
so my name's miri indy which means rainbow and it means the bridge between um for our ancestors to
reach like their afterlife and i'm a member of a group called the rainbow and i'm a member of the
which is what my sister was called which is the water putty which is the milky way
and that's where they go as like the stars and they live they live there
the thing is very supportive it doesn't matter if you're an indigenous student
wouldn't i bother to make sure that you're very well taken care of
at alita our signature program alita connect is something we're really passionate and proud of
we bring together groups of five to six people around the globe from diverse backgrounds sport
industry social venture and the arts we come together to learn and we're very proud of that
to connect and to collaborate vanessa ford chief operating officer at kukua the alita connect
experience for me has been transformational i met people that i would never have met from
totally different spheres it's very basic it's all about relationships it's all about how we
communicate and what the alita connect group does that is so powerful is when you bring two people
from two totally different worlds together there's no ego it just
leaves room for for the real you and i think that's what alita gave me was bringing back the
real me and and really connecting to my own leadership style loving uh the opportunity to
sit down with people like you and delve into their thinking and we've got these uh patterns that
we've seen across uh the work we do at alita and and starting with self um leadership um what what's
the way you fill your cup up in the busy life that you've got is there a routine or something
you go through and how do you fill your cup up and how do you fill your cup up and how do you
to make sure you're feeling your best in terms of routines well i've got my my cup of um uh coffee
right here mate um so yeah i i tend to start my day with a good cup of coffee um i'm i wouldn't
say i'm the earliest riser in the house like typically the kids are up before me because i'm
a lot on the road um and it's a lot of late nights and early flights i really rely heavily on a lot
of vitamins so i'm a little bit more of a go-do to make sure i'm feeling my best in terms of routines
so you know amiga i take a lot of mushroom paul stemmet um immunity um tablets um and and pine
bark extract and and you know i think i probably have a regime around about 60 vitamins that i take
every morning well and uh and a good cup of coffee um and uh yeah that tends to keep me energetic
i am quite conscious also this is something we chatted about at alita around balancing energy
levels and and not you know i don't know i don't know i don't know i don't know i don't know i don't
know i don't know i don't know i don't know i don't know i don't know i'm not expanding all of my energy
um in the in the work life um and ensuring that you know i'm i'm there and and still energetic at
the end of the day when the kids finish school or you know when they're playing a bunch of tennis
at the moment so you know even after that and and and same for once the kids are in bed can't say
i always do the the best job at that one that uh you know i definitely kind of it's something i
think about and i'm not conscious about and i think probably recognizing those moments and
where you really need high energy, whether through my calendar, like, you know, there's probably about five or six meetings that, you know, I really need to nail in a week that the rest, you know, I can probably kind of operate on, you know, 70, 80% energy levels. And just, I guess the conscious, you know, maintaining of those energy levels is something that I kind of focus on.
Fascinating way. I'm not surprised you think about it differently. I haven't heard anyone answer that around. You can maybe have an idea of what you need and there's six key things for the week that you want to be a hundred percent on and saving energy for your kids is a fascinating way to think about it. And yeah, I haven't heard anyone answer in that way before, but it makes sense when I think about exactly how you're living.
Is there one thing that you've always done as a leader that you never would change in any of the,
disciplines you've been involved in?
First of all, on the team side, I've always made sure that, um, you have people from diverse backgrounds, diverse cultures, um, thinking differently that, you know, that, that make up a team. And I guess I, I, I do come from a bit of a sporting background. So, you know, I'm kind of quite conscious that you don't want to all have strikers in your team or, you know, full forwards or anything like that. Um, cause if you do, you spend your whole time managing the egos.
So as a leader, um, I have really enjoyed the creating of diverse teams, you know, um, and, um, I think that is something that I've, I've really enjoyed. And, and I think seeing them thrive and grow is probably been some of the most rewarding, um, parts of, of my career. Um, and, um, yeah. And I think probably the other one is to, to see them thrive and grow, you really need to have great leadership.
Um, and you need to empower them. Um, I think you need to have honest conversations, um, in terms of their performance and, you know, where they can improve, but that should be done in a constructive way. But, you know, a lot of these things you tend to forget about, um, you know, once you're kind of busy running a business and you've got all the pressures of, of performance. Um, so yeah, so I would say, yeah, listening skills, um, diverse teams and, uh, empowering them.
Um, to kind of, you know, be the best that they can be.
Have you got a story of a visionary leader that's inspired you in the past and you felt compelled to, to follow their vision in any of the things you've done?
Yeah, I've been really lucky enough to, to work for many, um, or work alongside many and, and, and seen many. If I, if I was to say one, probably a pivotal one is a guy called John Ramage. I think he even played a couple of games for Carlton back in the day.
Okay.
But, um, really early.
Early on in my career, I, I worked at Westpac, um, in, and as a collections, uh, team leader, which was really, really fascinating. And, um, and, and our, and our boss of, of, uh, Westpac was this guy called John Ramage. Um, he's a footy coach, but he, he really installed in me, know your numbers. So we used to have these meetings and, uh, if you've ever worked in a call center, you know, it's a, it's a pretty surreal experience.
But, you know, you've got to pick up the phone within 30 seconds. No one really calls you if they're happy. So usually they're, um, pretty unhappy and either they don't want to speak to you or things like that. And we were collecting, you know, credit card debt, mortgage debt and things like that. So it wasn't really the most, um, happy environment to, to deal with. But what it made it really, you know, exhilarating and, and to me was that, that the numbers side of things. So we used to have these weekly meetings.
Okay.
You would be absolutely, um, you know, roasted. And, and I think, you know, going into those meetings and, and, you know, spending the time to kind of really dig into the numbers of the performance of your team was quite, quite an interesting one. And that's probably something that I kind of took with me. And, and he just installed a bit of a discipline that, you know, it, it actually wasn't okay to be mediocre. Um, and I think when you're, when you're a youngster, those kinds of things are quite pivotal.
Just having that, you know, know your numbers.
You know, he, he was quite big on, on, on the grammar side as well. So if you ever came to a presentation that didn't, you know, wasn't polished and didn't have a full stop or, you know, the, the formatting was, was all wrong. You know, he was quite strict, but it worked for me because I think I'd probably come out of this Steiner environment. Right. Which was, I don't, I can't even remember anything about getting taught about grammar or anything like that. But so, yeah. And, and for me, that was really early on where, you know, I, I kind of, you know, I, I kind of, you know, I, I kind of, I, I kind of, you know, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I
saw the power of leadership and I think there was a bunch of leaders that came out of that
business that have gone on to do great things. I'm pretty sure the next CEO of Westpac is going
to come from that group. It's fascinating, isn't it? I love that impact, isn't it, of someone that
has obviously stayed in your mind all these years and had an impact and it's the little
bits of leadership that stand out. You strike me as inherently curious in everything you do.
Do you actually carve out time in your day to be curious and can I ask how do you
implement that into the things that you do? I am incredibly curious. I probably read about
five or six books a week, mainly on Audible, but I do spend a lot of time on planes.
So my time to be curious on the book side is on planes and that is a time where
quite often internet doesn't work so people can't get in contact with you
and so it is a bit of a time for yourself and so I do maximize that. I do carve out time for
myself as well, whether it's in the morning, taking the dog for a walk. I kind of dive deep
into topics and I've rediscovered my love for tennis. So I'm spending about two hours a day
playing tennis, which is something...
You really need to be present for and I'm really enjoying having something that isn't digital
where I can kind of focus on, be present. It's physical, it's cognitive, it's incredibly
frustrating, but then also incredibly rewarding. And I've been really enjoying kind of the journey
of even as a much more senior individual, trying to kind of get better at something.
But yeah, I definitely kind of carve time out of my day every single day.
To do something that is new, essentially.
I've got to get a book recommendation from someone who's consuming the amount of books you are on an
annual basis. So what's the one, if you're going to recommend one to our audience, what should we
read?
I've just finished reading two really amazing books. I can't remember the author, but one was
called Chasing the Scream, which is about the history of the war on drugs. And it's told,
told in a story format. And it's, it's just fascinating what, what governments have done
and how it started. And, and, you know, like experiments like, like Portugal, for example,
that decriminalized everything, you know, nearly 30 years ago now. And then, you know, from,
you know, some of the terrible, you know, things that are happening in Canada and the US in terms
of drug addiction, it's like that. That was a truly fascinating book.
And then the other one I would say is Prisoners of Geography, which is more of a geopolitical book
around, and it kind of goes back, you know, up to a thousand years and kind of delves into the,
I guess, the history of power and geography. And, you know, for example, how did a tiny little
island, you know, off the coast of Europe become such a powerful country? And, you know, why hasn't
Africa kind of, you know, capitalized on, on drugs?
Being, you know, so minerally rich and, and things like that. So I found that fascinating as well.
You've sparked my curiosity on both of those. We're a bit obsessed with collaboration. Is there,
it seems like you've got plenty of great collaboration in their life. Is there one
that jumps out at you? Yeah. I mean, probably AMFE is just a really exciting collaboration.
If you were to spend time with the three of us, maybe as a fly on the wall,
you'd be like,
what are these guys talking about? You know, like you can not do that, but somehow we always
make it happen. We've done some just things where, you know, like, you know, I, even I didn't think
it was possible. And, and I think, you know, thriving off that energy that, you know, that,
I guess that lifts you up to unlock some of that human potential. And I can, I think you can only
get that through, you know, bouncing off ideas and,
and helping each other step on, you know, to get to the next level. Yeah. So I would say,
you know, the collaboration on, on AMFE is a big one. Right now we're, we, we're trying to
reinvent the, the Nile cruise. So after, after Egypt, we, you know, we spent some time on the
Nile and we were like, you know, I think this Nile cruise situation could be done a hell of a lot
better. So we're exploring a project.
Around, you know, taking the Nile cruises to the next level, which is really exciting,
really challenging and a long way from home, but, you know, spending time collaborating
with locals on that one and, and, you know, thinking about what is the art of the possible
there. I'm, I'm really looking forward to kind of redefining, you know, luxury and experience
on the Nile, which is just such a magical and historical place.
That sounds like it.
A trip to, to find your way onto, I mean, you've got 150 staff in, in AMFE. You've had
legal businesses all around the world and, and, and home base in South Africa.
How do you go about your communication when you're running so many different spaces? Have you got a
mantra that you think about with communication? I think when, when you're living in, in an
environment where nearly everyone is remote, you need to find ways that bring that personal,
just real local, personal kind of touch or personal interaction or water cooler conversations
into your daily life.
And so I think in the beginning of all of this, I tried to have a lot of more, just meetings
were, were more of social occasion and that didn't really work. So, so now actually I
spend, for nearly every meeting, you know, 10 to 15 minutes just, shooting the breeze
And I think if you live in this environment where, you know, pretty much my life is, if I'm not playing tennis or surfing, it's 30-minute Zoom conversations or Teams conversations, you know, back to back.
And so, yeah, so I've had to find a way to find that personal connection with my team that you probably find at the local pub afterwards that you can't get when they're sitting in Buenos Aires or, you know, or Bogota.
And so, yeah, so finding that, you know, personal digital connection has been really important.
I mean, carving out time in the meetings to ask about family.
Or a football game or, you know, the wedding or the holiday or something like that has been really important.
And then, obviously, WhatsApp because I've got so many things on the go.
There's quite, you know, especially for my business partners, you know, there's time for banter, but then there's also time for quick decisions and quick conversations.
So, I found, you know, the phone is an incredibly useful tool that allows you to kind of work from anywhere.
But you just couldn't do, you know, 10 years ago or something like that, you know.
Then maybe probably the final one is you really just have to make time to go visit and spend time with these people in one place.
So, for example, on the Stella side, you know, we've just come from, you know, a week in Sarasota, Florida, where we all chased alligators around a golf course and found out that your golf ball goes anywhere near the water.
You should not go get that golf ball.
So, yeah, like just like, you know, finding those times where you can get together and do things socially is really important too.
And even if you can't do that every day, finding a couple of times a year that you can kind of all get together.
Who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Who has been the greatest leader in my life?
I mean, I touched on John Ramage earlier on, and I probably think the other one would be a lady called Claire O'Brien.
She's now the CEO of Deutsche Bank for the legal.
And we worked together at the world's biggest law firm, Clifford Chance.
And basically they took a chance on me.
You know, I was a sailor at the time.
And they were like, Tice, we really like you.
We don't really know what you do, but we really want you to come and just try and shift the needle here at this law firm.
And without the support of her and her girlfriend.
And without the guidance and the time that she spent to kind of introduce me to the world of legal, I wouldn't be where I am today.
That's for sure.
She is a force of nature.
Quite often people say, if you want to storm the hill, you call Claire O'Brien in our industry.
And she's someone that is also very much in the background.
She doesn't like being in the limelight.
She doesn't like going to conferences and things like that.
Quite often she's too busy.
And.
She's also from Glasgow.
And so half the time you can't understand anything she's saying, but it's just, she's such a pleasure to work for.
And if, and she pushes you, like, I don't think anyone has ever pushed me in a leadership role.
I still remember her interview where I was, I was on cause I was a sailor and based at Monaco.
And I remember like sitting on the, on the, on the bow of the boat and saying for like the fourth
time.
In a row, like, look, I'm really sorry, but I can't, could you ask that question again?
Because I don't understand what you asked and, um, but yeah, thankfully after a bunch of years now, I I'm pretty good at picking that
Glaswegian that sends them understanding what they're saying.
Um, but it still does involve, um, some moments of lip reading.
What a champion.
I love, I love asking that question because there are these great heroes that change people's lives out there and clearly that, you know, someone that's
a forefront of, of mine for you.
We are in the leader.
Well, we, we love what collaboration does and seeing, you know, people come together like you and meet Baines and Hugh van Kylenburg and Vanessa forward.
Incredible person, a great friend of yours.
And Dr.
Troy Flanagan is, is one example of collaboration, but you've got so much variety of interests from, from, um, music to, to the legal world.
Is there been somebody thought, wow, that's the person I'd love to collaborate with.
Is there a name that jumps to mind?
Oh,
who would I like to collaborate with?
Uh, I, um, I'm quite lucky enough to spend some time with, um, some guys that are in the, in the film industry.
And, um, I think with the music world, um, uh, you can't see it behind me, but I've, I've been collecting vinyl records since I was a tiny kid.
And, um, I've been fascinated by soundtracks.
Um, I love making music that, uh, that is cinematic and, and story.
Yeah.
And I've been obsessed for quite a long time about film.
So I think if you ask me who I would love to collaborate with, it'd probably someone like Quentin Tarantino or, you know, the guys that are kind of just making like super cool films.
And I would love to do a soundtrack for, for a film.
You know, if I was to live my life over, like, uh, you know, I'd love to kind of delve into that topic, um, and, and have the opportunity to, to, to do that.
Yeah.
It's a, it's another extraordinary answer.
And I'm not surprised by, uh, you know, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the,
by the depth of things that interest you, mate.
As I said, this could take another 10 hours
and you wouldn't even scratch the surface
of what is going on in your mind and your world.
It's been a great pleasure to get to know you.
We both share a great mutual mate
and I've enjoyed the times we've got to catch up
and fascinated by the next chapter.
Stella, you'd like to buy shares in Tyson Ballard
and anything he says, just get on board
would be my final bit of advice.
But thanks for getting up early in the morning, mate,
to do this.
I know you're much happier behind the curtain,
but we appreciate you sharing your story today.
Thanks, mate.
It's been great.
Yeah, I really, really appreciate the time, Luke,
and hopefully we can catch up soon.
I'll be on the next plane to Portugal, mate.
Get me to one of those parties AMFE style anytime soon.
Thanks, mate.
It's been awesome.
Excellent.
Take care.