No doubt in my mind, you're going to be inspired by Umrah Omar, the founder of Safari Doctors
and one of the great humanitarians on the planet.
Learned so much from this conversation in so many places that I think you're going to
be really inspired by.
She talks about trusting in the DNA of what makes you and how her intolerance for injustice
has driven her success.
She feels as though she's built her life in reverse, helping others and making a difference
rather than waiting to retirement.
She was raised by her grandmother and she dreamed from the youngest possible age of
being a bridge between worlds, which she's done to great success.
She speaks of her father as the biggest feminist she knows and how the male influence in her
life has broken all stereotypes.
And she truly believes that humans are powerful and capable of so much.
Umrah Omar is an inspiration.
I'm sure you're going to enjoy this conversation.
We are incredibly privileged and lucky to collaborate with Umrah on our Alita Connect
program.
Umrah has a really fascinating diversity.
And that's what we do in this space.
We curate leaders from different backgrounds.
You don't have to be the founder of Safari Doctors to be part of it.
Head to alitacollective.com, book a discovery call.
We'd love to chat to you about it today.
Huge thanks as always to Jason Nicholas, his team from Temper Bedding.
We know leaders are really passionate about what sleep means in their routine.
A Temper mattress is NASA approved.
It's the world's best in bedding.
Check out Temper today.
Umrah's contribution to community and transforming the lives of others.
Is a remarkable story.
Born on the remote Pate Island, just off the northern coast of Kenya, she grew up in Nairobi
and pursued higher education in the United States.
Umrah earned a bachelor's degree in neuroscience and psychology, and then a master's degree
in social justice and intercultural relations from the world leading institute in Vermont.
Her early career took her to Washington, D.C., but a strong sense of duty drew her back to
Kenya.
In 2015, during a visit to her hometown, Umrah recognized the diversity and the diversity
and the entire need for health care in her community and founded Safari Doctors.
Safari Doctors operates mobile clinics across Kenya, reaching over 1,000 patients a month
through boats, motorcycles, and on foot.
Umrah's incredible work has seen her named as the UN Person of the Year in Kenya and
received the Africa Leaders for Change Award.
She was recognized by the World Economic Forum as a young global leader, a CNN top 10 hero,
and featured in Business Daily's Top 40 Under 40 Women.
A mother of two who splits her time.
Between Portugal and Kenya, Umrah, it's a great pleasure to meet you.
I've heard an incredible amount about you, and congratulations on the difference that
you're making.
Thank you, Luke, and I've heard so much about you and your football geniusness, so a mutual
feeling.
That's high praise.
I'm very happy to keep it there and not show you any videos that might underwhelm you,
but I understand Safari Doctors began with you wanting to make a difference in people's
well-being.
Can you tell us about that story?
Your passion for making a difference?
I think the Safari Doctors in Lamu, Kenya found me, I guess.
It combined all my passion.
It was home, it was healthcare, it was travel as well, and making a difference in that tiny
way.
So the idea was just to mobilize something on a monthly basis, support a nurse who travels
around five villages and gets access on the ground to the people.
Because one of the things that is really unfortunate for us women and for our children
is that health is a part of our daily existence versus waiting to get sick.
So if you're talking of immunizations or you're accessing family planning and so forth, it's
more of a way of life.
So how do you get it to the doorsteps is what Safari Doctors was about.
So it started off as a pet project of just making a tiny difference at home and then
took a life of its own.
And I love these words that are attributed to you, Omra.
Consistency, persistence, and dedication are what watered this seed of purpose into a tree.
And before you know it, you are part of a forest of change.
Can you explain why that means so much to you?
It means so much to me because it's a reflection of when we look at a seed.
If you look at a seed, it's like this, just this tiny little something.
And then what people come to see is when they're eating.
And when you're like, you know, you have a tree or a bush and it's like, oh my God, this
is amazing.
But you're like, actually, it started as a seed.
And what is the seed that defines us?
And not being overwhelmed by thinking of, okay, we have to become this huge mango tree
or this huge bush, but just being focused on nurturing that small seed.
And then so many things come together, whether it's the weather coming together, it's the
soil.
So that's how we are as humans and in the work that we do.
And for me, that's what really helps.
We do not get too overwhelmed about what we're doing.
It's like, do your part, Umrah, and then the rest will take care of itself.
And that's what happened with Safari Doctors.
That's what's happening.
That's what happens with raising kids.
You don't get a manual told, okay, this is how your adult would look like.
Therefore, do this today, this tomorrow.
So that's the philosophy around that consistency.
It's because you have to pace yourself, knowing that what you're a part of is much bigger
than yourself.
So just do your part.
And you mentioned.
Raising kids and you're a mother of two.
And do you take that same approach too, that you're really just in every day you can do
small things and hopefully at the end that you've made the contribution you want to your
own family?
It's because you know, you trust in that DNA, what makes you up and you do what you can
because or else it's kind of like moving countries.
Someone's like, you know, so what's your plan?
What are you, you know, in five years, two years?
I know there's something bigger that this is a journey of.
And sometimes you can.
You find what you're, where you're headed.
Sometimes you just open trusting that the step that you're taking in your leadership
journey, in your parenthood journey, in your workspaces, that it being open to what's unfolding
and trusting that you're, you're wired to go through that.
When they say helping others may be the secret to living a life that's not only happier,
but also healthier, wealthier, more productive and meaningful.
Your life I look at as this great life of contribution.
To others.
Is that how it's felt to you?
I felt very blessed.
Look, very, very blessed in terms of almost living my life in, in reverse.
You know how you work, build your career, retire, and then make a difference.
And then you give back or you do something, a tragedy happens.
And then that drives you to, you know, to make, make that impact.
So for me, after a year and a half of employment,
I was blessed.
And that I had that set up, whether it was a family or being back home or being able
to have a purpose, find me earlier on in life and being able to commit to that, to make
my work, work, be around that, to raise a family around that, to build a team around
that.
And then now I'm like, oh, no, that's kind of what people do when you retire or when
you're like, oh, I have time.
And so it's, it's in absolute reverse.
So being.
And I'm really grateful.
I'm really grateful that I'm able to have found that space that felt like I was making
a difference.
At the same time.
I could grow as an individual learn and build a career out of humanitarian work.
I think that that's a very nice place to be in.
I love how you say that that work found you.
I mentioned your, your study and your master's degree in the U S and you worked in Washington,
DC.
So you had that opportunity to take that path that a lot has changed.
Yeah.
a lot of people do is work for themselves and maybe build out the passions that support your
life. But something drew you, I think, as you said, in reverse to be able to find purpose and
then reverse engineer that. Was there a temptation for you to stay in the US and continue that path
or did it never feel quite right for you? I remember I did an interview once in college
and I was asked, what do you want to be when you grow up? And I was like, out of nowhere,
I was like, I want to be a bridge. And I always had that. I used to have these dreams when I was
a kid, which were really weird because I was raised by my grandma. But then we moved to Nairobi
with my parents later on. And I would dream there was this alleyway that we would play.
And the moment I walked through it, I was in my grandma's backyard. And so I really looked forward
to going to bed. I was like, this only happens when I'm sleeping. And that then translated to
wanting to be a bridge. I was like, okay, there's this very,
driven, ambitious, Western, civilized pace and world career. And the I, I, I talk of capitalism
on steroids. And then at the same time, there was that co-wiring of this communal space where
anything that you do, however small, can make a big difference. So over time, being able to be
able to transit between these different worlds, bring the best from each to the other has been
my dream set up. So it worked out eventually. I didn't know how it would work out. In my head,
I thought it would be maybe having a job at the World Health Organization and being posted in
different places for a while. But it actually turned out in a very organic role, a way that
I could define myself in my terms and build an organization around it.
It's fascinating to say it literally was your dream.
As a young girl to actually see yourself in that light. And then to be able to say those words
in college must have been interesting for you. Grew up on a tiny island of 3000 people,
I think surrounded by mangroves is sort of unique to think you can come back with all of that
expertise and knowledge and be that bridge in life. As you said, it's, it's turned out in a
way that maybe you couldn't have imagined, but do you think that was always your destiny?
It's, I feel like we all have an idea of what we dream or desire or feel like your
destiny.
And then now it's just along the way navigating the noise and the background chaos, you know,
like the echo that we had setting up the podcast. And it's quite hard, you know, you go, you kind
of really have, okay, let's log out, let's log back in, let's figure it out until you fine tune
to, to, you know, what it is, that's that safe space, that purposeful space for you. So it was,
I just feel very, very fortunate that
I could,
you know, define this journey for myself.
And we feel incredibly privileged to have been able to collaborate with you and a world called
Alita Connect that we're really passionate about curating groups of people from different
backgrounds that maybe wouldn't have got together. And I love your group because I'm sure this group
of people would never have connected from Paul Barnes from McLaren Racing in Formula One and
Carlos Custa from Arsenal. Nico Cain is a CEO of a huge organization and an amazing story. Justin
Longmuir, an Australian rules football coach in Fremantle in Australia, and your incredible story.
Can you tell us about, you know, sitting down with that group on a regular basis and what that's meant
for you?
At first, I was a little skeptical of the Alita Connect group, I would lie. You know, here I am,
this African girl villager and here, like, you know, five other senior white male officials
working in all these different fields. So I was like, oh, my friend's like, no, it's an amazing,
amazing process. It's going to unlock, like, you know, thoughts and spaces you didn't know
existed. And Matt was really cool. Stephanie was just fantastic. So like seven, I think we're
seven sessions in or something. It's, it defines the word creativity for me. So when I looked up
the word creativity to understand it, it defines it as the ability to like see connections where
none seem to exist. And I think that's the magic of Alita.
What it did. And sure enough, here we are, we're sitting, you know, there's, there's a football
component, here's Arsenal, you know, we, we run healthcare, and we use football as a tool of
communicating to young men and girls around sexual and reproductive rights, you know, so like, oh,
that's really, that's really random. And then the most random personal connection comes with Paul,
I'm like, Paul, in Formula One, like logistics, I'm like, okay, our life,
is around logistics and healthcare. And then you're learning about this person, like moving
hundreds of people across the globe. And then I'm like, Formula One, what are the chances? My son is
karting, he's in motorsports, he's like, we're like McLaren fans, you know, we have the hats
cheering, and I'm always rooting for Lando. So it was like, really an interesting space to be in
and having these platforms of like, not just leadership discussion, but like the back end,
of leadership. I think it's a part that, you know, when they say it's a lonely space,
and having this intimate group that's very intentional, open to being vulnerable,
and you can like bounce on your challenges with as well, was a very critical tool. So Alida was
definitely not my usual, you know, workshop panels, like humanitarian spaces, but more of an
intentional dissection of leadership. So yeah.
It's a beautiful description, Norma, and I just, you know, the way that you've described those
connections and the different thinking of people being open-minded, we often talk about
people for a long time have been in our silos, and we work in our spaces, and we end up with
that groupthink often to great effect. But when you put that random creativity, as you described it,
it can be quite powerful. And it sounds as though that's something that sort of really
resonated with you. That was a big takeaway for me. And just that urge,
we had one session with, I think his name was Ben, the conductor of the orchestra.
Ben Northey, who's the conductor of the Melbourne Symphony Orchestra,
is a beautiful, creative guy. Ben, he dropped into your group, did he, Norma?
It was very insightful. I went to a college that was an Oberlin College around music,
and not in a single, you know, million years would I have thought that, okay, here's
something that can show you linkages of no different than what we were doing on a field
hockey pitch.
Like I played field hockey, and I'm like, you know, from orchestra on stage or field
hockey or going to any part of the world, it was a very powerful illustration of teamwork
and leadership.
Norma, I read that you come from a family of very progressive men that have nurtured
the strong women in your world, and that there was a lot of misconception about, in your
words, your community. Can you tell us a bit about those strong men and the misconception
of your community that they have perhaps broken the trend from?
So we are, like, my father is the biggest feminist I know, before feminism existed.
Here's a man, the most, you know, eligible bachelor in town, politician, and, you know,
is like advanced in his space. And he achieved all this, you know, as a self-made person
to then go and marry.
And the first thing he does...
The first thing he does is get married, delays having kids, which is abnormal, because usually
that would be a really bad reputation, you know, being called. And then the first thing
he did was have to send my mom to school. And not just to school, but to Rockford, Illinois
in the United States for, like, away from these two young kids. And so everyone called
my parents, like, crazy. Like, these are the craziest human beings. You know, how does
a man get a young, beautiful wife and then, like, send her away?
And here's these two young kids. How reckless. And that was, like, the biggest investment
that could ever happen. And especially with three girls. With three girls, no boys at
home. And then that goes back, though, to looking at my grandma. She's, like, this strong
95-year-old lady who's, like, a matriarch. And at 5 a.m. in her house, it's, like, this
man having coffee. At 5 p.m. before the evening prayers, it's his mother. And she's, like,
this man having coffee.
So we come from a society that is honestly very matriarchal, as much as we don't like
to admit it. But now when you look at the impact of colonialism, when you look at the
impact of the Islamic influence that came of, you know, putting societies into boxes,
checkboxes, defining whether it's what went into our constitution, what went into the
prayers.
The patriarchy kind of starts diluting in. But if we look at other societies, like in
Kenya, we have the Kikuyu community, where men take their mothers' names as last names,
for example. But you don't hear that being talked about, because there's all this narrative
of, you know, we've got to fix this. There must be a gender issue here, and so forth.
So on my end, I'm just very aware of the fact that we cannot take a broad stroke.
We do have to point out the nuances, whether it's matriarchy, whether it's the strong men
who actually carry women on their shoulders for the next generation. And I've seen that
a lot growing up. And maybe that's why it's coming with the, you know, you can't tell
me no, you can't tell me that you can't, you know, do this. And I try to do the same
with the kids. I remember being told I couldn't swim. I'm like, you know what, I'm going to
swim, and I'm going to be the best swimmer that there is.
In school. And that happened. And so having more and more of these narratives come to
the forefront, look, I think is very critical.
Well, Maria, in Australia at the moment, there is a horrific epidemic of violence against
women. It's a national disgrace, I think, is a term a lot of us use. And these violent
acts that are happening on a regular basis, as you said, it's such a complex and nuanced
conversation that you, you know, growing up in a loving family and having what you described
as,
as a father and a mother, and you find it almost hard to comprehend. And do you think,
you know, we don't tell the stories like the progressiveness of your dad enough and
that we perhaps focus on the alternative sometimes? Is there part of the solution in that for
what is a really complex and horrible problem?
It is part of the solution. I mean, if you don't see more of such a reality, then you're
wired to think that it's not possible, or it doesn't exist, whether it's in sports,
you're talking domestic violence. We just had a meeting, a very interesting meeting
this morning with the political leaders around reproductive health as part of Safari Doctors
Program. And one of the guys said something very important. Whenever he's like, whenever
we talk family planning, we just think women. And maybe that's the problem is that men need
to be actively engaged to know that they're part of the situation as well. So if you're
coming home, and you just want your wife popping babies, everyone, you know, you're not going
here, but you don't understand the physiology of a woman, what she's going through, what
needs to happen, then that will always be a problem. You're addressing just like a one
end of it, and there's a hole at the end of the bucket, and you're just filling water
saying, you know, we're doing this. So if you look at issues of especially domestic
violence, a lot of the cases, and I don't have the stats to kind of spew out, is that
you'd see either it's like historic.
It's somebody who's witnessed it before in their family. It's kind of, there's this linear
progression around it of what someone experiences as familiar and then how they deal with it,
whether it's what they saw their mother go through or, or somebody within their close
space go through. So that's one of the tools is being like, this does not have to be the
how love is expressed. Like we've done surveys and communities where
women are like, you know, if I burn the food, I should be beaten. You know, what am I doing
burning food? But, but, but that, that's a basic understanding where it's like, no, it
doesn't, it doesn't have to be that way. And it has to happen to both parties because the
same guys who are perpetuating the violence, again, are coming from a history of violence,
a lot of them. So, so I think having these stories, what you're doing, what you guys
do, it's like getting information stories out there, realities out there. That is one
of the elements that we need to tackle.
Yeah, it's a beautiful thing to be able to share stories like yours. And it feels like
the world hasn't had too much space for that, isn't it? The nightly news tells stories of
grim and horror and the algorithms tend to work towards the negative bias, don't they?
And it's a fight back, isn't it, to hear.
The media is so responsible for this because it's like, you know, anything, every time
I'm always scrolling down, it's like worry stories or, you know, this happened, somebody
got killed or so on. So it's, it's, it's just, and that's an unfortunate thing.
It's an unfortunate space as well, that kind of digital for improvement.
Yeah. You know, the story of how progressive your grandfather must have been and your dad
at that time is incredibly inspiring. And you also founded a school to serve the focal
families where you grew up. But I, I think when I read that, a lot of us have great intentions,
but not many people get serious things done like you do. What sets you apart in that way?
How do you find a way, as you said, to get that seed to grow into the beautiful tree
that provides fruit, as you described?
What sets you apart?
I don't know. Look, as somebody, I'm like, you know, you don't have a problem and the
first thing she wants to do is fix it. Maybe it's that male quality that they call. But
I don't know. I just feel like humans are, we're very powerful. I think when I think
of all the great, you know, us being able to have this conversation, you think of people
who've done so much more, you know, think of the Graham Bells and Einstein and you're
like, oh my God.
I think of Mansa Musa and, you know, the pyramids. I don't know. I go into those weird spaces
where like, and therefore what we're trying to do is like nothing. It's absolutely nothing.
I'm like, you know, there's somebody who was sailing the seas back in the day without Google
Maps. I'm like, wow, that's impressive. So we were home and Safari Doctors, after a year,
I think I realized that it's no longer like a pet project that I could do from Nairobi
or New York.
And I had a 10-year-old boy. No, not 10 years. He's 10 years now. He was 10 months then.
And he hated going to school. He loved it the first two days. It was exciting. And then
after that, I would like have to sneak around and like walk him halfway and then like disappear
from an alley or, you know, get a donkey home and be like, hey, guess what? Today you're
going to school with a donkey. And it was just, I say every morning, I'm so happy to
be here as an adult. But my son is like so miserable.
And the idea of going to school. So then that's when three of us parents got together
who wanted our kids to have more of an experiential learning education versus sitting in a classroom
and looking at a blackboard. How could they be in a space where they could interact with
nature? They could learn colors by walking around and, you know, as opposed to from a
textbook. And then, so there was a space and we shoved three of them and then neighbor's
kids.
And I thought it would be just like a homeschooling experience where three of us got in, got a
teacher or two and taught in some subjects. And now we have 50 kids. My son and my daughter
were able to transition from that school to like one of the most competitive like international
schools. It's like, oh, so we must be doing something right. It can't be that bad because
everyone was like, they don't learn there. They're just playing and having too much fun.
So that's how we got in.
We have a school called Shambhala Shaila, which is in my front yard back at home in
Lamo. And we now have seven teachers and five staff members. So it's kids coming in from
8.30 with a full meal until end of the day. They get to do all these random village experiences,
but also global experiences. So being able to take like seven, eight kids, take them
to get passports and travel out of the country.
You know, creating random opportunities, have a swimming program because I really believe
in swimming and how much it did for me. So that's the little vision that translated into
this exciting. So I look forward to retiring and having like 50 kids running in the compound.
I love someone who's got a master's degree from one of the leading education institutes
in the world, sees the beauty in the creativity of letting kids play and learn in a different
way. It's another great story.
Yeah.
And I've had great privilege of sitting across from incredible people like you. And we think
that success leaves clues and that there are some patterns in leadership. I want to ask
you a handful of questions on that basis. Starting with self-leadership, we feel hard
to do what you do or what anyone achieves like you have without a sense of self-leadership.
What does that term mean to you?
I'm going to ask you as an athlete. I spin it on your table. Have you go from like athletics
and having the discipline to have a podcast?
Yeah.
And just sit around doing research. That's a lot of self-leadership. What drives you
to do that? Let me spin this one.
It's a lot easier asking the questions than answering as it turns out, Umrah. But I think
probably the discipline of sport gave me that belief to get out of bed. And morning routine,
I feel for me, has been something that's helped me in good stead by getting up and being active
and exercising and then starting the day in a positive way and building on those little
moments.
That discipline for me has turned out beneficial in other areas of being able to follow through
and do things because sport gave you that ability to be able to do that and take on
board feedback and want to be a constant learner and want to constantly improve. And I feel
athletes probably misunderstand that. They get to the end of their life and their sporting
life and they go, I know nothing. And often you do, but I think you take some of that
in your life. That for me is that self-leadership of starting the day with good habits and good
routines. It sets you free. It sets you free. It sets you free. It sets you free. It sets
me up for the rest of the day. How about you?
That's very true. With athleticism, having swum at Orillia and then picked up field hockey
and then seeing it in my son as well, I can see the difference. So that's definitely a
component. On my end, more severely though, I have a serious allergy to injustice, super
allergic to that. I'm talking, I will not be quiet. And I think for me, that's what I'm
talking about. And that's what pushes me to kind of, maybe it's almost like proving
a point that you say, whether it's like, oh, as women, you can't or shouldn't be able to
do this. I'm like, that invokes some serious self-leadership to prove otherwise. You're
talking about, oh, you know, talk about race. You talk about nationalism. You bring it.
But for me, it's like really puts up that fire. And especially in like seeing it for
the next generation, because I feel like we're on the same page. I feel like we're on the
same page almost in that phase of, it's no longer about aspiring, but about transmitting
before then checking out and being like, okay, you've done what you've done. So also the
young, the next generation is really inspiring. It drives me to have that push of, okay, we
need to pass that baton on. You need to be on top of your stuff. You need to be that
role model. You need to expand the boundaries.
Something like in 2022, we ran for office and everyone's like, you know, you're not
a politician. You've never, there's a lot of old guards, but it's like that, that, that
discipline of mobilizing resources, getting a team, being like almost a small band because
we're like a non-starter, the underdogs. For me, yeah, I'm driven by self-leadership for
me is because of the underdog, basically.
Yeah, I love that.
Incredible answer. We see people are really conscious now of how they positively impact
others in their environment. That sounds like the most ridiculous question to ask someone
who impacts people the way you do. But do you think about that on a daily basis that
the people you interact with and how you go about impacting people, is that something
you're conscious of every day?
No, I don't think it's like a mantra or I started meditation, but okay, these are the
five things I'm going to work on today.
I think it's just a way of like, you know, the same way you don't get up and think, oh,
I'm a man. What do I do when I go take a piss today? Like you just, it just happens. So
it's the same. It's just, it's just a, it's a space. It's a way. Sometimes you need to
put yourself in check, especially when you're getting like a battery low, when you're like,
you feel like your brain, I think it's, it's one of the hardest spaces in athletics is
when you're losing, you know, there's that.
That point where you're like, okay, then you need to be more conscious about it. You're
like, okay, you know what, this is the purpose that you got this, or here's where you turn
to for refueling and recharging and everything. But otherwise you just walk on it. And it's
the triggers that come around, you know, sometimes, what was it? I saw somebody like cutting the
line. I'm like, I think he's cutting that line. And we're just going to watch them cut
the line like that. And you go tap on the shoulder and they're like, you're really going
to call me out.
It's, it's just in you.
And that shows up in those little moments too. Like if there's any injustice, you can't
be silent. You'll, you'll, you'll pause. How many of the line is pushing in the line?
They're going, they're going back.
I wouldn't cross Umrah Omar, I think.
It would be in a nice way, because then we'll still joke about it and maybe even like have
a cup of tea later on. But it, and that's the, that's just the other thing though, is
also how do you navigate these experiences and spaces without, um,
fighting? It, it doesn't have to be a fight. Like it doesn't have to be, um, a confrontation.
And I think that's a space and that could question or could improve your, um, your position
as a leader. Um, I had that, I have to put myself in check a lot. Like, okay, Umrah,
this is what you want to fix, but this is your end goal, but how you get there will
determine, um, a lot of, uh, you know, the process will determine a lot. And, uh, that's,
um, that's, that's, that's, that's, that's, that's, that's, that's, that's, that's, that's, that's,
that's the hard space to navigate. Cause sometimes you want to yell, you want to like
slap or think you like, you have to put a smile on. I feel like, Hey,
creating safari doctors in your own school is a, is a, is a unique vision. How have you
gone about sort of sharing those visions and bringing them to life?
Um, we, that's a good question. Um, one of the most basic things is with the kids, like
when we have conversations and they're like, yeah, my mom does safari doctors. I want to,
you know, keep doing what you're doing when I, when you're older, when you, so just first is
just within the home. Um, and especially with my dad, I think he's the most proud and he's always
like checking in. Um, and then the beauty about it is that it just leads you to the next step to
do something else. So like, we just, we just built the first, um, semi Olympic pool in, in
Lama County. And that for me, like bigger than anything, because as an athlete, somebody who
wanted to be an Olympian, um, but couldn't because of the societal restrictions, I'm like,
whatever you do, it's like, it's safari doctors now is running itself. We have the team,
they have the, you know, they're doing the impact and I'm just there as like a sounding board
and then moving on to not set up the school more substantially. And then what that gives you the
leverage to do next. So that's the beauty I feel in the work that I do is like it's growth. Um,
and it's not gross, like a career,
growth of just watching yourself grow as an individual. It's growth of seeing, you know,
Mariam who started as a office assistant, who's not like a program manager. It's seeing Amina
who came in as an intern who now can stand in for my panel sitting in Dubai and like at the
biggest humanitarian conference. So, so that's, that's, I think is the most satisfying, um, uh,
part of, uh, of seeing this impact that you're, you're talking about.
And over, we see,
uh, curiosity is a word that, uh, comes up a lot. And through curiosity, um, leaders like you
approach their learning and development through being constantly curious. Does that resonate with
you? It's, um, it's, it's even stronger than curiosity, but what I love about the curiosity,
I always remember we're always told curiosity, kill the cat, curiosity, kill the cat. And then
one day, I don't know who it was. It was like, yeah. And satisfaction brought it back. Oh,
that's it. That's it. We're not stopping. We're going to poke our nose in everything. Um, but
yeah, there is a, there's a curiosity and then there's like an intensity and love of life and
possibilities as well. That kind of projects into that where, you know, there's no more you're
hungry. Yeah. You're curious. It's curiosity, that hunger of, um, um, whether it's making a
bigger impact or making a bigger, um,
you know, unlock, how do you put it? I don't even like the thing breaking glass ceilings because
there's no ceilings really, but just kind of like really flying for them further out. But at the
same time being connected, having your roots deep, I always think of the analogy of a tree and how
the roots are just as deep as the branches, but you never really see that, but you cannot go that
far out without going deeper down. So that's how the curiosity model should work.
Yeah. Beautifully said. Uh, communicating with clarity is something we see leaders are really
conscious of. How have you gone about your, uh, your communication?
Hmm. I think I did a good job of giving us a survey at the beginning, um, that we had to get
out to our colleagues to find out if we are as phenomenal as we're supposed to be, or as people
like Luke, um, dupe us into thinking we are, um, we, uh, so we'll keep back. That's, that's the
weakness actually. That's my weakness. And, uh, they're like,
the feedback was that, you know, we, we have these big visions. We have a leader of big vision,
but how do we get there? Or maybe they're too warped up in your head that you're not translating
it, um, to the team that, that has to do it. So that's my problem. I also see it, um, at home
sometimes. And then I'd be like, Oh, why is it done? But you didn't tell us you have to be done
at a certain time. I was like, Oh, you know, when you say done, it has to be done immediately.
So it's just that.
It makes you like think back and like, okay, maybe your brain is going, um, on 200 kilometers an hour,
but then you need to translate that to who you need to get to that speed as well. Yeah. So
communication, being clear, being, um, um, thoughtful as well in, uh, in how that should
be delivered, like what the expectation is from, from that, um, uh,
you, you're clear. And then upon being clear, it's also, is the capacity there,
um, that to be able to deliver on what you're trying to communicate.
And I appreciate you sharing that, isn't it? At the start of, um, the process asked you to,
to send out to all the people that you work with that, you know, a couple or, you know,
many as you like, and take on some feedback about your impact in your space. And the fact
that that was something that you wanted to get better at and, and, and some feedback your way
on communicating a little bit more clearly.
It takes a bit of courage, we think, uh, to do that, but is that been something that's
been beneficial then to say how I actually can put some work into that for you?
Yeah, that was been, that was very beneficial. It was also really helpful hearing the rest of
the team on what all they needed to work on the feedback, um, that they got from, from the team.
Cause you're usually, you're usually the one evaluating or getting feedback and you never
do what you call that 360 evaluation, which is something that, um, we're looking at introducing
in a healthy way in the organization.
Um, which brought up the question. I remember one of the breakout, we always had a breakout
session where every, um, a member kind of brought in what their hurdle was. And I remember
after that, my hurdle was, you know, who leads the leader. And I was like, it's something
that you take for granted. And it's a really dangerous space, um, uh, to be in as well,
because I get this feedback where it's like, okay, please communicate like clearly and
how you communicate and be, uh,
and let us know what needs to be done. Cause we're here to get stuff done. But my reaction,
my being emotional, um, about it is problematic. So that activity was really, really useful
in just being like, okay, stop. You're doing this in one way. How's that being received?
Um, it has to be a two way street. Like leadership can't be a one way street.
How important has collaboration been for you?
Collaboration has been healthy, healthy. It's like, actually I'm talking like physically,
literally healthy, um, collaborate, um, allow everyone to be able to delegate and it's more
effective. Um, uh, it's more, um, uh, practical and it's, it's just, it's healthy. I'm talking
like, especially like recently with Safari doctors being able to bring on board, let's
say like a deputy director and evaluation person and like have all these positions.
Cause before it felt like we, before, uh,
and, uh, learning about these leadership spaces, it felt like you're playing a football game with
eight players and the eight players were not playing a passing game. So you can imagine
somebody gets the ball, try to sprint, go score. Nothing goes in. Some next person is like, Oh,
I got this. I'm going to do it because I'm, you know, I want to deliver and I want to show,
but then you're like, no, you have to collaborate or else we just all end up losing. Um, so no,
it's been really, we've gone into an 11th year.
Who has been the greatest leader in your life?
No, and it's not, I know it's stereotypical. They all love their mom, but, um, my mom was
literally a leader, like professionally. Um, she was studying it when people are not studying it
in the eighties. Um, she'd left two kids at home and then she comes back to be this career woman,
but at the same time knows how to,
to balance with her social responsibilities as well. Being a wife, being like a daughter,
being a mother. And I think that's part of like a trade of leadership is how do you navigate
your different roles and your different spaces. And then the scariest thing I ever did was, uh,
look at her spreadsheet on how she leads and manages. I'm talking like she keeps like two
desktops and they're like all color coded and like, you know, who she's delegating to,
when she's following up, I'm like, Whoa, I can barely like, you know, put things on my WhatsApp
phone alerts. It's yeah. It was literally seeing how you can lead from the home to the community,
to the career, um, spaces. That was really impressive. And then she managed, she came
on to manage our political campaign and she maps everything out. She puts like,
it was literally like being in a, in a, in a war room and seeing that happen and getting to see
that firsthand and up close.
There wasn't a hesitation for you. It was instantaneous, wasn't it? To have that in
your life. And it's, uh, it's beautiful, isn't it? To have that influence that,
and without knowing you at all, it sounds a lot like the life that you've lived.
Can you say that in yourself?
Oh, I wish I, maybe I have like, um, a quarter of that discipline and the skill and
soberheadedness. Like if I was really generous, I'd say 33%, but she, and when you ask her,
ask leader, cause the first is like, Oh, that, that, you know, am I favoring? But I was like,
wait a minute. This is like a factual, like when you're talking about leadership, when I look at
the presentations that Stephanie gave us, you know, who's the person that comes close to,
um, to scoring an eight plus on that it's yeah. It's definitely. And we get to use that until
today. Like I get to use her as a sounding board. Like I said, when we were doing the campaign,
um, a year and a half ago, she was the one who had like map,
out everything she had like budgeted it, done all that stuff. So it's a resource that I still
get to tap into. We're obsessed with the collaboration and, um, what it means to get
people together out of their silos and so much that you've achieved. And I suspect so much more
to come. Is there anyone that you thought I'd love to collaborate with, whether it's safari
doctors or one of your other passions, it could be a hobby that you love. Is there a name you
thought, Oh, that's the person that I would love to collaborate with?
Um, yeah, I'm thinking of, uh, not an individual, but a field. Definitely. I think a politician,
an elected politician would be an interesting space. Someone who navigates the electorate and
like delivering, um, a mandate and it involves finances. It involves policies. It involves all
of that. So, and when I think of, um, I think of someone maybe like, uh, Jacinda Arden and
especially what, you know, her having to having a burnout and having to step out and knowing when
to draw the line, balancing the gender, um, aspect as well. So I'd really be curious to hear from
like female politician. Um, maybe I'm also biased in, in that space. And then the athletics is
always, um, uh, a big space to, to learn about collaboration. It's all about team and, um, it,
it just so, so like literal, um, uh, when, when you think of it.
So I would, it would be interesting to, yeah, to unlock those two spaces.
Well, Maritza, uh, fills you hard up to know that people are out there like you achieving what you're
achieving in such a humble, but brilliant way. And to, to share part of your story, as I said,
it's been inspiring to hear it from afar and I've been looking forward to, uh, to this conversation
and congratulations again on the amazing work that you continue to do. And I really appreciate
you taking the time to, uh, to catch up today. Thank you.
Thank you, Luke.
And have a good one.
Thanks for listening to another episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast. Huge thanks as always
to our great friends at Temper, and we encourage you to check out our Leader Connect program.
New episodes are out every Wednesday morning at 6am.