This week's guest on the Empowering Leaders podcast is the legendary Australian Olympic
gold medal winner, Steve Hooker. Fascinating discussion. I learned an enormous amount from
sitting down and spending some time with Steve. You'll hear him talk about his tendency for living
in the future, that while sometimes a curse is actually a superpower. And he describes in great
detail his incredible ability to visualize what he wants to achieve and then work his way back
from there to put a plan in place. So long as it's aligned with passion, he's able to solve
those problems that are required, which enabled him to achieve extraordinary things, certainly
in the sporting arena, which he did at the Olympic Games, but also in his life post-sport.
Steve also touches on the fact that it wasn't until he was 15 that he first tried pole vault
and he still remains the fourth highest pole vaulter of all time. He often talks about not
being an expert in anything other than jumping six meters with a pole in his
hand. He talks about not being an expert in anything other than jumping six meters with a
pole in his hand. He talks about not being an expert in anything other than jumping six meters with
a pole in his hand. But that couldn't be further from the truth from my experience with
the legendary Steve Hooker. He speaks about his skills and passion for problem solving
that he honed as an athlete. And that's what drives him every day in the work that he's doing
to this day. He also talks about understanding risk and consequences as an athlete. That's
transferred over into his role as a senior leader in business who is having extraordinary success
in this next part of his life. He also talks about surrounding himself with really clever people
and that guiding the group around him reminds him that he doesn't,
know exactly everything, doesn't need to know everything, but he's got an incredible way of
connecting people and joining the dots. Fascinating discussion with a great Australian Olympian,
but a really incredible thinker. I'm sure you're going to learn a lot from Steve Hooker.
It's people like Steve Hooker that are the inspiration for the work that we do at Alita.
We'd love you to check out our bespoke, facilitated Alita Connect program where we
bring together groups of five to six people, people like Steve from different backgrounds
with different thinkers.
And we love connecting people around the globe and supporting people's thinking
in this forum. Someone like Steve has got an incredible understanding of what it takes to
be successful, to connect and collaborate people at different levels is something we're really
passionate about. I often say, you don't have to be an Olympic gold medal winner like Steve Hooker
to be part of our program, Alita Connect. We love connecting with our friends from the arts and from
social venture and from the entrepreneurial space and from sport, bringing them together.
So I'd love you to check it out.
If you're interested, have a look at alitacollective.com. You can book a discovery call.
My great partner and friend, Matt Waterwitz, or I'll give you a call and love to follow up about
Alita Connect and our great passion for bringing different thinkers together.
Huge thanks as always to the team at Temper Bedding Australia, New Zealand.
Jason Nicholas and his team have been great supporters of the Empowering Leaders podcast,
are really passionate about bringing stories to the table like Steve Hooker today,
which I'm sure you're going to enjoy. And we know extraordinary athletes like Steve and great
leaders understand the value.
And investing in a mattress that is world-class, NASA approved, the best bedding in the world,
is an investment you will not regret. We spend a third of our life asleep.
Temper is a mattress like no other. I urge you to check it out.
On the 22nd of August, 2008, Steve Hooker became the first Australian male Olympic gold medalist
in a track and field event since Ralph Dubelle, 40 years earlier, the 1968 Mexico Olympics.
Steve Hooker is one of only a handful of athletes to hold Olympic World Championship,
IAAF World Championships.
He won the World Indoor Championship, IAAF Continental Cup, Commonwealth Games titles
at the same time after completing the set in 2010.
He's the first Australian man to hold both Olympic and World Championship titles concurrently.
Steve's personal best height of 6.06 metres has him placed in the top echelon in pole vaulting
history. Steve was the captain of the Australian athletics team from 2008 to 2012.
And his incredible discipline, commitment and work ethic has seen his outstanding success in sport
replicated in his business career.
Steve, it's always a great pleasure to spend some time with you. Thanks for taking the time
to catch up today.
No worries at all, Daz. Great to see you.
Can I take you back? I want to go back to that moment in 2008. Your great Russian rival
fails in his third attempt at 5.90 metres. You've clipped the bar twice from what I understand
at that height from memory and you had one more attempt. It's going to change your life
if you get over the bar. How do you get it right in that moment knowing that it's such
a significant time?
It's a long answer to that question because I hadn't had a good career.
Competition up to that point. I cleared my opening height on my first attempt and then
I cleared 5.80 metres and 5.85 metres both on third attempt clearances. So just staying alive
and not with great jumps, to be honest. But I started sort of finding my feet a little bit at
5.90 metres. My first attempt was okay. My second attempt was really good. And it meant I knew I was
on the right bit of equipment, the right pole with the right jump to clear 5.90. When you're
getting missed, it was obviously that's the door opening. That's my opportunity.
My destiny is in my own hands. And after that, I mean, I was excited and I knew it was my moment.
And that was the moment I'd be preparing for. And after what had been a really hard competition,
that jump, that was the easiest jump I had in the competition. You've been on the big stage and you
know what it's like when you get in that flow state and everything's just happening all on its
own. And it's the best example of flow I ever had in my life. Like the process just started taking
care of itself.
I watched myself prepare my pole, go to my approach mark. And then with no hesitation,
the jump started and felt good from the first step. And it was just about not getting it wrong
after that. And it was my best jump for the day. And yeah, amazing to in that moment to have all
that come together. And it comes down to something I'm sure we'll talk a lot about later, which is
vision. I had a very clear vision of that moment from a long way out and rehearsed that moment so
many times.
And in the lead up to that day, and then when it presented itself, it's like I'd done it a thousand
times already. It felt easy and natural.
It's making the hair stand on the back of my neck, Steve. Clearly, we all know that moment and
understand what it means. But I hear and looking at you tell that story again, that flow state,
that athlete, if you get that once or twice in your life, it's just a magical experience. To get
it at the moment that you wanted it more than any other, to me, is just remarkable. But as you said,
I know you visualizing that moment, and I know you visualizing that moment, and I know you visualizing
what you want to achieve has been a huge part of your success. Can you delve into that a little
bit? You seem to operate well by just having this crystal clear picture and then working
backwards. Is that a fair way to describe it? Yeah, that's me. Finally, I've just watched the
Arnie documentary on Netflix. I could just finish watching that with my wife, Katia, the last couple
of days. And so much stuff that he said resonates with me. He said the same thing, and he said it in
a way that really spoke to me. And I think that's what I'm trying to do. I think that's what I'm
trying to do. I think that's what I'm trying to do. I think that's what I'm trying to do. I think
he's basically lived in the future. And I feel like, and I'm not great company sometimes because
of that, but my head's so often down the road. And I've got to really, that's the easy thing for me
to do. That's the kind of the normal operating mode for me is to be at this point down the road
when all of the plans have come together and been realized and all of that's happened. The hard thing
for me to do is actually be present and enjoy the moment, enjoy the process and all of that sort of
stuff. So, yeah, I think that's a really good point. I think that's a really good point. I think
it's a bit of a blessing and a curse having that kind of mindset and that brain that works that
way. But for me, you're right. The vision is really straightforward. And then I feel like
aside from that, I'm just a very practical person who takes that thing, which some might say is
unachievable or impossible, but then figuring out the possible steps that you can take to get there
that unlock what might seem improbable or impossible into really achievable, doable next
steps. And then just slowly working through that process with that clear vision in mind.
And Steve, it's fascinating to me. I must admit, I can relate to that. A couple of people know me
well talking about you having a crystal ball and that you almost a few chapters ahead start talking
about what life's going to look like in an extended period of time. And I'm a bit like you. I can dream
in that state really happily, but I have to work hard to get back into exactly as that. So I've
spoken to many people like that, but does that work the same for you in terms of,
say, where you want to live or what your work life looks like? Is that something that's happening
for you all the time? All of it, it's a curse. Every bit of it. It's like, what's family life
going to be like? What's holidays going to be like? What's our house going to be like? All of
those sorts of things. I spend myself a lot of time down there. And then it frustrates my wife
a lot because I'll be like, I've got this vision. And then because I'm thinking so far out as well,
like all the variables change. So then all of a sudden the vision will change. I'm like, well,
it's still, it's just evolving now. Like I'm evolving it just five years at a time. I'm not
like changing my mind. It's just sort of, it's moving. Like it's moving based on the variables
changing. I guess you kind of work ahead of occurring and you get to respond earlier based
on the information at hand. And also I think you interpret the information that comes to you
differently. Like if you've got this vision for the future and you're like, here's where I'm going
to go. And it's based on the assumptions I have today. New information comes to hand and you're
like, oh, actually that's, that's contrary to what I thought. Like how does,
how does that impact on the vision? Vision's still viable. Vision gets better. Vision dies.
Like you could, you've got that opportunity to play that earlier than I guess reacting and
responding later. And, you know, assuming it's all going to be fine.
We'll have to introduce Cartier to Beck. They might need a joint counselling session.
Steve, it sounds eerily similar.
It's a tough gig.
And do you think that was a bit of a superpower for you when you applied that to something like
winning Olympic gold medal and jumping the magical six meter
mark that because you can live in that state so comfortably, it meant that you were able to then,
as you said, look at the variables, understand what it was going to take. Do you think that's,
was part of why that worked for you?
Yeah, I think so. Yeah. I think I break it down into three things when I talk about this. So
there's, there's vision, plan and purpose. And I think vision is being able to clearly see what
it is you're going to do. And in my sport, it was easy. So you said the date, 22nd of August,
2008, bird's nest in Beijing.
I knew what the stadium would look like. I could put myself inside that stadium on the pole vault
run up. It's on the D running between the a hundred meter start and the 200 meter start and see
myself jumping a bar in that environment. I've never been to Beijing before, but I know what
it's going to be like. I know what a stadium will be like. I can be there. So vision's easy. Yeah.
Having that moment, the bars around six meters, you've got one jump to win. I can create that
scenario. That's easy. Then how do you get to there? How do you be in the physical shape?
How do you, how do you have a preparation that's going to put you there? So you're in the window,
you're in the mix that that's from experience, like coupling together, you know, your good and
bad experiences. What does that look like? And then how do you build a plan around that? This
is a bit that's challenging because there's a lot of dreamers out there that can say, I can have a
vision of what the future might be look like. But it's like, there's one step in the process where
there's like this mental gap that I just don't believe I can jump it. It's a bridge too far.
How do I, how do I get from being a 500,
five meter 50 pole vaulted or 570 pole vaulted? I just can't see how I get faster or stronger or
improve this element of my technique, what that might be to get there. And as soon as there's that
gap, your brain knows that, right? Like your brain knows that I can't really believe in this vision
because there's no viable pathway for me to get there. Whereas if you see a map and you're like,
okay, here's my target. I'm going to Sydney. I'm going to drive up the human. There's a road and
I drive up the human. I'm there. Then you're like, cool. I believe I'll be in Sydney in 10 hours.
So a simple plan that clearly shows you that maps out the way to the vision is, is critical.
And if there's any bit that's not, you're not saying I can do that with belief, then
you've got to reassess the plan and break that down into smaller chunks that might be more
achievable. And I think you've got those two things, the vision and the plan, what people
struggle with is that daily purpose, but the plan's a link. So if you've got the plan, then
each day with purpose, you can turn up and say, I'm going to do this bit of it because I know it's
the larger body of work that's going to get me to, to the place that we're trying to get to.
It's a brilliant description, Steve. I'm completely fascinated by it. I love that you've got
that in such a system. And I think the important element maybe is the last one you spoke about to
me is that people achieve great things with purpose and everyone, even when you've got
great purpose, you still got to grind your way through. It's not every day is just joy,
is it? When you're trying to- Most of it's boring. Most of it's the boring
bits, you know, like the little things you've got to do, like just each day, just tick the box edge,
and then you look back and you're like, man, we did so much over that period of time.
And you can't do those boring bits unless you've got the exciting big vision at the end that you're
working towards. That's the fuel, you know, like that's what's driving you. That's what's pulling
you forward. I try and keep things as simple as possible. And I've spoken about this for a long
time, probably only the last 12 to 18 months, I've been able to get it that simple for myself to be
able to put into words how it feels to have a big campaign with a big goal that has lots of little
steps in it. But I could never-
I explained to people why every day I was like, I get out of bed and I'm going. I never really
understood why other people didn't. There's some people that are just driven without those other
elements. But for me, that was what created it, a clear vision and a really simple plan.
And I want to get to in a minute how you've been able to translate that into another chapter. I
think Olympic gold, everyone can understand, can't you? And that is a real, as you said,
that's a, you know, I like the way you say an easy vision. It's not necessarily that, but easy,
easy for some, but an easy one to picture, but then to execute it.
Yeah.
How do you then do that? Not many athletes find a second chapter, which I want to talk to you about.
I want to ask you about the courage part to me, because I still look and think, I always admire
any sport at the highest possible. It doesn't matter what it is. I think there's something
that you, but to me, to put a stick in the ground, launch yourself six meters in the air,
did that still, was there still a courage element for you running down that every time,
or had you overcome that and it was just something you felt comfortable with?
No, there was always, for me, a fear factor. Like I came to pole vault late. I started when I was 15.
So first time I came to pole vault, I was like, I'm going to do this. I'm going to do this.
I touched a pole vault pole, 15 years old. And Mondo DePlantis, who everyone's going to watch
in Paris next year, or the world championships next month in Budapest. Mondo started when he was
five. So you watch Mondo pole vault, and it's like watching a fish swim. It's like second nature,
really easy for him. And Steve, he's breaking all the world records at the moment, isn't he?
World record holder. He's jumped six meters and 22 centimeters. He's gone six centimeters higher
than Sergei Bubka. He's unbelievable, right? And a freak.
He's a freak athlete physically, but the thing that I see when I look at him is how natural and
seamless and frictionless his vault is. And he started when he was five. I jumped five meters
within 18 months or two years of starting pole vault. So I was really fast. I was like 17 when
I jumped five meters from zero. It took him 10 years to jump five meters. So he had all of this
skill building at this lower level, like less risk, no fear.
So now when he's jumping six meters, it's like, well, that's no different to him jumping four
meters or five meters or whatever, because he's built up that kind of resilience within the sport
over such a long period of time. He has a toolbox that I could never have imagined having in terms
of how he can adjust on the runway, how he can adjust his jump in the air, because he's gone
through all of these different phases of jumping with different amounts of speed and strength and
different techniques that have all evolved over time. So I love watching him jump. I'm totally
jealous of it because it looks so easy for him. And it was hard. It was hard for me to jump.
It was really hard for me. I had decent natural speed. I was sort of, I had that. I don't think
I ran technically like biomechanically particularly well, personally, like good speed. And I had one
good thing, which was aggressive shoulder drop in my jump. And those two things were enough for me to
pull together a really good five-year window of elite pole vaulting, but it was never easy.
I always felt like I was on the edge, like I had to be fully there to make it work.
And is that why,
he's so unique and breaking records is that not many, you know, most people were great athletes
and then they turned to pole vaulting. Your story is probably the most common path. There's very few
find it at five years of age. Am I right in saying that?
Yeah. Well, there's a generation now starting to come through whose dads were pole vaulters. So
Mondo's dad was a pole vaulter or their dads were their coaches, like who started coaching them
quite a bit younger. There's more and more coming through where that sort of seems to be a trend,
like second generation kids that have been around it for their whole lives.
Um, and they, they just look more natural. And the other, the other element as well is like,
we're saying it was, you always, I grew up in the era where they're all big guys, pole vaulting,
like 90 kilos was not uncommon for a pole vaulter. And the guys are doing well now,
70 to 80. Um, and so like lighter frames, finding the same heights using smaller equipment. And
that's like less stressful on the mind, less stressful on the body to do that as well. So,
whereas I was like, I had a big equipment as big as anyone really used that has,
its own kind of fear factor, you know, more risk, more weight that you're carrying in your hand,
you feel it physically. So there's a lot of elements there that kind of come into why is
it scary or why does fear come into play? But I think for me, the biggest thing was coming to it
late and trying to keep up with my progression, which happened quite quickly and quicker than I
could kind of adapt to it. You do come from athletic royalty though, Steve, your mum was
an Olympian in 1972. She won a Commonwealth game silver. Your dad's a four-time national champion
and a Commonwealth games representative. What,
what sort of influence was the athletic path always going to be you or did you sample other
stuff? Uh, no, I, it wasn't always necessarily for me. I always loved it. Uh, but I love playing
footy as well. Like I, I love my footy team that I played with growing up, my junior team and the
guys I played with and always really enjoyed that. And, uh, and then did athletics in the summer,
uh, was sort of my, my split and, and was doing that up until I was 17.
Nearly 18 and just had to, had to make the call. I think like I was, I took a year off in 99. I took
a year off playing footy for the, for my club to focus on pole vault training. And it got like
halfway through the season. And I was like, I just miss playing footy so much. Like, I just,
I just want to go and play with the guys. So I went and played the last six games
with, with my local club, with, um, with Baldwin. And,
I'd just done like, I didn't realize I'd just done like the perfect footy preseason. So I got
faster, stronger. I'd been in the gym and I went out there and all of a sudden I was like, how easy
is footy? Like I was getting touches, jumping all over guys, taking marks. And like off those six
games, got asked to go and train, do a preseason with Oakley Chargers. And they were the ones and,
and sort of, I know they did like David Park and scratch matches back then where, you know,
they'd put two Chargers teams together and figure out who would get on the list. And
so I played those games. And at the end of the season, I was like, oh, I'm going to play with
them. And at the end of that, they were like, well, what are you going to choose? Like, you know,
you're going to do footy if you are sort of, you're all in the footy or are you going to do
your pole vault? And I was like, I didn't realize I had to choose. If you're going to make me choose,
then I think, I think I want to go to the Olympics. So I want to, I'm going to go that way. I feel
like at that point when I could see the pathway to, when I was training with athletes, they were
preparing for Sydney and I could see the pathway to the Olympics. That's when it kind of was clear
for me, which way I wanted to go. And we've seen that brilliant crossover, Steve, uh, you know,
Mark Blitzhouse comes to mind, who was chasing Olympic, uh, dreams as a steeplechaser and his
conversion back to Australian football has been an incredible story in lots of ways. And, uh,
you know, two-time best and fairest winner. Was there a thought in your mind that there was a
second career or you did such an extended period of success in athletics? It was probably
beyond you by that stage. There was only one time where I thought about it a little bit.
And that was when Carmichael Hunt and Isabel Folau sort of got
contracts. And at the same time, it was when the sub rule was in and I was like,
I reckon I could come on and have a pretty good last quarter and a half of 40
and, you know, like come on with and have, you know, some effective speed and
all that sort of stuff. That was the only time it was half a thought, but
having since I played, I played a bit of country 40 with Shane Crawford when I was 39. So just
a year and a half ago and having played three back-to-back games on consecutive weekends,
the reality of that and the fantasy of that are very different. In your thirties or late
twenties, you don't bounce back like you do when you're 19. So that, that, um, that
fantasy, thankfully I got to live it out on a very small scale and realize what an absolute
fantasy it was. It's bloody tough. And I've got a mountain of respect for players that
go out and get through a 23 round season.
Having understood your mindset more clearly now and understand when you get a vision and
a plan and put passion into it, uh, nothing would have been, uh, beyond your capabilities,
uh,
from my point of view. You, you, you married an outstanding athlete. You mentioned cardio
earlier. You've got three kids and you see them daily on the, on the home front. What
sort of leader are you like on the home front with that athletic profile? Do you, do you
allow them to choose their own path? How does that play out?
Oh yeah, I'm involved. I'm a little bit involved. Like I'm more involved than my parents were.
You asked me, you asked me how my parents were as well. Sorry. And, and I think as, as
parents, they were amazing. Like particularly during my pole vault career, they were the
most supporting,
supportive parents on the home front and let my coach, my, my technical, my, my track
coach, like take care of things on the track. And that meant we had a really great relationship
through all of that. And they understood there wasn't the easiest times when I was sort of
like late, like last couple of years of high school, first couple of years is a trying
to transition from junior to senior athletics. It's hard. It's a hard process to go through.
Only, only looking back, I can appreciate how supportive they were and how much they
put up with my moods, the challenging kid I would have been as I was a teenager. And
I was going through that. They were great. And only, you know, only once you have kids,
you understand what that would be like, and you're going through it now with yours. So
they were amazing on that front. With my kids, I want them just to try everything and find
their passion. I thought my experience I had in the world through being a pole vaulter
was amazing. And all I wanted to do was learn it a bit younger. So I'm teaching them to
pole vault just because for a couple of reasons, it's fun. We enjoy it as long as, you know,
the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the,
the offer is always, do you want to go on pole vault today? It's not, we're going, do
you want to go on pole vault today? If they say yes, we go. If they say no, we don't. If
we get there and they want to, we do. If we get there and they don't want to, we don't.
And we'll find something else fun to do. We're going to play in the sand pit or do something
like that. But I want them to have that skillset there early so that they can have fun with
an event. Because the one bit of it that was hard for me was the mental side of it. Whereas
if they learn good technique and they learn how to do this really fun thing young, it
should be easy and enjoyable for the rest of their life. So long as they don't feel
pressure. And that's what I want for them for a couple of reasons. It's a great sport.
It opens up a whole bunch of opportunity. And if they ever want to go to college in
the US, like a pole vault scholarship's gold, there's just not many pole vaulters around
to get on a track program. So if they want to pursue that pathway, like their, their
mom went to Texas state university. That was, you know, she had the college scholarship
experience. If they want to go that way, having a background as a pole vaulter,
it's a pretty nice way to, a free education and a great experience in the US.
I love the way you described it, isn't it? You're sharing a passion, but it comes from
them only and their call and their decision. And, and, uh, fascinating to see. I always
have this theory, Steve, you can't manufacture passion. It's, uh, impossible to do it, but
yeah, you create the opportunities, don't you? And you support them wherever that path
takes and you hope they find something that they loved as much as, as you clearly did.
The transition from, you know, the incredible success, you're an Olympic gold medalist.
And I mentioned the continued success afterwards of world championships and to do that so consistently
for a period of time is a remarkable achievement, but then it ends. And like a lot of people
with sport, it's like, where do you find that again, that next passion? And you've done
that with great success. You were the CEO, uh, until pretty recently of a pretty massive
company and you tried a lot of different things. How did you find the skillset applying, uh,
from your athletic career into your, into your work life afterwards? How, what, what
served you well?
First one is knowing when you're loved.
Like knowing when something gets you excited and knowing that's possible. Cause I think
a lot of people go through life, not realizing you can really enjoy and really love and create
an environment of fun in your work. And I was really able to do that in my sport. And
that's what I was seeking in life. So constantly looking for that. And if it's not there asking,
like being critical and saying, well, why not? Like, is it the environment? Is it the
role? Is it me? Like what's, what's missing? Why this isn't like lighting the air? Why's
it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me?
Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why
is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why
is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me?
Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is
it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me?
it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it me? Why is it
how do you find a passion in your work so knowing that that has to be a part of it is the starting
point and then the next piece is is the vision piece like being able to as a leader in a business
understand where we're going being able to you know one of the things from my sport was having
a huge number of variables that you had to take into account to make a decision and and business
and and is very much like that being able to like see the big picture be able to understand your
kind of key metrics that you you've got available to help you make your decisions
and then commit commit to a decision make a call and then live with the consequences of that and
adapt as you move forward so it's those kind of things that come out of sport that are really
really useful in life like you just every week every year you've got to look at the variables
make a decision come up with the plan execute on the plan review the plan iterate as you go and at
the end you've got a result and it's black and white like
it's clear and so if you can if you can find the same way to kind of replicate that in your
business life then it's a pretty good way of of operating and if you can support those around you
to do the same it's it's useful yeah brilliant answer steve and you you also sampled a lot of
things on the way you started off with some talent management uh you did a tech startup you had um
you know restaurants and perhaps some of those are still playing out as well were they just you
sampling and trying to find as you said that passion was that how that path played out oh
yeah
all different so it's been a journey i think i started in property so my background is i did a
property degree at rmit in melbourne and got on a graduate role at stockland one of australia's
leading listed developers and so i from 2002 to 2006 was was training and working um within that
business so i'd work 20 hours a week and train 30 to 35 hours a week on top of that
um i did that in melbourne until 2005 started 2006
and then after the melbourne commonwealth games moved to perth and took a job in the stockland
office in perth so i had this i had my my career going early and that was off um off my first coach
mark stewart he was a he was a volunteer coach effectively and his full-time job was a university
lecturer at rmit and a lecturer in economics and so it was very important for him to see his
athletes with a life after sport not putting all their eggs in that basket particularly athletics
your likelihood of making any money's super slim so you've got to be prepared for life after sport
and so he was very supportive in training working around study and work and so i had a great
foundation uh from him and from and from those early days and from that work experience i had
with stockland and then you know start of 2007 i've gotten to world number one in 2006 start of
2007 you know just over 12 months out from beijing i was like i want to i've got to be a full-time
athlete for this window no stone unturned full focus to get the result so um made that decision
at that point in time and was was a good decision and was a full-time athlete through till 2010 no
other focus and then at that point like the long-term brain starts kicking in and i'm like
this isn't going to last forever what what's next and so started a small athlete management
business or i'm sports group it's still a business that's around today it does track and field
athlete representation curtis marshall's represented by oram and and stefan who still
runs that business out of germany so i was involved with that for 10 years in the end but
mainly in a supporting role and um not nothing too significant there for me but you know it's a
great business that supports a lot of athletes um get around europe and get to competitions and
um have the experiences that i had
over the years and i've been doing that for a long time and i've been doing that for a long time
um and then a year later was talking to amin sullivan we were both living in perth i i'd
started up with a mate like a like a small butcher outlet at um the subiaco markets because there was
none there and we lived nearby and we're like we would buy meat if it was here and other people
might so we just sort of were playing with that with a mate of ours who owned a butcher
and then amin had opened a cafe nearby and so we were supplying him and we were talking about
things and we found this amazing space um that we're
we thought could be a really good restaurant in perth it was on top of the freemantle surf
life-saving club and then amin myself and jamie dwyer hockey player um started a restaurant
not really you know amin had good experience he'd won celebrity master chef he had a profile in the
space and all of us thought this location is amazing um the perth food scene was really
evolving at that point in time if we can get a great chef on board and create a great experience
with this location we can have some success
that was a great business it just celebrated it's 10 it's called bib and tucker it just
celebrated its 10 year anniversary a couple of months ago um i just exited that myself i sold
my shares to scott bridger who's the chef amazing chef you know poured his heart and soul into that
restaurant and it's so great that he's got a big big stake in that restaurant as they move forward
and um so it's now amin scott and jamie taking that thing on but you know there's nothing that
teaches you more about the value of a dollar than running a restaurant like that it's hard
hard work big turnover high risk lots of staff big overhead like it's um there is a lot in that
and you know every single day your trading conditions are different based on the weather
and what's going on around you and what the parking situation is like like all these things
that you know you have to factor in but you see the benefit of having quality reporting like seeing
what the what the metrics are every day and seeing the trends over time because i was remote i was in
the u.s and i was in melbourne but i would get my daily reports and i would get my daily reports and
i would get my daily reports and i would get my daily reports and i would get my daily reports and
i'd i'd have the questions that i'd be asking you know this looks like this is trending the
wrong way like what's going on how can we fix it what are the opportunities so lots of lots
amazing lessons from that business and amin to his credit scott's done an amazing job with the
food but amin is a business owner just he did the right thing by jamie and i by really taking it on
and being the general manager and doing a sensational job there and really grateful for
what he did on that because you don't always get out of restaurants with your money you come from
hospitality you know how tough it can be i know well and i i just you know i've been in the
three olympians opening a restaurant what could possibly go wrong steve without any experience and
and i love it because you know we always get advised out of doing things but you know the
curiosity and the learning and you're applying like you know you're thinking and your logic to
it so to turn that is a great success stories and you know we've as a family been in the pub game
and hospitality life and everyone's going to open a pub and and i love when people do because you
need creative people to do it to the lessons are long and and quick sometimes at the same time so
i love hearing that story it's fascinating you know the property development world
for a lot of people we know there's enormous opportunities in it but where do you find the
passion it's you know i can see the passion jump in a high bar and win an olympic gold why does
property development provide that that passion for you um it's a very australian thing i think
probably there's two things that we talk about a sport and property so um i think everyone's got
an interest in it in australia and i always did growing up
um for me also i think the more you get into property development it's a problem solving game
and that's always what i've seen myself as so someone that can can uh it's a long-term game
you're going to have a long-term vision you're going to have patience so it takes a long time
to evolve you've got to think now about things that are going to be issues in four to five years
time um and solve the problems along the way what are the what are the barriers you're running into
and how do you how do you work with people to get around that because whilst it looks like it's
property it's a people game and it's all about relationships and building a team that can that
can together come come as one and and get to an outcome so it's um it's always exciting it's
always challenging and the rewards are big and the risks are high so it feels in a lot of ways like
my sport did um and i like being that environment you know like that risk appetite you get when you
mine um holds you in good stead you know like understand the risks be sure you can live with
the consequences and then make your decisions and commit so when you're doing what you did
in the first part of your life you're a leader for yourself effectively now you're leading other
people and you get the chance to to do that on a daily basis what what type of ceo have you been
what type of leader are you in the current space that you're working um yeah that's
so that the biggest challenge i faced was that so under there's a huge difference between
having your own vision and then turning that vision into a shared vision by
broader group like that's that's a really hard thing to do and i probably didn't understand how
hard that was at first i assumed you tell people once and then we're all saying the same thing
and we're all running in the same direction and that just couldn't be anything further from the
truth you know even if you do one beautiful presentation you're not going to be able to
that really shows people like that everyone interprets it interprets things so differently
and then also like having a really clear back to purpose plan vision breaking that down to the
simplest plan so everyone can see each day what the element is that you're working on how does
it fit into the overall plan how's that going to get us to our vision and finding 50 different ways
not one to explain that story so that over time it becomes a shared vision and understanding that
there's no one trick that's going to get everyone seeing things in the same way
persistence varied messages varied mediums of trying to get that message across
and just doing it over and over again so it's almost boring everyone's like yeah we get it and
that's probably the point when you're like okay it feels like if everyone's saying this is boring
then we're probably all of a sudden seeing the same thing and we can talk about it in the same
way and we can see the pathway that we're going to get there so that was a challenge understanding
that and it took a long time
but i mean i was one of the leaders at resumax group and the other one was aussie kia
and he's the managing director of resumax group and took a chance on me put me into a leadership
role early and it's been my greatest business mentor the the six years that we have spent
working together have been just unbelievable what i've learned from him seeing how his brain works
you know understanding how to deal with a crisis understanding how to deal with adversity
in business just there's um there's no university that could have taught me this
and then and then to be side by side with a guy like that working through the covid years
particularly a building business and someone in construction as well like just a huge amount of
experience that um we're able to get through and the fact that we're able to get through that with
a strong united
amalgamated team pretty much the same team we started with at the beginning of it is um
is an experience that i'm really grateful for it's the hardest thing ever but experience i'm
really grateful for um and that i got to do it with oz um fully supported and fully fully um
fully backed by him was um unbelievable yeah brilliant story to to understand it leads
really well steve to something that we're really passionate about working this space and
i love uh out of all the things i've done media wise to sit down and and
and listen to stories like yours but we see patterns in the way people lead and the success
leaves clues is something i often say that there is some consistency as you've described before it
shows up in different ways but love uh finding out where the patterns are and what i ask you
some dimensions of leadership that we think are uh you know quite consistent regardless of the
space you're in and we start with this sense of self-leadership uh steve that we feel like it's
hard to impact others unless you understand your own sense of self-leadership when i ask you that
does it mean to you um it's a hard one it was in the it was in the quest you know you might get
asked about self-leadership and i don't really know what that means like to be honest that's my
honest answer i'm like i don't really know what self-leadership means so what does it mean to me
i don't know it's like um i'm a very like i learn by doing things is my piece right so and the
biggest learnings i've had is when i've i've just been really honest about what i don't know
being and that i've
i feel like and i don't know if it's going to answer your question or not but but i'm i'm no
expert in anything except for probably jumping six meters with a fiberglass pole other than that i'm
not an expert in anything and i love that but i do know a little bit about a lot of things
and i love seeing how things connect and i and i love being around people who know a lot about
things and all of my my learnings and my growth has been about putting myself
putting myself
in the kind of middle of an environment where i'm not the expert but i'm surrounded by really
clever people and just assisting the group to get to the right outcome and that is super exciting
for me and i've i've done that enough times where like the imposter syndrome is gone and i'm not i
don't feel like i need to know everything because what i know is whatever whatever environment i go
into or whatever team we pull together there's going to be someone that knows we've just got to
leave the space for the kind of for the answer to come out for the expert to step forward and for
the solution to come up if we can define the problem properly the solution will present
and then we can work together on a plan you know then then it's just a planning exercise after that
which i'm comfortable with i'm comfortable i can come up with a plan so i don't know if that's
leadership or self-awareness or whatever but that's that's the one thing that i've learned
the most out of was just being in the deep end in the middle of things and realizing you don't
need to know someone knows or if we don't
we can figure it out the information's out there and being really comfortable with that
um that's been a that's been a big learning for me such a brilliant answer steve and i love the
way you answered that and it's profound because yeah some people say that to me i don't even
understand the question self-leash when i ask it though that's actually a reasonably common
response but what you just took us on then to me is is unique because a lot of us live this sort of
facade where well if i show you that i don't know the answer that's going to be a sign of
and so we we sort of make it up and we end up not allowing the answer to come we can't get proper
help or we can't collaborate properly because we don't want to be seen to not know and the way you
describe that to me is brett i can imagine in the restaurant you wouldn't have pretended to be an
expert on opening a restaurant because you weren't but you would have asked some curious questions
knowing you you would have been right in the middle of asking it yeah well how does this work
like how explain to me how this works i'm interested like and then and then all of a
sudden you know then all of a sudden the person who's come to you with a problem is like oh
it's because we're not doing that bit that i know about and yeah you just got to prompt prompt the
smart people to step back a little bit from the detail and then they're like oh yeah that's right
i know i know what i'm doing yeah yeah there's actually not a problem and i love the intelligence
and someone like you understanding your ability to be that connector and bring those pieces together
and execute a plan with with passion it's uh it's profound we see another dimension of leadership
steve around people in roles of leadership constant constantly conscious now of how they
that that's something they think about positive impact is that something that occurs to you
it's a weakness for me um it's a weakness for me and i think it's a weakness for a lot of people
that come from old school high performance sport like maybe not the recent high performance sport
i think that ethos has changed a little bit but i was looking for i was always as an athlete
looking for critical feedback um because i was like i know where i'm going like i just need to
worry about the things that are in the way like i'm not going to be able to do that i'm going to
i don't need to worry about it's going good like i know it's going good yeah fine but
what's not what's stopping us and i've been really guilty of just just going straight to okay here's
the problem here's how we're going to solve the problem rather than saying we're doing these seven
things amazingly um that is amazing that's an amazing piece of work this is great that's a
great bit of progress there but we've got this last piece here i just like especially when you're
busy and there's a lot on which certainly was the environment particularly
at resimax group is seven businesses in one you've got limited time and capacity for each one
my natural instinct was straight to the problem and the solution of the problem and then you move
on and then you you kind of don't think until afterwards about well that might have been
perceived as a bit of a negative bit of feedback to someone because i didn't mention this is going
great except for the last bit of it which we've just got to work on and then the whole thing's
great um definitely definitely a big weakness for me and something that every day i've been
i've got to work on still and we'll always have to because it's not my nature to focus on the good
my nature is to focus on the negative and fix it so being aware of that and trying to each day
do that is uh high on my list and i often fail yeah and i appreciate you sharing that we probably
came we did come out of the same era of sport where it's exactly the same and you just you
you get so used to the feedback that you crave it and you want it and you want it instantly and then
not realizing how blunt it can be and i had the same so comfortable with it yeah
it's like someone else would listen in and say you can't say that to someone it's like
it was meant from a good place i didn't mean it it was just trying to get to the point but i
probably feel very similar but you're right isn't it when you see you actually stopping
celebrating success you understand that's a healthier way even if it didn't come naturally
to you yeah and not even uh we definitely would do it like at a milestone point of view like
celebrate the successes each month and do all of that sort of stuff it's more in the moment
like that's the bit that i would struggle with because in the moment it's like it's action we're
we're not reflecting this is this is action solving this problem just taking the time to
realize that for everyone that's a big bit of their day and it's a big piece of their work and
you've got to in that moment recognize the positives and the growth that we've had and
then just talk on the net then get to the next step you know like that that's the challenge and
it's been good been good to learn that about myself and learn that it's part of me and do my
best to work on it the next dimension uh and you've given a brilliant answer to this
with leaders conscious of how they create and share a vision and i you know i've written down
some notes on what you said before because you described this in such a profound way that you
know was clear to you as an athlete but when you realize you had to bring a team along with you can
you give it a specific example you spoke about 45 different ways of having to do it and once you
felt people were bored that was a moment you thought you're on track is there can you describe
that in a in a specific example i think just the fact that i was able to walk away
as the ceo from this business is probably the best example so when i started it was a business that
was very much run with imagine a aussie as a central hub of this business and he he would he
would send out the tasks and the urgent business to do each day you know it would go out from him
each and every day here's what we're going to focus on today come back and let me know how you
went and then it just scaled beyond his ability to do that and so i came in to try and assist in
building a team and system the process and allow him to grow his capacity to do that and i think
even bigger and we're wildly successful in that because it mainly because of him mainly because
his capacity is so enormous his vision is so enormous his ability to understand and execute
commercially is unbelievable and my role was really sit behind that and make sure that then
where we're going because we're thinking three years ahead and the team's thinking about three
months ahead is to transpose that and then over the course of six years we went from
aussie leading to me and i was leading to then getting a senior management team that were really
clear on where we're going what they had to do to get there and their teams were then clear on what
they had to do and so it's just that evolution and so there's no one specific example it's just
doing that over and over again on terms of new products and new projects and new ways of doing
business and new systems that are in place over and over again until all of a sudden business
becomes a bit boring it's bigger there's more going on it's more interesting but it's not that
kind of fight or flight it's not that kind of fight or flight it's more interesting it's more
interesting every day when you turn up to the office and that's that's the best example that i
can give is that just consistency over time trying to make things simpler and clearer each and every
day has meant that yeah there's there's a group of leaders that all share the vision they all know
where they're going um they can do their work consistently every day and aussie's now got a
business that he can lead and um he can lead it with those senior leaders that are doing a fantastic
job with each of their parts of the business
and it was time for you to find a new challenge was that yeah i think um you know when we when we
set up we we'd agreed with each other that's a five to ten year project that we would work on
together and it was you know it's sort of the minimum commitment like what's your minimum
commitment and you know we ticked past five years and then my long-term brain started ticking and
it's like well if we're through five already then we're going to be at 10 before we know it
i mean i started just thinking about what do i want to do i've loved running aussie's business
i've loved building a business and i've loved building a business and i've loved building a
his vision but if i was to design my very own one what would that look like i had a break and
had time and headspace for the first time since covid really and i just had a book and started
writing things down and out of that kind of came a business plan that i felt really passionate about
for um you know a shared value property development model um that you know where
you can partner with landowners you can partner with builders and you can have social impact
off the back of your property developments and that got me really excited and
it's it's you know i took it to oz and we spoke about it and he said and i know oz and that's not
that's not his passion area you know like that's not the thing that gets him out of bed every
morning but certainly something that had sparked something in me and he's as the amazing leader
that he was it's just like i'll support you in whatever you want to do so you know explore it
look into it we can work this thing out here and you know we came up together with this kind of
transition program of how you know we could we can set the business up for success if i wasn't there
um and he would say i'm not going to do it i'm going to do it i'm going to do it i'm going to do it
in rolling out my new venture you know i still consult back to ozzy on special projects like
he's been that good to me off the back of um the experience that we've had together that you know
i continue to help him with what he's doing he continues to be a mentor for me and i hope that
that is something that continues indefinitely he's um been huge influence on my life and um
you know the best leader that i've been around and um yeah i mean i just feel i feel grateful
more than that like it would have been so easy for him to just say okay well if you're out you're
out most people would in his position but he's not most people and that's what makes him special
and unique and it's why he's got the team that he has and and the support of his people like he does
and that's a massive learning for me and something that i would love to emulate myself what a great
leadership story and i love the chance to share that uh steve we know that changes people's lives
doesn't it when you you lead that way and you do it with care and support brilliant things happen
and and people like you and people like you and people like you and people like you and people like
you go on and do that as well a curiosity is a is a word we we use and hear a lot for leaders that
through curiosity that's how they approach getting better and they're learning and development does
that resonate with you yep 100 i think the one thing for me is like i've been interested like
that's that's that's the way i've always kind of looked at it curiosity is probably a better word
might adopt that um but um just be interested in things you know like i'm i'm the world's worst
and everyone around me will vouch for this i'm horrible with names like it's the worst and i'll
tell you why as soon as i meet someone the least interesting thing for me about them is their name
like i meet them and we start talking and then i'm like like i could meet you i can see someone's
face i could tell you where they worked what jobs they'd been on like an interesting story that they
told me all that sort of stuff but the name is gone because i just want to get into the stuff
you know like i want to i want to understand what they do and ask them questions about how that
works and that's come since having sort of an entrepreneurial mindset
i think at a certain if you're if you're an entrepreneur you'll get this like you understand
that as soon as you open that box all you start thinking about is how things work and that's that's
the curiosity bit for me as soon as i remember one day i was like i wonder if i can come up with an
idea for a business and i'm just going to sit on the couch and then think of an idea for a business
and up until this point i've never done anything like this and i sat down i just started thinking
and i was like well you start them thinking about problems and what problems are there to be solved
and i think the business i came up on the couch was like
um the last meter courier service so you know there's you know there's the big distance and
then there's the last mile and i was like well what about the last meter you know we've got
phones that people are carrying around what if i'm sitting at the cafe and someone delivers my
parcel to me in the cafe like how amazing would that be like it's it's probably a bit much but um
that's what i thought of at the time and i was like okay that's an idea there's no one doing
that out there right now that's that's an idea and then once you had the idea the idea is one thing
and uh and i think ideas are infinite like they're not
ideas aren't that valuable a lot of people would say they are but i don't think they're that valuable
what's valuable then is what are the fundamentals that sit behind operationalizing an idea like
that how does it work how does that idea work and if you can if you can work your way through
how an idea works that's the entrepreneurial mindset and that's where interest comes in so
you hear someone you're like oh what are you doing like how does that work okay and then
what and then you could understand if you've got that mindset like and what are the metrics like
and and
one of the best project managers that we have in our business is a chef it was his training
is in chefing and he's one of the best project managers at resi max group but those two things
do come together there's a recipe and ingredients and there's the team and there's all those
And it's like, there's time constraints and all of these sorts of things that, and there's pressure and you can sort of see how they fit together when you're interested and you can, you start looking at kind of the components of something rather than just the end outcome.
So that's what I, that's where my curiosity is and the interest comes from that entrepreneur's mindset, I think, seeing how the bits work and the same with pole vault.
How do the bits of the pole vault come together to create the jump?
Yeah, I think that's my curiosity.
Fascinating insight into how you think.
Communicating with clarity is a dimension we see is a really common trait for leaders.
They understand that that's such an important part of how they're going to succeed.
How have you gone about that?
Yeah, I mean, that's the simplify the message, simplify the plan and then try and be consistent and then make it interesting.
That's the other piece.
Like it's got to be entertaining and interesting and inspire people.
Um, otherwise these days, particularly, particularly to recover, particularly when we're meeting in mediums like this, like over, over the internet, it's like, it's so easy for someone to find another screen.
It's so easy for someone to find something else to focus on.
If it's not short, sharp, clear to the point and entertaining, you'll lose, you will lose people.
So, uh, I feel like that's, um, some of the kind of can't be underestimated.
How important Steve's collaboration been for you?
Everything.
Yeah, because if you can't do anything by yourself, it's a non, it's a non-negotiable.
Yeah, brilliant answer.
And we, we've seen that, uh, you know, become more of a strength, isn't it?
If leaders understand that more and more now that away probably from the era we're in with hierarchy towards more collaboration.
Um, I think you've been ahead of most of my questions today, a bit like the way you think, but I get a sense.
So you might have a clear answer for this.
Who's been the greatest leader in your life?
I spoke about my, I spoke about my parents and that's, that got me.
Yeah.
It goes without saying Oz and yeah, he's back around.
So Oz is not a classically trained executive Oz.
Um, he won't mind me saying this.
He was a hustler.
Like he, he was the kid that would make counterfeit clothes at high school and sell them to his mates.
Like he was, he was trading things from, he was in the rag trade.
He went into hospitality, um, and everything he's done has, has been successful and he's approached in the same way with his same method, you know, and, and refined.
That method and learnt, learnt his lessons.
Um, and he had, he's the most tenacious person I've ever met.
Like, um, I, I call him the endurance athlete.
He can go for longer, harder for longer than anyone I've ever met.
He'll, he'll always wear down the problem before the problem wears him, wears him down.
Um, and then like any good endurance athlete, once it's done, he'll just break down then.
But he's, um, he's got a, he's got a way.
He's got a, he's got a way of physically pushing himself and you don't often talk about that in business, but he's got a way of physically pushing himself more than anyone I've ever seen.
And it was, um, amazing to see that and see that level of commitment that it takes if you want to really extend yourself and, and, and really do growth quickly and aggressively.
Like it's, it takes a lot.
It takes a lot.
And I saw that from him.
And then amongst all of that, and, and, and he's, he's in the trenches, right?
Like he's doing it himself.
So he's lead by example and supports his team.
He allow, he will know from his experience that the pathway that I may have been taking, it would, would result in maybe not the optimal result, but he'd let me take that path.
So he allowed failure when he could see the outcome coming.
And that was, they were the best lessons for me, like expensive for him sometimes, which is mind blowing.
Like he could say like, this is going to cost me money and not work, but you go.
And like, uh, yeah.
And like, uh, I would learn from that.
The team would learn from that and we'd all be better for it.
And he, he can see the value in that other than just the potential short-term loss that it would apply to that.
I could go on.
It's just a, it's an encyclopedia of knowledge that you get out of him.
And, um, it's about integrity in, in, in dealings.
Like if you say you're going to do something, you have to do something.
He, he can't sleep at night if he feels like he's been on the wrong side of the deal.
But if he's on the right side of the deal, he'll go hard.
And that's one thing you learn as well.
Like if, you know, do your deal, honor your deals.
If someone does the wrong thing on the other side, then you owe it to yourself to make sure they honor the deal.
Um, lots of stuff that may as a timid kind of introverted type person wouldn't naturally want to do or feel like was the right thing to do.
But also saying that out of that, out of conflict and things that might seem like they're conflict, stronger relationships are built and good partnerships are built.
And opportunities to collaborate again in the future are built.
Whereas if things are unsaid, if they're not addressed, if people don't understand the dynamic that needs to exist for a relationship to work, then there's no future in that relationship.
I don't know.
That's a lot.
I could go on.
I could go on for an hour just talking about him and what I've learned and how grateful I am for it.
I'm fascinated, uh, Steve.
I'd love to, uh, to meet him at some stage.
And I, I love the passion you speak about and the lessons learned you've got, you can articulate them in such a powerful way.
And I, and it's, yeah.
It's, it's part of why I love this, this forum because you get to share and you want to do that because I know the evidence suggests, you know, a lot of people work in environments where a leader may be struggling, you know, through sometimes no fault of their own, just lack of education and understanding.
And that, you know, that lessens people's lives.
A lot of people will get stuck in environments because they don't see a way out.
They've just got to hand to mouth and, and they want to feed their, you know, their family and look after themselves.
But you want to share stories like that.
I do personally.
I want to, I want to tell them more widely.
And maybe you'd be generous enough to, to, to see if he'd be up for telling it because it sounds like something we should get out into different environments.
And I'm sure it's going to apply to a lot of different spaces.
Is that, is that how you think about it?
Oh, you'd have a great show with him.
He's, um, and you get to talk about horse racing with him as well.
So you still get the sports crossover.
He's a Melbourne Cup winner, isn't he?
Everything.
I mean, he's won a Melbourne Cup, a Caulfield Cup, a Cox Place and all within the last sort of eight or nine years.
Like he's been prolific.
And, and, and again, he applies the same message.
He applies the same mentality to that.
He, you know, he's, he's got his network of people he trusts.
He's got his, his people that he goes into horses with and he, and creates like a really happy and fun environment, um, in those horses.
And it's the same thing.
It's the same way it applies to his business.
You know, like he's not, he's doing it because he wants to do it.
He's doing it because he loves it and it's a passion.
And he wants, he wants to do that with people that he enjoys working with, you know, trainers, agents, breeders, whatever.
You know?
He wants to work with that trusted network and then they all work for each other.
And, um, I believe that, you know, those relationships are the key to the success that he's had there.
A lot of people might point to luck, but that's not what I see when I look at Aussie.
I see anything but luck.
I see tenacity and planning and good relationships.
Not what it happens to consistently.
And, uh, yeah, I love it.
And it's a good way to live your life, isn't it?
With that sort of consistency and, uh, and passion.
Final question to you, Steve.
If you could collaborate, uh, we're a bit obsessed with collaboration and the work we're doing.
Have you collaborated with anyone on any of your passions?
And there are many of them.
I can hear them pour out of you.
Is there, is there a name that's, that's come to mind?
You thought that will be someone I'd love to collaborate with?
Um, I've, I've had the luck to do it, I think.
Like, I think collaborating with Aussie has been, I've been so lucky to do that.
Um, so I'll answer your question in a different way.
And my collaboration is, is how I can get people to work with me.
How I can get sport and movement and residential, sustainable residential housing together.
So, and there, there will be a huge collaboration that is required to make that work, but that's
the, the space that I really, I think is interesting.
I think it's a really interesting space to play in.
And, um, there's a huge opportunity for collaboration in that space.
So it's, um, it's about going on a journey, which I'm on now to, to find the people that,
that I'm going to go on that journey with.
And how we can execute upon, um, the opportunities that live in, in those sort of shared spaces.
So, uh, it's a bit of a different answer because I think I've been lucky with who I've collaborated
with and it's, um, set me up with an opportunity to create some future collaborations with
those, with those two areas crossing over.
You, you've got my curiosity.
I did say final question, but my curiosity is going.
I, I, can you give me a little bit more sport, uh, development?
So, you know, is it social housing?
What?
Is it, uh, you know, a problem that needs to be solved for all of us, but, um, is there
some more clues you can give us as to how that might play out?
Oh, well, I, I believe in a value share model.
I believe that there's a particular part of the market that'll look at a value share model.
So that's being landowners in particular, some landowners that will say like, I will
stay in this project if I can see a share of this project do some good.
So that's, that's the sort of value share element.
And that, and so that could, you know, that could play out in social.
Good back in the housing area or good back in the, yeah.
Yeah.
That could, that could, that could be social affordable housing, or that could be community
infrastructure.
That could be anything, right?
Anything that can have an impact.
Yeah.
And that might have been impacted a local, regional, national, international level, right?
Like you can, you can, you can choose your course, but the hypothesis is if a project
goes well, the investment should get a fair return.
Yeah.
If the market moves and a project goes well and you get a crazy super profit, maybe we
can reinvest some of that into, into community is the, is the underlying philosophy that
I, I.
I see.
And I believe there are other landowners and, and businesses that would, would have a similar
view.
And so it's that, it's that profit for purpose model applied to property.
And I'm just interested in, you know, I see, I see sports opportunities around the place
where, you know, where you can integrate sport and movement into, into housing and community
projects.
And yeah, that's something I find really interesting and want to explore wherever I can.
And what a brilliant project.
And given your mindset and your sense of purpose and your ability to execute a plan, I, I'm
fascinated, Steve.
I'd love to sit down in a, you know, another period of time and, and track that with great
interest.
And I love that you're applying your, your brilliant mind to it because both our love
of sport and we know what that does to, to, you know, and it's already there in community.
We know it's a big part of it, but I'm sure to integrate in a way that you're talking
about will be fascinating.
Steve, I've loved sitting down with you.
Always enjoy, as I said from the start.
Anytime to catch up with you always makes me smile.
Congratulations on everything that you're doing.
And I really appreciate you sharing some of your wisdom today.
Thanks very much.
Appreciate being on and thanks for running this podcast.
It's been fun.
Thank you for listening to the empowering leaders podcast powered by temper, a mattress
like no other.
And to make sure you don't miss an episode, click subscribe wherever you get your podcasts.