Valerie Condos-Field was awarded the Pac-12 US College Coach of the Century despite nearly
quitting two years into her career. She shares the great story of how she transformed her approach
completely. They asked me for a team meeting and I was like oh I love team meetings yeah let's
let's talk. One by one they went around the room and they gave me examples that were absolutely
true of how my coaching style was hurtful and demeaning. It made them feel less less than but
I remember sitting there and just willing myself my brain to be still so I could really hear them.
Intriguing to hear how one of the most successful coaches in US college history
explained that the focus was never on winning. Her coaching mantra became to develop champions
in life through sport. You are helping this person continue to make
these micro moment changes and decision and choices in their lives which are helping them
transform into a greater version of themselves. You'll also hear Valerie Condos-Field talk about
the legendary Simone Biles a once in a lifetime athlete. She was gifted and born with the perfect
physique and physiological attributes to do the sport of gymnastics. She will go down as the goat
before this last Olympic but she did
because she could and she wanted to experience it with a different mindset. It's people like
Valerie Condos that inspire the work we do at Alita. We're passionate about bringing together
people from diverse backgrounds from around the globe in groups of five or six to learn to connect
and to collaborate. Head to alitacollective.com book a discovery call today we'd love to chat to
you. Thanks as always to Jason Nicholas and his team from Tepper Bedding. NASA approved world's
best in bedding a mattress like no other. Valerie Condos-Field is a US college coach
voted as the packed world coach of the century a UCLA coaching hall of famer a seven-time national
champion across a remarkable 29 years as the head gymnastic coach at UCLA despite having no
background at all in the sport of gymnastics. Her TED talk why winning doesn't always equal success
has been viewed more than four million times renowned for her extraordinary leadership and
her coaching mantra to develop champions in life through sport. Valerie it's a great pleasure to
meet you today thanks for joining me. Thank you Luke so much.
I appreciate it. It's an extraordinary life that you've lived and when you listen to
some of those achievements back that I just read out what are you proud of most? All of it honestly
it never ceases to amaze me how it all like how did it all happen and I know how it happened
because I speak about it all the time but when I think about I had my entire adult career in the
world of athletics and I did not grow up in the world of athletics and then I was able to achieve
sustained success for three decades. I literally sometimes just shake my hand and go how did that
happen but then because I speak about it and I teach you about it so much I know how it happened.
Can we go back to the first few years as coach and you describe yourself as tough and testy and at
times maybe even nasty. You were close to giving it all away. Can you tell us about that time?
I was asked to be the head coach in the late 80s and this was the time when
in my mind a leader a strong leader had all the answers didn't have to ask anybody for their
opinion it was black and white and as a coach if you don't like it go find another team
and I felt that if I showed any signs of weakness meaning humility vulnerability
even an apology as to what I didn't know that I wouldn't have the command that I needed as a head
and so I literally just acted like what I thought a head coach should be and thankfully we did
absolutely horribly as a team. And Valerie that was the generation really I grew up playing
professional sport in that era where your coaches did crazy things they said crazy things to you
and if you couldn't cope bad luck someone else can and there was no other way really and so I
think that's what's remarkable about your story is that you did completely change paradise.
find a way and it took a number of your students and your athletes to come to you and sit you down
and say we don't like our sport under you as coach that's pretty confronting day can you tell us about
how that unfolded? Yeah I remember that so clearly they asked me for a team meeting and I was like
oh I love team meetings yeah let's let's talk and one by one they went around the room and they gave
me examples that were absolutely true of how my coaching style was hurtful
and demeaning and it made them feel less less than it didn't support them and they would say
to me I mean this was like 1991 maybe 92 but I I remember it so clearly because
oh I'm just tapping into something right now I talk about quite often the importance as a leader
to hone your listening skill and I think one reason why I remember it so clearly
is because I remember sitting in that room and willing myself to be still
and to really stop the the dialogue in my brain of all of my excuses as to why I did this and
I never said it like that and but you did that which is why I had to say that but I remember
sitting there and just willing myself my brain to be still so I could really hear them thank you for
this I just haven't thought about that before it was very very clear to me okay what do I want
them to feel less than do I want to be pushing them down these young vibrant talented smart
women no so either figure it out figure out a different way or quit and let somebody else do it
and then it takes incredible skill and will to change paradigm and a lot of people have that
and think you know I should do this a better way but then under pressure we go back to
our old habits and I suppose that is the intersection of your incredible friendship
as it turned out with the legendary coach John Wooden and for the audience that don't know about
coach Wooden won 10 national basketball championships in 12 seasons
seven in a row no other team had won more than four in a row or never has
before or since he won an incredible 88 consecutive games as as coach but he became an incredible
mentor for you can you tell me what you think about that and what do you think about that
tell everyone about how that came about well it came about because I was I had not met coach
Wooden yet and I was on my way to resign and I was walking through our student union and walking
through the bookstore I happened upon a book of coach Wooden his leadership book and I just
literally opened it up like this and it opened up to his definition of success and I thought well
you know what he won 10 national championships he was hailed as the greatest
coach of any sport that ever lived what does he say about winning and I read success is peace of
mind and knowing that you've done your best and I kept flipping through the pages because I was like
this made no sense to me this is like a Hallmark card success is peace of mind and knowing you've
done your best oh that's nice and I thought where is he going to talk about winning coaches are
hired to win we're not hired to be mentors or
second moms or dads or your pal we're hired to win so he must talk about winning and I kept going
through the pages and like I kept coming back to his definition of success and when I read it
enough times and read it slowly success is peace of mind and knowing you have done your best I've
had the biggest aha moment of my professional career I had not been trying to be my
best coach I had not been trying to be my best coach I had not been trying to be my best coach
I had been trying to be somebody else and I started connecting all the proverbial dots
whenever you try to be somebody else you will always be a second right them I will never be
as good as somebody being them as they are being them and what I learned later on in my years when
I tried to be coach wooden that was equally as bad because I was never going to be as good as
coach wouldn't being coach wouldn't and the worst part that happens is when you try to be somebody
else or even like somebody else you're not going to be as good as somebody else you're not going to
like somebody else it prevents you from truly developing into a first-rate you and so I didn't
resign I went back to my office and I thought what do I bring to the table as a head coach
of a UCLA gymnastics team and our sport is called artistic gymnastics
I grew up in the world of ballet there was a lot of
points that I didn't know I didn't know how to do it I didn't know how to do it I didn't know how to do it
I didn't know how to do it I didn't know how to do it I didn't know how to do it I didn't know how to do it
given to artistry in our sport what do I bring well you know what I can teach the artistry and
movement quality and choreograph better than anybody else that's coaching gymnastics in this
country I'm going to do that so that was the technical for me and then I had to start thinking
about though the bigger picture was I just really did not buy into this world of athletics where
it was all about winning
because it seemed really silly to me that athletics was all about being able to say haha
we beat you haha I beat you today haha my team's better than your team it's like how many gazillions
of dollars are spent every year in athletics there has to be more to athletics than haha we
beat you so what is that and then it became really clear once I got the noise out of haha we beat you
and winning winning winning then I understood
understood, athletics is a master class in teaching really, really, really tough life
lessons you don't learn in a classroom. Athletics teaches us about resilience and perseverance and
how to fall and get back up. Athletics teaches us about being a part of a team, something greater
than yourself. Athletics teaches you all those things you do not learn in math and English and
history and science. And I was like, oh my gosh, I could do this. I'm going to help my student
athletes become champions in life through sport. And my classroom is the gym. And I went, I remember
going to my athletic director and I remember saying, okay, I got this, but I'm not focusing
on winning. I'm going to focus on developing every single one of my student athletes into the best
superhuman superhero they can be. And because I was at UCLA and because I could recruit talent,
I knew that that would
translate to the competition floor. And then guess what? It did. And we started winning.
It's such a brilliant, clear mission, isn't it? Create champions in life through sport.
It makes perfect sense when you say it. And then the success flowed from there. And I encourage
everyone, if you haven't listened to Valerie's TED Talk, go and do it. It's brilliant. And the
title is Why Winning Doesn't Always Equal Success. You gave a really great answer of that. Can you
maybe lean on that a little bit more of why winning doesn't always equal success?
There is much more to it than just reading out the highlights at the end,
the seven-time national champion. Can you tell us why there's more meaning behind it?
Because winning is finite. Winning is one moment. Winning is a ring. Winning is a trophy. Winning is
that moment in time. But it's everything that you develop to be able to achieve that success
that lasts beyond the win. And so when you truly are thinking,
of your adventure in becoming the best athlete that you can be, you're developing all of those
traits and characteristics that I just listed for you. And when you stop playing, you still carry
those into everything you do in life, into your family, into your next job, into whatever you want
to do. Those characteristics don't leave you just because you're no longer an athlete or a coach.
It was really fun for me to keep,
connecting these dots and realizing that if I'm going to choose to coach this way,
to teach gymnastics and coach and motivate this way, I had to walk my tongue. Because you can't
help someone develop into a better version of themselves by dictating orders. You have to figure
out how to motivate them to want to get that 1% better each day, to want to see the goal. Even if
we've won a national championship,
how can we do it better? Tomorrow, not waiting for the next national championship, but tomorrow.
And when you do that, you start instilling all of those traits and strengths into yourself and
you become a champion in life yourself. I love you use the word dictate there and
a line of yours that I really love. You can dictate your way to a win or a championship,
but you can't dictate your way to success. Can you break that down for us more? Because
it really rings true. Yeah.
I'm sure that you and your listeners have heard the buzzwords nowadays, transactional versus
transformational leadership. And a transactional leader, parent, coach, teacher, someone who is,
has influence, a leader is simply someone who has influence over another human being.
And a transactional leader is, if you do this, the transaction will be, then you'll get that.
If you hit the home run, then you're going to get the pound back. If you strike out,
you will maybe ignored when you get in the dugout. That is transactional. And it's,
and it's very evident with a lot of parenting as well. That is dictating. That is authoritative
dictatorship. You are holding the power over this person. And they often, as we know this in sport,
too many times, the athlete is focusing on pleasing the coach instead of figuring out,
how to get better mentally, emotionally, and physically. And the converse of that,
as we say, is transformational leadership. And it's exactly what it sounds like.
Like you think of a transformer and as a coach, you are helping this person continue
to make these micro moment changes and decision and choices in their lives,
which are helping them transform into a greater version of themselves. In fact,
later on in my career,
someone would ask me, I remember being on airplanes and people would say, Oh,
what do you do for a living? Or do you work or whatever? And I'd say, yeah, I, I develop
superheroes and they would say, Oh, you work in Hollywood. And I go, no, I work near Hollywood,
but I help young women transform into these superheroes. Cause when you think about a
superhero, superhero, isn't jumping over buildings for bribing rights. That man's not
jumping over buildings and say,
aha, Superman, I beat you. They're doing it to help the world be a better place. And that was my
goal with our student athletes. So the challenge was how to motivate them to want to make different
choices in their lives. Valerie, one of my favorite sayings is success without fulfillment
is the ultimate failure. And do you subscribe to this winning coaches of one championships? And
you know, we see that in our part of the world in Australia, but what's left is broken relationships.
And dysfunction at the end, would you say even with the premierships and the championships that
doesn't equal success? A hundred percent. And that is, that is the underlying theme through my entire
TED talk. When you think about sport, when you think about business, so many of us around the
world, we have embraced this win at all costs culture. And when you do that, you can win.
You can make a lot of money.
But when you embrace that win at all costs culture philosophy, there are casualties. And the
casualty isn't a loss. The casualty isn't loss of money. The casualty are humans, mentally,
emotionally, and sometimes physically. That's a daunting responsibility to accept. But if you
don't accept it, you're burying your head in the sand. And all you're focusing on is your ego and
the end result. To be able to say, ha ha, I won. Ha ha, I beat you. Ha ha, my company made more
money than your company.
Valerie, we, um, we talk about parenting a lot in these conversations. You mentioned it. I see a
generation of parents now obsessed with their kids winning. What advice would you give to them?
A lot. Whenever I'm asked to speak with young adults, you know, gymnasts and all that, I said,
I'll do it all on condition parents are there. Because if we're just talking to the child about
not focusing on winning, but you're going home and the parents are just in your ear constantly,
and all they're doing is focusing on winning, the child doesn't have a chance. Um, I'm sure
you've heard this statistic that 95% of children decide to leave their sport on the car ride home
because they're enclosed in this little metal box.
And they can't get away from the questions. And one of my most favorite people to listen to on
podcasts and her books is, um, her name is Dr. Shefali.
Yeah, I did a podcast with Dr. Shefali, uh, Ms. Fowle. And, um, I encourage people to go back
at the conscious parenting expert and, and, and her language in this is brilliant, isn't it?
Is why overlay on your kids, something you didn't achieve yourself and trying to live
that vicariously through your own kids and the damage that's done.
And you mentioned the conversation in the car. I'm obsessed with that, isn't it? That opportunity
to literally, you know, destroy your kids, love the sport on the way home by comparing them
to someone else. Why didn't you play more like Simone Biles? Why didn't you achieve more? Or
the answer is we just love watching you play. We just love being there for you effectively. And
it's a, it's a great conversation. It's through all your leadership is that that's probably feels
like that's been the cornerstone of it. Yes. When I gave my TED talk in part of my TED talk,
as a parent, you'll know if you're focusing on the end result, or if you're really, truly focusing
on helping your child become the best version of themselves by the questions you ask them.
And I said, if you're asking questions about the end result, like, did you get an A? How many points
did you score? Did you win? You, you'll know you're really not truly interested in helping
them become the best version of themselves. And after my TED talk, I had a woman come up to me
and she said, Ms. Fowle.
I have to tell you, I am a stereotypical tiger mom. I was like, okay, well, your words, not my
words. Okay. And she said, when you were sending this, do you ask your kids about their grades?
And if they won, I was nodding my head because I was so proud of myself. And then I realized
that's not what I should be asking my kids. I said, you know what? Good for you. Good for you
for listening and processing. And she says, I'm going to ask my children different questions from
now on. I said, great. Good for you.
It's a profound thing is a real passion of mine with our four kids. And you're watching
just the obsessive nature of junior sport and the kids always get it right. The kids
totally understand their fair. They like to win, but at the end they move on really quickly. It's
their parents that hang on to, to, to this. And, and, you know, as you said, the statistics are
95% of kids lose their love of sport because of the conversation in the car with their parents. So
Simone Biles has transcended your sport in a way that is hard to imagine. I know you've got a
incredibly close relationship. You've produced and choreographed her tour. I believe coming up,
can you tell us a bit about her and, and yeah, that once in a lifetime type of athlete that
comes along? She is the once in a lifetime type of athlete. And part of it is she was gifted and
born with the perfect physique and physiological.
Attributes to do the sport of gymnastics. Not just physically, muscularly, but mentally as well
to be able to calculate two flips and three twists and know where she is in the air and all of that.
What I love, first of all, I recruited Simone to UCLA and she actually signed a national letter
of intent with us. And then she went pro. And so she said something in these last Olympics
that had NIL been around, she would have competed at UCLA for me. And I was like,
dang her to my heart.
Seven national champs would have become 10 national championships. Winning, winning, winning,
right? But what I love about her journey, and I love sharing with people, is she's not just a
one-hit wonder. It's not like she just won the all-around title in 2016 or 2021. She went through,
as we all know, a full mental shift with what we call in our sport twisties.
She has been really doing a deep dive with her therapist. They use to retrain your brain.
And when we first started rehearsals for the Golden America Tour and we were on a break,
I said, Simone, I am fascinated by this. Because you light up when you talk about
your therapist and counseling. And what is it that really has resonated with you?
Because you are different than you were four years ago. And she said, you know, Ms. Fowle,
she says, it's not just going through the gymnastic skills with this. She says,
but there is the process of just uncovering the layers of the trauma. And one layer after another,
after another. And she says, it sounds like it would have been frightening, but it wasn't.
It released me of all this pent-up tension that I've had for so many years. And for her to be
able to share that with the world, she didn't have to do another Olympic Games. She,
who is already the best in the world, she will go down as the GOAT before this last Olympics.
But she did because, A, she could, and she wanted to experience it with a different mindset.
Amazing story, isn't it? And as you said, an athlete that has taken your sport to levels
very few thought was probably possible. And it would be hard to match that again.
I love these conversations with people with unique backgrounds like yours. And we see
these patterns of what makes great leaders. And yours is an incredible leadership story.
Starting with self-leadership, I want to ask the question, what is one way that you fill up your
own cup so that you can be the person you want to be? That's a really great question.
I retired when I was 60. And so I think what a lot of us experience, if we thankfully live this long,
is you have a career. I had a career that was very structured. And so I didn't really have
to think about and plan my day, really. It was planned for me. And then I retired,
and even though I do a lot of speaking and a lot of teaching and a lot of this,
it's not structured. And I noticed the first few years that I was retired, it wasn't just
that I didn't have this identity anymore as the head coach of UCLA Gymnastics,
but I didn't have a structure. And so I was sleeping in late. I wasn't getting things done
during the day. And I was procrastinating. And I literally would just kind of walk by my bed and go,
I'm just going to lay down for a little bit. And I was in this lull, like this sadness and
state of depression, it felt like. And I just told, I coached myself up. And I was like, okay,
walk your talk here. What would you say to someone that told you this? And I'd say,
well, the first thing I would say is the night before, figure out your schedule for tomorrow.
The second thing I would tell myself is before you get out of bed, I want you to enumerate,
three things that you're really grateful for, to get yourself motivated for the day.
And then don't wait to be motivated, but just be disciplined to follow your schedule.
And part of that schedule is allotting time in that schedule for stillness.
Because a lot of what I'm doing is creatively, choreographing, writing another book,
speaking engagements. When I do a speaking engagement,
I will tell myself, I'm going to do this, I'm going to do that. And I'm going to do that.
To the company whom I'm speaking for. And that takes stillness. And that's something that I think
that we're really lacking in our society now. And it's something that we have to be extremely
intentional with to get in our days. I love speaking with 20 something year olds. And when
I ask them, how many of you scroll through social media through the day? They go, all the hands go
up. I go, how many of you?
And probably too much time scrolling through social. All their hands go up. How many of you
are scrolling through social media to numb out? Their hands go up. And then I start asking,
what are you needing to numb out from? The stresses of their days. Stresses of school,
stresses of friendships, stresses of social media, stresses of sport, stress, stress,
stress. I said, you have all this stress in your brain that you need to numb out,
from. And by scrolling through social media, you're putting more stuff in your brain.
That makes sense. And they just kind of look at me like, oh, yeah. I said, so hold up your phone.
Just hold your phone up. And they all hold up their phone. I said, okay, open your hand. And
they're like, I'm not opening my hand. My phone will drop. I'm like, exactly. Your phone is not
attached to you. You're attached to your phone. It's a choice.
And I think the, the, uh,
stillness that you described there, the pattern I think of the people I speak to the most is they
have some sort of practice in that space. You called it stillness and others, mindfulness or
meditation. But most people who, who work it out have got some part of that. And as you said,
particularly with the distraction of having that in our hand attached to us all the time,
that seems more and more relevant than ever. What is one thing that's always worked for you
as a leader that you would never change? Love. Uh,
want to just have a really strong conversation with someone and just say, what the hell do you
think you're doing? Thankfully, I have grown to the point where I don't allow myself, myself to
speak from a place of emotion and I will back off and I will think about the situation from a place
of love and empathy and compassion. And that, how can I help?
This person. And through that point of love, understanding that quite often it, what's
happening on the surface, isn't the issue. It's what's happening below the surface. And we don't
know someone else's story. We don't know their trauma. We don't know their triggers. We don't
know their history, but in any moment of the day, those things can be triggered. And for me to,
to suppose that I know,
know what someone else is going through is very arrogant. And so I, I don't do that. I'm very proud
that I don't do that. And I can call myself down to a place of coming from a place of love. And
you know, there's the, the, the term of tough love. I don't like the term tough, but I just
feel like, like honesty to be able to, to ask permission of someone and just say, I want to
have a hard conversation with you. And I'm asking your permission to be a hundred percent honest.
With you. And once you have that agreement, that's when the magic happens. That's when you
really start getting to the heart of the problem. Um, when I was asking some of our student athletes
about like the last few years of my career at UCLA, and what are the things that they really
remember about our culture that was developed at UCLA gymnastics, they all will say the one thing
that they practiced and learned. And that's when you really start getting to the heart of the problem.
And I would tell them, I said, you know, if you're not being a hundred percent honest with someone,
you're not being respectful because basically what you're saying is you're not strong enough
to handle the truth and to ask permission, to be that honest. And sometimes I would have an
athlete saying, Ms. Fell, not today. I just, I can't handle it today. And I'd say, totally
understand. Come by my office or let's go to coffee when, when you do want to talk about this.
Yeah. Beautiful answer. Um, we, we see people that have success, like you've had, uh, sustained
success over decades of a, of a really clear vision. I want to ask you a question. Has there
been a visionary leader in your life that, uh, you felt compelled to follow their, their vision?
Yes. Coach Wooden and my husband, Bobby Field was our defensive coordinator for football at UCLA.
And he's very, very, very much like John Wooden. When we first started dating,
so coach,
Wooden, my husband, they're kind of like this. Okay. They don't drink. They don't swear. They
don't get really hyper emotional a little bit. And when I first started dating Bobby,
he gave me a little flip a paper that said, be quick to listen, slow to speak and slow to anger.
It's just like on our second date. I was like, wow. Okay. Um, but as I said earlier,
part of what I did that wasn't good is I felt that I couldn't, I wasn't going to be a good person
if I didn't act like my husband did. And I talked to him about this at one point and he said, no,
no, no, no, no, no. You be you. I'm going to be me. You be you. And you're fiery and you're feisty
and you're all of that. It's just, you get yourself in trouble. Me, I get myself in trouble when I
cross the line.
To making it personal with someone. And so I looked back on my coaching career
and I can be honest and forthcoming and fiery and feisty and in your face, as long as it is
instructional. When it crosses the line to being personal, that's when it was not.
A college romance that, uh, that turned into a lifelong marriage. A great story. That's a
brave thing on a second date to say, be quick to listen, slow to speak. He's a,
he's a braver man than most. And for that to have landed well, that's a, that's a great story. I
love, um, thanks for sharing that. Curiosity is a word that we hear all the time in successful
leaders. How do you carve out time to be curious and how do you go about integrating that into
your life and your, your journey? Oh gosh, almost every moment of the day.
And I think that was part of my success when I decided to change my coaching style,
which was about, I don't know, two years into my being a head coach.
I had to ask a hundred questions a day because I knew nothing about gymnastics.
And so what we learned and what I've learned since is that one of the best ways to teach someone
is to give them a little bit of instruction and then let them quote unquote fail and just ask
them questions. How are you feeling? What were you thinking before? What, what do you think you
should do differently this next time? And I remember a student athlete,
you know, on balance fame and they'd fall and they'd come up to me. They'd say,
Ms. Val, what'd I do wrong? I'm like, I have no idea. Let's figure this out.
What were you thinking before? Let's watch the video. And I would learn along the way.
I think it was just enforced because I said I knew nothing. I am also an extremely curious person.
I want to read every single leadership book on the planet before I die. I love asking questions.
I have no problem.
I subscribe to the fact that there's no dumb or ignorant question. And so I have no problem
humbling myself to say, I have no clue what to do, or I don't know what you're talking about.
And it, as a coach, think about this. You know that you're going to have a successful season
when the team takes ownership of the team. Well, the best way to do that is to ask them
a hundred questions about their team culture, their team philosophy,
about team accountability, about team agreements. What are those going to look and sound like and
feel like? And get them in it instead of dictating them what the rules and the guidelines are going
to be. So back when I was coaching, the first day that everybody met, we would go over the
student athlete handbook, which were the rules and the guidelines. And if I were coaching today,
I would not use the word rules. I would really use
guidelines and agreements or standards, guidelines and agreements so that it is an
agreement and not a rule. Makes perfect sense. Has there been
an example of great collaboration in your life? Yeah. I love to collaborate. I love to collaborate
in everything I do. When I was coaching, I was very, very lucky to have an athletic department,
an athletic director that allowed me to go choreograph for a Sea World San Diego every year.
So the month of May, I would go down to San Diego and I choreographed their summer shows
that were like Cirque du Soleil type of shows. And early on, I didn't have to learn this. This
is just kind of like what I knew. I would be choreographing and the facility guys would be
walking behind me. And I'd say, hold on, come here. Okay, you guys, performers, do the first
thing I taught you. Okay. Then do the next thing that I just changed. Which do you like better?
And it sounds like a weird collaboration, but it was clear to me that I needed to craft something
that was going to be appealing, not to somebody who had two decades of dance experience behind
him, but to the common folk. And so I collaborate with everyone and I love to collaborate and I
hate, hate to craft things by myself. Yeah. Brilliant answer. And I love
hearing that story. Communication is probably the thing we most commonly hear from people,
that they're really understanding of how important that is in any leadership environment.
Have you had a mantra when it comes to how you've communicated in your roles?
Yeah. The most important communication skill to hone is listening. And I had a sports psychologist
at UCLA who, when we were talking about this, put the word listen up on the board. And then
he said, the secret to being a good listener is, the secret is in this word, just rearrange the
letters. And so when you rearrange the letters, it's spelled listen, it spells silent. And whenever
I share that with people, they go, oh, wow. But to truly listen, I think it's one of the greatest
gifts that we can give another human being. But when most of us are listening, pretending like
we're listening, we're thinking about what we're going to say next. And I don't think, I know,
it takes practice. Once again, the word stillness,
to get still so that you're able to truly listen with all of your senses, not just audibly. But
how are they saying it? What do they look like? What are their mannerisms? What's the energy
they're giving off? That's how you truly listen. And that is the most important communication skill
to have. Because if you're not listening, then it's just a one-way dialogue. Then you're just
waiting for that person to shut up so you can keep talking. It's a great description.
I love the detail you went into there. Because you can truly tell when someone's listening,
can't you? You know it instinctively. You can almost feel their brain ticking over,
waiting to interrupt you or someone. And even sitting across from you, you can just see you're
an intent listener. You just have got that practice. And I suppose it is a practice.
Valerie, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
My mother. My mother. Yeah. She was extremely compassionate. And I love,
I love the understanding, the difference between empathy and compassion. And empathy is when you
feel something with someone, but compassion is when you put an action to it. And so my mother
was extremely empathetic to everyone she met, but there was always an action for it that was very
compassionate. Yeah. Beautiful to hear. And I love it when someone has a family member or a parent
in their life and that immediately comes to mind. We're a bit obsessed with collaboration and
bringing,
great leaders together around the globe in what we do in our space and different thinking.
Has there been someone, and you've been able to collaborate with the legendary Coach Wooden and
your husband and Bobby and what he did, but have you thought, you know, Simone Biles in your recent
collaboration, but has there been someone you thought, God, I'd love to connect or collaborate
with them in any one of the passions in your life? Absolutely. I love the psychologist,
Michael Gervais. He's got a podcast and I bring,
I'm in and speak to my class all the time. I love collaborating with the director that
wrote and directed the Gold Over America tour. His name is Mark Swanhart. He goes by Swanee,
but he just has a different gift than I have. But to be able to bring his vision to life
through movement choreographically for this tour, I love collaborating with, when I first got the job
as the head coach, I was a coach. I was a coach. I was a coach. I was a coach. I was a coach. I was a coach.
I was a coach. I was a coach. I was a coach. I was a coach. I was a coach. I was a coach. I was a coach. I was a coach.
I called the other three head coaches around the country that had won national championships
and who were consistently putting 10,000 people in their arenas. And that was Suzanne Yoffin at
University of Georgia, Sarah Patterson at Alabama, and Greg Marston at the University of Utah.
And I just pick their brains constantly. I would love to collaborate with Bren Brown.
I would love to collaborate with Jay Shetty.
I would love to collect a lot you just name them I'm there I love I love hearing that and that's
fascinating so you direct competitors the people that you were going to compete against you rang
and asked how to create the success and they're open to sharing 100% all three of them literally
they opened their playbook to me it was truly truly remarkable and I do the same now there's
about five or six head coaches around the country that I'm mentoring and they you know I don't share
each other's secrets but it's like yes and and that's why it's so funny I just had a friend today
tell me are you gonna slow down I was like no no I'm not I will die then I'll slow down but I've
had so much fun at what I've done and I've made so many mistakes and I've learned so much through it
and I'm a consistent
learner and student of life and of leadership and all that I want to help as as those people
help me my learning curve be shorter I want to help somebody else's learning curve be shorter
if I can and the collaborative part of humanity is I mean that's just what we all should be doing
and you look back at what you achieve developing champions in life through sport is as good a
mission as you can and
And I love the definition of success, redefining what success means.
The trophies are there.
The championships are there.
But the impact on people's lives is such a great story to hear.
And I'm sure many people will be empowered by what you've been able to share today.
So thanks, Valerie.
I really appreciate you joining me.
Thank you.
And, you know, Luke, yes, I have a lot of trinkets.
I have rings.
I'm in the Hall of Fame.
But that's because I worked at UCLA.
That's because Coach Wooden always used to say, you can't win without talent.
And so I was able to attract and recruit talent.
But there are thousands of coaches that are just as fabulous and impactful and successful as I have been that don't have one ring.
But that doesn't mean that they haven't been successful in helping young people develop into champions in life.
And you don't need the ring to substantiate that.
All you need, truly, is an athlete, a student.
And at some point, you'll be able to say thank you.
Great note to finish on.
It's been a great privilege to spend some time with you.
Thanks, Valerie.
Appreciate it.
Thank you, Luke, so much.
I appreciate it.
Thanks for listening to another episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Huge thanks, as always, to our great friends at Tempa.
And we encourage you to check out our Leader Connect program.
New episodes are out every Wednesday morning at 6 a.m.