I'm sure you're going to love this story.
Vanessa Ford is an extraordinary individual in every possible way.
She in many ways to me is the real life version of the animated superhero she created, Super
Sema, an African superhero whose superpowers of science and technology and using her brilliant
mind are inspiring millions of young black boys and girls around the globe who for generations
have grown up not seeing someone who looks like them on TV.
Vanessa explains how important it has been for her embracing, in her own words, her incredible
big Afro hair and the story behind what that means for so many African women.
You'll also hear her talk about the support of Serena and Venus Williams and Oprah Winfrey
behind the scenes and investing in the world in which she operates.
The experience of being a young woman of colour working in the entertainment industry directly
for Harvey Weinstein.
I sincerely encourage you to listen to this.
This episode from Vanessa Ford.
She's a remarkable person who's changing the world for good.
We are really privileged to have Vanessa as part of our Alita Connect world.
She is collaborating with a diverse range of people around the globe.
It is a great privilege for us to have people like Vanessa Ford in our Alita Connect program.
We'd love you to check it out.
Head to alitacollective.com, book a discovery call and form your own group of five or six
people.
We'll talk to you about that anytime.
Huge thanks as always to Jason Nicholas and his team from Temper, Australia.
The world's best.
The best in bedding.
We spend a third of our life for sleep and Temper is a mattress like no other.
I encourage you to check it out today.
Vanessa Ford is literally changing the world.
Originally from Jamaica and raised in Canada, her professional career started as a fashion
model at 14 years of age, appearing in music videos, commercials and catwalks around the
world.
She studied biology at the University of Toronto, going on to complete a master's degree in
tropical medicine at Oxford University in the UK.
Vanessa had a stint at the Weinstein Company.
Alongside the likes of Quentin Tarantino and Nicole Kidman, she also worked as a producer
with Bob Marley's sons, Rowan and Ziggy, on the documentary, The Marley African Road Trip.
Vanessa is currently the Chief Operating Officer of Kukua.
And you know, I'd have to pick me up on that pronunciation, Vanessa, in a moment, because
I'm sure I haven't got that right.
A Kenyan-based education entertainment company that has a primarily female executive team.
Vanessa is the executive producer of the first African animated superhero series, Super
Senior.
Vanessa is a mother of three and manages her work between her home in Portugal and
Nairobi, Kenya.
What a remarkable and diverse life that you live, Vanessa.
It's great to see you today.
Wow.
What an intro.
Great to see you too, Luke.
Now, the pronunciation of your company, let me apologize on behalf of that.
Can you tell me?
Well, okay.
So it's pronounced Kukua.
Kukua is Swahili for to grow.
And also, Senma is Swahili for to speak up.
So we named our kind of chief, our number one character off of this idea of a little
girl who always speaks up, speaks her mind, never dilutes what she wants to say, is always
standing up for her friends.
And that was the kind of the thought process behind that.
Can't wait to delve into that.
Can't wait to delve into that more.
It's just a remarkable story of success and what you're doing.
As I said, it's literally changing the world.
But I might go back to the start a little bit.
14 years of age, it's young to travel the world and take on a modeling career.
Do you look fondly back at that chapter and has it helped you in your current life today?
Definitely.
I mean, I think it's been an absolutely unbelievable journey that I actually could not even have
dreamed for myself.
You know, being born and then raised in Toronto, but by parents.
Parents who both come from a small town in Treasure Beach, Jamaica, they came from
diametrically opposed backgrounds.
My mother is like a fashionista, ambitious corporate woman.
My dad is like a hippie, freestyle Jamaican guy, you know, and then falling in love and
having my sister and I.
And I think what was interesting about my experience growing up in Toronto, which is
the most multicultural city in the world, was that for me and most of my friends, I'm not
my own mom.
I think I was born and raised in Toronto, but my parents, my grandparents, my grandparents,
my cousins, my friends, we all had parents who were fresh off the boat from another
country.
So you were always like in between two very different worlds, you know, and you were
expected to speak both languages of those worlds to exist in both of those worlds, but
you never fully belong to either.
You know, that was a really important thing in a way for me to.
Almost.
Belong.
To myself.
14 you know everyone's like oh that's so young but actually I had already like prepared for that
you know going home entering the world where I smelled Jamaican food and hear patois and you know
and Bob Marley I'm playing on a record and then I'm going out to like oh literally opening the
doors to like snow and you know all these different cultures and I went to a French school
you know the only black kid in my in my class at the time so in a way that kind of prepared me
to kind of really be more independent be out on my own and you know studying at Oxford and getting
a university education I think I initially had wanted to just be on the runways and then eventually
do acting but with again with that Caribbean parenting you know it was all about the only
doctor lawyer and that you have to go to university so you know when I was thinking of
of going to Oxford I thought oh let me study what I know I'm good at which is and at the time the
HIV pandemic was really kind of at the tip of everyone's toes and so I thought you know I want
to I want to save the world let me learn more about global health epidemiology maybe be a doctor
in infectious diseases find a cure for HIV and then I was like oh my god I'm going to go to
HIV and then I ended up making a documentary in Kenya about a community of indigenous people
who are grappling with HIV as part of my thesis which made me think you know why should I work
in a hospital trying to change one patient's behavior at a time when I can tell this intimate
story about someone going through the same situation that not only inspires people to
change their behavior but can also
be shown to people all around the world and so so yeah I guess that documentary led to another
and then next thing you know I'm with Bob Marley's kids in South Africa traveling around on Ducati
bikes making a docu-series with the Discovery Channel and and then you know turned into
Weinstein Company working for a big major Hollywood studio
and then next thing you know I'm an entrepreneur working on three seasons making it to the cover
of Forbes Africa and being like one of the first black woman to be on the cover of Canada's biggest
magazine so I think the significance of these firsts and and also reading them in the headlines
also had a tremendous effect on my approach to like those leadership positions you've broken
your ground everywhere Vanessa when you you sum that up and it's as you said at the start it's a
remarkable diverse life and and there's a lot of drive in that isn't there to go and finish
tropical medicine and you're going to save the world from the HIV epidemic as it was at the time
and to have the the drive as you said maybe coming from the the Caribbean background I didn't realize
that's the thing is it that there's a bit of drive that comes out of families from that part of the
world I think it's just a bit of drive of the immigrant experience in general like moving to
a new country starting new starting a family especially
you know and I think my parents instilled that especially my mom she was like the definition of
a multi-hyphenate like she was working three different jobs she was you know antique dealing
she had a corporate job in the bank she was selling kids clothes on the weekend there was
always something happening and and I think I definitely there's this kind of survival instinct
that comes from the immigrant experience that I think you get a lot of that and I think it's
instilled naturally if you're if you're born in that because you know they come to a new country
that is totally different from their own and they want to not only assimilate but thrive and so
in a way you have to make those sacrifices and you have to yeah you have to find your your your
story in this new world that is that must be incredibly proud I want to I want to jump to
super sema and the animated series you've produced with incredible success I think it's been viewed
you know way more than 120 million times for African and black kids to see a superhero that
looks like them on tv is simply brilliant and then you've added the layer of science and technology
which is your background and and using your mind as a superpower again is incredible tell us about
the genesis of that and again you must be incredibly proud of the impact that's having
definitely I'm so proud and I'm you know having also three kids who are super sema's number one
fan also also helped um but yeah I think uh you know my journey with super sema started off
as many people do like when they become a parent you know I always wanted to be a mom someday I
just wasn't necessarily expecting it to be that day so early on in my career and I think when my
first son was born and I thought about really what do I want to give to this world and you
know, it makes you it was like a necessary shake up. And it really allowed me to reprioritize my
life in that sense. Whereas I used to be the person who would be, you know, the first on set
in the morning, and the last person to leave after midnight. Now I have something not only to go home
to, but having a baby, you know, that baby needs their mom. But here's something that people don't
really say enough is that actually, that like mom needs their babies too, right? And I feel like
when I became a mom, I was like, I actually want to be present. I want to be there. I don't want
to be jumping on a plane to Malaysia to save, you know, a production or, you know, putting out fires
and all of these different worldwide productions that we were working on in the time. And I
realized that actually, what can I do to give
this next generation, i.e. my own children, something that I never had. And I grew up,
you know, turning on the television, opening a magazine, and I never saw anyone with my color
skin, my big afro. I never had those, that opportunity to like, look at myself as a six
or seven year old, as a hero. You know, thankfully, I had a
I had a
I walked into my house and I had my mom, I had my aunt, I had Auntie Oprah on television. But those
were really the only role models I had. And then when I took the trajectory of science and biology
and physics, you know, I never had a teacher that looked like me. I was often and so I thought,
wow, what if this superhero was not only a little black girl, but what if she, her superpowers were
were the things that I think superpowers are, which is science, technology, engineering, arts, and math,
the whole STEAM framework. So I was just, I got really excited about this idea and about making
sure that this next generation of children would be watching and consuming things where that could
empower them. And I think as storytellers, we have that, yeah, we have that obligation to really
change the narrative. And I think that's what I'm trying to do. And I think that's what I'm trying to
do. And I think that's what I'm trying to do. And I think that's what I'm trying to do. Like, that's, like,
it's our agenda, we have we're given that position, we're given that platform, rather than just
putting out another thing that's already there. I felt SuperSama was like the culmination of all of
these different threads of my life as well coming together, you know, working still in the
entertainment space, being able to pull out my old Hollywood contacts to, you know, rope in, you
know, superstars like Lupita Nyong'o and getting them involved.
But yet, like being a mother, understanding the importance of education, understanding the
importance of entertaining education, like learning, but in a fun way. I felt like all of
these aspects really made me like was kind of the brainchild that SuperSama was born under. And then,
of course, I met Lucrezia, who is the CEO of Cuckoo, and she was making these characters in an app.
And then I met my cousin, who's a really nice guy who was kind of a big fan of me,
but also, you know, she was, like, you know, she was a really nice person, and she was kind of a
kind of a big fan of me. And then, of course, I met my cousin, who was the CEO of Cuckoo, who was
kind of like a big fan of me. And then, of course, I met my cousin, who was kind of a big fan of me.
And then, of course, I made my children into the kids that taught children how to read and write.
And then us joining forces, me with my own entertainment background, her with her kind of tech,
on a worldwide platform with the help of YouTube Originals, to have one of Africa's biggest stars,
Lupita Nyong'o, involved, that just became the recipe of success. And the timing was perfect.
We released it March 2021, just after kind of the Black Lives Matter movement happened. And that
was a really crucial moment because the whole world, you know, was looking at inclusion and
diversity in a different way. And we were already doing it for the last two years, but, and trying
to knock on all the doors and, and see who would open. So finally the world was ready to also
receive and digest a show like ours. So it was really, really exciting.
And there's so many brilliant parts to that, Vanessa, to jump into. And
you know, I look at mainstream TV now and everything's the same. It's reality TV and
I consume none of it. None of it has any interest. And there's very few things that are unique. And
what I love is not only have you done something that's right in your passion wheelhouse and
clearly about changing the world as you want it to be, but there's a massive,
massive audience for it. People are ready for, and that must be so fulfilling to
get success at that level, as well as do something so good.
Totally, totally. And I think, you know,
I always think of this Toni Morrison quote, and she says, you know,
freeing yourself is one thing, claiming ownership of that freed self was another,
bit by bit she had claimed herself. And I think of that quote often for me, because for me,
claiming is active. It's like an active word that describes the way you go through life.
You know, you can go through life positively accepting and being like passive and being used
as part of someone's vision and purpose, or you can really claim space to be who you are and go
through life according to your own agenda. And I think that being a black woman, and especially,
you know, when I was working in a more corporate structure, I think there's a certain amount of
going against the grain that you feel every day, even just being present, like particularly when
your goal is to be fully authentically true to yourself.
It does feel like you're claiming and reclaiming your space. And I think for me,
SuperSemma was a bit of that as well. You know, I think, yeah, I think the whole kind
of claiming culture, that term kind of came back into popular lexicon when Maxine Waters
very publicly in the hearings said, you know, I'm reclaiming my time and she kept repeating it.
And there was something so powerful about this older black woman within a judicial
system telling a room full of white men that, you know, I'm reclaiming my time.
So I think there's something about reclamation and claiming that felt very relevant and triumphant.
And yeah, I want that. And I want to do that. And I want to move through my life,
claiming and reclaiming what I think I deserve and what I want. And I think SuperSemma reflects
that decision and also to become an entrepreneur.
And to say no to other offers. You know, I could have transitioned from
one big Hollywood studio to another. And I really decided to say no because I felt like I would,
I didn't want to be owned or to be claimed. I wanted to do something for myself.
I wanted to do something for my family. I wanted to build that legacy.
And Vanessa, I think you've reclaimed your hair as well, from what I understand.
You've got the most extraordinary hair that I've ever seen.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
And is it true you used to spend hours just brushing it down and maybe conforming. And now
I think I read you say it's like a crown and it is an amazing Afro. It just seems I can't imagine
you without it. Tell us about that. Well, yes. I mean, first of all,
black girls and their hair, it's just a thing. We all grew up, especially 20 years ago,
the idea of like what was proper and good and not just like, yeah, I don't know, I'm just like,
just in society in general, but also in Caribbean and in many African American places, the idea of
like, you know, straight kind of pulled back, you know, quite Eurocentric features was, I mean,
that was the norm. And I remember fighting with my hair, sitting there, my mom combing, I would
cry, I would like, I wanted, you know, desperately to straighten it. And when I finally had this,
like, aha, you know, I remember going to interviews, and like, literally ironing my hair.
So at the time, I didn't, I couldn't even afford, like, a straight iron, my friends would sit there
and iron my hair for me. But this was also a big part of, you know,
not, how do I say, almost like not being seen, like, it was also a way, like, you didn't really
realize it. But in a way, it was kind of, it sounds a bit dramatic, but it's true. It's like,
you're aware that this is not just, it's a life force, but it's distracting. It tells something
about my history that maybe I don't want shown to the person that's interviewing me. It was really,
I think,
we wear a lot of masks. And I think, finally, letting my hair be free was also a reflection
of and like accepting it almost as my own superpower. My hair in a way is it's like my
calling card. It's like when I walk in a room, it's the thing that everyone reminds, you know,
remembers. You know, in a way, it was like, I knew that, like, my hair reflected my blackness,
and it's pure.
It's pure as form. I don't know, I wasn't sure if it was welcomed or understood, or respected in all
the rooms that I was in. And in a way, like me, allowing my hair to go natural, allowing it to be
big and beautiful and defy gravity, was me realizing also how to navigate these spaces
without compromising who I am.
It's an amazing story in itself, isn't it? When you describe it like that, and,
you know, you can't understand that coming from, you know, you look at me, I'm just happy to have
some hair. And I think, I look at you, and I just think it's, it's just amazing. You can never forget
Vanessa Ford, you know, how do you, you jump on the screen, and it's incredible, but not
understanding all that history that you explain that, you know, when you are the only black person
in a, in a room, or you work in a company where no one else looks like you, and you don't see
anyone else who looks like you. And what I love is that you've then put that onto the screen,
for hundreds of millions of people to see as a superpower, and you're living that, and it's cool.
What's even crazier, Luke, is that we obviously get a lot of fan mail, and comments, and on,
through our Instagram, and through our SuperSemma newsletter. What is so fascinating is that there
are literally hundreds of parents who have reached out to us who say, you know what,
after my child watched SuperSemma, they want to wear their hair natural.
After my child listened to, we have a song that's all about loving your hair. It goes,
I love my hair, I want to shout it out loud. And yeah, these moms and these dads are talking about
how their, their child has a whole new relationship with their hair, and with themselves, because
your hair becomes such a big part of your identity, and especially when you have, when it's
so big, it's almost becomes even, you know, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's,
bigger than, than you would think if your hair was straight. So I think, in a way, with SuperSemma,
that was also a very powerful thing that we weren't even directly addressing. It was totally
indirectly that we realized, wow, this is, this is like an interesting phenomenon, because SuperSemma
has her natural Afro hair. She has a couple braids in it, which is something that African women do
all the time. We're always switching up our, our styles.
And I think when the dolls came out, we also saw, you know, the SuperSemma dolls,
kids were untying her hair, and like rebraiding it, doing different buns, repurposing, you know,
and I think, I think that was really special, because the dolls also help children to like,
to then look at something else that they can play with every day. And they're like, wow,
SuperSemma has hair, just like mine, I can touch and I can feel it. And it's just like,
like mine. And listen, she's a superhero, you press that button, and she's like,
anything is possible. And I'm unstoppable. And, you know, it's very small things that
when you're six or seven, those, like, that really makes a difference. That really
makes that six or seven year old believe that they can grow up and be an astronaut and have an
head of Afro hair that will fit inside that helmet.
I love it, Vanessa. I want to change text.
I want to go back to something you mentioned before, you're working for one of the biggest
Hollywood studios. And, and you said you knock back opportunities to go to other ones. And now
you've got essentially a really strong female executive, and you're working out of Nairobi,
and you're doing all these incredible things at SuperSemma is and, and remarkable. But on the
other side, you work for the Weinstein organization, and we know, founded by Harvey Weinstein. And
we heard the horror stories that came out of that. And it really founded the Me Too movement. On that
part of, of where the world went from there, do you look back and think a young female in that
world? Was it as challenging as it sounded to be part of the entertainment industry as a young
female in that era?
Yeah, I think it was definitely challenging. I think there was so especially as a woman, in
general, I mean, adding a woman of color is a whole other layer. But being a woman in the world,
yeah, it was it was very intimidating. Given that I had these preparations,
of being very independent early on already traveling 1516. I think that gave me a different
perspective. But I remember walking into Harvey's office one day, and always feeling like you're
shapeshifting. So I remember walking into Harvey's office one day, and I felt like he was, you know,
you can you just know when it's not a good day. And thankfully, I worked in the London office. So
we were very far away. And I remember walking into the office one day, and I felt like he was,
you know, you can you just know when it's not a good day. And thankfully, I worked in the London
office. So we were very far away. But I would come to New York and LA every now and again and
walking into that office and, and just like my stomach turning and having to sit there and
present this whole kind of marketing plan for this new acquisition that we wanted to do that
you he definitely didn't want to do. It was almost like seeing yourself from above,
like an out of body experience in a way, but I just,
you know, I just put on like my badass, kind of female power boss mode and just said, you know,
I gotta give it everything I got. And I went in there. And all of his ooming and aahing and like,
no, Vanessa, no, Vanessa turned like, I walked out of there with a yes, let's just put it that way.
And it was like, that was like an everyday thing. You know, and I think it also made you reach out
and create this like,
support system.
support network of other women, especially other black women who are not necessarily
at the Weinstein company, but who are in other positions of power in the entertainment space.
And we created our own, we call it like the C-suites of like black female, like mentorship.
And we had our own dinners and we would, we would go out the same way how, you know,
no offense to you, Luke, but white men would go out on the golf course for centuries making deals
and like, you know, shooting around and chit-chatting and talking and kind of coaching
each other along in the business world. We had our own version of that in the kind of black
entertainment corporate space. And I think without that, I don't know if I could have,
I don't know if I could have, I don't know if I could have, I don't know if I could have
a really strong support system that really helped me to navigate those spaces. And I think right now
the entertainment space is a really interesting disrupted space. It really makes me excited to
be a part of the conversation because truthfully, I'm not interested in Hollywood for Hollywood's
sake. I've never been a capital F film head. Like I didn't go study film. I don't have,
the right last name or a trust fund. You know, I stumbled, I stumbled my way into film because I
really wanted to make a difference in the world by telling stories. My first documentary, which
actually was supposed to be a sidekick to my thesis, you know, ended up kind of kick-starting
this whole career. And then, you know, at my first job working at the Weinstein company,
the only opportunity there was to be a book scout. And I was like, yes, yes, yes, I'll do it. I'll do
it. And then I moved on to,
you know, I started working as a creative executive and head of productions and acquisitions.
You know, but when you look at my career, I think the red line has always been finding ways to make
what seems frivolous or superficial, like to infuse those conversations with depth and substance
and to connect it back to what is actually happening in the world. And I feel like that's my
lane within filmmaking. You know, don't get me wrong. I love actors. I love the Oscars, but
But for me, it's got to be deeper than that.
You know, it's got to be more than just a Hollywood ending.
And in a way, I feel like I'm a bit of a wild card because I'm always looking at everything through a cultural lens.
Like, how does this connect to the broader conversation, the broader context?
Because I really believe that film doesn't exist in a vacuum, at least not today.
You can't just put anything on screen on a movie theater and not expect to start conversations, good or bad.
You know, you have to be really thoughtful about the content and the context of what your content exists in.
So in this day and age with social media, you know, people care so much about who is making the films and how the films, like, who are behind it.
So it's not just what the films look like.
Right.
For me, it's like, what would I, like, what I would say about this moment is that there's so much that's happening in the world that can inspire a director or a storyteller.
There's so much disruption in the world of entertainment right now, but it's such a hard business.
So to be in it, especially in this day and age, you have to have a strong why.
You have to know why you are here.
You need to be able to translate that for this new era of viewers who want to, who really want to know what you're,
why is, you know, they want to know what you stand for, what your why stands for on top of giving them content that they want to just watch.
So I think the last thing, the last thing I'll say is in terms of creativity in this moment, there's like an overwhelming creativity because especially coming out of the pandemic,
so many people almost lost their businesses, their jobs, or did lose their businesses and are fighting back from these low points.
So I just think there's just fresh new energy.
And there's that new energy is feeling, you know, feeding into this entertainment space, I think it's a little bit more grounded than we've been in a while, because now it's like, what do people actually want to see and consume?
I feel like it needs to be a little bit more real or grounding in the stories that are being told.
And then you can also see the complete opposite of the spectrum, which is like, we've been in a pandemic for three years.
I just want to dream.
I want to put out the most.
Yeah.
Over the top fantastical content ever because it's an art form and I want to inspire from that space.
So I feel like you can see, you see, like you walk into a movie theater and you see both ends of the spectrum.
There's a place for both art forms right now.
And for me, Super Sema is a part of that.
You know, it's telling a why.
It's a story of me as a black woman and mother and producer wanting to make something for children.
But it's also.
It's also a story of my whole team of women from all over the world who are, like, egging on to, like, change the way, you know, the next kind of generation of role models and the way kids look at science and some of these further subjects.
So it's a very interesting space.
And I understand the Williams sisters and Oprah, that community have been great supporters of yours and picking up on what you said before.
And I think that, you know, the pandemic and the COVID, the creativity coming out of it, I think is real, isn't it?
People got locked in their homes for that time and it gave you time to stop and reflect and think.
I think there is this burst of creativity that's going on in the world.
And that's part of where I had the great privilege to intersect with you, Vanessa, in a thing we call Alita Connect and to have you part of our sort of growing community around the world of getting incredible thinkers like you together and learning from you.
And your world could not be more different.
And I love the fact that you've got a group of people from Troy Flanagan, who's the head of high performance at Milwaukee Bucks, Tyson Ballard.
I don't even know how to explain Tyson.
He's a polymath.
I think everything he does, he's legendary.
Hugh Van Kylenburg from the Resilience Project.
Amit Baines is a great friend of mine and does incredible work in his role as CEO.
So can you tell us about that experience of Alita Connect, Vanessa, for you?
The Alita Connect experience for me has been, like, transformational.
And not to put that as a soundbite, but it actually has because I met people that I would never have met from totally different spheres, from all walks of life, and throw us into a room where we're sitting there.
And what was so surprising about the Alita Connect group was that how vulnerable we got so soon.
Like, I was expecting that by week five, maybe people would start talking about their children.
By week one, we were talking about childhood trauma.
We were talking about, you know, unpacking some of our deepest, darkest secrets, you know.
And I realized through that group that, you know, also, even though it wasn't a group of Black women, we're all connected.
We all have all these different, as leaders, we have these strings of and patterns and situations that we all encounter.
So.
So even if one person is sitting on an NBA court, you know, paneling this incredible team to win a championship, and the other is signing, you know, government papers in Colombia, we all actually are going through the same things.
And it's very basic.
It's all about, you know, priorities.
It's about family.
It's about mental health.
It's about self-care.
You know, and so that's what I realized in the Alita Connect more than anything is that how much we're all connected, how much sharing each other's stories and being very vulnerable in our leadership styles actually was, for me, the superpower of Alita.
It wasn't just that I learned these unique leadership styles.
It was more that, actually, you know what?
Honesty and transparency and being authentic.
That's what true leadership is.
And leadership revolves are all around people.
So, you know, it's all about relationships.
It's all about how we communicate.
And I think we have this idea that leadership sits in this book of the 25, you know, habits of highly effective leaders.
But actually, leadership is like what you do in your everyday space, how you treat your family, how you treat your employees.
How you live and kind of breathe in this world.
And that was what I really realized in the Alita Connect group.
I was kind of going there searching for, you know, the top five leadership, you know, junkets that I'll get from that group.
But I left, actually, with a community of friends and a kind of support system and a network of guys that I can call on and vice versa.
You know, for life.
I wasn't expecting that.
I was thinking this is six weeks of a fun ride, of meeting new people.
And then after that, we're all going to go on our separate ways.
But we have a very active, you know, group that we're all communicating on WhatsApp.
We keep in touch.
We're supporting each other.
And somehow when you, I think, also what the Alita Connect group does that is so powerful is when you bring two people.
Two people from two totally different worlds, two careers, two paths together.
There's no ego.
There's no like, oh, I have to be, you know, be bigger or better or, you know, there's all of that dissipates.
And so it just leaves room for the real you.
And I think that's what Alita gave me was the real, was bringing back the real me and really connecting to my own leadership system.
Nothing I've ever heard.
I've never heard a better description ever.
Vanessa, you couldn't write that if you tried.
And I think for us, that was part of the joy of, it felt like the world had retreated back to our silos a little bit.
And we stuck to the things that we knew that were familiar.
And it was all about what I could get and how I could gain.
In generalisation, it felt like the world had drifted into that path and we've lost connections a lot.
And the ability to show up and meet someone totally random that we didn't know or weren't from our background.
And you described that so beautifully.
Isn't it?
There are people that would probably never come into your walk of life.
And likewise, I'm sitting here in Melbourne with someone of Jamaican heritage from Canada who's changing the world in the most extraordinary way.
And I love the randomness of it and how, you know, I'm learning so much from every word you're saying.
And that's the beauty, I think, of growing these communities and understanding people better and understanding my background is so different.
And I couldn't walk in your shoes, but maybe I can have more empathy now and understand what it's like for someone who doesn't get to know me.
Who doesn't get to see themselves in that image all the time.
And I think that's how we learn better.
That's how we share.
And that was a beautiful way that you described it, Vanessa.
We had this great privilege as that community has grown of seeing these patterns around what we think our leadership looks like in different settings.
And I want to ask you a handful of questions on that.
And we start with self-leadership, Vanessa.
We think it's hard to lead anyone else as a mother, as a CEO or anything without understanding your own sense of self-leadership.
What does self-leadership mean to you?
Self-leadership for me is about being myself.
And I'll keep it very simple, but it's really about being my authentic self.
And it's about also understanding that I am the captain of my own ship.
It's about what I spoke about earlier, about claiming space, you know, really owning my decisions and being confident in them.
And also, for me, it's also about self-leadership also is about breaking down barriers.
So cracking those glass ceilings and getting myself into spaces, you know, without compromising who I am, where someone that looks like me has never been so that I can pave the way for others to do the same.
And for me, that's a big part of what self-leadership means to me.
Beautifully said.
We see these.
Because diverse leaders are really conscious of how, on a daily basis, they positively impact people in their environment.
And I really think a lot about that positive impact on a day-to-day basis.
How have you gone about impacting people positively?
Well, I think, I mean, beyond just being a good person, I think, and how you define that.
And beyond changing the world at a global level as well.
So we're going to leave that part in as well.
But on a day-to-day?
Yeah, on a day-to-day.
I think, you know, for me, I think a big, you know, outwardly in the world, what looks like, it probably looks like SuperSama is my main focus.
You know, we have three seasons.
We have toys and books.
But I think I've been thinking more and more about stepping back and going inwards.
And also just being really present with my family.
Making sure that I'm still, I'm still feeding all these different projects and these things.
But for me, it's also being a good person is also about being, you know, being kind to myself, a little bit more kind to myself and being able to do all the things I want to do without giving up one of those things.
So I think it's about being out in the world and allowing one project to feed into the next.
One feeds the other.
And when that entity is big enough, it gets strong enough to feed the next.
And so it's kind of a circle of fulfillment.
And in a way, that's how I've lived my life.
I've never been someone who's been in one box, doing one thing.
People step into my office and they can't believe that I have a science degree on my wall.
Or like seeing my, all like my Harry Potter Oxford photos and understanding that, you know, that analytical mind went then into storytelling.
And then animation and now making music.
And just not having these self-limiting beliefs has been a way that I've been able to inspire others.
And through like mentorship and with my employees and my own children, friends, you know, always being there for people and making sure that I make time for the things and the people that I care.
Vanessa, we're also fascinated about how people like you who do things at the level of your own.
Well, you are go about creating and sharing your vision.
How have you gone about that?
Well, obviously, like with SuperSama, for example, the vision has been a culmination of many things as I've grown.
But I think the number one way that I've been able to kind of express my vision has just been in doing.
Like I'm not someone who really has been.
I had my shine very early on in my career, you know, doing modeling and acting and being on screen.
But then I think what's been most powerful for me has been going behind the scenes, actually, and picking up that pen and paper and writing and being like digging my hands deeper into the creative, into the creative elements.
And when people around you see you, not just talking about it.
But actually doing the work, I think that it just naturally inspires them to also want to do that.
And I think my vision has always been so big, you know, I've never been someone who's just like, oh, I want to get from here to there.
It's like, no, I want to change the world and and and getting people to jump on kind of our Kukua rocket ship that I like to call it and like blast off without, you know, leaving.
And I think that's been a testament to that has been like we literally we will in the SuperSumma office, we have a wall of all these women that we really believe in.
And we had Lupita up there.
We had Serena.
We had Oprah.
And it's still there.
We had all these pictures of all these women that we and we always said one day these women are going to walk through this office.
And just the fact that we've had, you know, not only some of those women, but also some of those women that are going to walk through this office.
Some of those women walk in our office, but some of them support us, some of them being investors, some of them being a part of our company and like believing in our vision.
That is like that says it all.
That is incredible, isn't it?
To have literally manifested that, have it on the wall and suddenly you have got the Williams sisters and Oprah and all of those legendary people in your corner.
Curiosity is a word that comes up a lot in the world of a leader and we see people so curious.
And through that, Vanessa, they're constantly growing and learning.
Is curiosity something that strikes a chord with you?
Big time.
I mean, I think curiosity is like the bedrock of like childlike wonder.
And for me, especially working in the children's space and making toys and books and like that is literally that like curiosity is the beginning of like unlocking your imagination.
So, I mean, I live and breathe curiosity.
It's like the one thing.
I try to get back to because I feel as an adult, you know, having been on this earth for longer than, you know, my childhood days.
It's like you're everything has like around you kind of closes that off, like wants to make you put you in a less creative, less curious space.
And I feel like, honestly, you know, even with our super semi team, we often just say, let's get into that sandbox.
Let's be creative.
Let's be curious.
And let's.
Let's play like it was literally that moment of like, let's go into the sandbox and play.
When do we ever play with this doll?
When do we ever, you know, get kids off the screen and into like actually creating and doing things?
And in order to do that, we have to do that, not just with our own children, but like with ourselves, with how we think about new ideas, how we pilot new ideas of episodes.
We are sitting there like playing around with.
Lego thinking of how can we, you know, how can super summon this next episode, save her pet goat using a GPS system that she has to technobate.
This is all comes from being curious and like wildly curious.
So I think curiosity is, is, is a big word for, for me and a, and a big part of my creative process.
And Vanessa communicating with clarity is another dimension we love asking about.
And that is your world is what.
You've been able to tell great stories, whether it's the Mali African road trip or the productions that you're on into doing this animated spectacular series.
I mean, you must be pretty sophisticated about how you communicate.
Have you given that thought or is it just getting in the sandbox and playing as you just said?
I've definitely given it thought.
There's no doubt.
I think communication is so important.
So I've definitely spent a lot of time watching and learning.
Some of my role models in that world, for me, communication is, has always been about just getting face to face with someone looking into their eyes, holding a hand, like communication has never, my style of communication has never been like, let me get on top of, on that Ted Ted X conference stage, even though I'm doing those things now deliver, delivering the keynote at web summit was definitely.
Yeah.
You know, had me sweating a couple of bullets, but, um, but the truth is that like my communication style is much more, um, intimate.
It's much more, I feel I get much more out of it when I'm with someone and I, and like the communication is not always verbal.
It's like, it's, it's in the subtle ways that, that someone inches a little bit closer to hear what you have to say.
It's in the way that someone reaches out.
Okay.
And it's a patchy when you're, you know, when something makes you emotional.
And I think for me, that's in a way been my superpower as well, because as a leader, I'm not just about being the type a, you know, I'll tell you what to do.
I'm ultra assertive.
I'm this, I'm that I can be that, but a big part of my leadership strength is also the vulnerability is also the empathy.
It's also the understanding.
And I think that communication.
That's a little bit more nurturing and a little bit more, um, as a little bit more subtle, surely has been a way that I've been able to also communicate my vision and bring people along for the ride because they don't just have to hear me say the words they can feel it.
They're touched by, they can, they hear the trembling in my voice when they know it means so much to me.
Um, and I think.
Yeah, I think in a way that's been something that has been a game changer in terms of how I look at the way I communicate.
Vanessa, how important has collaboration been for you?
Collaboration's been everything for me because at the end of the day, you know, when we started SuperSamo, we had no money.
We had just this brilliant idea.
We had to get people to believe in us.
We had to raise money.
We had to find VCs.
And, and leave.
And then when you had, when we had like the, the, the creators who, who agreed to jump on this bandwagon when there was, was nothing like ours that existed.
Um, it's much easier when you have like a clear prototype.
And when we were alive, we want to be the Disney, the Disney of learning from Africa to the world.
How do you communicate that without like something that you can, you can tangibly see or feel?
So I think.
We've needed a lot of people on this road, on this road show in order to make this happen.
Absolutely.
this happen. Even right now, we're working with a lot of partners, licensees in order to get
Supersend to many different spaces and to get on shelves and to get her into books and to get her
on when you open your Spotify, you know, we want you to hear her music and that's all through
collaboration. I think we would not have been where we are today with her. The Disney of learning
from Africa to the world. Now there's a big vision and on the way to creating it, I think
it's an incredible story. Vanessa, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
I know this is going to sound cliche, but it's definitely been my mother. I mean, everything
always comes back to her. She's always been the one that I've looked up to, the one that's always,
you know, calling me and reminding me like what's important. She's always like, oh, God is good.
You have to, you know, you have to think about the bigger, like she's connected me to a spiritual
side of myself that also makes me think more than, you know, what is here on this earth. Like it's so
much bigger than that. And I think my mom has, beyond just being my biggest fan, has been
definitely my biggest role model from when I was holding her hand, sitting in antique shops,
watching her, you know, buy and sell things and watching how she navigated all these different
spaces.
She went from being a boss lady in a bank to being a boss lady in an antique market stall. Like for
me, that is just like, wow. Seeing that very early on just makes you think, okay, anything is possible.
And Vanessa, I love it when someone immediately, you know, references that a mother or a parent or
mother and father, you realize how lucky you are. You have someone in your life
like that. And obviously for you straight away, that was an instant. There wasn't a lot of delay,
it was, you know, the inspiration of your mom. And you, you know, obviously you're passing that
onto your beautiful three, three children in such a powerful way. And I'm not surprised that that
answer came out. And we're a bit obsessed with the collaboration, Vanessa, in Alita and what
collaboration looks like now on a global scale. And I'm fascinated by the Supasema office and
on the board was Oprah and these incredible inspirational figures. There'd been one person
you could think of that you'd love to collaborate with that, you know, and you've got so many people
and so many passions. Maybe it is the SEMA work. Is there, is there a name that you could
reference that you'd love to work with? Oh, that is a very good question.
I think for me, the one person that I would like would really rock my world and like push
Supasema, push me into other territories is definitely the director, Ava DuVernay.
She is already, she has blown,
trailblazed through Hollywood at being, you know, the first black director to box office over a
billion dollars, the first black female director to, to be nominated for Oscars. I mean, but beyond
that, she is just, you know, having known people who work with her, you know, she's such a visionary
and she looks at things in, in totally different ways. And like what I was saying, she really
takes things in, in like a contextual way.
And so for me, it would be such a dream to work with someone like Ava, because she, I know I would
learn so much from her watching how she not only tells a story, but also she would take something
like what we have and bring it to life in a totally different way. I've been dreaming about
a Supasema movie for a long time. So the idea of going from a television series to then,
you know, a lot, a movie directed by Ava DuVernay would literally,
that would be a game changer for me. I think I could die a happy woman with that.
And anyone who's read what you do would have no doubt that that is entirely possible. And I'm not,
not surprised at all in the future if that happens. Can you tell, what are some of Ava's
works that we would know? I've got to admit, I'm not familiar. What's some of the stuff that would
be well known to us?
Probably the most well-known Selma. That one she did, she really did a lot of work.
Yeah, that's huge. And then she also, she did the 13th, which was the documentary series about
kind of corporal punishment in the U.S. and nominated for an Oscar. And then, you know,
she's also been, she's pretty much gotten nominated for every award possible.
Even short films like Say Yes. And she's done also the first Black female director to direct a
Disney film. And so I think she has, she has just like been a groundbreaking role model for the
whole Hollywood world because, you know, her as a director totally changes also the landscape of
how the story is told and what perspective you're looking at. And I think she's really opened it up
in a way, in the way that our conversation is opening up.
For you, that's like what she's done for like the whole world is open up this space of like looking
at, you know, some of these, looking at a Disney movie from a Black female perspective, you know,
and that hasn't been done before. So, yeah, pretty powerful stuff.
Pretty powerful and super Selma the movie coming to your screens at some stage. And I'm waiting and
would not be surprised at all. Vanessa, it's been a great privilege to spend some time with you.
Thank you so much.
Thank you for sharing your story. It is literally changed the world, as we said,
and thank you for taking the time today. And it's been great to catch up with you.
Really appreciate it.
Thank you so much, Luke. This has been such a joy. Honestly, I'm so grateful for Alita for
making all these opportunities.
Thanks for listening to another episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast. Huge thanks,
as always, to our great friends at Temper. And we encourage you to check out our Alita
Connect program. New episodes are out every Wednesday morning at 6am.