I always felt connected to Heath. I knew this was something special. I painted like a maniac
and I finished it three weeks later. I sent it to him and he passed that night.
Hello and welcome to another episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast. At Alita, we are
passionate about inspiring connections and creating a world of collaboration. Our signature
program Alita Connect curates groups of five to six leaders from diverse backgrounds in
the sport, industry, social venture and the arts who come together to learn, to connect
and to collaborate.
It's been amazing. Here you are on this Zoom call, feeling within the first session like
you intimately know these people and care for them. And then all of a sudden realising
that even though you're in totally different industries, we're all going through the same
thing or we've been through it and we can help each other.
Or there's just this hurdle that you can't see past and then you share it with the group
and there's five answers in 40 minutes and you think, I have not slept for two weeks
thinking about that. Like, how is this possible?
You're listening to stories and the breadcrumbs of what makes success and I constantly get
something out of these Zoom calls and catch-ups because we're all living the same stuff, aren't
we?
Yeah.
Extraordinary people.
Extraordinary people with extraordinary experience. What happens there is magical.
The Empowering Leaders podcast is proudly brought to you by Victoria University, where
cutting-edge sports and exercise science facilities like heat chambers, performance labs and altitude
environments mean VU is ranked seventh in the world for sports science. VU, uniquely
you. As always, a big thank you to Jason Nicholas and his team at Temper Bedding, a mattress
like no other. If you enjoy listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast, please subscribe
to the podcast. Be sure to subscribe and please, if you have a moment, we would love
you to leave a review so we can reach more listeners and empower more leaders.
This week's guest on the Empowering Leaders podcast is one of the world's most respected
and talented artists, Vincent Fantuzzo. Known for his iconic portraits, Vincent's incredible
talent has captured the essence of people like Heath Ledger, Sir Paul McCartney, Australia's
first female prime minister, Julia Gillard, and even met his wife, Asha Keddie, while
painting her portrait.
His work speaks for itself. He's a great artist. He's a great artist. He's a great artist.
He's a great artist. He's a great artist. He's a great artist. He's a great artist. He's a great artist.
His work speaks to not only his technical genius, but to his ability to capture the
essence of his subjects with a striking intimacy and connection. As the great artist David
Hockney once said, Vincent's work is not just about capturing a likeness, but capturing
the soul of his subjects. Vincent's remarkable story is told with incredible honesty in
his brilliant memoir, Unveiled. Vincent grew up in the commission housing in Melbourne's
Broad Meadows, severely dyslexic, left school at 14 years of age, and looked on the path
to crime and self-defense. He's a great artist. He's a great artist. He's a great artist.
He's a great artist. He's a great artist. He's a great artist. He's a great artist.
His evolution from a severely troubled upbringing to a powerhouse in the art world is nothing
short of incredible. With numerous awards, including multiple Archibald Prize nominations,
and his work hanging in prestigious collections worldwide, Vincent is a true leader in every
sense in the Australian art world. Great to meet you, Vincent. I heard so much about you,
mate. Thanks for taking the time.
Thanks, Luke. I'm going to get you to call my wife and tell her how lucky she is after
that.
You often think when you sit down and you read someone's...
bio back to them what do you what's your immediate thought i feel like it's a pinch myself thing but
it's also when you struggle and you have to hustle a lot of your life there's always that imposter
syndrome you know hovering over you so i know i am but i hope i am all that you wrote a brutally
honest memoir and it's it's it's sensational and reading it in preparation for this there was
an honesty and i understand you you spoke about things you hadn't spoken to
your wife ash or anyone about before how was that experience very emotional journey also like very
therapeutic as well um i kind of refer to like having therapy but i was getting paid so that
was good the only problem is i did all this therapy and now it's in a book for everyone to
read so it is a bit scary but i've had just even during this book tour i've had this incredible
response from very overwhelming response touching things i just didn't know art and a book could
have you know this power and i feel uh really humbled by it i think vincent it's a bit more
than art and a book it's your your story's remarkable a lot of people listening around
the world might know you know what it's like your parents came through the immigration
camps in broad meadows it was an extraordinarily tough upbringing and you found yourself
you know being arrested at one stage and in a few stages a few stages and we left a couple out and
and you know potentially going down this this path of self-destruction as i said in the introduction
can you give a sense to people just what it was like for you growing up you know i lived in fear
a lot um it was a bit of the wild west um i think you know there's five of us kids
then after my father left it was my mom and five kids
and i felt uh you know even though i was very surrounded i felt quite alone and quite scared
i know tough upbringings come in all different ways like mine was you know there's poverty and
violence and a few other things and but there's also kids in a privileged background that have a
tough upbringing and as there's a kid in a slum in india with a smile on his face because he's loved
and as a kid in a private school could be sexuality could be his parents aren't around and it's just
as tough i always try and do my best to be a good kid and i've always tried to be a good kid and i've
you know we can be very like-minded and have the same struggles from different backgrounds
vincent i heard someone say to me once that you know if you grew up in your circumstances
and a single parent and there was abuse and people sort of expect that it should be tough
but you're probably right if you grew up with a wealthy family and you neglected it no one really
cares about your story do they and they don't or you've had you've had it easy it's almost
a harder path in some ways is that is that possible yeah like even now people
will you know if they didn't know this story they might look at me as a privileged middle-aged
white guy living a dream and there's a lot more to all people like there's a story there and
it's why i love my job because i get to experience learn and explore people's stories and i think i
feel people's energy a lot if they're if it's dark i feel it if it's happy if it's dangerous
so it's it's a very emotional
journey also i should explain that listening to me talk is a bit like watching the tv and
someone keeps flicking their channels because i forget uh with my dyslexia adhd spectrum all of
those things are kind of what was the question i want to ask you about the severe dyslexia which
is a big part of of your life and and just how brutal the school system was for you growing up
but no concessions vincent's not intelligent you know he's not listening
how did this extraordinary artist emerge out of that and can you can you give us an insight
um i was in brazil recently and they don't speak much english there and everything's in another
language and uh you know it's a bit like that as a kid like everywhere you go um you can't read
anything you you know you're in a class and the teacher's writing on a board and you already feel
stupid and you don't want anyone to know so you
learn to pretend then you feel like a liar and a fake and what baffles me is i got through
the whole of school i didn't pass one thing i couldn't even write my street name down i didn't
even know what street i lived in dyslexia is not just reading and writing and maths it's
it's thinking and it's memory memory has a big part to play it's different for all people i mean
it's so complex i could talk about it all day you can have einstein maths
genius and he can't write you can have someone that's quite academic but their memory is shot i
fortunately i got all of them saying that i now know the gifts of dyslexia adhd and all those
diversities but at the time i was just um i would have loved to love school and i hated it
and what you're saying i think is such a topical thing and there'll be people listening and all of
us are parents we just want people to just love it
kids unconditionally regardless of and all of us have got blind spots was the word i'm searching
for but is it possible you went through these enormous challenges and there was not a lot of
care for you but do you think the way your brain works it's turned on this superpower of creativity
i know there's a creative genius i can see it in your work but but do you think that's what's come
out of the fact your brain doesn't work to read and write it's so turned on in their other ways
you connect with people
definitely
definitely now i realize at the time i just thought i was different so i was in a special
class special class has the blind kid deaf kid wheelchair me kid with Tourette's yelling and
all all of us misfits in one class and yeah but see this it's a real thing forget the question
just run it by me one more time yeah just the idea that there's a superpower in the way that
yes our brain works so if you're blind you develop your hearing
i have a brain i have a brain i have a brain i have a brain i have a brain i have a brain i have a brain
i had no way of learning you know i would watch tv to try and learn you know i know a lot about
you know the simpsons and seinfeld and all those things i learned through conversation and i was
the annoying kid that was asking too many questions i couldn't tell people that's the
only way i can learn and i think one you're hiding and you learn to hustle to keep a secret
so you're developing a sense of something there you start to understand people
and their emotions so you develop a different way of communicating so sometimes it's non-verbal
sometimes it's the energy of someone the look on their face you know it's like uh you can become a
lie detector you know like you'd feel i know what you're thinking right now adhd dyslexia all the
autism um some of these kids people adults old people they can be in a room at a party having
conversation listening to two other conversations and they're not going to be able to communicate
and noticing someone in the corner that no one's talking to and thinking about how they can help
them and also thinking about what they're going to cook for dinner and that can be overwhelming
and it can cause anxiety but it's also an incredible gift to have this and i heard a
teacher recently described that 20 years ago there was maybe three kids that they required special
attention for to support their education he's saying in year 12 there's three and a half
classrooms and they're not going to be able to cook for dinner and they're not going to be able to
cook for dinner and they're not going to be able to cook for dinner and they're not going to be able to
full of neurodivergent kids that we're now identifying more and more of so you've sort of
blazed this pathway i'm sure it's reassuring to people to go you know we just need to find what
these people are passionate about is that too simple a way to to describe it or no that's
that's pretty accurate and i would like to think that in diagnosing things like i don't want it to
be something people want because it seems cool or flavor of the month or they're trying to
answer a question for their child or themselves and it might not be that like sometimes you know
diversity is caused by you know a problem at home mental health all sorts of things when it comes to
these kids that you know have actually a neurodiverse situation a lot of parents are
embarrassed at first and then they think i'm going to get my kid a tutor and they're going to be as
good as the other kids at reading or writing what they're going to be able to do and i think that's
whatever their weakness is that's not going to happen like i tried my whole life to do certain
things and it just doesn't go into my head so when you force them to do something they can't
their self-confidence goes down and my boxing coach when i was a kid i was i was having a fight
first round this guy was just a thug he was just like flat out swinging and i i'm a competitive
person and i just started swinging back and
bit more solid like that's how he fights and jack renny said to me in the corner that's not the way
you fight if you fight his fight he's better at that than you and you're going to lose and he said
in order to win in life as well you got to concentrate on what you're good at so i always
think of that in life and with these kids if they're good at art let them do art they're going
to do it so much better than everyone else and they find their confidence i want to come back
to your boxing and the great jack renny
in your corner that that that explains a little bit i'll talk to you about that in a moment but
i'm gonna go back i look i'm seeing you across from someone who you know if you know that part
of melbourne and you know what you went through the likelihood that one of the world's great
artists is going to emerge out of a tough upbringing in broad meadows might be a trillion
to one how do we encourage more artists how do you you're sitting there from this position now
where you've been able to be that one in a billion or a trillion
how do you find the path for more artists to emerge like you have i'm very nervous too by the
way you can see my um i knew i could paint and i wanted a way out of the world i was in and
it's still a stereotype if you tell someone you're an artist they say what else do you do and people
think you can only be successful when you're dead i do watch my back a little bit prices were yeah
paintings will go up um and i think that's a good thing i think that's a good thing i think that's a
good thing i think the art world needs to change so if i was to ask generally people to name five
australian artists they can't when you're an artist and you're ambitious people can call you
a sellout a sports person a musician an actor they're allowed to make money they're allowed
to be ambitious people celebrate it they can have sponsorships um apply business class look
after their family the art world has to change their way show that art is cool it's an
incredible job you can be entrepreneurial and you can still have integrity and if they teach kids
we can show them that you can be successful and it is a way out there's a lot of creative kids out
there that are choosing a different path because they think it's you know i chose crime at one
point because i i looked up to these guys and i thought i want to drive a mercedes and and wear
sunglasses and look cool and it's not going to happen in the art world it's a great point you
may i've never thought of you know i don't know your world uh
at all well wouldn't pretend to but i think almost like the you actually started your career as a
part-time chef it's like the chefs have emerged out of the kitchen into great commercial success
and we celebrate those food geniuses now but not in the art world so much when we were at school
it was home economics and fancy food and wine people were scared to talk about it like to
articulate what they taste when they're drinking wine now everyone does it everyone's quite
confident and when you start to talk about it you start to talk about it and you start to talk about
art people say oh i don't know anything about art um i can't draw a stick figure but everyone
starts off as an artist like you go to a kid's class and it's just full of art and at some point
they're told you know it's not accurate enough or something but the beauty of i like all art
i paint the way i do because that's what comes naturally but art's conceptual and it's about
what you see is different to what i see what you've experienced and when we create it it's
individual and special so they also need to be taught that abstract art performance art whatever
it might be you can still be an artist i think we do need to teach kids um or people you know
look what jamie oliver and matt moran and things are done for the chef world how do we do it for
the art world yeah when you look at your your art and as i said i the genius of it blows me away i
can't even comprehend you doing what you do
it's easy but you just you see when you unveil julia gillard's portrait and it's still hanging
in parliament house and you can see the look on her face around you captured something in her that
other people hadn't seen and um is that connection that you find with people where it starts for you
connection is absolutely everything like you can you can replicate a bad photo you know you could
send it overseas somewhere and an art factory and they'll send it back to you and it will look like
the photograph
what matters to me not the traditional way of someone sitting in front of me
they're feeling self-conscious and so am i and you know when you spend a bit of time with someone
and you you earn each other's trust and you're genuinely interested and you start to talk about
something that hits home like we were talking earlier before the podcast about kids and sports
and parents and i could see the emotion in you coming out that's what i'm talking about
i'm looking for something that's really deep and connected so i spend time it's a bit like big
brother they forget the camera's around and i you know i might be snapping something and listening
um talking to a friend of yours if it was your portrait talking to your family just go and watch
you do something and you see movements in people's face their body language their someone says
something and my hair stands up and that's the moment i want to catch yeah so i believe you know
not religious uh you know maybe spiritual but a painting of any type or an artwork can have
emotion and an energy sometimes people look at an abstract colored patch and they've they feel
something you know so yeah no chatting to you i i feel i can sense that and we might come back and
talk kids sport in a moment potentially but i've got to go to 2008 you've got a great friendship
with heath ledger who's an incredible actor and human being and and you paint this remarkable
portrait that is award-winning and he says to you at the time this is going to change both of our
lives tragically he passed away not long afterwards can you tell us about your friendship with heath
ledger yeah well it's interesting you know what you're just saying about um connection being so
or we were saying about connection being so important i always felt connected to heath
we had a lot of mutual friends and would hang out in groups and we're all young and he had a lot of
friends that lived in melbourne from perth he would come and see them i was part of that group
sometimes you can know someone for a long time and you're kind of ready for this time or
conversation where things change and you can meet someone for an hour and your friends for life and
you kind of know it and we had this we've been waiting to do this portrait for a long time
and we've been waiting for this portrait for a long time and we've been waiting for this portrait
tell me if i'm taking too long just so happened he was in perth for christmas and i i went there as
well and we had this night where everything poured out of us like he told me things he had never
spoken about i told him things not for any reason just started happening i was telling him things he
was very complicated guy with a very complicated life and exceptionally talented and confident
vulnerable like just none of it makes sense
it was like uh one of the most meaningful nights i've had with someone like a really moving the
next day i turned up at his house seven in the morning something he answered the door in his
pajamas and his t-shirt off we hardly spoke and he took a chair outside and he sat on the chair
and i wasn't sure if what we were doing and for an awkwardly long time and i pulled my camera
thought this must be it started taking photos i wish i had filmed it
sat there for a long time and he just lost himself and i thought he was kind of gone out of his body
and he's staring then he got up like he was still sitting on a chair but another him got up and
started screaming roaring at himself and spit was coming out he's yelling at himself about things
that we had talked about in his life and um and he stopped and waited a while went around to the
other side and he started laughing and then after a while he started whispering in the other ear
and then talking yelling and i just watched it all and i was like fuck like this is like he just let
everything out of this silent him and that was how he's feeling about his life does he still trust
the same people do the new people in his life like him for who he is can he share his feelings
it's part of why i'm writing about a lot of things and then it stopped i knew this was something
special and i worked like a maniac his dad
told me recently that he always thought he wasn't going to be around for a long time
he was very ambitious about the future he didn't take his own life but i feel like he had this
feeling and he said it's going to change our lives and um yeah i you know i painted like a
maniac and i finished it three weeks later on i sent it to him that night and he passed that night
did you get to see it i don't know if you got to see it um he saw a sketch
that i did yeah it's just uh there's been so many strange coincidences since then and you know
interestingly his dad said they would have a bit of a headbutt about business decisions kim his
father is very business and he's the opposite and he never understood heath well and he said
i wish he knew that i now know him better than i ever did when he was around
and you donated that painting to
to heath's mom and um i love the process of being out of research or background she donated it to
the to the portrait gallery is that correct no portrait gallery awesome in canberra she
donated it after the archibald to the new south wales art gallery i gave it to her and she said
i feel selfish keeping it i want somewhere for people to understand heath and go and talk to him
yeah and they're choosing not to put that on the wall at the moment
so shout out to him and he's going to be a great artist and he's going to be a great artist and
i'm hoping that um you know she can do something different and it's not about me
it's about his family and his friends and people that loved him i and about heath yeah i'm not sure
why it's been in the basement i feel grateful from what i got from the archibald from the gallery i
just don't understand that decision i mean i shouldn't harp on this but perhaps if they don't
want to show up i'm not going to show up i'm not going to show up i'm not going to show up i'm not
maybe it could be shown somewhere else is that a possibility it's such an iconic thing that
it's been created it's yeah heath's family offered to buy it back they didn't even they
donated but they offered to buy it back hang it somewhere else um shout out to the gallery
hang the painting give it back sounds like in the art world that there is more politics than
it seems that there's is that something that's been difficult for you to bang that door down and
try and be the person you want to be in in a world that seems fairly hierarchical
full of politics um there's a lot of wankery in the art world there's also a lot of amazing people
and very generous people as well like art's given me everything i have and the art world's part of
that i try to get rid of the chip on my shoulder because i like to stay positive there's it
definitely needs to change it's very hard for young people to feel accepted you know like you
go into a white walled gallery and you know you're not buying an artwork and no one will talk to you
i had people laugh in my face
handing in my resume or my portfolio or something the music world's changed acting the art world's
still very closed doors to a lot of people i love that i'm sitting across from someone who's got a
master's in fine art from one of the world's leading i'm a professor as well really let's
not undersell you my apologies but who literally can't read or write and still struggles to
understand with the learning difficulties that you've got is that something that you've had to
force that down beyond all the hurdles that are there should we be able to open up those
opportunities more for young people with learning challenges yeah art's a visual language um and i
i really appreciate art history i love that people can defend their art or articulate art really well
i can't do that i can do it with you know do it with my mates i'll talk about art i like it i
don't i describe it the best i can it's not necessary you also have to go you have to finish
school do your 12 saying that i think school is very important not the academic side necessarily
because it's not for everyone but the social side and social development of young people
so it's about key points in their life you know they're formal they're hanging out like you end
the year together and you celebrate and you go away somewhere all these different things
that socially need to develop in kids and if they're not academic they leave and they miss out
and they turn into adults too fast you also need to finish high school to get into a university
and maybe the best artists out there can't finish high school or they should be able to finish high
school and they would but they kind of can't so you know if a kid can't do history in university
should they not be allowed to have a degree in art we all are born different
as we grow the experiences we have developed into outlooks uniquely our own
charting our life's course
no one sees an idea opinion or opportunity like you and no one sees you like v u
victoria university uniquely you my name is you i study uh territory preparation
i was born in iraq we had to move from iraq when i was six years old because of the war
when we went to jordan we just applied for a visa to come to australia thank god we got it and we
came here and i'm loving this offer so the course on studying gives me the opportunity to study
many other pathways and it gives me the opportunity to choose whatever i want it opens so many places
for me at elita our signature program elita connect is something we're really passionate and
proud of we bring together groups of five to six people from all over the world to work together to
six people around the globe from diverse backgrounds sport industry social venture and the
arts and come together to learn to connect and to collaborate liz ellis australian netball icon
and television presenter the thing that i've loved about it is not just the meetings that we have
with our group it's the thinking that you do the days and days afterwards someone says something
and it sparks a thought and within my sport and within women's sport i'm just someone who
i try to lead by keeping people talking about the issues
there's times when i think the person i'm trying to convince is not listening to me
it actually got me thinking about this is how i need to address my communication with them so it
was i can't tell you how much i enjoyed it you showed me a moment ago a portrait you did recently
of alex pereros a usc brazilian martial artist of the highest order and we were talking about
but a usc i've got three boys who love that sport for everyone as you as you said but
you're a you're a passionate boxer
i'm told incredibly capable tell us about that part of your life and did you ever think about
doing that seriously oh that was my dream growing up kids need a bit of support i got that through
jack renny he let me sweep the gym train for free i thought that was going to be my way out
i i didn't lose a boxing fight i did i did well i had lots of amateur fights kickboxing fights
jack at one point i'll get to that later uh let's go back to the question say it one more time
now i'm lost mate i i'm lost i'm lost i'm lost i'm lost i'm lost i'm lost i'm lost i'm lost i'm lost
what jack renny said to you i'm gonna keep you going i'll tell you what jack said i was training
very hard i finally found someone i never had any boundaries and yeah it makes a kid feel like
no you you want boundaries you don't want to ask for them because you're trying to be a rebel
jack was the first guy to set boundaries for me if you fuck up you get into fights if you're ever
a bully if you do drugs you're not training at this gym and uh it actually yeah i've
i hear his voice and it makes me emotional and i think of kids that don't have it
i also think of kids that get pushed too hard by their parents we were talking about
if someone has a dream they're gonna give every part of themselves you don't you don't have to
force them you just have to support them and i wasn't getting that support i got it from jack
but i wanted to thank jack so i did this sketch no one knew i could draw um i did a sketch of
lionel rose and johnny famijan i gave it to jack and i gave it to jack and i gave it to jack and i
gave it to jack and he um he he was in tears i never said he was that's not jack and uh he said
something like uh have a drink of water make a joke always helps um he said i know you're going
to be okay and then he said the next day this is the funny part slightly insulting slightly
complimentary he said i reckon you should be an artist not a boxer and it wasn't because i was
quite the opposite i found out recently that jack was actually um very passionate artist himself
his son rang me up after the book after australian story and said you wouldn't believe how much of
what you said uh was accurate about jack and he was also a passionate secret artist so it kind of
makes sense as well i just can see the amazing emotion you've got that jack runny's changed your
life and boxing gets a bad rap for not understanding that some of those gyms really
saved a lot of kids for exactly the way you described it
here's some you muck up you're out here's some boundaries for the first time in your life and
we before we started we i don't know how we did but we started getting onto spot asked how your
boys were and what they're into and they're passionate about soccer and it did jump off
this passion topic of mine being around junior sport and as you said really brilliantly just
then i just see parents that just they're ruining that beautiful environment because
it's a void in themselves they want to live vicariously through their kids
and
they're taking the joy away from kids and under agassi story yeah example and you're seeing that
as well and absolutely you can see kids get uh yelled out in their car park by their parents
this is what i'm talking about tough upbringing it could be it could be that like what's her name
australian female tennis player champion elena yep terrible father like that's that's a terrible
torporous upbringing and you know it's it's
so sad that she might have been more amazing and actually enjoyed herself i think it's like you
you know you don't let your kid have sugar their whole life and when they can they're having sugar
drugs and they're pregnant you know it's you can't control someone you know and a lot of parents are
trying to force their kid to live their dream it happens in the acting world happens in probably
in art as well but i think people push art less because there's not the fun i wonder
yeah i wonder sometimes if the parents want the celebrity that you look at some famous athletes
for example and their parents are in the light too you know and i wonder if they're chasing all of
that through their kids or you know a youtube kid you know they're not doing it themselves
the parents are yeah it's just a child abuse how do you approach being a dad to your two boys
back to a seinfeld reference when george decided to be a dad to his two boys
to do everything the opposite to how he thought he should he was successful i do everything the
opposite to kind of what i was shown when i was a kid um by choice i always think there's a way
i believe the cycle doesn't have to continue and success to me before anything else is when my boys
are adults and someone asks them about their dad they say that they were loved and you know and
they love me back so when it
comes to sports or anything they're doing i say whatever effort you put in i'll put in just as
much you know you want to train 45 minutes away all right i feel like i'm gonna be there too
that happens and also emotionally sports psychology is so important i remember i turned
up to a boxing match and i was worried about not the guy with tats and look tough nothing wrong
with tats by the way um i was worried about the kid that
turned up with a sports bag and their dad and i knew they had the support they had the psychology
and i was one i was envious of it and now i have so many stories like meeting oscar piastri recently
young kid i did his portrait he's just a kid and he has the weight of the world on his shoulders
especially in australia and he's so focused he's very strong and i think he'll be world champion
but i just saw this kid you know
and he's a kid he's 22 that's yeah he's still a baby yeah a billion dollars yeah it's worldwide
fans it's his country that's that's a lot yeah and he's good though he and he travels with his
um i know you'll call us sports psychology she was amazing spoke to her it's so important and
a lot of people don't have it and kids have the opposite they have someone busting their balls
it might not even be their dream yeah no i was sharing with you before and i
have no idea what you're talking about i don't know what you're talking about i don't know what
you're talking about i don't know what you're talking about i don't know what you're talking about
mentioned this before on the podcast this this idea of the conversation in the car and how
it ruins sport for many kids because they love it kids just love it and under 13 grand final
if they win it or they lose it five minutes the kids are over it the parents are the ones
this is the biggest thing in my life and they you get in the car all the kid wants you to say to
them is i love watching you play it's all you need to say yeah nothing else and i i remind myself
with that all the time still we just love watching you play but when we add all these other layers
why didn't you yeah you just ruin sport you know you ruin so many things for kids and if it's their
dream they will they're gonna feel like my my boy gets in the car and i hope you don't mind me
talking about you luca he gets in the car and he he's so passionate i think i really believe in the
dream and i'd like to get your opinion my 10 year old said to me the other day dad hard work beats
talent if talent doesn't work hard enough and i was like wow son that's amazing
where'd you get left from he said you told me years ago but i think it was ron barassi told me
that and did you paint ron i did yeah and really wise words from him also about teams and sports
and as a coach he said you're not coaching that just their performance you've got to think about
why they're not performing what's happening in their private life some people you need to yell
and some people need a hug you know it's it's you would know
my
more than i would but it's a big responsibility as a coach um and if you have a parent doing the
opposite it's tough especially when they're kids and it's a safe haven should be for everyone but
it hasn't always been the case so i love the opportunity to sit down and
the diverse uh thinking and your life story is so unique we have this sort of saying in our world
that success leaves clues and they're these patterns around why people even from the most
diverse backgrounds have success this idea that you've got to fill your own
cup up first before you can be good for anyone else so what do you do that makes you be at your
best for yourself so that you can be good for others i have the most incredible friends and
family you know i've created a family for myself through my friends as well um and that's just i
feel so grateful like i i do have my boxing group i always think about you know sports for a lot of
kids is that safe place so parents and parents and parents and parents and parents and parents and
don't fuck it up by you know making it not a happy place twice a week i have a bunch of guys
very diverse group of people from entrepreneurs business people surgeons musicians actors
directors dads from soccer friends all that disappears and we go boxing and in your studio
in my in my art studio and uh it's something magical has happened there to like
one is so committed it's like a cult you can come and check it out there's a um you have to
initiation no there's no there's no initiation um yeah it's just yeah how many how many turn up
this morning there was about 20 that was a big one sometimes there's six everyone really wants
to turn up sometimes they can't there's no ego there they all box equally as bad
they're not that bad everyone's improving a lot
i yell at them and make fun yeah we just put on music sweat a lot there's no ego it's not
macho kind of sparring each other it's just exercise it's great and that fills you up
oh you know so much fills me up it's that it's my kids it's my wife you know again success to me
is all of that yes i like to fly business class and i'll work really hard to send my kids to a
good school but i think it's uh just having good positive people like me for who i am and
no one there wants anything from each other my family doesn't want anything from me i like people
that connect because they like the person this is the one piece of advice that you've consistently
passed on in all the success that you've had find it might not even be what you're good at
but hopefully you are but find what you're passionate about and then every day is going
to be positive and successful and you'll probably fly um you know we're here for you
i get taught this lesson all the time michael godinski heath other friends like life can be
cut short you know someone like neil denneher just blows my mind with positivity surround
yourself with positive people and make your life and your work about something you're passionate
about pretty solid advice that the vision of what you do is is unique i'm assuming there's a
a team behind that as well that help you bring that vision to life how do you
share your unique view of the world to make that come together i i've listened to a lot of books
because i'm because of my um not being able to read and one of them was years and years ago
richard branson who's also dyslexic saying to be successful in life and business you need to know
what you're not good at and let your ego not in these words but let go of your ego and find
and allow people to do what you're not good at and don't micromanage
them so i'm not good at many many things and you know i've found people that can help me
and let them do what they're good at and i'll do what i am good at so people are inherently curious
who have success like you can you tell us how curiosity shows up for you and is there different
rabbit holes that your curiosity takes you down so this is another big deal for people that really
have strong adhd we can concentrate obsessively
for 15 hours i can i can get done when i'm in the zone not trying to brag but i could get two weeks
of what other people could do done in 15 hours and this is part of the gift but can i just jump on
that for a second sorry to interrupt you but so you've you've taken this and you can just paint
for 15 hours and it's and nothing else matters in that time i won't even stop to eat um i'll be
dehydrated i'll have my music on and i'll be in the zone and i'll be in the zone for 15 hours
i'll be dancing i'll be painting and having the best time in my life and the only thing that stops
me is absolute exhaustion and you're just on a roll it's like i i'm looking at this painting
come alive and i'm it's like this it's like drugs you can also have a fall from that as well but
with adhd and things like that you can also i'm very aware if i'm in the concentration zone i
have my art in front of me you can get in that zone on the internet you can get in that zone
you have a new little interest and you just become obsessed and time just disappears and
this is what happens to kids or adults that aren't aware of it you know next thing you know
you're a gaming dad that sits in the garage i don't do gaming but you know that you can fall
into these negative rabbit holes or positive i love cooking i might become obsessed i'm cooking
you know every single day i'm cooking i'm cooking i'm cooking i'm cooking i'm cooking i'm cooking
and they're like can you stop cooking this stuff and i have to get it right
um i've been trying to figure out forever i love people and i love success not just
celebrity of money or i just like successful people that are achieving great things game
changes and and i'm trying to figure out and you're probably doing the same what is it that
they all have in common often it's that they are passionate about it i haven't figured it out yet
have you figured it out
i'm figuring it out through you today and that's that's exactly what you picked up on is this
pattern around and and we see the patterns isn't it from an i need to know the the recipe for
coca-cola you know it's like and i think we see these these are being some of the common things
the next one i ask you about is this idea of collaboration i love this idea that the sort
of cost of great leadership is time and that to still be able to spend 15 hours on a panic as you
can but also to have a
family and make life function at the same time how do you make all that work well this makes me
think again a friend of mine uh larry kesselman very successful um lucky enough to have larry on
the podcast and oh really yes incredible uh so we're working together now so larry's helping me
with business and i'm sticking to the creative stuff we have nothing to gain from each other
except for the adventure of maybe changing the game a little bit like we talked about like the
chefs have done
nice to have that support he said to me extraordinary people put an extraordinary
effort most kids will be training three days a week there's a kid that's training
seven days a week not because he's forced to but you have to make sacrifices you know i watched
that david beckham doco and he looks like a big beautiful star and he was in bed early he was the
first one at training last one to leave all of that um you know obsessive wasn't it when you
that yeah what i what makes me scared of that is this balanced situation where i know i could paint
more but then my kids wouldn't know who i am yeah but then there is someone that's painting more and
they might be more successful and i'm competitive and i think oh well if i'm going to be able to do
that i need to do what the other person is doing i look at a lot of people very successful not all
of them and a lot of people that fall by the wayside in their lives and you know picasso
suicides all over the place and i'm like oh my god i'm not gonna be able to do that i'm not gonna be
and you know whatever tennis player has a good relationship with his family and we all love him
but they his kids might be falling to pieces so i um i also struggle with how do i push to the limit
of what fills my bucket there but also what's more important with my family and my friends
it's a great question isn't it and i ask that of myself all the time and other people around
what your definition of success means isn't it
and what does it mean to you it's i love you asher my kids i want them to say the same thing
about both of us and luca's mom as well you know i want them to say they were loved that i was a
good dad and that's why they're the great people that i hope they will be i don't want to we're
all going to fuck it up um michael godinski always said to me don't fuck it up a lot of
people say it to me for some reason um but i i don't want to fuck it up so you know i want to
inspire people to be artists to be successful but i don't want it not at any cost to my family
so success to me is finding this balance one of the great people michael godinski
anyone else the the next to me i want to talk to you about which i'm really fascinated to ask is
about the way people communicate is something they're pretty um clear on for the success they
have the traditional way of communicating for you reading and writing is that you're not just
writing has not been available to you by the sounds of it and and the challenge you've had
but even spending a little bit of time with you and having a coffee a minute ago you've got this
incredible way of almost instant connection and can you describe how that is is that something
you think about or i think we just bromance we just have an instant uh connection you know and
i i notice those things and i feel uh really grateful when they happen i'm very open to you
know some people say oh i have an
uh friends you know but then you might miss out on something really special in your life
you know and i remind myself not to judge as well you can meet someone on a day and it's not the day
and you judge them and you might you might miss out you know someone's dog died you know they're
having a bad day they're not going to be the friendly guy they normally would girl whatever
it is i try and give myself and other people chances
whom i'd say give someone a chance like i love people and i want to learn about them and i'm very
open to you know what i can learn i just love learning and meeting people is the best way to
learn vincent who's been the greatest leader in your life i could just run a whole list i have
such incredible friends i don't want to i don't want to not tell one of the good leaders in my
life i don't want to tell one of the good leaders in my life i don't want to tell one of the good leaders
in my life you know there's people like larry or mates like you know nick williams just people that
are there for me and i learned something from them but neil danaher um you know we had a very
special connection when you did neil's portrait yeah so the i now know uh more than ever about
footy i didn't grow up with it so i had no idea i didn't have a team my whole life asher is mad
about collingwood and i'm sorry even though she's got a massive hawthorne connection
yes her uncle was a bob ketty um i didn't know about football i only met neil for who he was
and when someone introduced us and i thought uh you know i feel people's energies and i was a
little bit worried about going to see him because he's not well and it's you know not worried i just
knew that i would feel it not at all i left there thinking i could take the world on and i don't
know what he was as a coach before you know as a person i don't know what he was as a person
i just know this guy in front of me and unlikely friends you know and i knew he liked me and i
liked him back and um yeah every time i see him i leave it's so it's weird i just think i can do
anything recently he asked asher and i to do he's doing a new campaign for a tv ad and he doesn't
necessarily like the crowds and all the people you know he has a lot of it and he was pretty quiet
that day and a lot of people
around i always give him a bit of shit and he gives me shit but he's got a very funny dark
sense of humor he can't speak so he looks at ipad and his eyes move and it says something
but he hadn't said much i made some crack at him i was walking off thinking i was cool he goes
that means hey hold on so everyone turns and they're all listening there's a whole crowd of
people and he's typing and then he says your hair looks shit house and it's just you know it's just
like i just love
that all this stuff going on in the world and he's cracking a joke is you know he might be the
most inspirational person i've ever been yeah company of and that yeah the fighting the beast
that he has and and that still have that humor and make you feel good when he was really supposed to
not live more than a year and he's 10 years on 11 years on raised 100 million dollars for disease
that no one survived long enough to and yet he has that impact uh you just want to be a better
person when you're around him and he's got a lot of humor and he's got a lot of humor and he's got
a lot of derp around neil denna don't you listen and he but he also just send me a text saying how
you doing yeah yeah random yes special amazing human being we're a bit obsessed vince with this
idea of collaboration and i look at all your work is effectively collaboration isn't it whether it's
painting michael godinski or neil danaher or this you know what we're doing yeah it's it's it's
everywhere has there been in any of your passions you thought god that's the one person and i'd love
Is there a name that comes to mind?
I've had great collaborators.
I've done a lot of work with Baz Luhrmann, Matt Moran.
I haven't even spoken about someone like Matt Moran.
He's like a brother, godfather to my kids, always giving me good advice.
He's a great leader to me as well.
The painting of Heath wouldn't be what it was unless it was a collaboration.
I love the visual language.
I would love to collaborate with a filmmaker and make a film.
I'm not sure I have a few friends in mind.
Yeah, but I want to tell a story.
Every night, I don't know about you or people listening, I don't sleep much,
but I dream so much.
It's exhausting, like epic films.
I see the lighting.
I can smell it.
I can hear.
I have dialogue that I couldn't come up with myself.
I'm like, fuck, I'm not that smart, and it's in my dream.
Do you remember it?
I have so many ideas.
I remember a lot of it, yeah.
I watch good films every night.
I'm exhausted when I wake up, but I want to share some of the stories.
Yeah, so taking the art creativity to the screen.
Comedy.
No, I'm just kidding.
Vincent, I could talk to you for another two hours.
It's such a fascinating thing to sit down.
I have a lot of questions for you.
Maybe one day we flip it and I podcast you.
And it would be far less interesting.
I promise you than this.
For those that, if you haven't had a chance, go and buy Unveiled.
It's an extraordinary piece of work, an amazing life story.
It's not a piece of work.
It's your life story, and it's remarkable.
I'm a piece of work.
It sounded a bit like that, didn't it, as I said that?
I encourage you to go and read it, buy it,
and if you haven't caught up with some of the geniuses of Vincent Fantuzo,
it's a great pleasure to spend some time with you.
Look, thanks heaps.