Today's conversation is without question the most heartbreaking and powerful conversation
I've ever had.
Wayne Holdsworth, as a father and husband, wants to share his story.
It's one I think everyone needs to listen to.
We know conversations like this may be triggering and difficult for many people.
There is help available, headspace.org.au or call Lifeline on 13 1114.
I got a call from Scott Pape, the Barefoot Investor, who I consider a friend.
I've been lucky enough to chat to him in this forum on a couple of occasions.
He's very kind-hearted, empathetic and full of integrity.
He rang me and he said, I've heard the most heartbreaking story ever.
He said, I'm writing about it in my column today.
It's the hardest thing I've ever had to write about.
And he went on to tell me of a 16-year-old boy in our community, as he described, happy,
healthy, captain of his footy team, who had taken his own life after being extorted on
the internet.
And he said to me, I know this is going to break your heart as well as a father of four.
He comes from...
a great family.
And I'd love you to meet his dad, Wayne Holdsworth.
Wayne, I'm sitting across from you today on the back of that conversation.
I can't express enough sympathy or empathy for what you and your family have gone through.
I can't imagine walking in your shoes at all.
But I know you're incredibly passionate about trying to protect someone else's family from
this happening to you and you want to tell the story.
Can you share it with us?
Yeah, I will, Luke.
And thank you very much for having me today.
It's really important that we share the messages that are important.
Yeah, back on October 24th, last year, 2023, my 17-year-old son then, he took his own life.
He took his own life at home and it was very early in the morning when I discovered him.
Unfortunately, he had hung himself and the only other person in the house at that point,
my wife had already gone to work, was my 15-year-old daughter.
And so to discover him and then to scream and then to try to manage a situation,
without my young daughter being affected by seeing him, was really confronting.
The grief, the sorrow, the helplessness, the blame, all those feelings just combined into one.
And, you know, I often talk about this, that, you know, when you're growing up as a young boy,
you often look to your mum or dad for guidance with regards to values and process and procedures
to run your life.
But there's no book as to how to find your son when they've just taken their own life.
And so you've got to find your son.
Flying by the seat of your pants, I laid him down after cutting him down
and my tears were dropping on his face.
He was cold and he was rigid and his face had changed colour totally.
And then to have to lay him down and then my daughter said they're on the phone now
and I grabbed the phone and asked her to stay there.
That whole process sticks with me every day.
And fortunately for me, Luke, I was connected with a group called Support Up.
And they gave me the tools, strength and resilience to be able to get through the funeral.
There was 700 at his funeral, which was quite a big funeral.
Then getting through that, getting back to work straight away, which is important to me.
I run basketball on the peninsula.
And then getting through Christmas was really difficult for the first time.
And I'm not only managing my feelings, but I'm managing my whole family as leader of the family.
You know, I have a 15-year-old, I have a 20-year-old and my oldest son is 30.
And when he heard the news, when I called him that morning, he runs a gym, Luke,
and he fell to the ground and just crawled up in a ball.
And so after Christmas, I thought to myself, there's three things that I can do.
I can take my own life and I did have suicidal thoughts leading up to that period.
I didn't think life was worth it.
The second thing was to just live the shell of the person that I wanted to be
and just go through life.
As a zombie, so to speak.
Well, the third thing was to use Max's death as a catalyst for change.
And so I chose the third thing.
And one thing that has always stuck in my mind,
and I've always worked in sport and administration,
is that things have changed in life.
Back in the 80s, expectations of men and women were different.
Community standards were different.
And if I use the AFL as an example,
they're leaders in the field of setting agenda,
for good people.
And one of the things I learned from them is that I had to evolve as a person.
I had to start to reconnect with people and to be able to listen better.
And so I talked to many experts in the field in mental health.
I call it mental fitness now because mental health is such a stigma.
And spoke to people in South Australia and New South Wales
that have got and developed some programs
that have been cutting edge that are making a difference.
Because unfortunately,
whether we like it or not,
here in Victoria and where I work down at Frankston,
there's a five-week waiting list at Headspace.
And so I know through research that if kids are feeling a certain way
and are struggling five weeks is a long period,
chances are they'll take their own life or do something, harm themselves.
I also know that 80% of the people that present to hospital
attempting to take their own life
end back there doing anything.
And again, or taking their own life.
So as a response to that, I said, enough is enough.
And I know it's a phrase used by many, but it is.
We have to educate everybody to be better friends,
to recognize the signs that I've been trained in now,
and to ensure that you've got really good listening skills.
And Luke, if I'd known what I know now back on the 23rd of October,
I wouldn't be here today.
I'd have my son, and I'd be watching him playing footy on Sunday.
It breaks your heart, mate.
I just can't even get the words out, mate, to understand.
The courage to take path three is remarkable, and it does.
You think of your own family, mate, in that light.
And I think the detail's hard to listen to
because we were told for so long not to talk about these things.
And you know now the evidence is we have to.
Yeah.
That's why you're here,
to share this with your family.
Yeah.
To share this conversation so families listen.
So I talked to my 17 and 13-year-old last night,
and I said, this is what I'm doing today.
This is the story of Mac.
This is what happened to him.
And I think probably worth giving some more detail.
He's 16.
He's living a happy life.
He's on Snapchat.
Gets a message from what appears to be a teenage girl.
This is happening every single day.
And he did what every parent hopes.
He came to you and said, Dad, I'm in trouble.
Yeah.
That's right, Luke.
That's exactly what happened.
He spent a lot of time after work,
or after footy training, in his room, on these mediums.
And one night, he had someone make contact with him
that he thought was a young girl.
And I've seen the photos of that young girl,
and she looked about 20.
And she eventually exposed herself and said to Mac,
oh, you play footy.
You must have abs.
Can you show me what you've got?
And he didn't.
He did.
Then she said, that's great.
Can I now see your face and full body?
And he shared that picture with whom he thought
was a young lady on the internet.
And this all occurred in 30 minutes.
So he was on the internet.
He was befriended.
And he was using Instagram and Snapchat,
as well as a couple of other programs.
And then the first...
The phone rang, and he picked the phone up.
And it was a middle-aged man.
He turned out to be from Liverpool, New South Wales.
And he was a money mule for a cartel in Russia.
And he said to Mac, I now have your photos.
I've hacked into your account, your Instagram account.
Here are some of the addresses.
And he was right.
He had...
Mac was a bit naive with social media.
And he said, if you do not give me $500,
I'm going to share these pictures.
And he gave Mac a bank account.
And Mac immediately sent the $500 to him,
which is a mistake.
He shouldn't have done that.
About five minutes after that, the phone rang again.
And it was the guy.
And he said, I've got the $500.
I want another $500.
And if you do not pay me the $500,
your parents will be embarrassed.
They will hate you.
Your friends will see you.
And you will want to kill yourself.
So Mac came rushing into me.
And he said, Dad, can we go into the kitchen?
I said, yeah, because my wife was there.
He said, Dad, I've made a mistake.
And he told me.
I said, mate, you've made no mistake.
And I put my arms around him.
And I had this anger in me, Luke,
that I'd like to rip this guy's throat out.
I was really angry because he told me what had happened.
And he was starting to...
He was really resilient.
He was in and under.
Football is really tough.
And he started getting a little bit emotional.
And I said, I'm with you, mate.
We'll sort this out.
And the phone rang again.
And I said, give it to me.
And he handed it to me.
And he said that I want $500.
And I said, well, I am Senior Detective Holdsworth
from the Mornington Police Station.
And I have your number.
And he said, I don't care.
I hope your son dies.
And I hope you die.
And at that point, I hung up.
I couldn't control that anymore.
So we went to the police.
Luke, we went to the police immediately.
And I said, Mac, are you OK to share this stuff?
And he said, as long as you don't see the pictures, Dad, of course.
Because I said, this guy's committed a really serious crime.
And we went to the Mornington Police.
And they were terrific, really supportive.
And they endorsed what I was saying about him being the victim.
Because Mac was embarrassed by it.
So the police said, we'll take down the details.
But there is no chance we're going to catch this guy.
He'll be a money mule.
And the bank account details will be from overseas.
And we can't trace it.
But we'll take down your details, et cetera.
And the statement.
Well, about three days later, I got a call.
And they said, we'd found him.
And I was elated.
And I said, how did you do that?
And he said, this money mule decided to cut out the cartel
and use his own bank account details.
And they were able to trace it.
And so they picked him up.
He was also on.
He had some drug charges as well.
And they charged him.
And then last January 2024, his case was heard.
Mac was asked to give a victim impact statement.
But all this got too much for him, Luke.
And he couldn't do it.
And I wrote one.
And I went to Liverpool in January 17th, I think it was.
I went there.
And with the full intention of reading this out,
the magistrate didn't allow it
because the accused decided with the prosecution and the defense
that he plead guilty to a lesser offense
of receiving the proceeds of crime.
And therefore, my statement wasn't valid.
And he received six months, of which he'd already served three.
He was already in for three months.
So he's out.
He was out in March or April.
And Luke, I have no doubt.
He showed no remorse.
In fact, when he was asked,
how do you plead?
He said, I plead guilty, but I'm the victim.
And so he's now on the streets now.
So I say to every parent out there, Luke, every parent,
that if your son or daughter falls into this trap,
don't give them any money.
Often they're bluffing and they haven't got the addresses.
In Mac's case, they did.
But take them on.
Yeah, the anger levels, mate, are off the charts.
I can't imagine.
You know, if you're to sit in court and the needle in a haystack
to actually find that person and the suspicion is that he's out there
doing the same thing again and six months is just bullshit.
It's for the devastation and the ripple that causes.
It's just, it's not enough.
It must make you angry beyond despair to have had to go up
and face that creep and that coward and see that happen.
What's the answer to that?
First of all, Luke,
in my opinion, there's been a miscarriage of justice here
in that I heard the man's voice and as soon as he spoke,
because he had an Asian accent,
as soon as he spoke and said not guilty and that he's the victim,
I started shaking because I remembered that voice
and that should have been used as some sort of evidence
because I recognised his voice.
But more importantly, he was allowed to plead guilty,
to a lesser charge.
The consequences of his actions caused my son in part
to take his own life.
And there is something so wrong with the legal system
to allow people like that to get through the net
because I have no doubt that the 17% increase
in the suicide rate here in Victoria in this quarter
compared to the first quarter of 2023
is related to extortion sexually.
Because sexual extortion is up 400%.
And the number one killer for young males in Australia
from Mac's age at 16 through to 54 is taking your own life.
It's a horrific statistic.
You said to me before,
if I had have known what I know now,
I wouldn't be sitting here and Mac would still be alive.
What have you learnt that you need to share?
Yeah, definitely.
Thanks, Luke.
It's about looking out for the signs
and looking out for the signs.
And one of the signs is that they change completely
and all of a sudden become overly happy.
And we planned a trip to Hawaii
about six weeks before he took his own life.
And we'd all saved up for two years.
We hadn't been on a holiday for ages as a family.
And we all went.
And he not only saved up for that,
but he spent his whole savings on that trip.
And he was buying shoes for all of us,
buying all, taking us out to dinner.
And I'm thinking, this is really odd
because he just wanted to have it.
And the last night we went to this restaurant
and we had to wait a little while, about 15 minutes.
And he said, hey, Dad, can we sit over there?
And Maggie, my wife,
would you mind taking a photo of the two of us?
And he put his arm around me.
And he wasn't overly that way,
but he put his arm around me and was smiling.
And there was another sign.
He's doing things that are a bit unusual.
And then,
the very night before,
he was the happiest I've ever seen him.
He was kicking his younger daughter
underneath the table at the dinner table
because I was cracking some real stupid dad jokes.
And he said to me,
as he was going to bed at nine o'clock,
because he got up pretty early,
he said, hey, Dad,
can I drive my car to work tomorrow?
He's on L plates to work tomorrow.
And I said, yeah, mate, no worries.
Just we'll go together.
And the very last words he said to me was,
I can't wait to drive my car in the morning.
And so there's that.
And he was really happy.
So that's one of the things.
One of the other things is that
if kids stop doing things that they normally love doing,
and it might be they love going to footy training,
for example,
or they love painting,
or they love hiking,
and all of a sudden they stop it.
That's a sign.
Something's not quite right.
And one of the questions that
when I do my presentations for Smack Talk,
I talk about,
if you see that,
don't be afraid to go up and say to someone,
I used to ride your bike a whole lot.
How come you don't ride it anymore?
And if they can't look you in the eye,
and if they start shaking,
or if they get a bit teary,
that's an opportunity to ask further questions.
And typically,
typically it's around their mental fitness.
And one of the hardest questions to ask someone
that breaks down in front of you
and looks down
and doesn't want to look you in the eye.
And if you ask them
if they've got suicidal thoughts
and they break down,
that's when you're in lifeline
and you will save their life.
Look, I gave a presentation
about six weeks ago.
And it was in the afternoon.
It was in the eastern suburbs.
And there was 80 people there.
And it was for adults.
And this person had slipped through
that was 15
because he was six foot seven
and he's a basketballer.
And he was there with his mum and dad.
In the afternoon,
I got a call,
a random call,
but I picked it up.
I always pick up calls now.
And it was this young voice.
And he said to me,
hi,
he didn't recognise,
he didn't tell us what his name was.
I was at your session today
and I heard you speak.
And I said,
you're 15.
He said, yeah,
I was with mum and dad.
I said, who's with you now?
And he said, mum's with me.
You're on loudspeaker.
And I said, how can I help you?
And he said,
Luke, he said to me,
I was on a bridge last night
at 15.
And I said,
right, where are you?
And we got to him.
And mate,
I put my arm around him and his mum
when we were in Lifeline.
And he now is okay.
He's seeing a counsellor.
But he was ringing me
at seven o'clock every night
for about two or three weeks
every night
just as a comfort call
and thank you.
Mate,
I just wish I'd known that.
I would have saved Mac.
And something,
it just has to change,
Wayne,
in the most prolific way.
I was looking up
before this conversation last night
of,
Mark Zuckerberg
makes $205 billion
a year Australian
out of putting that app
on our phones.
He makes close to $12 billion
every three weeks.
Teen suicides are at record levels.
Anxiety and mental health epidemic
is just of the likes of which
people don't even quite understand.
Eating disorder crisis.
And it's irrefutably linked
to those social media apps
that cost Mac his life.
It's destroying a generation.
I know you've,
you've spent time
lobbying government.
You're consistently up in Canberra
wanting to make a difference.
What's your message?
What do you say?
Yeah,
firstly,
my message to him,
hopefully he gets this one day,
is that he's cheating.
He's come into Australia
with his product or service
and doesn't fulfil the values
that Australians hold
nor the laws that they portray.
You know,
he had to stand for the sixth time
in front of the Senate,
turn around to a gallery
of 100 families,
had kids take their lives
and had to stand there
and they made him look at them
and made him take some accountability
and you thought that needle changed.
But we know whenever greed knows no bounds
and what does one human do
with that amount of money is in itself.
So there's so much scope
to be able to pull that back, isn't there?
But we, and we can make it,
we can make a difference.
India banned TikTok in a day.
That's right.
Done.
That's over.
Yep.
And, and I think with,
with him,
for an example,
you know,
it's not about the money,
it's about the power
and that reminds me of a person
that, you know,
terrorised his race way back
and we know who Adolf Hitler was
and I really,
I really worry about
that style of person
infiltrating Australia
with the power that he has.
However,
we now have an opportunity.
We know as Australians
that this exposure
is killing our young folk.
We have no,
no difficulty in understanding
that there's a direct relationship
with what they're being fed,
the algorithms that are underpinning
and,
and then the actions
that particularly young boys
and young girls are taking,
you know,
through eating disorders,
through sexual extortion,
through bullying.
And so we as Australians
have to say to the government,
enough is enough.
You have to make a call
on what our kids are allowed to do.
You tell them that
they have to wear a seatbelt in a car.
You tell them that you can't drive
until you're 18.
You say they can't drink
until they're 18,
although some do.
Why don't you?
Why don't you make a law
that says that kids under 16
cannot be exposed to this?
And if it needs to be 18,
so be it.
Because if the government does that
and I know Whipper's doing
a really good job in lobbying,
the kids be kids
are doing the same thing.
There's a joint select committee
set up in Canberra
that I met last week.
Some of the people
that are involved in that,
the chairperson of that,
they all agree
that this has to happen.
Well, bloody do it.
Get it done in August
and get legislation in November
and save our kids
because there will be some kids
that are clever enough
to get around it
and they'll work it out
or Zuckerberg
will sort something out.
But if we can at least
save 50% of those kids
and make it easier on the parents
so the parents aren't the bad guys,
it's the law.
I was home last night
and the conversation
still every night,
17 and 13 year olds still there,
the phones get locked in another room,
you fight to get them off them.
I've got active kids
that are healthy
and doing a whole range of things
but it's something that
I have people say to me,
just take them off it
and they are always people
who aren't parents.
Correct.
This is where their whole connection,
it's like asking them
to cut an arm or a leg off
is what you're effectively doing
and remove themselves
from their whole community.
What we need are some guardrails.
Now we're fighting hard
on the home fronts.
All of us,
we're not asleep at the wheel here
as parents
but as we said,
you know,
Seatbelts saved
tens of thousands of lives
because we needed legislation
to do,
there is no downside
Whippers campaign
to get the 36 months
and the age limit up
is an absolute no brainer.
We can go further on this,
do zero damage
and only have the upside
and I think
we just,
we can't afford
more tragedies like this.
They're happening
far too often, Wayne
and for you to,
as you said,
take the path of education,
you know,
more strength to your arm on this.
Yeah, thanks mate.
Look,
you know the figures.
There was 801 people
that took their own life
in Victoria alone
in 2023.
There were 299 people
die on the road
so it's two and a half times
the number of people
died on the road,
took their life
compared to dying on the roads
and 50 people drowned.
So in comparison,
and when I was growing up
in the mid-70s,
there was a campaign
Declare War on 1034
because it was 1034 people
died on Victorian roads
that year
and now it's down to 299.
As you said, Luke,
we're the first country,
our first state in the world
to introduce compulsory seatbelts,
drink driving laws,
better roads,
better vehicles,
better education
so it can be done.
We have to do it
because our kids
are becoming,
they're so precious
and to lose them
because of things
that we're in control of,
it's not as if they've developed
a rare form of cancer
or they're in a car accident
and it's unavoidable.
This is avoidable
and we're lame as citizens
if we don't force the government
to make a difference
and to change it.
They'll look back on our generation
and shake their head
and say,
what the fuck did you guys do?
And the language,
the language is there on purpose
because the solutions are there
and I have to mention
this beautiful,
extraordinary person,
Zoe Kalar,
who's created We Are Right.
I don't know if you've come across it.
It takes out the anonymity
so immediately 90% of the hate is gone.
It's social media for good.
It's putting that 135 billion US
from Zuckerberg
back into the hands of community.
It's only positivity in there.
They could switch off
the hate and the algorithms tomorrow
but they keep you on those apps
with anxiety,
anger,
because they know
that's what keeps you
and they jam advertising at you
to make more money.
We can pull that back.
You know, government,
spend your digital advertising
on We Are Right.
Let's get the community voice
coming through.
Let's legislate to up the age limit,
which is a no-brainer.
Let's have an education program
that you're doing every single day
teaching families
how to deal with this better
to save lives.
It's an incredible contribution
you're making, Wayne.
I know it's heartbreaking
to even think about
what you've been through
but, you know,
I didn't meet your beautiful
young lad, mate.
I wish I did
but I feel like he's going to save
a lot of people, mate.
Yeah, yeah.
I'm doing it.
I'm doing what I do now
to create a legacy for him
and to use his death as a catalyst
to do more in this space
and, you know,
I've been out now to see
just over 1,500 people
normally in the after hours
because I work, you know,
Monday to Saturday
in basketball full-time.
And my board have been
really supportive
to allow me to do
what I need to do
to help the community.
And when I talk to people
about the signs,
it's new to them.
When I talk to them
about the statistics,
it's new to them.
You know, one in five people
here in Australia
have suicidal thoughts.
You know, we talk about
fitness in the footy field.
You know, we see someone
limping into the change rooms
and, you know,
Christian Petrarca, you know,
coming off the ground
and, you know,
that's had so much
exposure.
Because it was such
a horrific injury.
Because we can see it.
But mental fitness,
we can't see it.
But I want people to ask
not only how you're going,
Christian, you know,
physically,
but how's your mental fitness going?
And if he says,
shit, it's at about five or six now,
we need to talk to him more.
And we need to be talking
to people that have got
mental challenges
and to be able to support them
through that.
And know what to do.
You know, 12 people
have come into my office alone.
You know, big basketballs.
You think that are
impervious to this.
They've come in crying.
You know, I have to tell them
to sit down so I can
get level with them.
You know, and
they're in a world of pain.
But if I can do that
and then I refer them on
to someone that can help them,
they multiply that by
20 and 40 and 100.
And then we're fighting back.
And so,
my program called
Smack Talk.
So if anyone wants to jump online
and book a session,
it's free.
I go out to anywhere in Victoria.
I'm going to New South Wales
and Queensland on weekends
to educate people,
sporting groups,
corporate groups.
And I'll talk to mums and dads
about the signs,
about having good listing skills,
about the statistics.
Just trying to make a difference, mate.
Why no one would choose this path.
You didn't choose this path.
But, you know,
heroes come in,
all shapes and sizes.
And, yeah,
I'm full of admiration for
you and your family
and what you've been through.
And thanks for joining me today
and telling the story.
Thanks very much, Luke.
Pleasure.
Thanks for listening to another episode
of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Huge thanks, as always,
to our great friends at Temper.
And we encourage you to check out
our Leader Connect program.
New episodes are out
every Wednesday morning at 6am.