I'm sure you're going to enjoy this week's episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast
with the extraordinary Dr. Shefali from her office in New York.
Dr. Shefali is arguably the world's leading voice on parenting.
You'll hear Shefali talk about how idiotic and crazy her words are, the old model of
parenting is.
The strange notion, she says, that we think our kids owe us something and the revolution
she's starting that tells parents that we need to work on ourselves before we can have
any hope of parenting consciously, a word that she uses and has really brought to the
mainstream, conscious parenting.
She reminds us that we actually learn more from our kids than our kids learn from us.
And you'll hear her bemusement, the story I tell her that in Australia we have parent
umpire escorts at junior sport to protect teenage umpires from other parents and that
sometimes the umpire escorts themselves abuse umpires.
She found that extraordinary but not surprising would be the way I would describe it.
Thank you.
We'll jump on and have a chat to you about how you can start your own journey of self-development
with us at Aleda.
We'd love to hear from you and love sharing stories like we are today with the remarkable
Dr.
Shefali.
Huge thanks as always to the team at Tempur Australia and New Zealand to Jason Nicholas
and his team, the extraordinary support that they give us in bringing stories like this
to the table thank you to temper sleep and recovery as we know are crucial in achieving
success in all aspects of life and then investing in your sleep and your success has never been
easier i've been sleeping on mattresses provided by temper for more than 15 years it's a life
changing experience when you think about so much of your life is spent in bed to invest in a temper
mattress is an investment that you will never regret dr shifali was born in bombay india before
moving to san francisco at the age of 21 she did a master's degree at the california institute of
integrated studies and a phd in clinical psychology at columbia university she's a three times new
york times best-selling author her book the conscious parent has been endorsed by oprah
winfrey as a parenting revolution she's an international speaker recognized globally as
an expert in family dynamics and personal development integrating her expertise in
western psychology and eastern philosophy dr shifali it's great to spend
some time with you this morning thanks for your time oh absolutely thank you for having me
shifali we're passionate in the conversations i have around talking to different leaders in
different settings and i love the opportunity whether it's someone who works in sport or works
in the arts or in a range of different areas but probably to me the thing shifali that unites us
all is our leadership on the home front and you've put that term conscious parenting on the map
globally can you explain for you what conscious parenting
means so in order to understand conscious parenting we do need to understand the traditional
parenting model which conscious parenting is trying to revolutionize so the traditional
parenting model is the one that probably you and i were raised in it's a model steeped in
parent knows best children should be obedient and follow the parents ways and it is bathed in
a fear-based model
of parenting mostly it's an underpinning of fear and control and shame and then all the things that
come when the child is not controllable and conscious parenting debunks that and changes
the playing field and talks about how the parent really needs to raise themselves i mean that's what
parenting is otherwise it would be called childing or kidding right some people say
kidding because the focus is on the parent
and i think when we don't focus on the parent and we instead focus on the child
presuming that we have this uber control and it's our mandate to have this control and use this
control to raise supersonic super achieving perfect children then this actually absolves
the parent of any real accountability for what they bring into the dynamic for how they
mess up their children and how they actually obstruct their children from achieving the very
goals that we think we should be achieving such as self-worth and empowerment and leadership and
direction the old paradigm the traditional model actually greatly impinges on our capacity to foster
that in our children so conscious parenting is a revolutionary model that speaks about speaks to
the parent raising themselves and i think it's a very important model that we need to be able to
understand that they must do the inner work to heal their own inner baggage from childhood
so that they can then truly see their children for who their children are versus an extension of their
utopic fantasy and uh all these expectations that the parent thinks is their right to have
around their children yeah it's such a brilliant shift in in mindset for everyone who's a parent
in my mind i love how you talk about perfect parenting
is your language that there's no ideal parent there's no ideal child and and i often talk you
know as a father of four that parenting guilt you get sometimes when you have a bad moment or you
yell at one of your kids or you know you just generally lose your cool or you get it wrong
is your message to that to say hey you know what you just got to do the best you possibly can with
the resources available to you and and strive to be the best example and then you are going to get
it wrong sometimes yeah we are going to get it wrong a lot of the times and even just what
you said that when our child is doing something wrong even that we can't say with objectivity
because that frame that interpretation is based on our conditioning our emotional baggage i mean
we could call a two-year-old throwing a tantrum as doing something wrong when actually they're
doing nothing wrong like zero nothing there's no need to even get upset the reason we get upset
is because we had an expectation and a
of how we would be in control and how the child would follow our ways so any deviation from that
we label as bad the child is doing something wrong and then we have this thing in the traditional
parenting model called parental discipline and we have this unchecked unlicensed unsupervised
power of our children to utilize anything under that rubric and actually we call it love so it's
all so messed up and uh it really
has consequences and we're seeing the consequences in our own lives we see oh damn i'm really not
filled with worth i'm really not uh independent and directed i'm heavily enmeshed or codependent
or passive and all these things come from early childhood patterns and the mandate that the
parent has that they need to create a child needs to be transformed to a mandate that they need to
heal themselves
and if we can just heal ourselves 95 of our problems with our children will go away because
our children will still have issues and they will still meet failure and they will still
enter dysfunctional relationships but the way we handle it will be so vastly profoundly
altered transformed and you know we can always make the choice of do i need to control the child
which is the old mandate or can i seek to understand attune
and connect with the child so conscious parenting moves away from control and fear and shame from
the old paradigm to one of connection before control and correction yeah and when you articulate
it as beautifully as you do there it's it's such the worthwhile goal and the attempt to uh to
achieve that makes a lot of sense that where do you sit then on some boundaries for your kids
as you said not control but you are as you said you know trying to fill them with love and love and
fill them with being present but clearly at some stage there has to be some boundaries as a parent
as well how do you how do you feel about that yeah well you you've asked the quote this in the third
question going into the interview uh because it's such a common example of when i start talking
about this immediately parents feel heckled like oh my goodness she's she's bullying me into
something and i cannot give up this control so you call it boundaries but but you're
coming from fear like hello can we have any boundaries right so i never said we can't have
boundaries but i think what people hear is oh she's talking about an anarchy and i refuse
to live in an anarchy and of course boundaries are part of any conscious relationship we aren't
going to give our children alcohol at the age of five and crack cocaine at the age of 10 don't
worry i'm not advocating that we we in fact have more boundaries when we're healed
we actually have a greater sense of awareness and attunement of what the child needs because
we're truly in the present moment not using the child for our own idealistic utopic fantasies
that are really a reflection of how bad we feel for ourselves and we're truly present so when
we're truly present with someone after being present for ourselves including our children
we automatically
have sane logical boundaries. You see, most of our boundaries come from this insane need to have
so many rules. And then we feel out of control when all these rules are not met, right? We have
to bathe them at 6.05 and have dinner by 7.42 and in bed by 8.12. We've created all these rules.
And it's because we have not examined how conditioned we are in culture. So the other
day, a family came to me, a couple with two children, and their biggest fight is that the
two children, no matter that their ages were four and six, some real small age, real young age,
these children were not sitting at the dinner table to eat dinner. And so when I, this is such
a common thing, you would wonder that, you know, why would people spend so much money to fix this
situation? But apparently it's a big deal. So when children don't sit at the table, parents lose their
shit, because it's our
conditioning that happy families sit together and talk, adult style, right? Well, children don't sit
at tables, and they don't want to sit with the adults, and they don't want to talk. Children
play, children move, children laugh, children giggle, children are aimlessly distracted.
And it drives parents crazy. So we've created a rule. And now we're talking about disrespectful
children. And now we're talking about punishment and boundaries. Guess what? None of it was
important.
None of it. We could just have had dinner on the floor, or dinner while moving and dancing and
playing. And so it comes from a conditioning. And once we examine our conditioning, and realize
that most of our conditioning is artificial, and really not attuned to what's happening before us,
we would realize that, oh, this idea of boundaries, which is amazing, but really, we mean control,
is not even important.
I bet you, if I took the last five times you were triggered by your children,
I can show you that it had to do with your conditioning and nothing to do with bad children.
Beautifully said. And yeah, it is a revolution, isn't it? And it does make sense. The practice
of it is the interesting part as well. You touched on this at the start, Dr. Shefali,
when you were talking about this obsession parents have got. I see in our community,
we've got a two-year-old with a golf club in his hand. You can see someone's trying to create the
next Tiger Woods. And I often hear parents with their kids during their last year of high school
saying, we're doing year 12. And all of the social engineering to try and get the friends they want
their kids to get. Can you expand on that? What's your advice to parents? Because that seems to be
such commonplace now, living vicariously through our kids. Yes. So that is a psychological disease.
And you have to ask yourself as a parent,
why do I need my child to achieve a social status or a level of greatness? Why? No, really, why?
We only do that not because we love our children, but because we feel so much inner lack of worth
ourselves that we use our children vicariously to fulfill that inner void. Because if you are
a fulfilled human being, and if you are very content in your own life's purpose, you will be
to allow your child to discover their own. And you will not direct it and micromanage it
because you don't need the badge of honor that your child is the next Tiger Woods.
And parents don't like this. But this is the revolution. We cannot use our children
to fill this emptiness within us. Our children's lives are theirs. They have nothing to do with
ours. Yes, they cost us a bundle and their pain in the neck. But the reward of that is not that
they now have to achieve greatness.
For us, the reward has to be implicit in the fact that we chose to have these children.
But now we have no right or jurisdiction to dictate and mandate how they live their lives.
Because we've decided that that's an honorable goal to be the next Tiger Woods or to be the next
Serena or Venus. And it worked for Serena and Venus, but please do not think it'll work for you.
And we don't know the cost. And we don't know the price.
Both the parent and the family and those children paid. And we've heard many stories of
adult superstars who talk about the plague of their childhood and how childhood was robbed
from them. Our children deserve a childhood to be children, not to become superstars in
the making for us parents to affix to a goal that will make us feel very worthy.
And I love, again, how you say, kids owe you nothing. They may choose to give you,
some love and respect, but they don't owe you anything. And that you talk about a savior
complex that we have and that martyrdom of parenting. It's again, another paradigm that
has to be shifted, doesn't it? Because it just results in more pain.
Right. So we have a savior complex. Some of us, not all of us, but those of us who have,
have this kind of playing God in our children's lives because we couldn't save ourselves and we
could not save our partners that we tried.
Uh, desperately. It doesn't work with adults. It's, and we think, ah, these children are ours
and therefore their mind to possess and control. I can play savior and God with them. And it's a
real Machiavellian, uh, manic delusion that we suffer from, but we, it's couched. You see,
it's disguised in love, in this idea that you're loving your children, right? So parents will say,
oh my goodness, I spent my whole life for the past 10 years.
At the baseball field. And I gave up all my weekends, but I don't think any child ever at
the age of four said to their parents, please, you know, I want to live my entire weekends for
the next 10 years on a baseball field. And if they do, and if they love it, they won't need
the parents sitting there sacrificing their time. So it's just a very contorted overzealous approach
that we parents have. And if we're really honest, which few of us are, it's because we want to
fill in the blanks.
A mandate about how we can be better parents for ourselves. We, we feel successful when we
see our children be successful. So Shafali, in the moment for parents, because, you know,
it's, it's, when you're sitting here having a nice relaxing conversation with you, it's a,
it's an easier conversation, but as we all know, we get stressed and we get tired and,
um, and moments happen. What sort of strategies have you got then
in those stressful moments to, to be more conscious?
Yeah. Well, listening to me is really never relaxing people, you know, get driven to anxiety
and they turn, they probably already turned off the podcast, um, because I call parents to examine
themselves and no one likes to do that. So in the moment, practical strategies, right. It there's,
there, there are none really, uh, you have to go through a process. So I wrote this book called
the parenting map. It's my fourth parenting book because I give the how to, but the how to,
has 20 steps. And most of them have to do with us examining our belief systems. Why are you on
that baseball field at two o'clock on a Saturday when you are exhausted and cranky and your child
is hating it and you're hating it? Why asking yourself at every moment, what am I doing here?
Is this about me or is this about my child? So the first practical strategy is awareness
and awareness doesn't seem practical, does it? Uh, every parent wants me to just say the magic
words and there's a wand and I can sell the wand. And that's the practical strategy. The
practical strategy is only awareness. And after awareness is activation of choices. You make
different choices, but you have to undo belief systems to make different choices. Parenting is
really the most unlicensed, uh, you know, job in the world where we don't have any mental status
check to, to become a parent. We are unsupervised. There's no continuing education.
And that is, uh, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's,
it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's,
it's appalling, isn't it? Uh, because again, the delusion of the old paradigm is that parents
know best. We actually don't know best actually. I mean, just this morning I was telling a mother,
uh, you know, can you actually not take your child out to lunch? And she was like, why? I
wanted to bond. I said, no, you don't want to bond. You want your child to bond to you.
There's a big difference. And she's like, no, no, no, no, no. I just wanted to find out how
she's doing. I said, uh-huh. You wanted to find out how she's doing.
We always have an agenda. Every sentence is an agenda. And she, she finally was like, okay,
what do you want me to do? I said, if you tell me you're going for lunch simply to exude love,
to exude warmth and, uh, give your child a sense of worth, then you can go. But if you're going
for a transaction or a deal or a negotiation or an agenda that you're going to feel good about
your parenting, that is not conscious parenting. And children figure that out and children
dissociate from us and they disconnect because they sense that every time they're around this
person, AKA the parent, there's something that needs to be done that they're not doing. And
there's always a life lesson and there's always an opinion and a sermon and a lecture. And the
practical is to connect. But first you have to be aware that you're not connected to your children.
You're using them as objects and minions, puppets to arrive at point A and children don't want to
arrive anywhere. They just want to be seen for the essence. It's like us going out with friends
and you have this friend who constantly tries to make you something else, makes you lose weight,
wear the right sunscreen, change your hairstyle, right? That's how we parents are.
And we don't like that friend. We like the friend who accepts us for who we are
and then works with that, but first sees us for who we are. So parents, when they listen to this,
they're like, Oh, what, you know, what rubbish? Of course I see my child for who it is they are.
I can guarantee you,
if, if every parent saw their child for who it is they truly were, we would not have addicts.
We would not have dysfunction. We would not have anger the way we do. We would be living in a very
different society. So the power of attuning to your child takes tremendous parental consciousness,
discipline, boundaries. The parent really needs the boundaries. It's the parent who's out of
control. Yeah. It's, it's so powerful. The words that,
you say, and it, and it does resonate so strongly. I've been smiling through this because your mind
goes to your own parenting, isn't it? And, and, and your own challenges in your own failures. And
just to me, it's the ultimate goal, isn't it? To want to do this, to do this well. And I was
thinking we've got four Shefali, our three boys and a girl, our second eldest is our only daughter,
Sienna. And we get very direct feedback from her at 18 years of age. She said to me the other day,
she said, I get my anger issues from you and my bitchiness from mum, she said the other day.
And for us,
any sense that you're trying to overlay any of you, your stuff on her, she just immediately gives
you the feedback. And it's like the kids know, they actually tell you, don't they? If you stop
and listen, it's like, Hey, I am doing that there. I am overlaying just, uh, be present as you said.
And, and then it tends to work out. Right. And, and there are certain boundaries that are
in stone. And I talk about that in one of my books, there are life enhancing boundaries,
like have a shower, please, at least a few times a week and brush your teeth every day.
And can you please go to school and just get through till 12th grade? Can we at least get an
education? Of course, but they're very few. If you really count the true life enhancing boundaries,
they're not more than five. I can guarantee you. And I've listed them out because how do we know
something is life enhancing and therefore should be in stone? It's because it'll be ubiquitous.
It'll be something that we all have to do in the modern world. And I say modern world,
because I can take out two from that.
Five, because in the old world, we didn't even have to do all five, but there's only five. So
if you as a parent stay aligned to, is this life or death? Is this worth going to war for? Is this
really important? If we all were going to die tomorrow, then you stay really calm, really
stable. Life is bliss and everyone's in flow. But because the modern world doesn't stay basic and
simple, and we've added pottery lessons and no, no, no dissing pottery, but,
being backwards and sign language and playing the trombone and learning how to make jewelry.
I mean, just endless things we want our children to become when they grow up. A little bit of
Julia Roberts, a little bit of Michael Phelps, a little bit of a football star, a little bit of
the Dalai Lama, a little bit of the Mother Teresa. I mean, we're crazy. Every day we have a new goal
for our children, right? So who drives the ship? We do, and we're driving it into the gutter.
You know, our children will tell us very clearly how to proceed.
What to invest in. And then parents will tell me, oh, but I just signed my four-year-old for a year
of piano lessons. And I say to the parent, well, what were you thinking? Like, do you not know who
a four-year-old is? Do you not know who a 17-year-old is? Don't spend money on them, right?
Don't invest in long-term projects because these children have holes in their brain and their brain
cannot sustain long-term goals, right? My child is 20, my daughter. I'm still telling her to say
please and thank you. I'll be so happy if...
That'll come out voluntarily from her mouth. And I'm so impressed at my parenting when it does.
So if you keep it very simple and you keep the expectations basic,
just because they are a completely different human being. We think we can micromanage this
entity, this corporation called these children. And that is our delusion. And we set ourselves
up and them up for failure. So every turn of the childhood, there's a failure happening.
Because of an unimaginable, impossible expectation. Take away the expectation,
the child is never a disappointment. Understand who children are, children will rarely disappoint
you because they're on point children. If you understand how really fragile their memory is
and how really disorganized and scrambled their brains are, you will have very, very basic
expectations. And then everything is a win after that. But if you have highfalutin,
expectations, you're setting yourself up. It's just like in a marriage, right? Really know who
your person is. Don't think there's something they're not. And don't think you can carve them
into something they're not because you will really suffer. And Shefala, you mentioned your
own daughter. Is there a layer when you're the conscious parenting expert globally and your
daughter is aware of that? Does that add an extra layer for you? It adds a lot of pressure. And I
tell my daughter to not hang out with my people unless she's willing to represent properly. And I
tell her, but she loves it. Oh, she just eats it up. And every time I lose my mind or I'm acting
very, very childish, she loves to tell me, oh, who is the conscious parent now? Oh, I see Dr.
Shefali. I see Dr. Shefali here. And she puts me in my place, but I love it because I want to be
called out. And I'm not pretending to be amazing in the first place.
So that's why in all my books, I write about my four powers and my absolute wretched ego and
talk about the fact that this is what it means to be a parent. But we all think we're these
infallible human beings and then set up our children to believe they need to be
perfectionistic, infallible beings because we're all living in utter
unacceptance of who it is we are as we are.
I'm okay being a total failure as a parent. You see, I'm okay if my child tells me that. I'm okay
with my child being ordinary, but most people are not. And that's why we live in inauthentic
relationships and everyone is faking it and hiding our true selves from each other.
Yeah, again, they're incredible words of wisdom. And as you said, you zoom out and you think of all
the challenges that are going on in the world, aren't they? As you said, with addiction and
the disconnect that's going on in the world. And I think that's a really important thing.
So much of it on the home front, isn't it? If we can understand that as accepting our kids for who
they are and being there. Nurture versus nature, where do you sit on that? It's one of the ultimate
debates, isn't it? How much do we affect them in the home front? How much influence do we have?
Well, there is an inexplicable and indisputable temperament and biological truth. I cannot
have brown eyes. I cannot have brown eyes. I cannot have brown eyes. I cannot have brown eyes. I cannot
be who I'm not on some basic biological level. And that biology feeds our temperament and the
temperament comes wired. Now, of course, we have neuroplasticity and of course, there's epigenetics.
But the mold, you know, with four children, it's kind of set. You kind of saw the differences
right away. My daughter is who she is today that she was at two years old,
just a grown up version of that. So when we honor the temperament,
which I call the essence, and we flow with that child's essence, we will have so much more flow
and beauty. You know, when my child was around, I think, 10 or 12, I wanted to be a competitive
mother, right? I wanted my child to be in horse riding champion races and do all the tournaments.
I wanted to buy a horse, buy a stable. I loved everything about it. It was all me, me, me.
But I tried to pretend it was me. I tried to pretend it was me. I tried to pretend it was me.
It could be her. And I was like, every other child I was seeing was in competitions. And my
daughter told me clearly, Mom, I hate it. I'm not a ham. I don't like attention. I don't like to be
judged. But I didn't listen. And I pushed her because I said to myself, no, no, when she she
doesn't know what she's talking about, when she does her first competition and does well, she will
see how amazing that aphrodisiac is because I'm a glutton for it. Surely she'll be a glutton for it.
So I pushed her.
She did it. She came second. And I thought, ah, see, I knew best. I should just see. Now she's
going to come out so thrilled and tell me, thank you, mother. You're my lifesaver. And
you've given me purpose. And she came out of the ring so angry with me. And she threw her,
you know, I had made beautiful pigtails. She threw the ribbon through the $500 jacket and
threw the helmet. I was like, what's wrong? Like you won. And she said, I don't care about winning.
I told her.
I hate being judged. I hate being the center of attention. And do you know what happened? She
gave up horse riding all together. She stopped horse riding. Like to punish me, she stopped
horse riding. And I was so humbled. And I blamed myself. And I immediately realized that I was
trying to push it. By then, I had done enough work on myself. But see, still, I pushed it. Even
though I was 10 years into conscious parenting, I was like, no, no, no, I can definitely push her.
And I apologized. And to this day, she will tell people how I've ruined her love for horses. I
ruined her childhood. She's right on that level. I totally didn't listen to her. And she knew best.
And I also raised a child to tell me when she doesn't want, but she was still young. So I had
a little wiggle room. But then she closed that door completely and taught me a grave, humble
lesson. Listen to your children. The answers are right there. Listen to your children. The answers
are right there. They will tell you how to proceed. And I did keep the receipt for the $500 jacket,
and I returned it. So you just have to listen and follow your children's temperament. They will tell
you who they are, and how much you can push them, and when to back off. And that's why parenting
done consciously is a very attuned, synchronized dance between parent and child.
The synchronized dance. It's,
again, another great theme that you write about regularly. I just heard you say,
you know, I apologized to my daughter then. I got it wrong. It's something that I've tried to do the
many times and the many mistakes along the way, because it wasn't something that I ever, I never
heard parents ever, growing up ever. Is that the right thing to do, if you get it wrong, to sit
down and put your hand up? Yeah, but that's only level one, right?
Children really don't need to hear our apology. That's a great first step. What they really need
is transformed behavior.
And, you know, many times we say, sorry, just for the child to say, okay, I forgive you. It's okay.
And then we come back with, well, if you had not, if you had not just done that, then mommy wouldn't
have raised a voice. Like if you had just listened, daddy wouldn't have lost his shit.
So we always trying to get our, you know, make them feel bad too. So apology is wonderful,
but often it's artificial and superficial. What's really important is to check your pattern.
Really,
go inward, inward and ask, well, why did I do that? What about my ego needed that in that
moment? What about my patterns are showing up again? And that's why in my book, The Parenting
Map, I show parents their five ego patterns and identifying that and then working on it and
healing it is the way to truly apologize with metamorphosis.
So Farley, the essence of the podcast I talk about is different leadership in different
settings. And as I said off the top, but to me, we are all leaders on the home front and we all
have this, as you said, it's this unlicensed, unregulated thing. You don't have to sit a
course or be regulated to be a parent. And there is no ongoing training as you described,
but we feel like success leaves clues. And we see people who tend to have consistently
positive experiences in life have these similar patterns. So I wanted to ask you,
a handful of questions along those lines. We feel like self-leadership, and it's probably the
essence of what you're talking about in every sense, isn't it? That if you're not leading
yourself, how can you lead your kids? What does that term mean to you, self-leadership?
Yeah, is leading your own happiness and leading your own worth. And what that means is that you
are accountable for your own successes, for your own happiness. It doesn't come from
anyone on the outside. And when you own and take accountability for your own self-directing,
your own self-governance, you then honor it in the child. When you value your own self-initiative,
when you value your life's path for all the mistakes, for all the waywardness,
but you see how the 10 mistakes you made from the ages of 15 to 35 got you to,
where you are now at 40, you honor that wayward path. And you begin to trust that life can look
awry and life can look disheveled, but we're learning from it. And so actually, when you have
that self-realization, you actually push your child to own their own path. Because you know
that a person who loses 100 pounds based on their own inner motivation versus a person who loses
100 pounds for a wedding or a pageant, the difference there in sustainability is so vast
that you would rather the child find their own inner voice and hold onto it because that'll last
versus you directing the ship and you steering the way and know that it will not last. But see,
you have to see it operating in your own life to value your own authentic quest,
to value it in your child's life.
I would rather personally, my child be a quote unquote failure according to society's standards,
but do it her own way with me guiding and ushering for sure versus me directing her
and she's a superstar, super athlete, super achiever.
Yeah, it's a brilliant thought and observation. And I love the way you described that, isn't it?
And it is, it's such a confronting thing for parents to understand, isn't it? But it's,
as you said, the other part is just,
you referenced a lot of those so-called superstars that were child stars and you hear and see the
pain of the cost of that. If you could actually put that out and understand that the benefits
would no way stack up. We see people in different environments really conscious how they positively
impact others in their environment. I think about that consciously. How have you gone about that
from your world? Yeah, I mean, you are an emblem of your healing. So,
you are the symbol of that. And once you've healed or you are in that process, you're never
completely healed. You become this positive force everywhere you go versus being a disruptive force.
And, you know, many people who follow my work report, you know, these grand transformations,
which are very obvious to me. I mean, I'm not surprised because these foundational principles
are so,
well-founded and they're so, so common sense in a way, but they do require tremendous discipline
from the parent to move away from what culture has told us is important, right? So, conscious
parenting moves away from the matrix and the traditional paradigms and it questions everything.
Yeah, that's right. Use the term being a maverick as a parent. It definitely stacks up.
Creating and sharing a vision is another dimension,
leadership we see. And the conscious parenting vision is a profound one, isn't it? You are
disrupting, as you said, the system of what we expected and what we understood in the past. I
mean, how have you gone about creating and sharing that vision and doing such a good job with it?
Well, I do it every day. I mean, I see clients. I have a coaching institute where I train people
to do the work I do. I have courses. I write these books. I mean, my whole life is around
helping others live better and connect more.
And become more authentic. But again, I can only take people as far as I've gone myself.
So, I have not touched certain frontiers. I'm not going to be able to take clients over that
threshold. Therefore, each one of us has the power to transform other people's lives. But first,
we have to work on ourselves. And that leads to the next
dimension I want to talk to you about. Curiosity is a word we hear a lot from people when they
approach life with a really curious lens. And through that, they're constantly learning and
developing through curiosity. Does that resonate with you?
Yeah, curiosity is the key for learning. But we need to be curious to challenge
what we're listening to. We shouldn't be curious about, say, for example, how to become skinnier,
prettier, wealthier. Like, don't be curious to fall into what society says. Be curious to ask,
why the hell does society say that in the first place? That's the ultimate curiosity,
is to disrupt and deconstruct what
we've been raised with. What has been the intellectual food and the emotional food
that culture and your caregivers have been giving you since you were young? Can you look at that and
deconstruct that and don't take it at face value? Dare to challenge, why is this on my plate in the
first place? Who said that? Why is that a rule? And that is where you become really brave, right?
It's, if you're curious about how to do more,
what culture has told you, that's only being a follower. Real curiosity is to challenge
the systems in place and to look at them for their farce. And most of them are farcical and
lies. And they're not truly upholding of our deepest yearnings as a human being, which is
to be authentic, to be connected, to be seen, to be valued, not for our looks,
our money, our cars, our achievements. Our greatest yearning is to be seen for who it is we
are. And yet most of us don't allow ourselves or don't allow ourselves to see another for who it
is they are. We keep piling on these belief systems. So if society says, as we know, we need
to be high achieving, have a lot of money, be part of the crowd, be famous. And if we're curious
to do those things, meaning how can I be more famous?
How can I follow society's ways? How can I be richer? That is not the true maverick curiosity.
That's falling in line and following what culture says. True curiosity is to say,
why the hell are we talking about this in the first place? Where did this come from?
And to really examine the roots of all the belief systems. So a lot of my work is
challenging cultures, paradigms, and dismantling them.
Yeah, it's such a brilliant why to explain curiosity.
As you said, isn't it? No, you're right. People have this, yeah, as you said, the following aspect
of wanting to be more like what the mainstream world tells us to be more like. But that's a
brilliant understanding of it. The next dimension on what it was communicating with clarity, and you
have got a really brilliant way that, to use an Australian term, it's like a punch in the face
sometimes, your language. It's right at you. Is that something you've strategically thought about?
Is that I'm going to be able to make an impact? I'm going to
challenge people right from the start? Was that always your way of communicating? Or is that a
fair description in your way? Yeah, no, it's not strategic. It's just
the way I see the world. And I try to be very sweet about it. I write lyrical poetry,
just to make it palatable. Yeah, I mean, I'm not meaning to be, I didn't even set out to be
revolutionary. I'm really nothing I'm saying is so revolutionary. The reason it's revolutionary,
is because we're living in an absolutely idiotic, insane way. So now if I come out with this,
which is to live in a sane way, I sound revolutionary. But really, what's insane is
the way we're living. All our institutions are very constricting and limiting and devoid of
the essence of who we are as humans. And who we are as humans, as I said, is to be connected,
to be seen for who it is we are, and to do.
So I think we're all going to have to get away with all this insanity that we're currently steeped
in.
And it's, you know, I love the way you say that this, it is idiotic and insane. And sometimes
you actually need to stop and press pause. I was just thinking, I spent a lot of time with my kids
at junior sport. And here in Australia, junior sport has become crazy. Like it's just we have
to have our umpires have escorts to start so a parent doesn't threaten the umpire. And then
I've seen the umpire escorts actually threaten the umpire. And now we've got rules where,
you know, we're going to have to have umpires, which is, you know, we're going to have to have
You can't have parents around the huddle at quarter time
because you can't trust parents not to do something insane.
And you're right.
We just say, okay, let's make another rule.
Let's, you know, ban parents and segregate.
Yeah, how stupid, right?
Right, let's have bodyguards for the umpires.
How about let's not call parents to the game?
Yeah.
And how about let's not make it a big deal?
When did junior sports become an institution
and become a whole corporate entity?
That's what I'm trying to say.
So, you know, there's this Buddhist story
about rescuing babies down the stream.
So you keep rescuing the babies down the stream,
but no one stops to ask,
where the hell are these babies coming from, right?
Can we kill a few down, but go up and find the source
so we don't keep doing this for the rest of our lives?
So that's what, you know, the umpire and the parents
are childish adults who have no business
doing this to children, but no one is realizing that.
So we keep creating all these, you know, hire more people.
And it's just, how stupid are we?
But we don't want to see that.
And I say that with benevolence, you know, how silly we are
because we're really grown up children.
We've not yet grown up.
I mean, I have rarely, barely met like five adults in my life.
Like real adults.
And I'm not counting myself.
As one of them.
So I'm not letting myself off the hook either.
But unfortunately, you know, we see on a global scale,
a lot of that children, as you call them,
are in senior, senior leadership positions, aren't they?
And, you know, global international leaders
who haven't grown up and the behavior becomes quite scary then, doesn't it?
Yes.
And then we have, you know, armies.
And then we have, you know, political, you know,
rules and strategies.
And big business meetings.
And really, if you really go to the top of the stream
to ask what the source of our misery is,
we will see how it was self-created out of ego.
All of it we're seeing right now is out of ego.
And capitalism, really.
I call parents the greatest prey to capitalism
because capitalism knows that parents have this ego
and they use us.
By giving us this idea that we can create these amazing children.
So everyone thinks that they can, but no one really can.
Children who are, quote unquote, super talented are outliers.
But we all want to have super talented children.
Average is such a dirty word in the house.
Oh, my goodness.
We can't say we're average.
This is a problem.
Not everyone can be super, super, you know, amazing.
Most of us are average.
But no.
Every parent wants to have a supersonic child.
You have four children.
You want each one to be supersonic.
However, when you accept the average essence in every human being,
that's when you actually see the beauty of who they are.
But it's not based on culture standards.
Yeah, beautifully said.
Again, how important has collaboration been for you, Dr. Shefali, in your work?
Collaboration is the key, you know.
I mean, there's nothing I could have done.
Every achievement I've achieved at, I can tell you who helped me.
And the whole thread of how I got here.
I know piece by piece at every inflection point who helped me.
And so I bow down to being connected.
We are humans in relationship.
And to pretend that we're not.
And that's...
That's for the good and the bad, yes.
But to pretend that we're not and that we can do this on our own
is, again, our ignorance talking.
Shefali, two final questions.
Who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Well, I think spiritually, you know, in terms of wisdom,
I follow the teachings of the Buddha.
I'm not Buddhist, but I just follow his teachings.
And if he even existed.
And so that's...
That's been my greatest North Star.
But I think in terms of, you know, mortals, I think my mother, you know,
just watching how she has been a human in my life, my dear, you know, friends.
I've had so many great, amazing relationships.
My child has been my leader.
I mean, bar none, really, in the past 20 years.
I've been a servant of her growth and following her lead.
And I cannot tell you how much I've learned.
You know, every book is inspired by her audacity and her unique authenticity.
And so it can be for every human being if they are willing to allow their children to be their awakeners.
Shefali, you mentioned your mother first, instinctively.
Did she have an essence of conscious parenting when you grew up?
She says she didn't.
But I think I just hit the jackpot.
She is just really the most open, you know, non-artificial human being.
Just so authentic and honest and real.
And she never pushed me to become anything.
She's constantly surprised that I can do anything right now, which sounds like an insult.
But it's actually so refreshing and liberating because anything I do, she's so thrilled about, you know.
So you would wonder what expectations she had.
But it's because she had such a low bar for me that I could do anything, right?
It gave me such freedom.
And many parents talk about, well, shouldn't you have a high bar for your children so they can reach that bar?
I go, no.
Your high bar should be that they follow their lead.
The high bar should be that they listen to their own wisdom.
The high bar should be that they follow their authentic truth.
Then they get to create the bar in terms of success.
But, you know, when we say a high bar, we just mean, you know, achievement and money.
Yeah, absolutely.
And one of your great lines is one of the goals of parenting should be to make yourself irrelevant.
And it sounds like that's your essence of your mom in lots of ways, isn't it?
She handed the reins over to you.
In the spirit of collaboration, if I can get that word out, if you could collaborate with anyone.
You've had some amazing collaboration.
I mentioned Oprah Winfrey off the top.
And clearly that was.
It must have been an amazing support to have her back your work.
Have you thought, God, to really take conscious parenting or any part of your life?
Has it been someone you thought that's who I'd love to collaborate with?
You know, not to toot any horn.
I had the Dalai Lama, Eckhart Tolle, Oprah Winfrey as my top three people that before I started this journey to, you know, have them write a forward or support my work.
And none of them are parents.
Yeah, mind you.
But they were such wisdom teachers for me.
And I've been so blessed because I got to connect with all three of them.
And they supported me.
So after these three, I don't know whether I need any more.
I'm very sated and very blessed.
And I'm not greedy anymore.
You know, I got the Dalai Lama.
Then I wanted Eckhart.
I got Eckhart.
Then I wanted Oprah.
I got Oprah.
I wanted Oprah again.
I got her again.
I wanted her again.
So now I'm just not greedy.
I'm not so greedy anymore.
But if you said, no, come on, you could get Oprah again.
Would you want her?
I'd be like, of course, I want her again.
She's my ultimate.
She's the ultimate embodiment of somebody who is trying to live authentically a life of service.
She has the whole package, in my opinion.
I did say final question, but I can't help but ask the Dalai Lama.
I mean, did he?
Did he, in essence, get your work?
Did he really understand what you're trying to spread?
Yeah, I don't know how much he understood, but he did give me a foreword for my first book.
But yeah, I don't know whether he really read my book even, but I'm hoping that his people,
you know how these things are.
But I was so blessed because getting his foreword was very hard to do back then.
I don't know how it is now.
You know, and Eckhart Tolle is one of our leading wisdom teachers.
And he's a friend.
And I look up to him so much.
And really, a lot of my blessings have come from his wisdom.
Dr. Shefali, really appreciate your time.
In my mind, it is the ultimate leadership story to pass on and to start with self and to understand that if we,
as you say, to heal yourself and to be on that journey, that's the best example you can have.
And so much wisdom in the letting go and celebrating our kids for whatever they are
and however they are.
It's such a profound message to pass on.
I really appreciate you taking the time.
Thank you.
And I think my book, The Parenting Map, is available.
But that's what people need to read if they want to become conscious parents.
Thank you for listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast, powered by temper, a mattress like no other.
And to make sure you don't miss an episode, click subscribe wherever you get your podcasts.