I hope you enjoyed this week's episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast with an incredible
Australian, Tara Winkler. Tara's leadership in exposing the horrific outcomes for more than
8 million kids around the world who end up in orphanages or other institutions is a compelling
story to hear. Many of those children are actually, in fact, not orphans, but are removed
from extremely poor families and exploited. Tara's work in shining a light on this situation
has been a global shift in a positive way. Brilliant to hear how Tara, from just 19 years
of age, has dedicated her life to exposing how power, privilege and oppression intersect with
charity work. Her passion for igniting local wisdom, investing in preventative measures
and explaining that people living in abject poverty often don't lack the wherewithal,
just the resources, is an incredibly inspiring story. I'm sure you're going to enjoy this
conversation. It is people like Tara Winkler who inspire the work that we do.
To check it out, head to elitacollective.com and have a look at our signature program,
Elita Connect, where we bring together inspiring people like Tara Winkler in bespoke groups of
five or six to connect, to learn, to share and pass on great stories of leadership like Tara's
is. And we'd encourage you to check it out. We are constantly curating groups of five to six
people around the globe to come together in this format called Elita Connect. We'd love to do that
with you. Book a discovery call and we'll share it with you.
We'd love to share with you a bit more information on the passion we have for Elita Connect and
bringing together people around the globe in an expanding community. Big thanks as always to the
great team from Temper, Australia and New Zealand. We aim to give away more fantastic prizes.
Congratulations to our winner of the $9,000 Temper mattress. Sleeping on a Temper bed is
something that will change your life. We spend a third of our life asleep and people who have
success who just heard about and you hear more about Tara Winkler understand that sleeping well
allows you to live a sustained, successful life. And so investing in a Temper bed is a great way to
start doing that. Thanks again to Jason Nicholas and his team for their ongoing support of the
Empowering Leaders podcast. Tara Winkler is an extraordinary Australian humanitarian. In 2011,
she was recognised as the New South Wales Young Australian of the Year for her work in establishing
the Cambodian Children's Trust. Her inspirational TED talk on why we need to end the era of
orphanages has been viewed more than 1.2 million times. Tara Winkler is an extraordinary Australian
and helped to shine a powerful light on the plight of more than 8 million children around the globe
living in orphanage-like institutions. Tara's contribution as a child protection leader and
activist is a remarkable story. Tara, I've been looking forward to catching up with you. Thanks
for joining me today. Hi, Luke. Thanks for having me. Tara, your 19th birthday, your mum and dad
give you, as a birthday gift, I understand, a trip around Southeast Asia and you find your way
to Cambodia in what turns out to be a life-changing experience. Can you tell us
about the path that that set you on? Yeah, so I was 19, nearly 20 years ago now. I went travelling
around Southeast Asia, Thailand, Laos, Vietnam. Last stop was Cambodia and I think like a lot of
people when they're travelling through countries in the global south, I felt uncomfortable being
on a holiday surrounded by so much poverty and just wanted to do something to give back while
I was there. So I went and visited some orphanages and just donated some clothes and books and toys
and things to try and help the kids that I met there. But one of the orphanages,
I visited on that trip, was desperately poor and I had never seen poverty like that before in my
life. There were kids there that were HIV positive that didn't have access to medical treatment and
they were just eating scraps from the monastery down the road, didn't have enough food to eat and
it was very confronting. So I felt compelled to do something more to help. So I fundraised in
Australia and then returned to Cambodia the following year to volunteer at the orphanage
for a few months. So I taught English and got all the kids to the dentist for the first time in
a year. And then over the course of the next year, I continued supporting the orphanage and
eventually came to discover that the director of the orphanage was very corrupt and had been
embezzling every cent donated to the orphanage. And in my absence, the kids were suffering such
gross neglect that they were forced to catch mice and things to feed themselves. I also found out
later that they were being subjected to physical and sexual abuse. And so I didn't feel like I
could just turn my back on kids who I'd come to know and care about and they begged me to help
get them out. I worked with a local team and the local authorities to set up a new orphanage. And
then on the 17th of August 2007, we turned up with a bus and rescued the kids out of that orphanage
and brought them to our new orphanage to give them a safe new home. So yeah, I was 19, 21 at
that point, very naive and suddenly responsible for 14 little people. But yeah, I mean, that's
sort of took another strange turn because it took me about six months to learn to speak
Khmer fluently. And then when I could communicate properly with the kids, they started telling me
about their families, that they weren't actually orphans at all, which came as quite a shock
because I just dedicated my whole life to set up this orphanage for kids who I thought had no one
in the world to love or care for them. It's an amazing trajectory. A lot of
people are moved by abject poverty and have that experience. Very few people
you have, which is this sense of, I'm going to go back and make a difference. As you said,
you're 21 years of age, you've suddenly got 14 children effectively that are relying on you
to support them. Where did you find that within yourself to push through and make a difference?
I grew up in a really socially conscious family with social justice being a big sort of driver.
My grandma was a Holocaust survivor. It was her and her sister that survived afterwards. So I
grew up hearing stories of what can happen when good people do nothing.
And so that was a big driving force when I got to Cambodia and met these kids. They were also
grandchildren of Holocaust survivors from the Khmer Rouge genocide. And so I guess that resonated
with me and I guess the intergenerational trauma from my family. And Tara, you found that when you
were able to speak fluent Khmer, which in itself is incredibly able to engage in that way, but
as you said, large percentages of these kids actually weren't orphans, that they had family
members that could have been orphans. And so I think that's a big driving force when I got to
Cambodia. So I think that's a big driving force when I got to Cambodia. And so I think that's a big
driving force when I got to Cambodia. And so I think that's a big driving force when I got to
care for them or still could. And you found also it's not just a Cambodian issue. This is a global
issue. Can you explain how that works and why these kids are being exploited in that way?
At first, I thought I just sort of stumbled across this isolated case, just this one bad orphanage
that was like operating like a business, like essentially removing children from their families
and using them as commodities to attract donations from tourists like me. But actually, it was
indicative of a much larger problem. There'd been, you know, there'd been a lot of people who were
a huge boom in the number of orphanages across many countries in the global south. In Cambodia,
between 2005 and 2010, the number of orphanages increased by 75%. And the number of children
being institutionalized doubled, despite the fact that 80% of the children living in those
orphanages are not actually orphans, but children from poor families. And even the remaining 20%,
who maybe had lost mom or dad, mostly have had other living relatives, grandparents,
aunties, uncles, who could have been caring for them with some support. I think the most shocking
thing of all to realize was what is actually fueling that boom in orphanages, because it was
us, the tourists, the volunteers, the donors, the well-meaning support from people like me,
who visit these children and volunteer and donate, who are unwittingly fueling an industry
that exploits children and tears families apart. So yeah, I mean, in the years,
since I tried my best to raise awareness about the harms of orphanages and what happens to
children when they're institutionalized, I did a TED Talk and published a book on it, and
Australian Story, 60 Minutes, and testified at the Parliamentary Inquiry into Modern Slavery,
which ended up being the first time in history that a government acknowledged that the movement
of children from families into orphanages is a form of trafficking and therefore a form of
modern-day slavery. But to say that it's not a form of modern slavery, it's a form of modern
slavery, despite all that, the problem persists. I realize that the only way we'll ever have any
hope of solving this orphanage crisis is if we address the root cause of it, which is the sort
of neocolonial, imperialist nature of the international charity sector.
And Tara, I want to talk to you about that and your campaign and your mission on that,
which is profound. Just going back a moment, I encourage everyone to have a listen to your TED
Talk if you haven't, because it's in 30 and a half minutes.
It does justice to what you uncovered and how you did. And I didn't always thought of orphanages
as a standalone thing that saved kids myself. I didn't understand. And then you listen to you and
you talk about other institutions, whether they be boarding houses or places where kids are removed
from their families. And the stats that you reel off are horrific, aren't they? 10 times more likely
kids that are brought up in institutions to fall into sex slavery, 40 times more likely to have a
criminal record, 500 more times more.
Likely to take their own lives. The data on it is just horrific. And when you remove kids from
families, did that form part of your change in what your work is to say, we have to close down
these institutions and family-based care is a big part of the way forward?
Absolutely. I mean, you just have to look at why we don't have orphanages in this country anymore.
We've known for over a hundred years what happens to children when they grow up in an institutional
setting. And like you just said, it has a huge impact on the trajectory of their lives. It also
is not the traditional way that...
Cambodia has ever dealt with problems of orphaned and vulnerable children. It's a Western-imposed
concept. Traditionally, orphaned and vulnerable children were cared for within a kinship care
environment with the sort of idea that the village raises the child, sort of community-based care
approach. And so essentially that's what we're trying to get back to. And I guess what it shines
a light on is the harms of Western-imposed...
When you think about it this way, you can imagine if a foreign-based organisation was in charge of
social services in Australia, or we're running the way that we educate our kids that are needy
and having issues, we would be appalled by it. We wouldn't allow it for a second. And yet that is
the model that the West imposes on third world countries and has done for years. And that's what
you're trying to point out, isn't it? That that is not the way forward.
That's exactly right. So if you think about it, it's not the way forward. It's the way forward.
Imagine if all of our social services, our public education and healthcare and social welfare was
controlled by private organisations in China or Japan or Nepal, whatever, Russia. It's a horrific
thought. And that is the role that international charities play in a country like Cambodia.
They create this privatised system of social support that runs in parallel to the local
public system. And then when we're in a country like Cambodia, we're in a position where we're
in control of this foreign privatised parallel system of social support. What we tend to do then
is invest downstream into what I call downstream development, which is sort of the ambulance at
the bottom of the cliff. And we do that because that tends to be what raises money, what pulls
on the heartstrings when we see people in crisis. People are then moved to give and to donate and
to help. But what that creates is this crisis-driven system where these communities are without any
dependable social protection system that would prevent them from ending up in crisis. So it's
kind of like build it and they will come. We end up with a very well-resourced crisis-driven system
where families have no choice. So a family living in abject poverty, there is no social support
services for them. But what there is, is orphanages. A lot of people will say to me,
like, how could a family, you know, I could never give up my child. How could a family do that? But
first of all, you have to understand that, like,
acknowledging back-breaking pressures of that kind of poverty. And they're really left with no
choice. And they believe it's going to be a path out of poverty to a better life.
What we know to be true is that the best way to create a healthy, flourishing society is through
a well-resourced public social protection system that raises the living standards for the whole
community, where they have access to high-quality public services, health care, education, housing,
and social support.
Which then prevent them from ending up in crisis in the first place.
I want to talk about your Village Hive project, which is extraordinary. And the data coming out
of it, from what you read, the reports from the Cambodian Children's Trust is a brilliant
concept and idea. I'll talk to you about it in a moment. I want to go back to the language you
use. This white saviour complex is a word I see that you reference, and that the white males often
in the West decide that we're going to go. And well-meaning at times, isn't it?
To save, you know, people in poverty. But you're saying that is never, ever going to be the
solution, and it just entrenches abject poverty, and we need to disrupt that in a way. And is that
something that philanthropic organisations have got to get their head around, that they have to
change the way they invest?
Yeah, look, I mean, I think if you look at the thing that we're trying to achieve,
it's empowerment. And this sort of system, this system of social support that we've created,
that charities create in a country like Cambodia,
this privatised parallel system that leaves communities totally dependent,
ongoing on aid and foreign investment, is the most disempowering system you can imagine. It's
paternalistic, it's patronising. And as I said, it goes against the very thing we're trying to
achieve, which is empowerment. Because contrary to popular belief, empowerment is not about
teaching a man to fish. Trust me, they know how to catch a fish. Empowerment is about power,
and who is in control and who is making the decisions. Yeah, one thing that I know to be
true after 15 years of living and working in Cambodia is that all of the knowledge and wisdom
required to solve complex social problems lives within local communities. What they lack is the
resources, not the wherewithal. And so having white people come in to build their houses,
dig their wells and save their children really goes against everything that we're trying to achieve.
And I love your language as well. Igniting local wisdom is a term I read a lot about in research
for this chat today with you, is that the answers remain within local communities. And as you said,
empowering them to have the resources to solve their challenges and doing that in a meaningful
way. And then having an exit strategy as well. I read that as well. You don't see the Cambodian
Children's Trust as the answer. You want to empower communities to then be resourced enough to sort out
the deep challenges that are there. Yeah, I really believe that the way that you can see
whether a charity is working upstream and invested in solving the root cause of problems and things
is with an exit strategy. It's like a great proclamation of their intent to solve problems
and not just perpetuate and capitalize on them. It's something that we really believe in at CCT.
That's been something that's sort of come out more recently in more recent years is basically,
realizing that if we ever want this work to be truly sustainable, like who better than the local
community to have a vested interest in their own prosperity? It's never going to be sustainable
if we're there implementing it for them forever. Quite early, obviously, we closed the orphanage
and began reuniting the children with their families and then started building prevention
and early intervention services to prevent kids from being separated from their families in the
first place. But we were delivering those services ourselves out of privately run
centers and things like that. And what we realized is that work will never be sustainable. And
actually, it was through the pandemic a lot. I was really worried that we would end up in some
sort of global financial crisis. And if all our funding dried up, then all of Northwest Cambodia
would be without social services. And it's a very precarious system. And that's part of the problem
with this sort of privatized parallel system is there's no reliability for local communities. And
it's often dependent on the local community. And it's often dependent on the local community. And
it's often dependent on funding cycles and when funding starts and stops. For a while, there might
be some family planning services in a community, and then the funding ends, and then they go away.
It's a very precarious, unreliable system of social support. And so what we decided to do was,
it's basically a decolonization movement to take the programs that we have run and developed over
all these years in collaboration with the community through a process of co-creation
and hand that over through integrating that work into the public sector to create a public social
protection system that is wholly owned, run, and controlled by the local community. Once we've
finished handing that over, we can then exit that community, and they have a functioning
social protection system that raises the standard of living for the entire community.
I love the language that you use there, Tara. Co-creating, collaborating, igniting local wisdom.
Such a shift, isn't it, from coming in, and we've got the answers and the funds to solve your
problems. And it really does line up. And I think it's a very precarious system. And I think it's a
great leadership looks like, Tara, which is exactly that, collaborative. And we know the
research says if you co-create with the people that you're trying to get an outcome with,
that's what works, because it's part of what you're actually listening to the people that
you're effectively trying to work with. In whatever setting, yours is just such a profound
space, isn't it, where lives are saved and changed by these decisions. The Village Hive project that
came out of it, you've given a little bit of insight. It's a fantastic initiative. Can you
explain how it works?
How it works, the sort of nuts and bolts of it is we focus, instead of focusing the
predominant funding and everything on creating crisis services, which is in downstream model,
we invest most of our funding into prevention and early intervention. So that's public health and
public education, building up the public village health clinics and all of the public schools
in the community. And then once those basic public services are functioning and running at a high
quality, we introduce the public health clinics and all of the public schools in the community.
We also introduce an early intervention program, which takes vulnerable families who are at risk of
crisis through a process of self-determined change, where we initially would come in and
the social workers will do an assessment with the family and the family will work out what sort of
basic needs they're lacking. And then there's a support payment provided so that we know from
day one that the kids and family have access to all of their basic needs, health, education,
housing, all their identification documents.
And then they go on through a process of self-determined empowerment through literacy in
income generation and finance, go through a bunch of training. And then they develop a financial
goal, which is how much they need to sort of cover their basic needs. And then they'll go through a
sort of visioning process where they work out how they're going to reach that goal. And for a lot
of families, I mean, that might be employment. And for a lot of families, it'll be through setting up
a micro business. And then they're coached in how to write a business. And then they're coached in
a business plan and then establish that business. And then they go through a sort of cycle of
growing and developing that business until they reach their financial goal. And then they set up
a savings program, which is run through the community and family supporting each other
through community savings programs. And once they have meeting all their basic needs and have
reached that financial goal and have enough savings, they can exit the program and are
self-reliant. So it's a brilliant integrated model. And I can't help but think
I'm looking at someone who at 19 years of age went for a holiday. And I believe at the time,
you were a promising film maker and passionate about the film industry. Do you sit back and
think, I'm solving something that so many people around the world haven't been able to tackle? Do
you sort of see the sliding door moment and think, God, life could have been different? Do you reflect
on that at all? Yeah, I mean, it does feel like a lifetime ago. I just have always been someone to
go with the flow of life.
And it's just pushed me very clearly in one direction. And it's been tough. There's been a
lot of really tough, tough things that I've been through. But I'm also very grateful for the work
that I do. It's a privilege. Tara, I spoke to Peter Singer on this
podcast, the founder of The Life You Can Save. And he's a passionate advocate for effective
altruism. And he talks a lot about the, to paraphrase poorly, but the excess wealth in
the West and to distribute that back to...
To the third world countries. And he says, I'm not sitting here on this iPhone without us having
benefited from the low cost models that we have imposed on the West. And to give the maximum amount
of value in life and to have the most fulfillment is to share that excess wealth of the West. Is
that part of it? Do you think, Tara, that shifting mindset that just says, hey, we actually owe this
money back and we need to distribute it more evenly and fairly?
Yeah, I think there's a sort of narrative that we kind of grew up with, that we grew up in these
wealthy countries and where our country is wealthy of our own making. And these countries in the
global South are poor of their own making. But actually, if you look back through history,
200 years ago, poor countries were only two or three times poorer than rich countries. And then
after colonialism, they were 30 times poorer.
And now they're 80 times poorer. And so you really have to look at the way in which we have
developed is off the back of siphoning funds out of the global South. And it still happens today
through unequal trade and patents and tax havens and all the rest that $2 trillion flows from South
to North every year. And we give back $130 billion, but still, it's unequal. And I think,
yeah, we have responsibility as citizens of the most privileged, wealthy countries on this nation
to create a fairer, more equal, more egalitarian world.
That's why your story is so incredibly inspiring, Tara, to dedicate your life to this message and
to do it in such a profound way and support so many people in the way that you do. I love sitting
down with people like you and different stories of leadership.
Passion, Tara, that shows up in different ways. We see these sort of common traits. I often use
the term that someone shared with us in this podcast, success leaves clues and why someone
like you has got the resilience to be able to, with all the challenges, and you've had some
serious challenges along the way, personal and also opening an orphanage and then working out
that you were actually part of the problem and having the courage to own that and to change
path and to describe it the way you did today. But we think it's very hard to lead someone else
without a sense of self-leadership. Tara, does that resonate with you?
How do you describe self-leadership?
I mean, introspection and self-reflection is a huge part of my life. And I guess that's,
I should say that as well, one major caveat when talking about leadership in my sector,
that I fundamentally believe that the time has long passed that we should be allowing
foreigners to lead development work in countries like Cambodia, because it's paternalistic and
patronising and disempowering.
And on that point, sorry, Tara, to interrupt, I believe 100% of the
Cambodian Children's Trust now are locals. Is that correct?
Yeah, absolutely. 100% locally staffed and locally led, and also now handing over all
the programs to the local community to control and run by themselves. So that's a really big,
and coming to that realisation took a lot of self-reflection and introspection and
navel-gazing to kind of, yeah, figure out that.
Been more than one mea culpa in my career.
Yeah. And when you think about that, I pick on that for a moment, isn't it? It's why it's so
powerful, your stories. And you wrote the book about why not to open orphanages. And your talk
was an experience, as you said, as a 19-year-old trying to be as well-meaning and positive as you
have been. I mean, have there been hard lessons to learn?
Yeah, definitely. Very jagged little pill to swallow. And sometimes,
difficult to have these conversations sometimes, I think, because these are really confronting
subjects. And you see yourself as a good person, and you're trying to do a good thing,
and then you're sort of aware of the fact that some of your unconscious beliefs may have been
harmful. They can be quite, yeah, destabilising, difficult things to hear. But that's why I've
sort of been such a proponent of kind of falling on my sword and admitting the mistakes that I made
and public mea culpas, so that...
Other people feel like they can be brave enough to kind of admit that they might have got it wrong
as well.
Which is a great example in itself, isn't it, Tara? A lot of people find that impossibly hard
to do, is to put their hand up and admit they don't have the answers or they got it wrong. And
it's such an empowering model to be able to be truthful and honest and understand that's part
of your own learning. And the same for all of us. Everyone has that experience. Another dimension
of leadership, and this almost feels like a question. I can't...
Because we think leaders are now really conscious of how they positively impact others on a daily
basis. And we think about it in our environments. That's your life, effectively, is positive impact
on other people. Have you thought about it in that way? When you wake up at the start of the day,
this is how I want to show up and have a positive impact?
I mean, I guess I've sort of led CCT through, you know, trying to role model
how I, you know, how we... And we try and do that through the whole organisation, like how we want
these social workers to be able to do that. And I think that's a really good question.
To work with families, we try and role model that all the way through the organisation. I'm really
a big believer in Simon Sinek's golden circle and starting with the why. And that's a really big
part of what's driven CCT is bringing everybody along on that journey and trying to make everyone
as passionate about why we're doing this as I am. And really focus. So we've had a lot of really
deep conversations about... Have you read Paulo Ferreira's Pedagogy of the Oppressed?
No, I haven't. But I'll read it.
I'll write that down. Yeah. Can you say that again, Paul?
Paulo Ferreira. He's a Brazilian philosopher and educator. And it was written in the 60s,
but it's as relevant today as ever. I recommend it for anyone who...
Pedagogy of the West, did you say?
Of the Oppressed.
Of the Oppressed, yeah.
Yeah. So he has a concept in that that he outlines called conscientisation, which is the process of
raising critical consciousness through intensive dialogue, or as he says, dialogical action, which
yeah, inspires people.
To kind of rise up and take action. And so we use that process and really focus on painting a really
clear North Star for everybody. And doing that is a really great way, I think, to give people the
freedom to achieve the mission and the aim in whichever way they see fit in a sort of
self-determined way. And it gives people then the freedom to kind of make mistakes and change
tact and the freedom to fail, which I think is hugely important if innovation is something that
you value. You've got to create an environment that's safe enough that people feel like they can
try and fail. And I try and role model that myself.
Yeah. Thanks for sharing that, Tara. And it leads, you spoke about creating a really clear North Star
and we see people who have the sustained success that you're having in your world are really clear
about how they create and share a vision. Yours is a powerful shift in the way we deal with
children and institutions around the country.
How have you gone about creating that vision and sharing it?
Yeah, well, through conscientization, like I said, and process of co-creation. So everything that we
do at CCT is co-created with the teams and the local wider communities and the families and the
kids themselves. It's not just my vision, but it's a vision that we've all kind of created
together. And then there's a lot of buy-in and ownership and accountability then for everybody
who's involved.
Thoughts on curiosity? We see people,
in these roles like yours, are really curious. And through that curiosity, that's how they
approach their learning and development, constantly wanting to improve. Does curiosity
play a role for you?
Yeah, hugely. I don't really have heroes in my life. I'm kind of an opponent to the idea of
heroes on the grounds that there's this sort of sense that heroes are off doing these impossibly
great things that the rest of us can't do and thereby kind of excuse us out of not doing
anything. I have been inspired hugely by,
thought leaders, Christopher Hitchens and Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie, Jason Hickel,
Paulo Ferreira. And not so much in kind of what they think, but in how they think and that they
are free thinkers and think for themselves and think outside the box. And so that's, yeah,
that's been a hugely inspirational part of my life.
Tara, we see people who understand their leadership communicating with great clarity. And you
have in so many great forums. I mentioned the TED Talk and you wrote a book about it.
Brilliant book. And you've told your story on 60 Minutes, an Australian story. And with great
clarity. Have you thought about your communication and the way that you've been able to tell your
story?
Yeah, I always, I try and kind of, especially in this, like when I'm crafting like the TED Talk
and my book and things, really try and join the dots together for everyone so that it's like,
because sometimes when you're in the sector and there's a lot of jargon and there's a lot of,
so I try and keep it.
It's like simple as possible. I actually, I actually went to NIDA and did a bootcamp in
public speaking because that was absolutely not something that came naturally to me at all. So
when they asked me to speak at TED, I contacted NIDA and they were kind enough to kind of put
me through a bootcamp, which changed my life, honestly. It was, yeah, one of the greatest
things I've ever done.
Oh, that's a great insight. I get the sense, Tara, talking to you that the joyful part for
you is being on the ground speaking, Kamara, and working with the kids and the work you do.
Yeah.
But it's still, get the sense that being the face of this movement and the Cambodian Children's
Trust is something that you have to work on, that it's not, you don't like, forget the sense,
you don't like talking about it in your role. And it is, how have you dealt with that?
Yeah. Yeah. I'm an introvert and not comfortable in front of a camera or a microphone. Like,
as I said, that's why I went off and did the course with NIDA. I was, yeah, very, very bad
at interviews and public speaking and everything, really. And I'm not being humble. I was,
just not born with that natural skill set. Yeah. I mean, I just have tried to do my best
because I guess I believe so much in what we're doing and more and more as the years go on and
CCT's mission has evolved and it's become about something, something bigger than just helping,
you know, a few kids and a few families in Northwest Cambodia, but really trying to shine
a light on what I see as massive problems in the international development sector. And that we do
have a novel way of solving it. And that could potentially have implications and ripple effect
around the world. And I really, I'm more passionate about what we're doing today than I
ever have been. And I guess I try and just speak from that place of passion and remember why it is
I'm doing it, even though, even though it's really hard. Yeah. The passion comes out. Can I just ask,
was there something you could pass on from the NIDA bootcamp on public speaking that,
that stayed with you? Honestly, so many things. I, I'm going to sound like I'm advertising,
but it was truly life-changing. Especially when you're doing a short speech, it's so much more
than a performance than it is a kind of a talk, a one hour keynote where you've got your slides
and you can click through and you know, your stuff and you'll get to your point eventually.
But for those shorter speeches, it's a, it's a performance and I, I am not a performer. And so
it was a lot of little things. Like I naturally talk pretty fast. And so they taught me how to
slow down and really focus on like, how was it? How was it? How was it? How was it? How was it?
The sentences and where the emphasis should lie and the inflection. And when you're doing that
and you're thinking about like each word and how you're going to articulate it and how you're going
to deliver that, that sentence, it suddenly, it sort of puts you in the moment and you don't have
that sort of brain mouth disconnection where you sort of get off and you say, what did I say? I
can't even remember. It's, I think it's almost a mindfulness technique to be honest. But it puts
you in the moment. It keeps you connected with what you're saying rather than letting your head
run away and have a whole separate conversation. That's brilliant. How important Tara has
collaboration been for you? Collaboration is the backbone of everything that we do. Local
collaboration that is. So that, and that was a real big challenge through COVID because everything
that we do is done in co-creation and collaboration with the wider community. That made it really
difficult to do through COVID with all the lockdowns and things. And that was a bit of a
hold up with our Village Hive project. And the total aim of that is to hand over the entire
Village Hive initiative to all of the 10 district, all of the 10 communes in Battambang district
and then exit ourselves after that. So we've now done the first, the first commune and
the second commune is underway this year. It's all done through collaboration with,
with the wider community. And potentially scale that around the globe. Is that an
option? Well, look, I don't know. We'll see what happens. Basically we want to prove that
it's possible. Again, we've got some universities behind us building the evidence base for the,
for the model. Once we do it in Battambang district, then we'll have a case for the
Cambodian government to potentially scale that across Cambodia. And I mean, it really would
then be one of the first upstream, like prevention focused child protection systems in, in the world.
We don't have one here and it's, you know,
to me, it's crazy that we have a child protection system that waits till, you know, children are
harmed and in crisis before we intervene like that. That's not child protection, that's child
abuse. And most child protection systems in the world are like that. They're, they're reactionary
and they're not, there's not enough supports built around families to prevent kids from
ever needing to end up in out of home care. And this could be an answer to that.
Yeah. What an amazing thought and you know, the preventive method, as opposed to,
waiting for the ambulance at the bottom of the cliff is, it makes sense to, to hear you say it,
and I hope more strength to, to the work you're doing. Who's been the greatest leader in your
life, Tara? The greatest leader in my life. I'm going to say my co-founder,
Panjeta. He's truly the most remarkable leader. I've learned so much from him over the, these 15
years that we've been working together. He's just the most humble person and he truly, he truly
leads by inspiring.
The people around him, including me.
Is there a sense that he thought lots of people come over and say, I'm going to come back and
help and that he doubted whether or not that you would, would follow through initially? Did I
read that or was it immediately, you're going to build this together?
Well, that's the kids, the kids used to say that a lot, that there would, there was a lot of,
you know, tourists coming in and out of their lives and always promising to come back and,
you know, never doing it. I, I am really lucky. I'm really lucky to have connected with the people
that I did. The, the kids that I met initially and that they were huge, hugely inspiring for me
as well. Sunette Chan, who's my best friend. She was one of the oldest kids that we rescued out of
the orphanage. And we do a lot of the awareness raising together. I mean, she's also been a huge
inspiration to me through these years. Yeah.
In the spirit of, of collaboration and I love asking this question in the space you're in,
have you thought about it? If I could collaborate with that person or that organisation,
in any area of your life, Tara, but clearly what the work you're doing is the passion that jumps
out. Has there been someone that you've thought that would be an ideal boost to the work that
you're doing? Dream collaboration. I mean, honestly, anyone really, like all the, all the
dreamers and rebels and renegades and people who believe what we believe and willing to kind of
collaborate and help us make it possible, build a more fair, egalitarian world.
I'd welcome any collaboration because it is going to, it's, it's not something that we can do
alone. It's not, it's not a job for one person or one organisation. It's, it is going to take
an army of people to, to create systems change on that scale. So the more, the more, the merrier.
And I think sometimes we, we think that, you know, a job like that is kind of a utopian fantasy,
but, you know, if you think back through civilisation, all of the, the major changes
that we've had in the past, you know, we've had a lot of, you know, we've had a lot of
democracy, the end of slavery, vote for women, gay marriage, they all once upon a time seemed
like a utopian fantasy. So. Beautifully said. And you can make a
donation to the CCT, the Cambodian Children's Trust that was co-founded with Tara and the great
leader that she spoke of, and also the Village Hive project as well, which as you just heard
from Tara is an incredible programme that's unfolding and the initial reports I'm reading,
even post-COVID, which you thought might've been more challenging, it seems to be
working in exactly the way that, that you'd hoped. Tara, it's an incredible story. I've
enjoyed listening to it from afar, but I appreciate you sharing it with us
today and wish you all the best. Thanks for taking the time.
Thanks, Luke. It's great to speak to you.
Thank you for listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast, powered by temper,
a mattress like no other. And to make sure you don't miss an episode,
click subscribe wherever you get your podcasts.