Well, I hope you enjoyed this conversation with the iconic Australian, Stephanie Alexander,
whose influence on educating Australians on the passion for eating well and living a good life
through good food is profound. I loved her thoughts on energy, passion and enthusiasm,
trumping almost everything else in life. And how educating through example is so much more
powerful and changing behaviour than lecturing people on how they should eat. It's iconic
leaders like Stephanie Alexander that inspire the work that we do at Alita. Love you to check
out our bespoke Alita Connect program where we bring together diverse leaders from around the
globe, people like Stephanie Alexander and her passion and enthusiasm for the world of food,
with sports leaders, leaders from social venture and the arts into these groups of five or six
people to connect, to learn, to share and to collaborate in ways that perhaps they haven't
done before. Love you to check it out. Head to alitacollective.com, book a discovery call.
We'd love to jump on a call with you and see.
If you want to start your journey with us and Alita Connect. Huge thanks as always and every
week to Jason Nicholas and the team at Temper Bedding, a mattress like no other. We really
appreciate their support in bringing incredible leaders like Stephanie Alexander to the table.
We know success leaves clues and leaders like Stephanie all value their sleep and understand
the importance of sleep for a better life. Investing in a temper mattress is something
that will change your sleep and change your life for the better.
Stephanie Alexander is regarded as one of Australia's great food educators. Her reputation
has been earned through her 30 years as an owner chef in several restaurants, as the author of 18
influential books and hundreds of articles about food matters and for her groundbreaking work
and creating the Stephanie Alexander Kitchen Garden Foundation, for which she was made an
officer of the Order of Australia in recognition of her extraordinary contribution. Kitchen Garden
Program is represented in more than 11 countries. Stephanie Alexander is regarded as one of the
primary schools and in more than 1,000 schools and learning centres Australia-wide. Stephanie,
it's a great pleasure to meet you and congratulations on an incredible life of
success and what a great legacy you've got. Thank you, Luke.
It's great to see you. You've been an incredible leader and pioneer in educating Australians
in your belief that good food is essential to living well. Stephanie, what does good food
look and sound like for you? I think, what does good food sound like?
Well, I really do think that it is one of life's most accessible pleasures and joys. And it is
always a great sadness to me that so many people, for various reasons, don't agree with me.
They find it hard. They find it difficult. It makes them very anxious. And I guess my reason
for almost everything I do is to convince people that not only is it a beautiful and wonderful and
yummy thing.
But it really is very accessible to everybody.
And what an amazing storyline that you've had in sharing that. And for a lot of people,
it is the most stressful thing of the day, isn't it, Stephanie, around
mealtime and trying to do that in a healthy and comfortable way for the family. And I think your
language has been brilliant around sharing simple techniques to make that accessible.
Has that been your mission in lots of ways? Well, it certainly hasn't been. Health has not
been top of mind.
I've been on a list of things, which doesn't mean that I don't value eating well and doing things
that are great for one's body. But I just prefer to feel that what is important is the communication
that happens between friends and families, the conversations you have, the opening of your mind
to different possibilities, being aware of different ways of doing things. But pleasure,
pleasure, pleasure.
Right at the centre of it, because I really believe you don't change anyone's behaviour about
anything if you wave your finger at them and say, don't do this, don't do that. But you will change
their behaviour if they have an experience which is hands-on, in the case of the children in the
kitchen garden. And their energy and their curiosity are as involved as their taste buds.
Yeah, I love the way that you frame that, Stephanie. Can I ask you about the food education
part?
I agree with you. All the research says waving your finger and trying to scold someone into
changing behaviour doesn't work. But in preparation for this, Devin, I was thinking about an occasion,
my wife and I were at a friend's house and the kids were bouncing off the walls. They were young
and they'd been eating Froot Loops. And the mum, who was a really well-educated and smart lady,
had turned to us and said, I'm glad that they've got some fruit in them today. And you look at a
box of that fruit and you're like, oh, that's good. I'm glad that they've got some fruit in them today.
And you look at that alleged breakfast cereal and you effectively have given the kids a kilo
of sugar. And you wonder why they're bouncing off the walls and a touch out of control. Were
you surprised sometimes by the lack of understanding of what good food actually is?
I am surprised. And there's lots and lots of reasons we could go on about that or I could
go on about that for hours and hours, which I'm sure you don't want me to. And it does seem to me
that there has been a bit of a thing with
the Anglo-Saxon culture. It has not been one that has incorporated the pleasures of growing
your own food and encouraging your young ones to come out in the garden and help you
pick a tomato or dig for a potato. So share in that sense of the magic of growth. And that
all sounds very airy-fairy and arty, but it's really how a lot of people in the world live,
that they are involved.
They're involved in producing at least some of their food. And if they don't grow it themselves,
they choose to purchase it in a place where they're talking to people who understand what
they're buying. And they can say, are these the most luscious pears you've got? Or the person,
the man or the woman selling it will say, this is the best time of the year for artichokes.
So you're actually, you are communicating and you're communicating enthusiasm as well as
knowledge.
And when that's missing, you know, you do have this big lack. And it does astonish me that
somebody who's had some sort of reasonable general education can either believe the words
of the advertisers, which we know are always geared to making a sale, rather than using their
common sense.
Yeah, it is. And it becomes a huge issue. And I won't get too hung up on this point, Stephanie,
but it is a bit of a passion of mine as well.
And fortunate enough to, you know, my mother was at the market every day. And, you know,
as a kid, you wanted, you know, perhaps what some of the other kids were getting. But, you know,
she had a really clear sense of health and my beautiful wife and the amount of care that goes
into the nutrition and the meals that we enjoy on a nightly basis in that community. But then
you go to the kids' party. And I know there's a place for this. And you look at the table and you
go, that is food you would never dream of consuming yourself.
It's full of preservatives and additives and colourings. And I know there is a place for that
in a small space. But it seems, as you said, that Anglo-Saxon culture has been around food that
doesn't even actually look like food in the end. It's become a bit of a challenge, hasn't it?
Well, this whole business of, you know, never leaving the table with anything left on your
plate or, you know, we'll bring it out again the next meal. I hope that doesn't exist anymore.
But, you know, as opposed to the
sort of tables that probably you have regularly, and I certainly have regularly, where you set out
food on platters and the children, you know, they don't necessarily like every single thing that's
there. But what they do see is the people whom they respect and love are diving into all these
things so that even if they decide at the age of four, they don't really like olives. It doesn't
mean that they say, well, you know, if I see an olive, I'll faint. It just means the palate's
developed as they get older and you've got a good grounding. And I always think, you know,
if you come from a family where meals often end with the fruit bowl, you know, lovely nectarine
or a pear or something, you're much more likely to have children who will be fruit lovers for life
and will always have that as part of their diet, not because they're being told it's healthy,
nutritious, full of vitamins, but because they like it. And I love your point is that the example
is always the way, isn't it? What they say is always the way, isn't it? And I think that's
what they end up taking on board, isn't it? You can lecture all you like, but if the behaviours
they witness are different, it's always going to be a challenge. And the Stephanie Alexander
Kitchen Garden Project in schools is an incredible legacy, as I said off the top. And I got to see
it firsthand at the primary school that my kids went to and saw that, you know, the kids grow
and harvest their own food and prepare and share fresh meals and, you know, delicious food that
was prepared. And I think your language is saying,
can we then show them and teach them positive food habits for life? You must be incredibly proud of
where that project's got to. I certainly am. And of course,
during the COVID years, we had all, everybody was a bit mucked around and many schools found it
difficult to keep going during those years. After all, there were many schools that were actually
physically closed. But as soon as life started to resume, those kitchen gardens have, oh,
I can't say all of them. But
many of them that I know of have just picked up the pieces and rebuilt and re-nourished the soil
and away they've gone again. And the pleasure and the enjoyment that is on, that is in evidence
whenever I visit one of those schools, if I'm feeling a bit down in the dumps, I come away
saying, what they're doing is really important and it works. These kids are so excited about
what they're doing. And some of them develop the most amazing knife skills and all the other
sorts of actual motor skills and interest in food generally.
Yeah. And as you said earlier, the great Italian families that I grew up with
always had the veggie garden going and always brought fresh produce and would
come over with whatever was growing in season. And that culture, they brought beautifully to
Australia. But you're right, there's an element that have grown up with not even understanding
what a potato...
The potato milk comes from or how it is. And so what you've done is such a profound
thing to educate so many kids to understand. And then often, isn't it, when it's prepared that way
and you get to taste something that you've grown and eaten yourself, it's a pretty special
presentation, isn't it, when it all works?
And they feel very, very proud. It's a way of increasing self-esteem. It's a program which
is utterly inclusive. Every child, no matter what their abilities in any other area,
can be involved in this.
Every kid seems to love digging holes or knocking bamboo poles in the soil to support a plant.
And they certainly all love to be allowed to use a knife because often at home,
the parents freak out if they touch a knife, whereas we show them how to use a knife properly.
Stephanie, your fifth book, The Cook's Companion, has become a genuine Bible for
chefs and cooks and food lovers and really everyone. Over 500,000 copies sold since it
was first published in 1996.
It's a brilliant success. Why do you think it's resonated with so many people?
Because it's clear. Because I haven't, as a former librarian, I'm very good on the A to Z.
And I knew that that was a really supremely simple method of organization.
So it was based on the produce. It was clear. I tried to think of every possible thing that
would be concerning people. How do I store it? How do I know it's a good one? Does it only come at
a certain time of the year? And then there's those little marginal notes a lot of people
absolutely love where they're not recipes, they're ideas. Put a handful of walnuts with
a something or other and toss it with a bit of olive oil and put it on a plate. Now, that's the
sort of cooking that good cooks love to do because it's just a challenge to you every night. I open
the fridge door. Oh, yes.
I've got that bit of celeriac I've even used. Right. Okay. Out it comes.
Yeah. It's brilliant. And as you said, sometimes the best genius is the simplicity, isn't it? And
for you then to have trained chefs and cooks who have that alongside them at the same time,
and obviously your history, you went back and you said you started as a librarian,
trained as a librarian. Did you dream at that young age that life in food as a business was
a possibility or did that just emerge?
As you got older? Well, it was always my great interest,
but it didn't occur to me or to my parents that a life in food was on the horizon. The general
feeling when I was a teenager, when I was 18, 19 and going to university was that you got trained
for something vocationally and you did it. But in recreationally, even when I was 17, 18,
the thing I loved to do most was to cook for other people. So I managed to do both together for a
while.
And then the sort of the feeling in the society changed in Melbourne, and there seemed to be a
possibility for people to have a go themselves. And so the first BYO restaurants in Melbourne
were run by people who were genuine food enthusiasts. Almost none of them, and I probably
could say none of them had had any formal training, but they had a lot of love for lovely food and for
helping.
And I think that's something that I've learned over the years. I think that's something that I've
learned over the years.
And now we sit here, Stephanie, and, you know, the Kitchen Garden program we've spoken about and what
you've done to educate Australians over so many years, but they're about to make a movie of you
and your experience in 1997 in Tuscany in Italy with your great friend, another food legend in
Maggie Beer, taking Australian food lovers and running cooking classes in that part of the world.
Can I ask you what it feels like to about to have a movie made after you? And can you tell me a bit
about your life?
Well, I think it's a great experience. I think it's a great experience. I think it's a great
experience.
It's a lifelong friendship.
There's not many details yet, Luke, and I think it's really still on the drawing board.
Actually, in the next few days, going to spend a day or so with Maggie. One of the things we'll be
talking about is how far this project has got. It was great. It was very funny when they first put
it to us. We both thought it was hilarious and we couldn't believe that it was going to happen.
And we still don't believe it's going to happen.
It does seem as if the producer...
The producer seems to think it's going to happen. So I don't know much more than that now,
excepting that it is rather fun.
Yeah, it's cool. I was reading a bit of the plot and understanding a bit, you know,
the two books emerged out of that trip to Italy. And I'm fascinated. And I'm reading from the
producer who's had some great success in other Netflix shows as well, but talking about this
great friendship as well. And can you tell us about that, your lifelong friendship with Maggie Beer?
Well, I think we both found ourselves in restaurants at a time when, as I said before,
these BYO restaurants or owner-operated restaurants were just starting to happen in Australia.
And I think we would both admit that we had bitten off, I hate to say more than we can chew,
because we in fact chewed it quite successfully. But it was a strain. And Maggie was a couple of
years behind me in experience at that time. And I think we both found ourselves in restaurants at a
point. And we got together at some group gathering of young cooks. And she and I found that we both
shared a whole lot of feelings about food and about growing things. And look, we just hit it
off. And we've been hitting it off ever since. And the custody thing was really because we had had
a holiday in Umbria two years prior.
And we had loved it so much, loved the Italian way of life, the Italian way of food. And we kept
saying to each other, how can we come back again? But we've got businesses to run. How can we do it?
And so we spent a lot of time mulling over thoughts. And then the idea came that we would
take people to Tuscany. We would not be saying we are great Italian cooks. We are saying,
come with us and let's explore what it is.
That makes Italian food and way of life so very, very special and so appealing and have a good time
at the same time. Can I ask you this question, Stephanie? I know your love of French cuisine
and the French love of food as well from a young age. And you've spent many years going back and
forth to France and clearly Tuscany. And you've traveled around the world. Can you share with us
one of your great memorable food experiences from your travels?
Oh God, there've been so many. I mean, my heart probably still belongs in France. Although
if I can say my special occasion country is France. I also love Italian food, but it's
those two countries have a very special place for me. And I was fortunate enough during my
restaurant years to be able to visit a great number of the very finest French restaurants
at the time. This is in the 80s probably.
And it was fascinating. It was fascinating to observe how just the systems, just the systems
were very important to understand because without system, you can't achieve these things. And I was
very, very, very conscious of the systems that were in operation in these grand restaurants.
I had one at a restaurant called Trois Rheaux in the country, in the regional,
and I stayed there for nine days. And I was given the full run of the place and stayed in the kitchen
from early in the morning till the last service watching what happened. And I learned such a lot.
And one of the things I learned was that a grand restaurant like that, it has to have systems
because it is a very hierarchical situation, which wasn't necessarily what we had in Melbourne.
But I could see how things were made possible by having
specific systems and responsibilities and people responding to this person and that person.
So it was a bit about leadership. And the food was fabulous. So out of a very systematic approach
came some really wonderful results. And that leadership you've brought back
to Australia and in your education, and you go to, if you're lucky enough to spend some time
in France, you see food as a way of life, isn't it? And you often hear about,
the French way of eating, it's such a pleasurable experience, isn't it? Every meal and really
taking time to sit down and connect and all the things you've spoken about, haven't you, around
community and they eat beautifully, the French, but they don't seem to overindulge either. Is that
a fair snapshot? Well, I think that's right. They can remember as a greedy Australian
and one of my very, when I was a student in France, living there for a year and in my early
months of living there, you would go to a little tiny country cafe, which was always had a respect
for the food, but wasn't fancy. And when it came to cheese, this is very definitely before the
eighties. This is more like late sixties. When the cheese, the cheese board would be just put
on the table and the waiter would walk away. Now the greedy Australian would say, my God,
all of this.
A piece of camembert, bit of this and bit of that. And then you would probably later on feel
extremely, well, not sick, but you'd feel very, as if you'd eaten a huge dinner, but you'd watch
the French at the next table. They'd still get the full cheese board put on the table and they
would look it over whilst they were having a conversation and they'd say to themselves,
I think I'll have the brie tonight. And they would cut a modest slice. That's all they wanted.
There was a sense of an understanding.
When moderation was okay. So it balanced moderation, which people talk about all the
time. Again, it's something you model, is being modelled for you at home.
And I just, yeah, beautifully said, I want to go back to just that final, not final,
but the thought of mine again, and you come back, as you said, to the Anglo-Saxon way
of eating and we're bombarded our kids with these fast food advertising every day and meals are
quick and cheap and clearly lacking.
Nutrition. I mean, you've done an enormous amount to re-educate back the other way. Is it a fair
fight, Stephanie? Because it's so overwhelming sometimes, isn't it? How, particularly in low
socioeconomic areas in Australia, the kids, that's all they see when they hear and experience food.
Well, it is a battle. I don't think it's a fair battle. I think my answer would be
probably,
probably need to hope that this generation of young people that we're helping learn about
lovely food will take those lessons into their own life and will model a different sort of behaviour
because they will understand how to make a simple soup. They will understand how you can
have dinner with three vegetables and a small amount of protein. Now, they do understand that
because that's what they're actually doing. They're practising that all the time.
I don't know that I can feel very confident about changing the behaviour of our adult
population. I think that they've got their own antecedents. They either come from a country
where eating is a joyous experience and moderate portions are the norm, or they don't. And I don't
think I can help. But I do think the fact that our young kids are bombarded with so many highly
common...
You know, so many colourful, so many appealing advertisements, it's asking a lot of a young child
not to be influenced by this. And as we know, pester power is alive and well in the supermarket
queue. I don't... I agree with you. A little indulgence now and then is of no consequence
at all. But you certainly don't want to get into the habit of that's what everybody eats every day.
And I see this. Stephanie Alexander,
that story is a great leadership story in Australia. And what you've done for food
education, as I said off the top, is an amazing contribution. And Stephanie, I've loved the
opportunity to sit down with someone from the arts or from a sporting world or a business world. And
you've probably combined a lot of those passions. And we see these... Really, what we see are some
success-lose-clues type of dimensions in what great leadership looks like. And I'd like to ask
you about some of those patterns that we've seen. Starting, Stephanie, with this idea of
self-leadership. We don't think anyone can lead someone else, as you've done so beautifully,
without an idea of what it means to lead themselves. Does that resonate with you?
I think probably the quality that has been
paramount in the decisions I've made and the people who've influenced me
is genuine enthusiasm. Yes, competence in the area that I'm interested in, but more particularly,
enthusiasm.
And an ability to communicate that enthusiasm and the beauty of whatever it is that they're
talking about. I can remember an English teacher in my very early years in high school who was just
so inspiring. I can remember another, even a maths teacher, and I'm appalling at maths, but
she gave the enthusiasm that it was something that was worth persevering with. And at university,
there were one or two lecturers that I...
I used to love the lectures because they communicated in their own love of the material.
And I think that that sort of enthusiasm is incredibly engaging.
No doubt. You've shared your love of all things food in such an incredible way. We see leaders
are really conscious of how they positively impact others in the environment on a daily basis. And I
read about you and your restaurants and the amount of people that came through that were trained
beautifully and went on and opened their doors to the world. And I think that's a really important
thing. And I think that's a really important thing. And I think that's a really important thing.
restaurants or then had impact elsewhere. Can you share with us your passion for impacting
others in the environments that you've worked in?
Well, just this last weekend, I went to be the guest of honour at Annie Smith's restaurant in
Trentham, Victoria to celebrate Mother's Day. And she was having this lunch and said to the
room full of people, which was very lovely,
Stephanie is my kitchen mother. She everything I know, she told me, well, that is absolutely not
true. But it was lovely to hear her say that. And she had asked me to design the menu, which she
then cooked. So that is she is one of my very, very special foodie friends. But there are a lot
of people who have worked with me and alongside me. And I think I would reiterate that what they've
got for me is
very positive modelling, because I really do live what I say, you know, I just don't eat fast food,
because it doesn't seem to me to be as interesting as the food I can cook myself. That doesn't mean
that I don't eat a bit of street food here and there. But I do like sushi. But you know, I'm not
tempted by the packaged product when I can go home and make something much more beautiful. So I've
watched people go on to run their own restaurants.
And it's over such a long time now. Often we've lost touch. But when I meet people or I go into a
restaurant, there's often somebody who comes up and says, I worked for you at such and such. Now
that includes, of course, the dishwashers and the front of house staff. And I don't always remember
their names. But they remember the experience as positive and enthusiastic. And so you know, I stick
with it. Enthusiasm is sweeps all before it.
And it's a great, great message to share. I appreciate you doing that. You've had some
big vision ahead of your time, as you said, running restaurants in Melbourne,
before it was even thought possible for people that didn't have formal training and your vision
in the Stephanie Alexander Kitchen Garden program as well. We see leaders are really conscious about
how they go about creating that vision and then sharing it. Can you give us an insight into how
you've done that? Well, I think the risk of repeating myself,
just that I live it. And so when I'm working with somebody in the kitchen, I can't help sharing with
them a bigger picture. You know, if we're chopping up leeks, I might say, goodness, I remember having
this beautiful, this beautiful pasta dish or this beautiful pastry, which was full of leeks that
have been softly stewed in butter for about 15 minutes, then drained and then mixed with such.
And the person who's chopping the leeks,
just hears that it's a sort of part of it's another track going through their mind.
But if it happens every day and a different, different product every day,
they do get a different sense of the possibilities of food. And a lot of the people that I influenced
positively, I'd like to think they were young people full of enthusiasm, but they often
didn't have very strong food backgrounds. They were interested and they became,
very competent, but they took on a lot of knowledge and they understood that food was
more than just nutrients. You're not just absorbing calories. You're eating people's stories. And
that's probably not a great answer. No, it's a great answer. And I'm pondering
because I can hear my mother's words in your language. I feel very fortunate. When you look
back and you realize that was the care that was put into...
The meals, you didn't necessarily appreciate and understand that when you were growing up,
but you look back now and say, as you've said so beautifully, that has flowed through,
I hope, to our kids as well.
And I hope I should have made a mention of my own mother because she was an extraordinarily
strong influence on my entire life, not just the cooking, because she really also really
cared about it. And it was terribly important to her. Her main creative outlet was cooking.
It was, what are we going to eat tonight? What shall I plant in the garden? It just was
something that, as you say, you don't know at the time. You're not aware at the time of how
much you're absorbing, but it's all there. Stephanie, we see curiosity as a common
trait and a word that comes up a lot in these conversations. And curious leaders then use
that as their way to keep growing and evolving. How have you tapped into curiosity?
Stephanie Kempf Well, I think from my
decades of the restaurant, through reading and through traveling and experiencing and tasting,
I feel I've stopped doing that to some extent. I just feel
at this advanced age, I'm just letting it all cure a bit in the brain now.
I want to ask you about the next dimension, communicating with clarity. You're 18 books
in, I think, and a new one about to be released, which I'd love you to tell us about.
Stephanie Kempf
If you can. But the communication that you have is a very clear and distinct way. And you mentioned
that in The Cook's Companion, the simplicity of it is the genius. Can you tell us about how you've
communicated your message? Stephanie Kempf
Well, writing, I love writing. I love words. I'd love to find another way of, I mean,
I can't write a novel. I just know that I can't do that. But I do enjoy very much the writing. So
the books have usually... Stephanie Kempf
It's usually been a task associated with pleasure, a lot of hard work, but it's been
pleasurable hard work. And the next book is called Fresh, and it is inspired by the work
of the Kitchen Garden Foundation, and hopefully enlivened by little stories about what happens
in particular schools. So it's also seen as being a way of families seeing how they can produce
lovely dishes, which their kids can help with. So it's meant to be for families,
and to inspire families to cook some of the things that have been cooked successfully by young people.
Dr. Tim Jackson What a great concept. I can't
wait to see it, and a great continuation of the brilliant work that you've done. And I love that
you've started in primary schools. I know there's a Stephanie Alexander Kitchen Garden secondary
program now as well, but capturing the kids when they're that creative and open-minded is
a brilliant way to go about it. Collaboration is something we see leaders now really,
conscious of, Stephanie, how they collaborate, how often they do. How important has collaboration
been for you? Stephanie Alexander Kitchen Garden
Well, as a not-for-profit foundation, of course, it has been, I'm not sure if that's exactly what
you mean, but we have had to collaborate. We have had to look for funders. We've had to look for
people who can support us because, of course, none of these things happen without people being
paid salaries and so on. So we've had a sort of a checker,
career with government, both state and federal. Sometimes we've had some positive help. Sometimes
we've had years when we haven't had positive help. We have a social partnership with Coles,
which has been very, very helpful for us. We have got philanthropic partners. We have
corporate partners. And all of those, we're very, very grateful to all of that assistance,
because without it, the foundation could not possibly exist. So,
and I think that story would be very familiar to anyone who's involved in a not-for-profit
organisation. It can keep you awake at night and does. But I think that anyone who really helps us,
we try to make sure that we take them to several schools pretty early on in our association. And
that gives a major reinforcement that they can see what they're helping is important.
And for you to hit the targets that you aim for is incredible, isn't it? To be
represented in an organisation that's so important to you.
Over a thousand schools is an incredible achievement. And no doubt, as you said,
with that collaborative approach, and it's not an easy sector to be successful in. And you've
done it with great skill. Can I ask you, Stephanie, who's been the greatest leader in your life?
Probably my mother. And she was such a shy person. She would be astonished to hear me say that.
I just somehow absorbed all the values that mattered to her.
And as I've got older, understood why some of them were so important. Probably when I was
10, 12 years old, I didn't realise what I was seeing when I saw the way she arranged flowers,
or the way that she chose beautiful things to put on the table. They were not expensive,
but just a lovely vase or a beautiful bowl. All of that was very, very important to her. And it's
now very, very important to me. So that, you know, the preparation for a meal is multifaceted.
I think I'll put that on that green plate. Sounds mad, doesn't it? But it's got to be something.
I've seen it. I feel lucky to have been around that sort of preparation and the passion for it.
And, you know, we grew up in the hospitality game as well, in the pub space. And to see,
you know, that care and the beauty of bringing people together is, again, something I feel,
you know, connected with your story.
Same way. And to have that influence, as you get older, you genuinely appreciate it.
We are a bit obsessed with collaboration in the leadership world, Stephanie. And I'll ask you
this question, final question. If you could collaborate with anyone on anything, and you've
done that so superbly in so many areas, you know, with Maggie Beer and the Kitchen Garden Foundation,
has there been one person you thought, wow, I'd love that to connect and collaborate with that
person anywhere in the world on any one of your passions?
I certainly, at the very, very beginning of the Kitchen Garden,
Foundation, I was extremely influenced by Alice Waters in Berkeley, California,
about she started a kitchen garden program called the Edible Schoolyard. But it was a different
model. But nonetheless, it did influence me. She took on a school that was very underprivileged
in Berkeley. And she created a model which still exists. But her model is different in the sense
that she wasn't trying to spread it into other schools. She wanted to create a model that was
not just a model. She wanted people to come and see a working kitchen garden, and then to decide
how they would like to apply it, if at all, in their own situation. Whereas right from the
beginning, I wanted our first school to just be a model, certainly, but I wanted to spread it into
other schools. I actually wanted the physical achievement of being able to say, this idea is
being carried forward. But she did influence me.
Collaboration. I mean, I'm very, very grateful to the organizations that have
helped us along the way, people like the Ian Potter Foundation. These things have been very
important at a certain time. I can't think of a single... I also have a wonderful CEO. And I think
as an organization, it's been very important for me to grow and say, my skills are not in governance.
And I've had... And I would...
I've been happy to pass over those skills to an effective board and a CEO. And I still am
important in spreading the image and spreading the flavor of the foundation to a possible new
prospect. Because as I say, we're always looking for people who will support us and allow us to
develop. And I love the words have come out so clearly in this conversation, the energy and the
enthusiasm.
And as you said before, it trumps everything in lots of ways. And I can still hear that
in everything that you say and your expansion. I can't wait to get a copy of Fresh. It'll be
another brilliant piece of work from Stephanie Alexander. Thank you for your incredible
contribution and leadership in all of our lives and in Australia and understanding food better,
understanding your passion for it. It's been a great privilege to spend some time with you.
Thank you.
Thank you, Luke. It's been lovely.
Thank you for listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Powered by Temper, a mattress like no other. And to make sure you don't miss an episode,
click subscribe wherever you get your podcasts.