What I know to be true is that I think in comedy, you can still pretty much say whatever
you want.
I think in broader society, you can't necessarily say whatever you want anymore because humor
in those senses is contextual in all senses, right?
There are things that I would happily say within the confines of my standup show in
a room full of people who've been there all night.
Hello, and welcome to another episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
At Alita, we are passionate about inspiring connections and creating a world of collaboration.
Our signature program, Alita Connect, curates groups of five to six leaders from diverse
backgrounds in sport, industry, social venture, and the arts who come together to learn, to
connect, and to collaborate.
Kirsten King, founder of Fluid Form Pilates.
It's been amazing.
Here you are on this Zoom call.
So, feeling within the first session like you intimately know these people and care
for them, and then all of a sudden realizing that even though you're in totally different
industries, we're all going through the same thing, or we've been through it and we can
help each other, or there's just this hurdle that you can't see past, and then you share
it with the group, and there's five answers in 40 minutes, and you think, I have not slept
for two weeks.
Think about it.
Think about that.
Like, how is this possible?
Craig McRae, senior coach of the Collingwood Football Club.
You're listening to stories and the breadcrumbs of what makes success, and I constantly get
something out of these Zoom calls and catch-ups, because we're all living the same stuff, aren't
we?
Extraordinary people with extraordinary experience.
What happens there is magical.
The Empowering Leaders podcast is proudly brought to you by Victoria University, where cutting-edge
sports and exercise science facilities like heat chambers,
performance labs, and altitude environments mean VU is ranked seventh in the world for
sports science.
VU, uniquely you.
As always, a big thank you to Jason Nicholas and his team at Temper Bedding, a mattress
like no other.
If you enjoy listening to the Empowering Leaders podcast, be sure to subscribe, and please,
if you have a moment, we would love you to leave a review so we can reach more listeners
and empower more leaders.
Will Anderson is one of the most respected voices in the entertainment industry.
He's a world-famous comedian, a multiple-award-winning television host, internationally respected
comedian.
Will's ability to dissect complex issues, stop laughing at me, mate, with humour and
intelligence has seen him sell out shows around Australia and the world.
In 2008, Will became the executive producer and host of Gruen.
You've got to fact-check me here on a few things.
And one of the most successful shows in Australian television history.
He has several outstanding podcasts, The Brilliant Willosophy, Tofop, which is 30-odd foot of
pod, with his great mate, Charlie Clawson.
He's an author.
He's an author of three books, largely drawn from his brilliant writing, The Sunday Roast,
published in Sunday newspapers around Australia.
Co-hosted Triple J's Breakfast Show with Adam Spencer, The Glasshouse on the ABC, and in
recent times, The Brilliant Question Everything.
He's fresh from doing improv shows at the Comedy Festival.
He's a genius in every sense.
Great to see you, mate.
Mate, that was a lot of stuff.
Felt like a lot of stuff.
It's the most homework I've ever done.
Yeah, it was good.
Ever.
I mean, it's rare that anybody uses the term respected in regard to me or my career.
So that did make me giggle a little bit.
Do you know, as I was writing that, I thought, I know you're going to laugh, but you're a
hard man to sum up.
You're a hard man to capture in a paragraph.
Jack of all trades, master of none.
That's what it is.
Well, you're a country boy from Sale in Victoria, son of dairy farmers.
How young were you where you realised milking cows was not going to be your future?
Yeah.
So it's funny because I examine this theme so often, and often even in my work.
In fact, in my last year's show.
I think what was so legitimate was me going back to sort of the jokes that I would make
about growing up on a farm or about my dad and these sort of things when I first started
doing comedy through the eyes of somebody who is now the same age as my dad was when
I started doing comedy and whether I did see them differently.
So I really went back and had a good think about, talked to mum and dad about the idea
of, you know, when did you know that I wasn't going to be a farmer?
Were you very invested in the idea that I was going to be a farmer?
You know, in entertainment, they're always joking about the.
The idea of Nepo babies, you know, the next generation, you and I know you're from a
football family, generations of footballers, a bit of a family tradition.
Farming is a little bit like that in that often the next generation farmer comes because
their parents, you know, were involved in the farming industry in some way.
But my dad, despite the fact that he's been a farmer all his life and the fact that his
dad was a farmer, never really put any pressure on us, any of the kids.
This is a thing that, you know, I back for the Bulldogs in the AFL.
But my dad's a Geelong fan, everybody else in the family.
So his dad, James, and then all his kids and all their grandkids are Collingwood.
Every single one of them.
We were a Collingwood family.
The only exception to the Collingwood family was dad, who just decided he wanted to pick
his own team and barrack for Geelong.
When we were growing up, dad said the exact same thing to us.
He said, you don't have to barrack for Geelong.
You all get to pick your own team.
My brother barracks for Essendon and I barrack for, you know, for the Bulldogs.
My sister barracks for St Kilda.
You know, we all just chose a different team.
And it was a bit like that in the way that they raised us as kids.
There was all this, always this expectation that dad was a farmer from the age of 14 or
15 when he started farming because he wanted to be a farmer.
He moved down the road to his own farm and started that when he was 15.
He didn't take over the family farm.
He wanted to be on the land and build a farm and have this, this lifestyle.
And what our parents were very big on for us was that they wanted us to
have those same opportunities to pursue something that we also loved or had a passion for.
So my brother went back and eventually took over the family farm.
And I have talked to him about it because he went off and he was a builder and he lived
in London and traveled all over Europe with his friends and had that whole experience,
lived in Western Australia for a while, traveled around Australia.
But he did say that about every year dad would check in and sort of say,
how are you feeling?
Do you think that you might come back to the farm?
Never any pressure to do it.
But there was.
A yearly check-in to say, you know, cause I mean, obviously dad and mum built this great
big farm, like, yeah, well this, you know, family business, they were like, what, what
happens to it when we stopped doing it?
Um, those calls never came to me.
So I think, I think from both sides, it was a mutual agreement.
You know, like sometimes when people say things are in a mutual agreement and you're like,
that doesn't really feel like it was both sides.
I think this was one where we both knew that it wasn't going to be for either of us.
And I've met your brother and he looks like the son of a.
Um, and he's a great fella and, and it looks like potentially that was always going to
be the case, but do you look, but you must look back and think, geez, that's forward
thinking of your parents to be, cause a lot of parents struggle with that.
They just can't help, but see the world through their own vision and they want their own kids
to be like them.
That, that must've, you must be pretty respectful of that when you look back how accepting they
were.
I am.
I, you don't know that you have good parents until you meet people who haven't been as
lucky.
Cause when you have good parents, you assume that.
Yeah.
Your parents are good or you have the luxury of looking at the things that annoy you about
your parents and, you know, pretending like they're bad things.
Whereas when you grow up and you see the world and you see the great headstart, it can be
in life that my parents are humble parents.
Like, you know, not, not, nothing particularly flashy.
We weren't particularly well off, you know, they're farmers, they work for a living.
It's a small farm.
It's a family farm or that sort of thing.
But my, my mum had a thing that she used to say, which was like, as a parent, your responsibility
is to love your family.