This week's guest on the Empowering Leaders podcast is an extraordinary individual.
Zoe Kalar is the founder of We Are 8.
She is a serial success in the tech entrepreneur world and has achieved incredible things.
One of the biggest issues facing us all, for me, are the algorithms of social media, what
they're doing to our young kids, the amount of time we're spending on our screens, the
divisiveness of the way that the world is unfolding through the world of social media.
But how do we change it?
How do we put that genie back in the bottle?
Well, Zoe Kalar may well be the one person on the planet capable of finding a solution.
We Are 8 is an incredible innovation.
It's changing the world of advertising.
You're going to hear Zoe talk about the hurdles she's overcome to be a successful female tech
entrepreneur, why she believes governments need to take a stronger stand against social
media platforms, and she's calling on brands to shift more of their money towards people
and the planet.
It's one of my favorite stories.
Zoe has a...
A vision, an energy, and an inspiring way about her that is truly unique.
We are incredibly privileged to collaborate with Zoe in our Elita Connect program.
We curate groups of five to six people from around the globe to come together to learn,
to share, and connect.
And it's people like Zoe who inspire the work that we do.
We'd love you to have a look at it.
Head to elitacollective.com and book a discovery call today.
Big thank you to the team at Temper, Jason Nicholas and his team, great supporters of
conversations like this with Zoe.
We know that great leaders are united by the need for sleep and investing in a mattress
like Temper will be a decision that changes your life.
Zoe Collar is literally changing the world for good through her social media platform,
We Are 8.
We Are 8 is on track to disrupt the hundred plus billion dollars of annual advertising
money that flows directly to Mark Zuckerberg at Facebook, putting that money back in our
hands as users, charities, and creators of positive content.
To give you an idea of the possibilities...
We Are 8 is on track to disrupt the hundred plus billion dollars of annual advertising
money that flows directly to Mark Zuckerberg at Facebook, putting that money back in our
hands as users, charities, and creators.
When one percent of the population, 80 million people, watch two minutes of ad content a
week, We Are 8 will be putting more than a billion dollars a month back into the community
and charity.
On top of that, there is a zero hate on We Are 8 with sophisticated AI tech in place.
Pat Cummings, Australian cricket legend, Rio Ferdinand, Manchester United superstar, and
a roll call of some of the most influential and conscientious investors around the globe
are backing Zoe in her mission at We Are 8.
We Are 8 is on track to disrupt the hundred plus billion dollars of annual advertising
money that flows directly to Mark Zuckerberg at Facebook, putting that money back in our
hands as users, charities, and creators.
Zoe's record of success in the media tech and startup world is a remarkable story in itself, selling her first media business back in 1997, successfully bringing Andrew Lloyd Webber's work to China and most recently creating and eventually selling Standard Media Index, a tech platform that transformed the advertising and media landscape in the US.
Zoe, it is great to see, incredibly inspiring what you're doing. You know I'm a fanatic when it comes to sharing the way I write stories, so it's great to be able to do it in this format. Thanks for joining me.
Thanks Luke, it's just brilliant to be here.
I want to talk to you first from a mother's point of view, because our kids are growing up in this world of Instagram and Facebook and Snapchat and these platforms are irrefutably leading to teen suicides. There's a horrific spike in eating disorders and mental health epidemic really for our kids. Is that the reason why you're dedicating your life to this?
There's nothing surprising about starting this conversation with that question, Luke.
Because, you know, you're all about getting to the heart and there's so many reasons why I've built this, but that is right at the heart. I mean, we have our kids living on social technology that is irrefutably damaging and kids spending four to six hours a day on average, which is three to four months of their lives a year on social media control.
Wow.
Where the entire framework is built to control what we see, how we feel. And so for me, it was how can we reimagine a world that I want my kids to live in and I want my friends' kids to live in and I want my friends to live in and I want to live in where we're safe and we're free to be ourselves, our biggest, most inspired, inspiring version of ourselves,
without fear that someone masked is going to walk through the door and start abusing us.
And I think I just came hot off the discussion. There was a BBC three-hour conversation with some families that had gone through the tragic loss of their kids suiciding and I met one of them.
I really had to hold myself together.
A beautiful man.
A beautiful man, Ian Russell, that tragically lost his daughter, Molly Russell, to suicide. He's a really prominent voice here in the UK. It was the first case many years ago where the coroner cited social media as the key cause and at what point do we as leaders, as technologists, as mums, as dads, as people say, enough?
This is just not okay. And it was really that. I couldn't bear the idea that my kids were having to live in this world with that being forced on them. And I couldn't see anyone else doing anything about it because everyone else thinks big tech is too difficult to change. And it is too difficult to change. But what's not too difficult is imagining a world past that, where we're shifting.
We've shifted the power of big tech back into the hands of the people, where people are safe to be themselves and where we don't have to live in fear of being abused every day.
And Zoe, I look back at Facebook was created by Mark Zuckerberg at college to judge women on their appearance. And when you think about where that has now led to and we now understand the damage that it's causing, it's like you're this perfect person that's come along with your media.
And your determination to just say, you know what, I'm not copying this. I'm going to, as you said, find a way. Does it feel like your life purpose has come to this point? And I know we're putting a lot of pressure on you, Zoe, to fix a problem that the world, I think now starting to understand just how bad this is. Does it feel like you've arrived at this time in your life or not?
Do you know, it's funny because I think it's been eight years and $57 million to build.
Build an architect, a solution that is the evolution, but it feels now we're at the starting line. So I think if it wasn't, if it didn't feel like my life purpose, I don't think I could have been resilient enough to keep going, honestly, Luke, at times, because it's really difficult for people to imagine a world post.
I mean, we look at Zuckerberg. I look at that an original thing, as you say, it was built to judge and literally rank.
Women to get dates. And if we think about it, Facebook's become a massive manifestation of judgment. So for things become a big manifestation of their original intention. And whilst for all the good Facebook does to connect us, because that part is beautiful, you know, they were on a mission to connect everyone in the world.
But unfortunately, because of the judgment and the lack of boundaries and protection and safeguards and economic models that valued people and everything else that was broken, it's now just become something massive that's incredibly damaging for people in society.
It definitely feels like a life purpose. It feels now like we've worked out how to build it. We've built it, the entire ecosystem.
And it's exciting now, because I can see, I can see it. And the people that are now part of it, it feels like the world is now seeing it. Things that I saw eight years ago were actually quite painful. You know, the climate, I remember where I was saying, Oh, my God, we've got 15 years until the damage we've done to the planet is irreversible.
We've got a world where kids now.
I'm feeling judged and in a mental health crisis. And it's just going to get worse. I know I'm here actually, to just build tech to navigate the way through that, that it just feels like my job. Beyond that, now I'm in the mode of, Oh, my God, what is possible, when we're actually, you can't be anonymous, when we're all safe to show up as ourselves, when there's an economic framework that pumps the money back to people and communities.
When we can come together around a common goal. I want to be at that party. If I got a push notification saying, Do you want to be one of 80 million people today that spends 30 seconds watching an ad, donates it to the water crisis, and we're going to build 30 wells in India right now. Like, yes, I want to be at that party. And then I want to feel and then I want to dance,
Luke, because I feel like I've given it away. Ninety seconds and then I want to dance, really. And that's awesome.
joy out the other side of being being able to do something good people are feeling hopeless
and not valued and that's just a completely shit way to to be yeah sign me up for that party uh
zoe and i i think there is a community we're gonna have a big one i'm looking forward to uh
to uh to catching up in person that's going to be uh be a lot of fun can you just explain to people
what you've built and how the way i rate model it seems like the impossible task you're taking
on these giants that have got money that almost incomprehensible to think 120 billion dollars of
revenue that actually doesn't even make sense to most of us to go to one company and effectively
half of that to one person how have you built tech that's going to challenge that i know wouldn't you
like to know what he is doing with all that money 135 billion dollars a year you have to think
wow for me
i had to see because the economic crisis climate crisis mental health crisis they're all interlinked
at a sort of macro level and and micro level but for me it's it i needed to break it down
into the chunks and work out how to do each piece and that if i look at the economic challenge in
itself when we look at the money i mean governments don't have enough money teachers aren't paid
enough
you know nurses aren't paid enough here in the uk we're seeing hospital workers go to food banks
once a week and eight million people out of a population of 60 not get enough food on the table
every day if we look at each thing and break down the economic crisis for example all i could see
how do we get more money into the hands of people and so for us if i look at the way facebook make
money
they make money by keeping us controlled and scrolling every day for as long as humanly
possible their goal is to keep us squished within that feed and never stop because then they can
just service more ads facebook make money from advertising from brands and 100 nearly 135
billion dollars last year and the crazy thing is their ad units only deliver 0.04 engagement rate
anyway so the ad unit doesn't even work people can i jump into that so before you finish because
can you explain that in real terms because it feels as though everyone has been conned that
spend your money on instagram that's where the audience is there's everyone is located there so
you need to to have your ad spend there but you you know this space better than anyone else because
you build an index to actually measure this so in terms of customer acquisition why is that number
so poor and why have we been conned by it can you can you give us a little bit of time to talk about that
a bit more on that look in the old days tv ads got a lot of attention and really worked i can
actually still sing jingles from the 70s luke but if you asked me any ad that i saw across digital
i actually can't even remember and our human brains have started to block it all out there
are a lot of people on instagram no question but our brains are not absorbing the information
if we hit
enough times then eventually and throw enough stuff out there some things are going to work
but that's like saying i'm getting these results it's working for me but i've never actually
imagined or seen what it could be in a better way and in our all our advertisers are getting
67 times more attention they're getting more engagement they're getting better transactional
results
and they're making feel people feel really good and loved you know our biggest complaint luke
from all our citizens is that they don't get enough ads people want eight minutes of ads on
eight a day because every time they get loved and and watch a brand ad money goes into their
eight wallet money goes to charities money goes to communities and money goes to the planet
and then you can pay a bill pay your spotify or pay it forward to a charity
and so who would you say is going to be the one that's going to be the one that's going to be the
one that's going to be the one that's going to be the one that's going to be the one that's going to
be the one that's going to have the most impact on the world
that there's a world where people want to watch ads
and that's the first bit because we realized if we could build an ad unit that people want to watch
and money and is shared with them and we make positive impact together
then that's naturally going to work better for brands and i'm part of that again sorry to
interrupt zoe because i am really passionate about that i haven't seen an ad or absorbed an
ad for for maybe six or seven years because i don't watch free-to-air tv i watch live sport
only i don't operate on those platforms because i'm in that bizarre uh era where i missed it and
now uh you know through a passion space of accounts but you can skip the ads you don't on
podcasts i skip ads that i don't want to listen to but then your app comes along and it's like
hey that's going to give me a credit direct into my wallet you've gone and got nike and ebay and
cadbury and nestle and heineken and so the big advertisers are getting it so i watch my ad on
for two minutes and then i answer a question at the end for and i know then that the credit comes
and i can donate that to someone or i can pay off my phone bill or my spotify account or so that's
the integrated system that you've worked isn't reverse engineering it so that people are wanting
to just to stay on and then the advertisers are actually getting people properly watching that's
part of the model isn't it yeah totally so it's real people because in digital advertising 50
of it is fraud when ads are
pinged out over the internet so so we eliminate fraud it's validated identity real people
we bring the brand and the people together if you think about it advertising is a 500 billion
dollar industry built on getting people's attention to then selling them something
and yet people have never been valued in the economic equation you know it's like trying to
bombard you
but if i came up to you and said luke i'd really love 30 seconds of your time if i dropped money
into your wallet donated to charity and donated to planet projects would you give me 30 seconds
please oh yeah okay zoe i will so it feels people human beings deserve because we're the target of
the ads surely we deserve to be respected and valued and we deserve to be valued and we deserve to be
grand
am i somehow
i don't know what we know rachel tell me i don't know how to answer your question
that uh to the least of our knowledge is that it covers so many types of things and and interesting
things so it's the thing about deep Zielinger because today we have
people who want is
show went live the ad went live in app and then it was also across a lot of other premium.coms
and websites and the publishers then are healthy again and more of the money shared with them so
our vision is wherever you watch a golden eight ad whether it's in app or on any of the great
publishers that we want to help make healthy again money is dropping back into your wallet
and then you can feel really good pay your things make positive impact and so the whole
ad economic flow is transformed the old world is fraud broken we think we've got to be there
it kind of it doesn't really work now we've got a world where you can reach the people that you
want to reach make them feel really good and respected and it just works 67 times better than
all the other shit ones that i love
you
yeah people often say well just switch it off take it off your phone and tell your kids to do
that well that's just not reality because that's where their social connections are it's as you
said the great part is connecting the world and catching up with friends that you hadn't before
the evil has jumped in on top of it and those algorithms that are there to divide us are
creating more hate and more nastiness than we've ever experienced before so let's keep the good
stuff earn some money donate that and pass that on and create a
a
great community with all the same features except that you've turned off the hate and you've turned
off the ability to be fake on there and so that technology is available to mark zuckerberg and
facebook they could do that in a second but they choose not to as you say because they want to keep
you angry they want to keep you uh sending uh negative things out into the world because then
they can bombard you with more ads and so i love spreading this story though because it's it's the
modern issue that i think all of us you know you look at your own kids and you're like oh my god i'm
thankfully they're healthy but the biggest fight every day is still when i go upstairs in a minute
it's hey boys enough get off the phones get off the every family's facing that crisis and
and tragically some aren't surviving it and that's the thing right because if i look at
building one part of the solution at the time at a time fix the economic model build the ad unit
that gets money in people's pockets and you know if eight million million people in the uk
can't afford to buy a car they can't afford to buy a car they can't afford to buy a car they can't
get food another eight million people can watch one ad donate 20p to fair share which can get
another eight million people food so there's the economic solve and the buying engine then on top
of that we've wrapped around the social experience but what's really exciting about that we've built
that framework we've now built in it's like building a house luke the most the most critical
pieces the
foundation the plumbing the electricity infrastructure all those things that you
can't see are really expensive and really painful to do particularly when you're redesigning it
we've now built all of that so it's free from hate we've integrated recognition software so every
video image comment is scanned on the way through we've built ai we've actually had to retrain
machines loads of machines we've built a lot of machines we've built a lot of machines we've built
a lot of machines we've built a lot of machines we've built a lot of machines we've built a lot of
which took us six months longer than we thought because machines think that we all hate each other
and just want money money and power and so we've retrained it to detect directed hate so now you
can't be anonymous an engine's there to protect you from the hate i love the joy that that comes
when you speak about that and and and you mentioned the sort of social divide and and the issues
that's creating in the u.s.
i think three members of the walmart family are worth the the entire wealth of the bottom 50
percent of america that's how ridiculous the the divide has got these big tech entrepreneurs are
worth 70 80 100 billion dollars and more and and and we've got you know the gross domestic product
of some small nations are less than their annual earnings imagine in a country like india to be
able to put money back into people's hands through an app and give back to community the way that
you're doing um is just so exciting the thing that i i'm i'm sort of baffled with so you're the most
bankable person i think i've ever met your history is everything you do turns to success you've made
money for people in all of your ventures i mentioned some of them in the introduction but
female tech entrepreneurs get excluded from the pool in ridiculous ways can you share with
the the frustration of that that everyone listening to this this is a cause you you
have to get behind either either use it or
find a way to to put some money behind it but there's still hurdles you've got to overcome that
are that are really challenging it's a great question and one that i ask myself almost on a
daily basis look what can i be doing better i mean look the data and i can't thank you enough
for the introduction to lev shevkin and tracy warren because she is a an absolute powerhouse
change maker she's just got government legislation through in the
u.s that is now means that all vcs have to report on female-led companies that they're
investing in because the reality is female founders get 1.7 percent of all funding all vc
funding and so it's very very difficult to build something big i mean elon can send seven rockets
into space that crash and burn but people will still back because there'll be an eighth so
you have to have money i mean the ecosystem we've built is 57 million dollars and actually
anyone that sees the market size and everything we've built would say oh my god how have you done
it for that and the buying engine which honestly our version of facebook ad manager where all the
brands can buy through it uses ai it's going to transform media buying completely it's actually
a thermonuclear weapon in a good way but the reality is it's just i don't look like elon musk
i don't look like mark zuckerberg i'm 55 and had a shit ton of experience seeing big problems
building technology putting together world-class teams getting people successful exits and i still
have to fight every day for it but but it's shifting and the reality is that i don't look like
the only way to and but i'm not prepared to just sit down and complain about it i just am getting
on with that because i also know what we've built is transformational it's working for the biggest
brands in the world and the world is waking up to and this is why i love india because modi took a
stand he banned tiktok all the other governments are suing the social networks they're talking
about it it's very simple it is damaging for society and it's damaging for the world and it's
it's fueling knowingly fueling teen suicide and self-harm it's knowingly making our societies i
would argue it's just dumbing everything down making people feel really not valued so just stop
just stop governments take a stand ban it because there's an evolution now but because that process
is too slow we've just got to get on with it
so it's a tough old road but with thanks to amazing women and men like you advocating and
getting in the trenches with us because i look at young girls that want to be engineers or reimagine
things and i i don't want it to be this path we need to be able to absolutely be free to imagine
the biggest things work out how to do it and we need to be able to absolutely be free to imagine
the biggest things work out how to do it and have the support to execute on it and i can't wait to
we are eight becomes a hundred billion dollar company and then we can pump i can personally
pump so much money back into founder you know female and diverse led teams all the things that
i want to make impact on using our tech but the status quo is broken there's this fragility and
massive civil unrest from an economic perspective that is so much more than just the economic
simply not sustainable and it's almost laughable that on a macro level we think
there is so much the economic divide doesn't work the greed from big tech doesn't work
our societies are self-harming and suiciding the mental health crisis is an epidemic the climate
is screaming for our help at what point do we say oh shit we better do something about
about this and tragically as a as a as a race i mean do we need to cut down the last tree to
sort of work out that the trees are important and it feels like we're at that point isn't it where
it's got as you said it's it's you cry if you didn't laugh because it's it's so damaging and
it's so in front of us and it's something we're all facing but you have what i love there's great
champions that are on your side who are getting behind you and who have led with their money and
with their profile as well and i think it's a really important thing to do and i think it's a
and their voices yeah can you share with uh with us some of the people that are really backing what
you're doing so for a start well you luke you're fabulous really low level but i'm trying
do you know i think it's been a really fascinating process actually because i believe you know there
is inherent good in most people and there's enormous support now from our community we're
1.6 million people in app everything we're doing is really getting huge support from
from the people you know at which is beautiful that means more to me than anything apart from
which the complaint about we want more ads so we need to stand together and call on brands to shift
more of their money back to people in the planet but incredible people i mean artists like shepherd
fairy who actually
he created the obama hope image you know right at the forefront of change we've got ushers and
investor rio ferdinand who you know he led manchester united to victory he's a great leader
and that the sport music we've got this incredible francisco nunez he's a conductor in new york city
he's put together this most beautiful
diverse choir of 2 000 kids from every borough every race religion gender and they literally
sing in harmony he believes he was put on this earth to teach the world to sing in perfect harmony
which the optimist that i am i believe we as human beings around the world can come together
see what we have in common not what divides us
so inspired every day and these incredible people you know patricia arquette actress huge change maker
the super vet who is um he he does 200 operations on animals that no one in the world world does
but now communities saying all these organizations that want their kids
on safe platforms that want to live on safe platforms but it comes talking about safety
isn't very sexy so we've built all the safe plumbing now let's be cool as with a heartbeat
and that and that's the stage where we are right now let's be you know let's be rebels and
change makers and shake shit up together because now we can be free to do that but you just you
just can't be
um don't be don't throw hate like that's enough of that exists in the old world
yeah beautifully said and it is inspiring and unfortunately has permeated all of our lives
sewer is out there of twitter and social media and it's created a language that i think a
generation of growing up and thinking that's actually part of the way you converse i see
it in the football industry here in australia that that i love it's this beautiful community
but now we interact in ways that are
are terrible when we want to sack people and we i find it really hard to listen to this thing
that's this great community game that that's permeated that part of the world as well and
it feels as though people have trained to to sort of be louder and and and have a hot take or
something that's a bit with an edge that doesn't necessarily um you know create this positive
positivity and so i love we need to share these there's so many great stories out there are people
all around the planet doing brilliant things that aren't getting a platform because they're not
being shared and we need to share more of them and it's been also brilliant so to collaborate
with you and a passion space that we talk about here a lot around a leader connect as well and to
have uh you and um andy walsh who's got an amazing story with his work that he's doing at liminal and
and and with red bull and the high performance um andy cohen who's a beautiful incredible uh
human being is um one of the most successful finance people in the world with jp morgan
rio
first
is obviously a great supporter of yours jude bolton is one of my favorite people in the world
of afl so again it's sort of our way of connecting people for good too zoe and it feels like it's when
we're so wrapped to be able to um have you in that space as well do you know it's funny luke
because firstly it's an incredible experience and i can't thank you enough i realized since
the age of 21 it's the first time you know when you're always pushing to build and to
and spending money on tech and the best team and everyone else you actually i realized that i'd never
actually done anything for myself um you know i put a lot of people around me to coach me and
help learn but just a group that i felt really safe with and as you say andy andy jude rio
stacy moderating i mean we're talking about incredible people i learn so much about people
on those calls i can't even begin to tell you and they make me feel i've never had it actually
i realize i've never had that before so and neither has rio actually when you when you used
to the sort of the hotbed of coaching and then you move into the next stage of your life i mean
i look at rio and just think all of that greatness is just practice for what he's about to do
because i actually see him on the world stage representing the voices of 200
million people when we go into governments and big companies and drive for change in the world
like i see him as a representative voice of the 200 million people on aid saying this is what we
can do and so i believe it's really helping him i know it's helping him i know it's amazing i feel
like i'm in hot house learning mode and and you know i think we've had technology
that's sort of shaped our society but we haven't had leaders that say no so i think part of the
thing with instagram it's well everyone else is showing up there i've got to be there everyone
else is there that's where i've got to be and then everyone follows and i think what's exciting now
we're seeing people that are there was a there were eight celebs in the u.s that just came out
and said we're saying no to social media and we're saying no to social media and we're saying no to
social and i think there's never been an alternative so and we haven't been quite ready
honestly like our tech everything hasn't been ready but we're ready now and what we're seeing
we're switching on at the end of the month a love count and comment count because all our talent
are getting more loves and comments than they are on instagram despite us having a lot less audience
it's the brave leaders and when you talk about the abuse
that teams are getting we see abuse in politics abuse in sport abuse that i mean 20 years ago
it never would have been acceptable and it feels like we've just like a frog in a pot of boiling
water you know it's just become acceptable and now the norm until there's a group of us that say
this is actually shit for everyone there's a much better way
i love it zoe and i i'm going to tell this story and i know um the person i mentioned will be
comfortable with it because i actually spoke to him about it last week um luke hodge is a four-time
premiership legend in our space one of the greatest players that has has played the game
he grew up in uh western districts uh from you know the old school country stock you don't meet
a more resilient and brilliant person and he did his first commentary game with me and like your
first day your first day at school and you know i'm not going to lie to you i'm not going to lie to you
um and at halftime he went to check on his kids just to see where they were and he got on his
phone and then i remember after halftime his face was sort of a bit ashen and he didn't really speak
in the second half you know which calling the game and i remember checking him after said you're okay
and he said no i'm not actually he said look i jumped onto my social media account and here's
what people said about me at halftime and i read some of the comments i could not believe you know
you are a fucking you know the dumbest fuckwit that's ever
called again and i was thinking if luke hodge with all that resilience and all that success
and one of the toughest and if he can get affected by that what hope does a 15 year old girl at
school have or a young person in a teenage brain trying to grow up like it just sort of hit me in
the face and i was like this is what we're dealing with like it's so evil and it's so pervasive that
no one's safe from that and as you said now we have a choice you've created a choice check out
if you haven't seen it before it's brilliant it's uh something that we just all have to
find a way and it's where our kids can still connect and still communicate and and it's where
the world's shifting to whether we like it or not so i want to ask you these questions because
we have used this term a lot someone said it to me in this podcast success leaves clues and we feel
like there's these great patterns around why people like you are capable of doing extraordinary
things and we love the idea of of leadership and start with self-leadership and it's we feel like
unless you have a sense of your own self-leadership what does that mean to you
clarity i think it's something that i've always been working on so it's clarity of where you're
going and for me it's i've always been really good at the big picture vision then for me it's
breaking it down into really bite-sized chunks so that everyone around you whether it's tech
product any commercial or any kind of commercial or any kind of commercial or any kind of commercial
cfo funding they can actually come on the journey with you so leadership firstly inspiration
being really clear um you know you're in the trenches every single day choosing this path
for all my sins luke this is where i have been for my entire life but but i know i'm meant to be
here so it's staying inspired bringing
everyone up reconnecting them with the big big vision breaking it down so it doesn't feel
overwhelming celebrating the proof points which again i could be better at i work on these things
every day as stacy said in one of our sessions it was a beautiful comment listen to understand
i actually said to everyone i'm gonna get tattooed i think on my arm because i know i need to be
better at that listen to understand
so you know i i think it is showing by example every day i mean it's just resilience belief
and knowing and exceptional actually just just the standard you walk past is the standard you
accept and i'm not prepared to sit on the sidelines with any of it i love you know the way you speak
about that i'm not surprised because every time i
you know i've spoken to you i you i feel that energy and i feel inspired uh by uh by the way
that you are we see people really conscious on a daily basis this almost sounds like a ridiculous
question to ask you because your project's going to change the world but we see people focused on
the impact they have every day in their environment everyone they interact with and they're
sophisticated about that positive impact on others is that something you're conscious of
i'm one of those people that ends up and some people probably wouldn't believe this but i
overanalyze self all the time i mean i i remember when um you know when my mom i grew up in a really
working class area and you know mom and dad both worked dad was a doctor mom was a nurse you know
the shopping it was you know i remember being at the supermarket and her holding items back
before going through did we have enough money to have everything we wanted i remember
feeling i'm high high empathy so i'd feel the pain and i just wanted to take that away i didn't
want her to feel like that i could feel the it was really really intense for me as a kid and i
could feel it all around me when it was too strong i used to hold my breath because i couldn't and
mom would say darling you've got to breathe you've got because i just couldn't if i saw someone doing
something really
abusive or anything i just couldn't i i absorbed it so i had to learn to stop it so i think
for me there's a real i just want to help i want to do things for others and i think
if we all did a little bit for others god we'd live in a beautiful society you know i think if
if we started caring for each other and speak to each other and listen to understand which i
work on every day um but it's it's we need to care for each other more you know i hear those comments
that your beautiful uh commentating colleague went through and i just think no one should have
to go through that like that hearing that puts fire in my belly like you have no idea like it
it is not okay and we just need to so yes and
how good it feels when we start to care for each other that's where the joy is you know that's
that's right right the highest form of living isn't it when you are contributing and what and
what you're doing at that level is quite remarkable we're fascinated about how people go about creating
and sharing a vision this this is a massive vision that's a game changer for the planet i loved how
you said you break things down into bite-sized pieces but how do you go about you know sharing
your vision that's as big as we are right do you know a funny thing i was thinking i found a book
that i had when my son was 19 who's 19 now when he i was pregnant with him and i wrote down what
what's my life's purpose like what what is it and it just kept coming back to this line
i am on this planet to inspire empower and enable a billion people to make positive impact every day
and i and in this book are all the ideas where did that come from that was just a bubble that
came in into your brain yeah that's it yeah and i just read an article about professor sacks
it was in the new york time or new york something about the one percent and the one percent have
enough money to solve every problem in the world and i just i wrote him professor sacks a letter
at the time and i wrote him a letter and i wrote him a letter and i wrote him a letter and i wrote
which he never responded to by the way and it was i agree with you absolutely one percent have
enough power to solve all the big problems the reality is they're not going to do it
so what it's going to take is the people uniting to come together so i then i actually thought
even back then 19 years ago how do i make it fun and easy
for a billion people
to make positive impact every day because if we can make it fun and easy
then that's what's going to make us all feel really good and so i think it started way back
then and there were all sorts of game ideas and other things and then it was actually the layers
of the exciting part is now that we have the economic model solved and the buying engine
now that we have the social media free from hate and everything else
now the icing is the game using our technology now we can play the game on how inspiring and
creative can we be to just we've got all the bits now we're just coming together and
and doing amazing stuff every day so i think i haven't heard you say that before but to have that
before you know that was pre-facebook pre-instagram and so now what i love about it is that that that's
Those pathways are there.
We've all got them on our phone.
We're used to scrolling.
We can connect a billion people now, which we couldn't 19 years ago
when you didn't understand.
It's just a matter of  and they talk about, you know, addiction.
You've just got to create a different pathway for that.
But it's got to be fun and it's got to be equally creating
that same dopamine.
You've done it.
It's there.
It's just now getting people to delete one and transfer over to the other
and it sounds simple, but that's the mission, isn't it?
It's possible now to have a billion people doing this.
It's genuinely
Right, and you don't have to delete.
Facebook connected a billion people on the planet,
and for that I'm hugely grateful because now while that's happening,
we can inspire them, empower them to make positive impact every day
over here where they feel valued.
And so I couldn't have done this without that actually.
And put money back into the community, put money back into people's hands
and share that wealth that the 1%  we're never going
to get rid of it.
We're never going to give up, as you described.
It's an amazing vision and it's there.
That's the incredible part is that you're on the cusp.
But we use the word curiosity a lot and we hear it come up a lot,
that people who achieve extraordinary things like you have done
right throughout your life, they're really curious.
And through that curiosity, they're constantly learning
and developing themselves.
Does that ring true for you?
Yeah, I think all of us learn.
I mean, and I get reminded every day my beautiful partner says to me,
oh, so what have we learned today?
You know, and it's  and actually we talk about it in the morning.
I really now consciously start each day.
I'm going to show up and do my best.
But that's what keeps life really exciting,
particularly when you're navigating a new path.
You know, you've got a vision, you've got the building blocks,
you've got all the bits.
That's life.
That's the life joy.
What am I going to learn every day?
Because even the day after, you know, you're going to be able to do a lot.
You're going to be able to do a lot.
Even the difficult stuff, even the painful stuff,
that's the best actually.
It's so true and I'm really grateful to learn from some
of the most incredible people.
And this is why a leader and what you've put together,
it's not just a normal group dynamic, that the way you've structured it
and the way you put people together and because of who you and Matt are,
it feels safe.
And there feels trust at the core, Luke, unlike anything else.
And that is very, very rare.
I know for all the people that are part of our group, it's really rare
because if you can fast-track the trust, then you can and that you're not going
to feel like an idiot if you ask stupid questions or show up in vulnerable ways.
That's really the only way.
Very kind of you to say.
You can learn.
And it feels.
My cap up to hear that because we love that idea of inspiring these connections
of people that would never have got together normally that share
that common good and it is a community of people that all the things
that you're talking about want to show up and want to be
in each other's corner.
And as you said.
Luke, do you know I was thinking, imagine, I just, I know I've talked
about this briefly, but a leader, groups of eight in a, I mean,
imagine when we've got 100 million people.
And with your framework, we can literally be groups of eight in a,
where we're actually learning together.
Imagine when we have someone from Israel, Palestine, Ukraine, Russia.
I mean, we need to start talking again.
We need to start talking again in environment of safety and trust.
I mean, I think you're a leader.
Groups of eight inside eight could be.
Amazing.
Yeah, we love that idea of being able to zoom out from your day-to-day
and spend an hour and 15, you know, and the tech's there, isn't it?
We can do what you and I are doing and you're in the UK and I'm in Melbourne today.
And we've now been given these tools that have probably gone off in a direction
we never hoped they would, but if you use them for good,
the possibilities is extraordinary.
And, you know, we're so inspired by what you're doing and how you're going about it.
And as we said, any form of collaboration,
collaboration with where our eight is right in our wheelhouse.
The other dimension I wanted to speak to you about was this idea of communicating with
clarity and we see people who achieve what you are consistently have got a really clear
why they communicate as you have.
Is that something that you've thought about or is it just evolved?
It's funny.
I have to work on it really hard because I see it as one of my weaknesses, actually.
Yeah.
And something I've had to strengthen.
So I look at each of my exec team, I've worked with my chief technology officer for a long
time so we can work in shorthand and I literally, I can say something, he gets it completely.
He maps it out, comes back to me, we tweak and then frame it out.
Other people on those calls, I have no idea what either of you were talking about.
So the funny thing is it's something that I really work on, particularly when we're reimagining
things that theoretically can't be done.
I mean, someone at one of the big media companies said to me the other day, you've reimagined
digital advertising in a way that works better, is more cost efficient, delivers scale and
values people and publishers.
Yeah.
We've been trying to do that and there has been no, we haven't worked out how to do it.
On one side, that's good, but communicating that along the way has been really difficult.
So communicating big things that are complex underneath, validated identity, centralized
wallet, ads where you get paid, social that's free from hate, all of those things, we've
got to work on that.
I think there are many, many things at the bottom that of us can't do.
A lot of us feel like we're working on the right thing.
And then there's the other thing that has just been very small, which is that we're
building up the space to the extent that we can.
So when we have a conversation with one of our clients, we're building up the space to
make sure that they follow along, we're building up the space to the extent that we can work
on the right thing.
And that's what I think is important is to get the information out and the conversation
is still going, but we've got to work on it.
So the learning off of the words has become very important for most people here.
And then there are more people in the world that want to go through what we call the
virtual space, which is the part of it that's very, very important.
learn all of that but just come and see the real me from 20 absolutely amazing people
is more exciting and clearer to the public you speak to i know families of of people and people
in our world that are living this sort of online life that is not even remotely close to who they
are and the and and the chaos and it's you know so long as it looks okay on instagram that is
supposed to be a modern version of living and really below that is just a lot of despair and
tragedy and pain you know and that's the same if you all of us we're all trying to be as close as
we can to our ourselves and and when you are that's as joyful as it gets isn't it when you're
putting on the mask it's and and unfortunately again that world's created second version of
ourselves that um you know is impossible to really live up to so again i love uh i love how you've
been able to uh solve that issue and give
people an opportunity without hate because you can't you know you've created the platform you
get booted off if you hate on we are right you've got to be yourself i can show that you're not a
robot you're not someone that's uh you know that's not real so i love it how important has
collaboration been for you though in all your success it's everything actually you can't first
you can't build something big without other people building it with you
really exceptional people building it with you so it's everything both with my exec team with all
our partners with all our media partners with our publishers with talent with people it's everything
and i've learned a lot about collaboration because i think one of the things is funny is all those
areas that we learn about with the elita process i feel like i'm in 101 other people would say
yes there's amazing
collaboration or there's amazing whatever i feel like i'm at the starting line which is a beautiful
thing to feel safe enough i can feel at the starting line because then everything feels
fast-tracked but collaboration is critical for the world we've built technology that is enabling
collaboration at a whole new level because there isn't any collaboration being exhibited people
young people now just cancel if they don't like something there's no
space to grow and so we've got to relearn that and re-teach it in a framework that supports that
and so collaboration is critical to me as a leader collaboration is critical to the world
if we're going to get through increasing crises on every level so i spoke to uh tim copper on this
podcast not long ago and that's a astronaut who's building the new international space station can
you believe that and i think it's a really important thing to do and i think it's a really
even incredible guy and he was referencing that collaboration in space simply happened because
a russian cosmonaut and an american astronaut just became great friends and we're fascinated
and curious by the different ways each program did back in the in the space race era and they
just we're going to be much better if we just share and do this together and you still get
that collaboration now you know russian america collaborating today and sharing the international
space station
so we can do it in space we just haven't mastered doing it on earth and and as weird as that sounds
as you said that at the global level that is where it all starts isn't it is one person to
another person reaching out or two leaders crossing that divide that is causing all of
the war and and tragedy that we're seeing at the moment it's uh it's fascinating i love that story
by the way because what those people what those astronauts did they put normal
earthly value stuff control greed none of that mattered because they were just both curious
about something beyond themselves and so none of this other stuff mattered it's that's a beautiful
story if we can all put the other stuff aside and just focus on something beyond ourselves
then we've got a beautiful world so who's been the greatest leader in your life
i have
have many I think you know at times I mean I as a young girl I would look at
people like Bill Gates I always felt even as a young girl at university I actually always knew
that Bill Gates would be on my board actually that was just a and I and so I always admired
that I think sometimes the closer that you get the big tech leaders I used to admire massively
the big media leaders I mean don't hold this against me but I used to really admire and study
Rupert Murdoch actually the thing that made me sad the more I grew and the more companies I built
is the is the success that they had but the power and control and greed
and the power and control and greed
that i saw as the common thread in all of them so so even though i was inspired massively by what
they were able to do and achieve and by what someone like gates is saying about the world
but the inability to let go of the control um some of that stuff makes me sad the closer i get
to it which is a fascinating answer and i'm i'm so curious about that because there's a genius
behind the scale and and rupert murdoch's business story is one of the most remarkable in in human
history and and what's been able to for a inherited an adelaide uh newspaper and and that was it it's
not as though he was gifted the keys to people think that even though he's second generation but
to have the control of the u.s media and to be able to do what he's done fascinating to
understand
how he achieved that as you said it's the byproduct of it that maybe in the end everyone
gets a little bit uh way late about it probably it leads into we're a bit obsessed with collaboration
in in the space that we're passionate about a leader and creating this world of collaboration
and i suppose ask that question you're collaborating with incredible people is there
is there one that springs to mind you think god if i could just you know and you mentioned two
historical figures there is it one person that in your world you think about that would be great to
collaborate with
there's many and actually i see the eight as a force of collaboration i see you know people coming
together to collaborate with each other in our framework i've actually imagined two heads inside
the eights you know people that you would never imagine collaborating collaborating i i a vice
president al gore i mean we've got the the climate reality project on eight which is his foundation
which is very important to me and i think it's a very important thing to do and i think it's a very
exciting their ceo is incredible um what david blood has done with the generation fund uh so he
has partnered with al gore to create a really big fund focused on a lot of climate things
he's a phenomenal leader who i know very well actually um and is driving transformation
in capital structures and that gives me hope for the world in in
in a different way completely different from a older me who's a former man i think i think
it needs to be a lot more well yesterday's talk was quite different from today i think
i would really love to collaborate with and his work and also the work of lloyd suarez who's
with us is quite a bit off but i think that really does add to it but perhaps you of all
these people who are in insurance are also sessioners who offer these very similar ways
to what we're proposing i think he's doing it in the world of capital flow and we're doing it
at capital flow for the people so i would i would love to collaborate with uh david blood and and foram
and vice president el gore if you're listening to this um on a on a deeper level but um i hope to be
who's one of our investors too, I hope that we are the framework
by which global leaders can collaborate again.
People can collaborate with each other and there's
an economic framework and a healthy society,
non-abusive framework that we can all collaborate
and listen, actively listen to understand each other again.
And we might walk away from the table not agreeing, but that's okay.
I might have come a little bit further to understanding your side
and you might have come a little bit further.
Even so, we can live at the table harmoniously.
And I don't want to diminish the intensity of what people have had
to endure or the injustice that they have had to endure or see,
but somehow we're on this little blue dot at the same time
and we're on this little blue dot at the same time
and we're on this little blue dot at the same time.
And there's enough resources for all of us.
We need to look after each other again.
What a beautiful note to finish on.
It makes me feel positive about the world talking to you
and that someone has come up with a solution to bring people
back to the table, as you said.
It used to be the great thing at a dinner table that you would learn
from someone else and you could have very opposing views
of the world or politics, but you'd learn from each other
and it feels like we've lost that art that now we want
to cancel each other or we...
We want to bear arms because someone's red and someone's blue
and it's got crazy to the point where, as you said,
it's beyond laughable and I just love every bit
of what We Are 8 stands for.
It's incredible that you're the person that's out in front
but collaborating with these incredible people around the globe.
So more strength to you, Zoe, in everything that you do.
Couldn't be more passionate about it and I've been looking forward
to telling the story today.
So thanks again for sharing it.
Thanks, Luke.
Thank you for all your support and everything.
Thank you for everything that you're doing.
I think this is...
Our collaboration is the start of something really great.
Thanks for listening to another episode of the Empowering Leaders podcast.
Huge thanks, as always, to our great friends at Temper
and we encourage you to check out our Leader Connect program.
New episodes are out every Wednesday morning at 6am.